20160617_113227.jpg

<line>United States</line>

<line>1882</line>

<Title>Gabon
The Africa Complaint
of the Ningué Island [unreadable but possibly "Mission"
American protestant
M. Walker</Title>

<number>99</number>

<label>20 Lecture Room
Liberty Equality Fraternity
French Republic
Ministry of Foreign Affairs</label>

<end of document></end>


20160617_113139.jpg
[originally written in English]


20160617_113147.jpg
[originally written in English]



20160617_113200.jpg
[originally written in English]


20160617_113206.jpg
[originally written in English]


20160617_113214.jpg
[originally written in English]


20160617_113227.jpg

<note>One of his letters from Morton August 5th, 1882</note>

<Date> Paris, August 28, 1882</Date>

<stanza> There, the arrival of [unreadable], 
the United States Ministry already told me
that the buildings of the house
[unreadable] of Ningué Island
were [unreadable] in the [unreadable]
I see [unreadable] to serve by
the [crossed out] [unreadable] indigenous [crossed out]
that you had them by the [unreadable] by the to [unreadable] whose
[unreadable] were joined, the superior beta missiont, Reverend
Walker, who [unreadable], already had
communicated to your deparment with the data of 
March 10th [crossed out] [unreadable] [unreadable]
the incursion was the tool of victory that will be the [unreadable]
of the expediction facts [rest unreadable]
from your friends by the "Marabout"
[unreadable from beginning] from Gabon and it 
[unable to translate]
[unable to translate]
3,500 francs</stanza>

<stanza> I am obliged to serve you
well [unreadable] in this affair and  
to know the following from me
[unable to translate] the 
complaint [unable to translate rest] Walker
[crossed out] will have conforted</stanza>
<end of document></end>




20160617_113238.jpg

<note> Ministry of the Navy and the Colonies </note>

[crossed out]

<note>Direction of the Colonies</note>

<note>First Office</note>

<note> Nota. The responses must
be addressed to the Minister et shared 
indicated margins below.</note>

<note>To the subjects of a complaint
[unreadable] by the American Protestant
Mission of Ningué Island</note>

<stamp>Political Direction November 13, 1882</stamp>

<Date>Paris, November 10 (/240m.) 1882</Date>

<line>Mr. Council President [v.] Dear Colleague,</line>

<stanza>In the communication from last October 28th,
a letter by which M, the United States Minister
presented to you a coplaint about the 
American protestant mission and the Ningué Island
during the obtainment of resharing the prejudice that was set out against him
[during] the tour of the "Marabout" in the Como, you wanted to ask me well of your knowing
of the following that this complaint would be conducted</stanza>

<stanza>I may not, to this regard, refer myself to the letter 
that I had the honor of addressing you on the last of June 3rd,
which cancelled all that was necessary in the document
for clarifying to you the extremity [unreadable word]
with which must be met wiht a complaint 
of this nature presented by the foreigners.
I will oblige you to represent this communication
to which was found that it was joined with a prepared note [unreadable]
far from me, that I am going to do to restore to your eyes
[unreadable word] that you come to this conclusion to
prioritize their demands of [unreadable word] and to ask
to prove the formal complaint that the [unreadable]
[unreadable] were students on the land
[unreadable] their was regularly done to renovate the following determined condition.</stanza>

To Mr. Council President, the Minister of Foreign Affairs

<end of document></end>



20160617_113247.jpg

<line>In [unreadable] around November 10, 1864</line>

<stanza>I am pleased to give you [unreadable] of these [unreadable]
i [unreadable] entirely to Mr. the United States Minister to Paris et ask him to invite
Mr. Walker to give support to the his complaint 
of the necessary gentrifications</stanza>

<stanza>I will be obliged to resend the note
that was joined in whcih it will have be of use to you.</stanza>

<stanza>Agree, Mr. Council President and dear Colleague, 
the assurances of my utmost consideration.</stanza>

<line>The Ministry of the Navy and of the Colonies</line>

<signature>[unreadable]</signature>

<end of document></end>



20160617_113252.jpg

<note>Minister of the Navy and of the Colonies
[unreadable-2 words] of State
of the Colonies
Direction of the Colonies
First Office<note>

<date>Paris, April [left blank] 1882</date>

<note>[unreadable] I have the letter from the 
[unreadable] to off.[?] from June 3, 1882</note>

<Title>Note</Title>
    
<stanza>Some reiterated complaints against the 
inidgenous families' schemes by some
negociators established in Gabon drove
Mr. Hanet Clery to embark on an expedition
in the rivers. Phemboë and Como</stanza>
    
<stanza>In the Phemboë, a small boat of an appartment to a German house from 
Hambourg was welcomed to shot of a gun by the N'Gouna Lahouin, 
Chancogo and Befino. In the Como, a shared side of the house [unreadable] and the Memezes 
were equally attacked in front of the Kango village,blocked and
driven in a faraway creek; on the men was nearly injured</stanza>
    
<stanza>[unreadable] The merchants traded
in these rivers, will declare themselves insufficiently
protected. One of the two shared notably, 
was asked to be authorised to complain about the protection of their government.</stanza>
    
<end of document></end>


20160617_113304.jpg

<stanza>There was a unanimous 
pity in asking about the penalty of the Lahouins.</stanza>
    
<stanza>Mr. Hanet Cléry will send the Marabout
with the obtained order guaranteeing the indigenous
or burning their villages.
This expedition has a tour,raising the complaints of the
majority of houses who traded 
in the rivers, not only because [unreadable-2 words]
and the warehouses of their subcontractors and subontractors
waiting by the fireof the "Marabout," but
again, because the indigenous having profited
from the plunder some merhchandises accorded somes 
wtithout subcontractors have[unreadable] of 
considerable losses on the duration of [unreadable]
who were confiding in them their complaints.</stanza>
    
<stanza>The compensated total of informal complaints and demands
were raised to nearly 118, 000." and one waits to one month [unreadable] of others.</stanza>
    
<stanza>nearly all the houses who 
claimed, belong to foreigners.
and it is possible that asking them informally 
would be pushed by their governments. The Mr. Hanet Cléry wished 
that nothing will be there. It is there for less</stanza>
    
<end of document></end>
    
    
20160617_113308.jpg

<stanza>necessary to examine the raised [unreadable]
In order to obtain the [unreadable-4 words]
Mr. Hanet Cléry was [unreadable-2 words] to close the
riviers,ending the [unreadable]
of traffic for time long enough 
to reflect on the indigenous and bringing them to
agree to some arrangements.</stanza>
    
<stanza> A [unreadable-2 words] to 
merhants, preventing them the[unreadable] of rivers
were pending, and [unreadable] them to indicate
the period necessary for [unreadable] of
engaged personnel and volunteers in the rivers. Waiting
by a local stop, the arms and munitions trade
was forbidden. Like to the [unreadable] further than
the blockade didn't have the following effect.</stanza>
    
<stanza>At first, [unreadable]
the merchants ask seemingly enormously exaggerated,
their doors are far from being established 
and justified ad il was impossible to them
to evaluate, because Mr. Hanet Cléry declares
that it had some months entirely to return to Libreville 
all the merchandise scattered in the hands of merchants and under
Interesting merchants' houses who</stanza>
    
<end of document></end>
    
160617_113319.jpg

<line>traffic in the rivers.</line>

<stanza>Of other parts, in the resident villages
Como to Phemboë who were burned down,
all the merchandises who were able to be recognized belonged to merchants
and some others. Merchants were moved by the 
Senegalese in the expedition without the orders of 
the Lieutenant the Guibot ship which confirms
he saw safe movement of this 
2000 neat range of logs and some
bags of salt.</stanza>
    
<stanza>When it comes to establishments who were 
able to be formed by the merchants in the rivers,
they assisted nearly all [unreadable] of the local administration, et no one was officially 
recognized.</stanza>
    
<stanza>The terms of a stop on November 20th 
of 1864, "the buyers and dealers 
in owned land and others and builidings,
in which this title knows, must be authorised by the 
Superior Commander.</stanza>
    
<stanza>The plotted demands must
be addressed in writing to the 
Superior Commander. They must indicate the</stanza>
    
<end of document></end>
    
20160617_113325.jpg

<stanza>"situation, the capacity of the land
"asks that the profession and 
"the nationality of the demander who
"will be indicated, in other, the genre
"of industry to which it has the intention
"of consecrating the concession that it
"solicits...</stanza>
    
<stanza>The aforementioned stop determine a [unreadable]
of conditions whom no one appears to have
been filled in on the complaints. Some of the
have invoked the prescription
who, in all state of the cause, could not
be previously at the aforementioned stop of 1864 who
regulated the conditions of establishements in 
Gabon.</stanza>
    
<stanza>The question that is previously posed
to all exams est this: is the 
right to compensation acquired to complaints?</stanza>
    
<stanza>The law of july 10 1791 says, article
32: "the case concluded that where places and posts
"were declared in a state of war, the demolitions
"will be judged necessary not trained 
by anyone for compensation of the properties.</stanza>
    
<end of document></end>
    
    
20160617_113338.jpg

<line>Article 39 of the law of August 10, 1853 est again more explicite:</line>
    
<stanza>[unreadable] occupation, all use 
withdrawn, all demolition, destruction
and other damage resulting from a fact
of war or of gripping measure of defense,
by being under the authority of the military
in the state's headquarters, being by a body of a detachment
for a year in the face of the enemy,
no open to any compensation."</stanza>
    
<stanza>The laws of August 16th of 1793, August 16 
au II, April 16th of 1816, July 10th of 1851
does not apply to the zone of defense fortifications
and posts, but it notes that the principle
of noncompensation is not particular to 
damages [unreadable] bythe defense of a place
besieged, but il applies to all 
damages [unreadable] by a military action
commit to a countryside role or by a 
detachment in the face of the enemy.</stanza>
    
<stanza>The law of August 11, 1792, is designed
in the biggest spirit of national solidarity
who drives the Revolution, a accepting
the principle of assistance or compensation to</stanza>
    
<stanza> French citizens who, during the
war, lost, by fact of 
external enemies, all or parts of their 
properties (First Article)</stanza>
    
<stanza>It determines therefore (Articles 2, 4, 7,
10, and 13) the conditions in which it will 
become justified of these losses and obtain the
anticipated aid.</stanza>

<stanza>Article 4, These whose properties
"have been devastated, will present at the
"municipality in place of the memory
"detailing and estimating the losses that they
proved. They will join a 
"certified extract of their sides of the imposition
"to the roles of the contribution of mobile
"properties.</stanza>
    
<stanza>In the proceeding exposé, or
note that the Gabon 
claims were not filled on the condition of
declaring and noticing land
properties where [unreadable] established 
the cases and the warehouses where
they are decorated in the name of 
warehouses.</stanza>
    
<stanza>Article 10 of the law of 1792
stipulates: the assistance and compensation</stanza>