<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="KS"><!-- Kayla Schirf --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionary Activity</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->
<term>Janssen, Camille</term>
<term>Léopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term>Emin Pasha, 1840-1892</term>
<term>Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904</term>
<term>Taft, Alphonso, 1810-1891</term> <!-- Spelled as "Alfonso" in text.-->
<term>Williams, George Washington, 1849-1891</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
<term>Accra</term>
<term>Aruhwimi River</term>
<term>Banana Point</term>
<term>Basoko</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Boma</term>
<term>the Congo</term>
<term>the Congo River</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Holland</term> <!-- Should I put down Netherlands?--> 
<term>Kinshasa</term> <!-- Was  Léopoldville-->
<term>Lagos</term>
<term>Lake Tanganyika</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>London</term>
<term>Newton Theological Seminary</term>
<term>N'Gombe</term> <!-- Couldn't find.-->
<term>Pennsylvania</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Portuguese Coast</term>
<term>Seventh Cataract</term>
<term>Stanley-Falls</term>
<term>Stanley-Pool</term>
<term>Twelfth Baptist Church of Boston</term>
<term>United States</term>
<term>Upper River</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KS"><!-- scanned, ocred, and encoded --></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<div2 type="titles">
<head>George Washington Williams,
1849-1891</head>
<p><rs type="person">George Washington Williams</rs> was born in <rs type="place">Pennsylvania</rs> of free
parents and was of mixed Negro, German, and Welsh ancestry. He
received his early education in <rs type="place">Pennsylvania</rs> and at the age of fourteen 
enlisted in the Union Army. After the war he attended the <placeName>Newton 
Theological Seminary</placeName>, from which he was graduated in 1874.
His first pastorate was the <placeName>Twelfth Baptist Church of Boston</placeName>, the
oldest Negro religious community in that city.</p>
<p>During his lifetime, <rs type="person">George Washington Williams</rs> had several
careers. He was the editor of two newspapers, the <hi rend="italic">Commoner</hi> in
<name type="city">Washington</name>, and the <hi rend="italic">Southwestern Review</hi> in <name type="city">Cincinnati</name>, and for
most of his life he combined the roles of scholar, minister, politician,
and lawyer, having studied law in the office of <rs>Judge <name><sic>Alfonso</sic> Taft</name></rs>
and later at the <rs type="place">Cincinnati Law School</rs>. <rs type="person">Mr. Williams</rs> was author of
the first encyclopedic history of the Negro, <hi rend="italic">The Negro Race in
America</hi>, published in 1883, and he was nominated as the first
Negro member of the Ohio legislature in 1877. His interest in <placeName>Africa</placeName>,
however, goes back many years to his valedictory address entitled
<q>"Christianity in Africa"</q>, given at <rs type="place">Newton Theological Seminary</rs>.
Toward the end of his life, George Washington Williams was commissioned 
by the United States government to make an investigation 
of conditions in the <country>Congo</country>, and he was also at one time Minister
to <placeName>Haiti</placeName>.</p></div2>
<div2>
<head>AN OPEN LETTER TO <rs> HIS SERENE MAJESTY <name>LEOPOLD II</name>, KING
OF THE BELGIANS AND SOVEREIGN OF THE INDEPENDENT
STATE OF CONGO</rs> BY <rs>COLONEL, THE HONORABLE <name>GEO. W.
WILLIAMS</name></rs>, OF THE <placeName>UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</placeName></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Good and Great Friend,</hi></p>
<p>I have the honour to submit for <rs>your Majesty's</rs> consideration
some reflections respecting the <country><sic>Independant</sic> State of Congo</country>, based
upon a careful study and inspection of the country and character of
<fw>98</fw>
<fw>HOW NEGRO AMERICANS CAN HELP</fw>
the personal Government you have established upon the <placeName>African
Continent</placeName>. . . .</p>
<p>It afforded me great pleasure to avail myself of the opportunity
afforded me last year, of visiting your State in Africa; and how
thoroughly I have been disenchanted, disappointed and disheartened, 
it is now my painful duty to make known to <rs>your Majesty</rs> in
plain but respectful language. Every charge which I am about to
bring against <rs>your Majesty's</rs> personal Government in the <country>Congo</country> has
been carefully investigated; a list of competent and veracious witnesses, 
documents, letters, official records and data has been faithfully
prepared, which will be deposited with <rs>Her Brittannic Majesty's</rs>
<rs>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</rs>, until such time as an International 
Commission can be created with power to send for persons
and papers, to administer oaths, and attest the truth or falsity of
these charges. . . .</p>
<p>There were instances in which <abbr type="title">MR.</abbr> <rs type="person">HENRY M. STANLEY</rs> sent one
white man, with four or five <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> soldiers, to make treaties with
native chiefs. The staple argument was that the white man's heart had
grown sick of the wars and rumours of war between one chief and
another, between one village and another; that the white man was at
peace with his black brother, and desired to <q>"confederate all African
tribes"</q> for the general defense and public welfare. All the sleight-of-hand 
tricks had been carefully rehearsed, and he was now ready for
his work. A number of electric batteries had been purchased in
<name type="city">London</name>, and when attached to the arm under the coat, communicated 
with a band of ribbon which passed over the palm of the white
brother's hand, and when he gave the black brother a cordial grasp
of the hand the black brother was greatly surprised to find his white
brother so strong, that he nearly knocked him off his feet in giving
him the hand of fellowship. When the native inquired about the
disparity of strength between himself and his white brother, he was
told that the white man could pull up trees and perform the most
prodigious feats of strength. Next came the lens act. The white
brother took from his pocket a cigar, carelessly bit off the end, held
up his glass to the sun and complaisantly smoked his cigar to the
great amazement and terror of his black brother. The white man
explained his intimate relation to the sun, and declared that if he
were to request him to burn up his black brother's village it would be
done. The third act was the gun trick. The white man took a percussion 
cap gun, tore the end of the paper which held the powder to
the bullet, and poured the powder and paper into the gun, at the
same time slipping the bullet into the sleeve of the left arm. A cap
<fw>H                                           99</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
was placed upon the nipple of the gun, and the black brother was
implored to step off ten yards and shoot at his white brother to
demonstrate his statement that he was a spirit, and, therefore, could
not be killed. After much begging the black brother aims the gun at
his white brother, pulls the trigger, the gun is discharged, the white
man stoops . . . and takes the bullet from his shoe!</p>
<p>By such means as these, too silly and disgusting to mention, and a
few boxes of gin, whole villages have been signed away to your
Majesty. . . .</p>
<p>When I arrived in the <country>Congo</country>, I naturally sought for the results of
the brilliant programme: <q><hi rend="italic">"fostering care"</hi></q>, <q><hi rend="italic">"benevolent enterprise"</hi></q>,
an <q><hi rend="italic">"honest and practical effort"</hi></q> to increase the knowledge of the
natives <q><hi rend="italic">"and secure their welfare"</hi></q>. I had never been able to conceive
of Europeans, establishing a government in a tropical country,
without building a hospital; and yet from the mouth of the <geogName>Congo
River</geogName> to its head-waters, here at the seventh cataract, a distance of
1,448 miles, there is not a solitary hospital for Europeans, and only
three sheds for sick Africans in the service of the State, not fit to be
occupied by a horse. Sick sailors frequently die on board their
vessels at <geogName>Banana Point</geogName>; and if it were not for the humanity of the
<rs type="org">Dutch Trading Company</rs> at that place—who have often opened their
private hospital to the sick of other countries—many more might die.
There is not a single chaplain in the employ of <rs>your Majesty's</rs>
Government to console the sick or bury the dead. Your white men
sicken and die in their quarters or on the caravan road, and seldom
have christian burial. With few exceptions, the surgeons of <rs>your
Majesty's</rs> Government have been gentlemen of professional ability,
devoted to duty, but usually left with few medical stores and no
quarters in which to treat their patients. The African soldiers and
labourers of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government fare worse than the whites,
because they have poorer quarters, quite as bad as those of the natives;
and in the sheds, called hospitals, they languish upon a bed of bamboo
poles without blankets, pillows or any food different from that served
to them when well, rice and fish.</p>
<p>I was anxious to see to what extent the natives had <q><hi rend="italic">"adopted the
fostering care"</hi></q> of your Majesty's <q><hi rend="italic">"benevolent enterprise"</hi></q> (?), and
I was doomed to bitter disappointment. Instead of the natives of the
Congo <q>"adopting the fostering care"</q> of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government,
they everywhere complain that their land has been taken from them
by force; that the Government is cruel and arbitrary, and declare
that they neither love nor respect the Government and its flag. <rs>Your
Majesty's</rs> Government has sequestered their land, burned their
<fw>100</fw>
<fw>HOW NEGRO AMERICANS CAN HELP</fw>
towns, stolen their property, enslaved their women and children, and
committed other crimes too numerous to mention in detail. It is
natural that they everywhere shrink from <q><hi rend="italic">"the fostering care"</hi></q> your
Majesty's Government so eagerly proffers them.</p>
<p>There has been, to my absolute knowledge, no <q><hi rend="italic">"honest and practical 
effort made to increase their knowledge and secure their welfare"</hi></q>
<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government has never spent one franc for educational 
purposes, nor instituted any practical system of industrialism.
Indeed the most unpractical measures have been adopted <hi rend="italic">against</hi> the
natives in nearly every respect; and in the capital of <rs>your Majesty's</rs>
Government at <name type="city">Boma</name> there is not a native employed. The labour
system is radically unpractical; the soldiers and labourers of your
Majesty's Government are very largely imported from <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> at a
cost of £10 <hi rend="italic">per capita,</hi> and from <sic><country>Sierre Leone</country></sic>, <country>Liberia</country>, <name type="city">Accra</name> and
<name type="city">Lagos</name> at from <measure type="currency">£1</measure> to <measure type="currency">£1/10</measure> <hi rend="italic">per capita.</hi> These recruits are transported
under circumstances more cruel than cattle in European countries.
They eat their rice twice a day by the use of their fingers; they often
thirst for water when the season is dry; they are exposed to the heat
and rain, and sleep upon the damp and filthy decks of the vessels
often so closely crowded as to lie in human ordure. And, of course,
many die.</p>
<p>Upon the arrival of the survivors in the <country>Congo</country> they are set to work
as labourers at one shilling a day; as soldiers they are promised
sixteen shillings per month, in English money, but are usually paid
off in cheap handkerchiefs and poisonous gin. The cruel and unjust
treatment to which these people are subjected breaks the spirits of
many of them, makes them distrust and despise <rs>your Majesty's</rs>
Government. They are enemies, not patriots.</p>
<p>There are from sixty to seventy officers of the Belgian army in the
service of your Majesty's Government in the <country>Congo</country> of whom only
about thirty are at their post; the other half are in Belgium on furlough. 
These officers draw double pay—as soldiers and as civilians.
It is not my duty to criticise the unlawful and unconstitutional use of
these officers coming into the service of this African State. Such
criticism will come with more grace from some Belgian statesman,
who may remember that there is no constitutional or organic relation
subsisting between his Government and the purely personal and
absolute monarchy <rs>your Majesty</rs> has established in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. But I
take the liberty to say that many of these officers are too young and
inexperienced to be entrusted with the difficult work of dealing with
native races. They are ignorant of native character, lack wisdom,
justice, fortitude and patience. They have estranged the natives from
<fw>101</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
<rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government, have sown the seed of discord between
tribes and villages, and some of them have stained the uniform of the
Belgian officer with murder, arson and robbery. Other officers have
served the State faithfully, and deserve well of their Royal Master....</p>
<p>From these general observations I wish now to pass to specific
charges against <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government.</p>
<p>FIRST.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government is deficient in the moral,
military and financial strength, necessary to govern a territory of
1,508,000 square miles, 7,251 miles of navigation, and 31,694 square
miles of lake surface. In the <geogName>Lower Congo River</geogName> there is but one
post, in the cataract region one. From <name type="city">Leopoldville</name> to <placeName>N'Gombe</placeName>, a
distance of more than 300 miles, there is not a single soldier or
civilian. Not one out of every twenty State-officials know the language 
of the natives, although they are constantly issuing laws,
difficult even for Europeans, and expect the natives to comprehend
and obey them. Cruelties of the most astounding character are
practised by the natives, such as burying slaves alive in the grave of a
dead chief, cutting off the heads of captured warriors in native combats, 
and no effort is put forth by <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government to
prevent them. Between 800 and 1,000 slaves are sold to be eaten by
the natives of the <country>Congo State</country> annually; and slave raids, accomplished
by the most cruel and murderous agencies, are carried on within the
territorial limits of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government which is impotent.
There are only 2,300 soldiers in the <country>Congo</country>.</p>
<p>SECOND.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government has established nearly
fifty posts, consisting of from two to eight mercenary slave-soldiers
from the East Coast. There is no white commissioned officer at these
posts; they are in charge of the black <country>Zanzibar</country> soldiers, and the State
expects them not only to sustain themselves, but to raid enough to
feed the garrisons where the white men are stationed. These piratical,
buccaneering posts compel the natives to furnish them with fish,
goats, fowls, and vegetables at the mouths of their muskets; and
whenever the natives refuse to feed these vampires, they report to the
main station and white officers come with an expeditionary force and
burn away the homes of the natives. These black soldiers, many of
whom are slaves, exercise the power of life and death. They are
ignorant and cruel, because they do not comprehend the natives;
they are imposed upon them by the State. They make no report as to
the number of robberies they commit, or the number of lives they
take; they are only required to subsist upon the natives and thus
relieve <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government of the cost of feeding them.
They are the greatest curse the country suffers now.</p>
<fw>102</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF  AFRICA</fw>
<p>THIRD.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government is guilty of violating its
contracts made with its soldiers, mechanics and workmen, many of
whom are subjects of other Governments. Their letters never reach
home.</p>
<p>FOURTH.—The Courts of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government are abortive,
unjust, partial and delinquent. I have personally witnessed and
examined their clumsy operations. The laws printed and circulated in
Europe "for the protection of the blacks" in the Congo, are a dead
letter and a fraud. I have heard an officer of the Belgian Army
pleading the cause of a white man of low degree who had been
guilty of beating and stabbing a black man, and urging race distinctions 
and prejudices as good and sufficient reasons why his client
should be adjudged innocent. I know of prisoners remaining in
custody for six and ten months because they were not judged. I saw
the white servant of the Governor-General, <rs type="person">CAMILLE JANSSEN</rs>,
detected in stealing a bottle of wine from a hotel table. A few hours
later the Procurer-General searched his room and found many more
stolen bottles of wine and other things, not the property of servants.
No one can be prosecuted in the <country>State of Congo</country> without an order of
the Governor-General, and as he refused to allow his servant to be
arrested, nothing could be done. The black servants in the hotel,
where the wine had been stolen, had been often accused and beaten
for these thefts, and now they were glad to be vindicated. But to the
surprise of every honest man, the thief was sheltered by the Governor-General 
of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government.</p>
<p>FIFTH.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government is excessively cruel to its
prisoners, condemning them, for the slightest offences, to the chain
gang, the like of which cannot be seen in any other Government in the
civilised or uncivilised world. Often these ox-chains eat into the necks
of the prisoners and produce sores about which the flies circle,
aggravating the running wound; so the prisoner is constantly worried.
These poor creatures are frequently beaten with a dried piece of
hippopotamus skin, called a <q>"chicote"</q>, and usually the blood flows
at every stroke when well laid on. But the cruelties visited upon
soldiers and workmen are not to be compared with the sufferings of
the poor natives who, upon the slightest pretext, are thrust into the
wretched prisons here in the <geogName>Upper River</geogName>. I cannot deal with the
dimensions of these prisons in this letter, but will do so in my report
to my Government.</p>
<p>SIXTH.—Women are imported into your Majesty's Government for
immoral purposes. They are introduced by two methods, viz., black
men are dispatched to the <geogName>Portuguese coast</geogName> where they engage these
<fw>103</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
women as mistresses of white men, who pay to the procurer a monthly
sum. The other method is by capturing native women and condemning 
them to seven years' servitude for some imaginary crime against
the State with which the villages of these women are charged. The
State then hires these woman out to the highest bidder, the officers
having the first choice and then the men. Whenever children are
born of such relations, the State maintains that the women being its
property the child belongs to it also. Not long ago a Belgian trader
had a child by a slave-woman of the State, and he tried to secure
possession of it that he might educate it, but the Chief of the Station
where he resided, refused to be moved by his entreaties. At length he
appealed to the Governor-General, and he gave him the woman and
thus the trader obtained the child also. This was, however, an unusual
case of generosity and clemency; and there is only one post that I
know of where there is not to be found children of the civil and
military officers of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government abandoned to
degradation; white men bringing their own flesh and blood under the
lash of a most cruel master, the <country>State of Congo</country>.</p>
<p>SEVENTH.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government is engaged in trade and
commerce, competing with the organised trade companies of <country>Belgium</country>, 
<country>England</country>, <country>France</country>, <country>Portugal</country> and <country>Holland</country>. It taxes all trading
companies and exempts its own goods from export-duty, and makes
many of its officers ivory-traders, with the promise of a liberal commission 
upon all they can buy or get for the State. State soldiers
patrol many villages forbidding the natives to trade with any person
but a State official, and when the natives refuse to accept the price
of the State, their goods are seized by the Government that promised
them <q>"protection"</q>. When natives have persisted in trading with the
trade-companies the State has punished their independence by
burning the villages in the vicinity of the trading houses and driving
the natives away.</p>
<p>EIGHTH.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government has violated the General
Act of the Conference of Berlin by firing upon native canoes; by
confiscating the property of natives; by intimidating native traders,
and preventing them from trading with white trading companies;
by quartering troops in native villages when there is no war; by
causing vessels bound from <placeName>"Stanley-Pool"</placeName> to <placeName>"Stanley-Falls"</placeName>, to
break their journey and leave the <country>Congo</country>, ascend the <geogName>Aruhwimi river</geogName>
to <name type="city">Basoko</name>, to be visited and show their papers; by forbidding a
mission steamer to fly its national flag without permission from a
local Government; by permitting the natives to carry on the slave-trade, 
and by engaging in the wholesale and retail slave-trade itself.</p>
<fw>104</fw>
<fw>HOW NEGRO AMERICANS CAN HELP</fw>
<p>NINTH.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government has been, and is now,
guilty of waging unjust and cruel wars against natives, with the hope
of securing slaves and women, to minister to the behests of the officers
of your Government. In such slave-hunting raids one village is armed
by the State against the other, and the force thus secured is incorporated 
with the regular troops. I have no adequate terms with
which to depict to <rs>your Majesty</rs> the brutal acts of your soldiers
upon such raids as these. The soldiers who open the combat are
usually the bloodthirsty cannibalistic Bangalas, who give no quarter
to the aged grandmother or nursing child at the breast of its mother.
There are instances in which they have brought the heads of their
victims to their white officers on the expeditionary steamers, and
afterwards eaten the bodies of slain children. In one war two Belgian
Army officers saw, from the deck of their steamer, a native in a canoe
some distance away. He was not a combatant and was ignorant of
the conflict in progress upon the shore, some distance away. The
officers made a wager of £5 that they could hit the native with their
rifles. Three shots were fired and the native fell dead, pierced through
the head, and the trade canoe was transformed into a funeral barge
and floated silently down the river. . . .</p>
<p>TENTH.—Your Majesty's Government is engaged in the slave-trade,
wholesale and retail. It buys and sells and steals slaves. <rs>Your
Majesty's</rs> Government gives £3 per head for ablebodied slaves for
military service. Officers at the chief stations get the men and receive
the money when they are transfered to the State; but there are some
middle-men who only get from twenty to twenty-five francs per
head. Three hundred and sixteen slaves were sent down the river
recently, and others are to follow. These poor natives are sent
hundreds of miles away from their villages, to serve among other
natives whose language they do not know. When these men run
away a reward of 1,000 N'taka is offered. Not long ago such a
recaptured slave was given one hundred "chikote" each day until he
died. Three hundred N'taka—brassrod—is the price the State pays
for a slave, when bought from a native. The labour force at the
stations of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government in the Upper River is
composed of slaves of all ages and both sexes.</p>
<p>ELEVENTH.—<rs>Your Majesty's</rs> Government has concluded a contract 
with the Arab Governor at this place for the establishment of a
line of military posts from the <geogName>Seventh Cataract</geogName> to <geogName>Lake Tanganyika</geogName>
territory to which <rs>your Majesty</rs> has no more legal claim, than I have
to be Commander-in-Chief of the Belgian army. For this work the
Arab Governor is to receive five hundred stands of arms, five
<fw>105</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
thousand kegs of powder, and £20,000 sterling, to be paid in several
instalments. As I write, the news reaches me that these much-treasured 
and long-looked for materials of war are to be discharged
at <name type="city">Basoko</name>, and the Resident here is to be given the discretion as to
the distribution of them. There is a feeling of deep discontent among
the Arabs here, and they seem to feel that they are being trifled with.
As to the significance of this move Europe and America can judge
without any comment from me, especially England.</p>
<p>TWELFTH.—The agents of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government have misrepresented 
the <country>Congo</country> country and the <country>Congo</country> railway. <abbr type="title">Mr.</abbr> <rs type="person">H. M.
STANLEY</rs>, the man who was your chief agent in setting up your
authority in this country, has grossly misrepresented the character
of the country. Instead of it being fertile and productive it is sterile
and unproductive. The natives can scarcely subsist upon the vegetable 
life produced in some parts of the country. Nor will this condition 
of affairs change until the native shall have been taught by the
European the dignity, utility and blessing of labour. There is no
improvement among the natives, because there is an impassable
gulf between them and <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government, a gulf which can
never be bridged. <rs type="person">HENRY M. STANLEY'S</rs> name produces a shudder
among this simple folk when mentioned; they remember his broken
promises, his copious profanity, his hot temper, his heavy blows,
his severe and rigorous measures, by which they were mulcted of
their lands. His last appearance in the <country>Congo</country> produced a profound
sensation among them, when he led 500 <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> soldiers with 300
campfollowers on his way to relieve <rs type="person">EMIN PASHA</rs>. They thought it
meant complete subjugation, and they fled in confusion. But the
only thing they found in the wake of his march was misery. No white
man commanded his rear column, and his troops were allowed to
straggle, sicken and die; and their bones were scattered over more
than two hundred miles of territory. . . .</p></div2>
<div2>
<head>CONCLUSIONS</head>
<p>Against the deceit, fraud, robberies, arson, murder, slave-raiding,
and general policy of cruelty of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government to the
natives, stands their record of unexampled patience, long-suffering
and forgiving spirit, which put the boasted civilisation and professed
religion of <rs>your Majesty's</rs> Government to the blush. During thirteen
years only one white man has lost his life by the hands of the natives,
and only two white men have been killed in the <country>Congo</country>. <rs type="person">Major
<fw>106</fw>
<fw>HOW NEGRO AMERICANS CAN HELP</fw>
BARTTELOT</rs> was shot by a <placeName>Zanzibar</placeName> soldier, and the captain of a
Belgian trading-boat was the victim of his own rash and unjust
treatment of a native chief.</p>
<p>All the crimes perpetrated in the <country>Congo</country> have been done in your
name, and you must answer at the bar of Public Sentiment for the
misgovernment of a people, whose lives and fortunes were entrusted
to you by the august Conference of Berlin, 1884-1885. I now appeal
to the Powers which committed this infant State to <rs>your Majesty's</rs>
charge, and to the great States which gave it international being; and
whose majestic law you have scorned and trampled upon, to call and
create an International Commission to investigate the charges
herein preferred in the name of Humanity, Commerce, Constitutional 
Government and Christian Civilisation.</p>
<p>I base this appeal upon the terms of Article 36 of Chapter VII of
the General Act of the Conference of Berlin, in which that august
assembly of Sovereign States reserved to themselves the right <q>"to
introduce into it later and by common accord the modifications or
ameliorations, the utility of which may be demonstrated experience"</q>.</p>
<p>I appeal to the Belgian people and to their Constitutional Government, 
so proud of its traditions, replete with the song and story of its
champions of human liberty, and so jealous of its present position in
the sisterhood of European States—to cleanse itself from the imputation 
of the crimes with which <rs>your Majesty's</rs> personal <country>State of
Congo</country> is polluted.</p>
<p>I appeal to Anti-Slavery Societies in all parts of Christendom, to
Philanthropists, Christians, Statesmen, and to the great mass of
people everywhere, to call upon the Governments of Europe, to
hasten the close of the tragedy your Majesty's unlimited Monarchy
is enacting in the <country>Congo</country>.</p>
<p>I appeal to our Heavenly Father, whose service is perfect love, in
witness of the purity of my motives and the integrity of my aims; and
to history and mankind I appeal for the demonstration and vindication 
of the truthfulness of the charge I have herein briefly outlined.</p>
<p>And all this upon the word of honour of a gentleman, I subscribe
myself your Majesty's humble and obedient servant,</p>
<p>Geo. W. Williams</p>
<p><name type="city">Stanley Falls,</name> <placeName>Central Africa</placeName>,</p>
<p><date when="1890-07-18">July 18th, 1890.</date></p>
<fw>107</fw>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>