<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="llg.con.050.01">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>New York Times, "England Firm on Congo"</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Locating Lord Greystoke</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">llg.con.050.01</idno>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">England Firm on Congo</title>
<title level="j">New York Times</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<biblScope type="page">4</biblScope>
<date when="1908-02-27">February 27, 1908</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Newspaper</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="labels">
<term/>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="llg.con.050.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-11-13" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-10-02" who="#kln">Initial encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<div2 type="titles">

<p>England Firm on Congo.</p>

<p>House of Commons Will Support Government Move to Transfer Control.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>London, Feb. 26. -- The House of Commons to-night, after a short debate, adopted a very strong resolution relating to the <placeName key="con" n="mapped"><country type="colony">Congo Free State</country></placeName>.</p>

<p>The resolution asks the Government to do all in its power to bring about the transfer of the control of the Congo region, and assures the Government that if it shall fail to accomplish this transfer in a diplomatic way within a reasonable time the House will heartily support it in any measures it may take, either alone or in conjunction with the powers that signed the Berlin Act, to insure the effective carrying out of the provisions of that act.</p>

<p>Speeches on both sides of the House severely indicted the existing administration of the Congo Independent State and urged the Government to take steps to leave the Belgian Government in no doubt regarding the settled determination of the people to assert Great Britain's treaty rights.</p>

<p>Sir Edward Grey, Secretary for Foreign Affairs, in a speech sympathizing with the terms of the resolution, repudiated on behalf of the Government any desire to establish political or territorial claims, or do anything directed against the Belgian people. No transfer, he said, would be satisfactory unless it gave the Belgian Parliament a free hand and full control. It would be impossible for Great Britain to take the initiative while the discussion on the Congo question was proceeding between King Leopold and his people.</p>

<p>"But," he added, "this Government will always welcome and co-operation of the other powers, and if at the close of the Belgian Parliament session we have to deal with the existing government of the Congo unchanged, we must be free to deal with the questions arising out of our own treaty rights in our own way." </p>

<p>Earl Percy, on behalf of the opposition, expressed approval of Sir Edward's statement, and the resolution was adopted without division.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
