<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="llg.con.009.01">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Origin of the Congo Free State, Considered from the Standpoint of International Law</title>
<author n="Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942">Jesse Siddall Reeves</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Locating Lord Greystoke</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">llg.con.009.01</idno>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Origin of the Congo Free State, Considered from the Standpoint of International Law</title>
<author n="Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942">Jesse Siddall Reeves</author>
<date when="1909-01">January 1909</date>
<title level="j" type="main">The American Journal of International Law</title>
<biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
<biblScope type="pages">103-118</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="labels">
<term/>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Lake Tanganyika</term>
<term>Sudan</term> <!-- not sure if referring to a river or the country? not encoded for mapping at this time -->
<term>Zambezi River</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="llg.con.009.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-11-13" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-08-20" who="#kln">Initial transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Origin of the Congo Free State, Considered from the Standpoint of International Law</head>

<head type="sub">By Jesse Siddall Reeves</head>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about four pages">
<desc>irrelevant to author's discussion</desc>
</gap>

<p>Leopold declared that he had no selfish or ulterior aim,
and, although it has been charged that at this early date, when there
was no exact geographical knowledge of central Africa, he had
colonial aspirations for Belgium,<ref type="footnote" target="n01">1</ref> there seems to be no conclusive
evidence to prove the assertion. This conference resulted in the
organization known as L'Association Internationale pour l'Exploration
et la Civilisation de l'Afrique Centrale," or, shortly, L'Association
Internationale Africaine. It had at the outset three objects:
First, to explore scientifically the unknown parts of Africa; second,
to facilitate the opening of roads by which civilization might be
introduced into central Africa; and, third, to find means of suppressing
the negro slave trade in Africa. The methods for the
attainment of these objects were (1) an organization "upon one
common international plan" for the exploration of Africa from
ocean to ocean and from the <placeName key="riv.zam" n="mapped"><geogName type="river">Zambesi</geogName></placeName> to the Soudan, and (2) the
establishment of scientific and relief stations within this territory.
Both of the objects were therefore, scientific and humanitarian. The
methods were to be international, i. e., distinctly nonpolitical. An
important and perhaps significant action was the adoption of a flag
to cover the proposed expeditions and the stations to be established.
At the time this flag was to have a status, if possible, like that of the
Red Cross.<ref type="footnote" target="n02">2</ref> An international commission was instituted which held
a meeting in June, 1877, to formulate further plans. Tn addition to
various national committees of the association there was to be an
executive committee, resident at Brussels, under the immediate direction
of Leopold, to which the several national committees were to
send funds for the prosecution of the work. After the session of
June, 1877, the International Commission seems to have done nothing.
The various national committees had little or no vitality at any
time. What activity Leopold's interest aroused outside of Belgium
took the form of national or private expeditions. The Belgian committee,
however, energized by Leopold, sent an expedition to <placeName key="lak.tan" n="mapped"><geogName type="lake">Tanganyika</geogName></placeName>, which had few results, geographical or otherwise. It served,
however, to give continuity to the organization and to, perpetuate the
name of the association.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about three pages"/>

<p>In 1884 its territorial claims were large; it comprised the territory
south of the Congo and drained by that river and its affluents. But
up to the time of the Berlin Conference there had been no delimitation
of its territories. Its population was numerous, it is true, having
been estimated at from eleven to thirty millions. But these were the
blacks, subject to their own primitive rule of life, dwelling in more
or less settled fashion in tribal organizations, just as they had for
centuries. Of the whites there were at this time about two hundred
and fifty, nearly all of whom were in the service of the association.
How many of the blacks were conscious of the existence of the
alleged sovereign authority of the association, there is no evidence.
Later events lead one to think that they were few. Some of these
were tribes which resisted, more or less successfully, all exercise of
that authority. Outside the small spheres of the various stations, no
actual control over the natives was at first attempted. The association
was not even able at all times to maintain uninterrupted communication
among its stations. What organization there was for the
purpose of enforcing the sovereign will, or of political administration,
was the company of two hundred and fifty whites, one white
person for each one hundred thousand or so of blacks. Nor was the
association in any wise "self-contained." It was directed from
Brussels and sustained out of Leopold's private purse. Even as to
the whites there is nothing to show that they were bound by any tie
of political allegiance to the association. Each servant or officer was
recruited for a certain number of years' service. It has never been
contended that any of the Belgians in its service foreswore allegiance
to Belgium, substituting therefor an allegiance to the International
Association of the Congo.<ref type="footnote" target="n03">3</ref></p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about one page"/>

<p>Whether led by the belief that Leopold was doing his work for
the benefit of England,<ref type="footnote" target="n04">4</ref> or in order to check the growing colonial
power of France, Lord Granville found himself the center of attack
when he signed the Anglo-Portuguese treaty of February 26, 1884.
The date may be taken as the terminus a quo of the really political
significance of the Congo project. This treaty recognized the hitherto
shadowy title of Portugal to that part of the African west coast
through which the <placeName key="riv.con" n="mapped"><geogName type="river">Congo River</geogName></placeName> debouches, between 5° 12' and 8°
south latitude. This volte-face on the part of Great Britain, which
had previously denied Portugal's claims, was denounced by the
British press and in Parliament. Leopold appealed to Granville to
wait before acting, in order to inquire into the validity of the treaties
between Stanley and the native chiefs.<ref type="footnote" target="n05">5</ref> More important still were
the protests of the continental powers. France declared that she
would not be bound by the treaty (March 13). Germany served a
like notice (April 18).<ref type="footnote" target="n06">6</ref> The Anglo-Portuguese treaty, therefore,
allowed France and Germany to make common cause against the
power which would have deprived Leopold of an outlet from his territories.
While Great Britain and Portugal had agreed upon a joint
commission for the Congo River, Germany and France came forward
with a proposition for an international commission for the river,
such as had been considered some time before by the Institute of
International Law. These two Powers were drawn into an entente
by which Leopold would surely be the gainer.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about four pages"/>

<p>It is impossible within the limits of the present paper to enter
into detail as to the results of the Berlin Conference as embodied
in its General Act. The scope of the meeting was broader than
Bismarck had originally suggested. Certain parts of the General
Act refer particularly to the regime for the Congo, though nowhere
is the Congo Association mentioned. The terms of the General Act
are general and affect all territories with the so-called "conventional
free-trade zone" as defined by the act. That tho conference applied
its stipulations to a territory larger than the mere geographical <placeName key="bas.con" n="mapped"><geogName type="basin">basin
of the Congo</geogName></placeName> was due to the initiative of the American representatives.
Mr. Kasson suggested that the "commercial basin" of the
Congo should be considered, rather than the geographical one. Stanley
urged this plan, but was surprised to notice" a curious reluctance
to speak, as if there was some grand scheme of state involved."<ref type="footnote" target="n07">7</ref> A matter of policy was indeed involved, for by adopting the so-called
"conventional zone" of the Congo, all powers having territory
within it were affected. The provisions of the General Act were
thereby made to apply not only to Belgian and French Congo, but
practically to all territory between the Atlantic and Indian oceans,
from the Zambesi to 5° north latitude on the east, and from 2° 30'
north latitude to 80° south latitude on the west. Within this territory
there was to be absolute freedom of commerce. No power
which exercised rights of sovereignty within the zone was to grant
monopolies or privileges of any kind in commercial matters.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about two pages"/>

<p>Freedom from import duties in the conventional zone, while making
for commercial freedom, seriously handicapped the <placeName key="con" n="mapped"><country type="colony">Congo Free
State</country></placeName> in its internal administration by cutting off a large and necessary
source of income. In 1890 the representatives of the powers
again assembled, this time at Brussels. The ostensible purpose
of this meeting was to take further steps for the suppression of the
slave trade. Before the Brussels Conference had progressed far,
it developed that an attempt would be made to modify the onerous
restrictions of the former act in reference to import duties. A provision
for limited import duties was after long debate duly incorporated
in the Brussels General Act, for the purpose of better enabling
the Free State to wipe out the slave trade. In other respects
the Berlin Act stands to-day. The impression has been general that
the provisions of that act have been violated j that within late years,
at least, the natives have been treated with no due regard for their
"moral and material amelioration," such as the act prescribed. When
charges of violation of the spirit of the Berlin Act were brought
against the Congo Free State answer was made either by way of
general denial or by a "tu quoque" argument, or else that if there
had been some necessary disregard of the means of moral or of
material regeneration, the State was within its right, as it was sovereign
and independent; that as such sovereign and independent
state it was the sole judge of the truth or falsity of the charges. Of
course there were other answers, but these three groups comprise
most of them. The force of public opinion, however, resulted in
the appointment of a commission for the investigation of the charges
of maladministration. This commission reported upon certain grave
abuses in the form of labor taxes and of unrestricted forced services
demanded both by the State and by the State's concessionary
companies. Slowly -- too slowly for many active reformers -- public
sentiment became a force which the absolute sovereign of the Congo
did not withstand. A new conference which might review the whole
question of the condition of the natives in the conventional zone,
both within and without. the Congo Free State, was declined by
certain of the continental powers when Great Britain proposed it
in 1903. The only remaining sanction was that of ultranational
public opinion. This, voiced in protests by more than one government,
was reflected in Belgium. Leopold had as early as 1889
devised the Congo to Belgium. Later he agreed to permit Belgium
to annex it if she so desired, after a term of years. After long negotiations
between Belgium and Leopold, the Congo Free State now
passes out of existence and becomes in fact what it should have
been long ago, a Belgian colony. As a colony it will be subject to
government by discussion. In that country where party strife is
active, where liberal ideas find such ready expression, responsible
parliamentary government must surely be a guaranty that the provisions
of the Berlin Act will be observed in spirit as well as in letter.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="one paragraph"/>

</div1>

</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<note xml:id="n01">1. Keltie, The Partition of Africa (1st ed.), 119.</note>
<note xml:id="n02">2. E. Banning, Africa and the Brussels Conference, London, 1877, 155.</note>
<note xml:id="n03">3. Naturalization in the Congo Free State was established in 1892 by a decree of Leopold of December 27 of that year. Lycops, Les Codes Congolais, 161.</note>
<note xml:id="n04">4. Keltie, The Partition of Africa, 1st ed., 143, who quotes an unnamed source for the statement.</note>
<note xml:id="n05">5. Boulger, The Congo State, 42.</note>
<note xml:id="n06">6. Cattier, ep. cit., 25, makes the unsupported assertion that Holland and the United States also protested.</note>
<note xml:id="n07">7. Stanley, The Congo, II, 304.</note>
</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI>
