<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="llg.ber.002.02">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Congo Treaty. Analysis</title>
<author n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>Locating Lord Greystoke</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">llg.ber.002.02</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>

<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Berlin Conference</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="document" target="llg.ber.002.01">Document</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-08-05" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<div2 type="bibliography">
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Congo Treaty</title>
<author n="Bright, Jacob">Jacob Bright</author>
<title level="j">Bristol Selected Pamphlets</title>
<date when="1884">1884</date>
<note type="source">http://www.jstor.org/stable/60243738</note>
<biblScope type="part">portions of the pamphlet relating to the Berlin Conference</biblScope>
</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>Jacob Bright (1821-1899) was a member of the British Parliament, representing the Borough of Manchester from 1867-1874 and from 1876-1885. From 1886-1895, he represented the Southwest Division of Manchester. Bright was a Liberal who challenged Prime Minister William Ewart Gladstone's support of a treaty that would recognize Portugal's control over both sides of the Congo River. Bright successfully prevented ratification of the Congo Treaty in the House of Commons. The <ref type="internal" target="llg.ber.001.01">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref> would later insure the freedom of commerce on the Congo.<ref type="footnote" target="n00.01">1</ref> Bright's article lays out a case for rejecting the treaty, in part by depicting the Portuguese as greedy, depraved rulers incapable of developing "commerce and civilization" on the continent. He surveys Portuguese contact with Africa since the fifteenth century and concludes that the places in Africa where commerce thrives are free from Portuguese influence.</p>

<p>While Jacob Bright wrote this article eight months before the convening of the Berlin Conference in the winter of 1884, he raises many questions about the freedom of navigation and commerce in the Congo region. Essentially, his opposition to the Congo Treaty signed by Great Britain and Portugal anticipated the issues that the Berlin conferees would debate&#8212;chief among them, whether or not Portugal would continue to wield control over the Congo River and its tributaries with access to the Atlantic Ocean and the Congo Basin.</p>


<div3 xml:id="llg.ber.002.01.e001">

<head type="sub">Vivi &amp; Stanley Pool</head>

<p>Stanley Pool (present-day Malebo Pool) is "a lake-like expansion of the lower Congo River above Livingstone Falls, between the [present-day] Republic of the Congo (Brazzaville) to the west and the [present-day] Democratic Republic of the Congo (Kinshasa) to the east." The Pool, renamed by the <orgName key="int.ass">International Association of the Congo</orgName> (IAC) after explorer <persName key="stanley.henry">Henry Morton Stanley</persName>, was of strategic important to those seeking access to various rivers in the Congo region. E. Delmar Morgan, noted traveler and fellow of the Royal Geographical Society, wrote in 1884 that "[u]pwards of 5000 miles of navigable rivers are accessible from Stanley Pool; three steamers are already launched on its waters, and accompanied Stanley on his last expedition, while a fourth is on its way out." Vivi was established as a station/trading post in 1879 by Stanley and the Comit&#233; d'&#201;tudes du Haut-Congo. Vivi later became the capital of the Congo Free State. As Bright notes, there was no direct route from Vivi to Stanley Pool. While both sites fell under the control of the IAC, the Berlin conferees would have to determine whether they were subject to free navigation and free commerce.<ref type="footnote" target="n01.01">2</ref></p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="llg.ber.002.01.e002">

<head type="sub">Kinsembo &amp; Ambriz</head>

<p>The Portuguese&#8212;led by the governor of Angola, Jos&#233; Coelho do Amaral&#8212;seized Ambriz in 1855. A port town under African rule, Ambriz had access to the Loge River, which flows directly into the Atlantic Ocean. After the Portuguese occupation of the town, Ambriz and Luanda served as the main ports for Portuguese trade and constituted part of the buffer zone that separated the Portuguese kingdom of Angola from the indigenous kingdom of Kongo. Former British slave traders in the region such as Sir John Tobin and Charles Horsfall turned to "legitimate trade," primarily in palm oil, after the abolition of the slave trade in 1807. Horsfall, Tobin, and Edward Hatton Cookson had established palm oil factories in Ambriz in 1845; however, all three factories moved to Kinsembo in 1856. In this excerpt, Bright points out that in 1856, the Crown authorized its navy to prevent Portuguese attempts to extend its territory beyond Ambriz. He quotes Lord John Russell, Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (1865–1866), who in 1860 warned the Portuguese that if they continued to impinge on British trading rights in the region, war might ensue. In 1876, after the formation of what became the Congo Free State, Lord Derby reiterated that the British would protect its rights to trade in the region based at Kinsembo. The Berlin Conference, in calling for the freedom of navigation of the Congo and Niger Rivers, in effect settled the dispute between Great Britain and Portugal over access to the Congo Basin.<ref type="footnote" target="n02.01">3</ref></p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="llg.ber.002.01.e003">

<head type="sub">St. Thomas Island &amp; Luanda</head>

<p>The Portuguese landed on St. Thomas Island (known primarily as S&#227;o Tom&#233; Island) in 1471, but did not establish a settlement until 1493. Portuguese explorer Paulo Dias de Novais founded Loando (Luanda) in 1576. Both the Island and Luanda (which would become the capital of Angola) were centers for the Portuguese slave trade from Africa to Brazil. The Portuguese abolished the transatlantic slave trade in 1836; however, Bright cites Lord Mayo who witnessed slave trading routed between St. Thomas and Luanda. Abolishing the interior and coastal slave trades in West and Central Africa, which Bright claimed benefited the Portuguese exclusively, became a focal point of the Berlin Conference.<ref type="footnote" target="n03.01">4</ref></p>


</div3>


<div3 xml:id="llg.ber.002.01.e004">

<head type="sub">Zanzibar</head>

<p>Zanzibar is an island off the coast of East Africa and was one of the Swahili city-states, which were part of the vast Indian Ocean trading networks in ancient times. In the fourth century, Greek merchants traded with Zanzibar. From about 1000-1500 CE, the Arab and Muslim influences on Zanzibar increased and some indigenous merchants became Muslim, although many claimed Persian heritage. When the Portuguese arrived in the fifteenth century, they effectively took control of the trade and annexed Zanzibar into its empire circa 1504. In 1698, the Sultanate of Oman wrested Zanzibar from Portuguese control. Bright mocks the Portuguese for "losing" Zanzibar to the "Arabs." He claims that the trade from Zanzibar controlled by the "natives" (Kiswahili-speaking peoples) is nearly ten times that of the trade coming from Mozambique under Portuguese control. During the Berlin Conference, free trade in the "Conventional Congo Basin" included Zanzibar; however, the Sultan of Zanzibar (who was not invited to the Conference) claimed sovereignty over the eastern part of Africa from the island to Lake Tanganyika, which ostensibly would require merchants to pay duties to trade in his territory. While Bright appears to approve of the trade flourishing under the sultanate, the conferees saw the Sultan as a menace to free "legitimate" trade in East Africa citing his sanctioning of the East African slave trade along the "Swahili coast." In 1890, the British declared Zanzibar a protectorate, after the slave trade had been abolished according to the dictates of the <ref type="internal" target="#llg.ber.001.001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref>.<ref type="footnote" target="n04.01">5</ref></p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="llg.ber.002.01.e005">

<head type="sub">Ambriz &amp; Kinsembo</head>

<p>The Portuguese&#8212;led by the governor of Angola, Jos&#233; Coelho do Amaral&#8212;seized Ambriz in 1855. A port town under African rule, Ambriz had access to the Loge River, which flows directly into the Atlantic Ocean. After the Portuguese occupation of the town, Ambriz and Luanda served as the main ports for Portuguese trade and constituted part of the buffer zone that separated the Portuguese kingdom of Angola from the indigenous kingdom of Kongo. Former British slave traders in the region such as Sir John Tobin and Charles Horsfall turned to "legitimate trade," primarily in palm oil, after the abolition of the slave trade in 1807. Horsfall, Tobin, and Edward Hatton Cookson had established palm oil factories in Ambriz in 1845; however, all three factories moved to Kinsembo in 1856. In this excerpt, Bright points out that in 1856, the Crown authorized its navy to prevent Portuguese attempts to extend its territory beyond Ambriz. He quotes Lord John Russell, Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (1865–1866), who in 1860 warned the Portuguese that if they continued to impinge on British trading rights in the region, war might ensue. In 1876, after the formation of what became the Congo Free State, Lord Derby reiterated that the British would protect its rights to trade in the region based at Kinsembo. The Berlin Conference, in calling for the freedom of navigation of the Congo and Niger Rivers, in effect settled the dispute between Great Britain and Portugal over access to the Congo Basin.<ref type="footnote" target="n05.01">6</ref></p>

</div3>


</div2>

</div1>

</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<note xml:id="n00.01">1. "<ref type="external" target="http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=F00915F83C5911738DDDA00894D9415B8985F0D3">Jacob Bright Dead</ref>," <hi rend="italics">The New York Times</hi> November 9, 1899.</note>


<note xml:id="n01.01">2. <hi rend="italics">Encyclop&#230;dia Britannica Online,</hi> s. v. <ref type="external" target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/359978/Malebo-Pool">"Malebo Pool,"</ref> accessed January 7, 2014; E. Delmar Morgan, "Notes on the Lower Congo, from Its Mouth to Stanley Pool," <hi rend="italics">Proceedings of the Royal Geographical Society and Monthly Record of Geography</hi> vol. 6, no. 4 (April 1884), 193; Ch. Didier Gondola, <hi rend="italics">The History of Congo Greenwood Histories of the Modern Nations</hi> (Westport, CT: Greenwood Press, 2002), 75; Mumbanza Mwa Bawele, "Afro-European Relations in the Western Congo Basin, c. 1884-1885" in Stig F&#246;rster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 471-473.</note>

<note xml:id="n02.01">3. Martin Lynn, "Change and Continuity in the British Palm Oil Trade with West Africa, 1830-55," <hi rend="italics">The Journal of African History</hi> 22, no. 3 (1981), 340-346, fn. 27.</note>

<note xml:id="n03.01">4. Gervase Clarence-Smith, "The Portuguese and Spanish Roles in the Scramble for Africa: An Economic Interpretation" in Stig F&#246;rster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 219.</note>

<note xml:id="n04.01">5. Julius O. Adekunle, "East African States" in Toyin Falola, ed., <hi rend="italics">Africa: Volume 1, African History Before 1885</hi> (Durham, North Carolina: Carolina Academic Press, 2000), 193, 196-197, 203-204; Imanuel Geiss, "Free Trade, Internationalization of the Congo, and the Principle of Effective Occupation," in Stig F&#246;rster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 276; John Iliffe, <hi rend="italics">Africans: The History of a Continent</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995), 192.</note>

<note xml:id="n05.01">6. Martin Lynn, "Change and Continuity in the British Palm Oil Trade with West Africa, 1830-55," <hi rend="italics">The Journal of African History</hi> 22, no. 3 (1981), 340-346, fn. 27.</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>
</TEI>