<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>
George W. Williams, "1862--Emancipation Day--1884; The Negro as a Political Problem"
</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0013</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">1862--Emancipation Day--1884; The Negro as a Political Problem</title>
<title level="m">Apropos of Africa: Sentiments of Negro American Leaders on Africa from the 1800s to the 1950s</title>
<author n="Williams, George W.">George W. Williams</author>
<editor/>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<publisher>A. Mudge &amp; Son, printers, 1884</publisher>
<date when="1884">1884</date>
<biblScope unit="page">44-47</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Book</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019" who="sab">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p00" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.000"/>

<p>1862--EMANCIPATION DAY--1884</p>

<p>The Negro as a Political Problem.</p>

<p>ORATION
BY THE
HON. GEORGE W. WILLIAMS,
OR MASSACHUSETTES,
AT THE
ASBURY CHURCH, WAHSINGTON, D.C.,
APRIL 16, 1884.</p>

<ab>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA
PROPERTY OF 
LIBRARY
AT CHAPEL HILL</ab>

<p>"From every hill instict with life is sent
Gratitude-- a mental saerament,
That from their neck they loosen'd felt the yoke--
That the first link in slavery's chain was broke."</p>

<p>BOSTON:
ALFRED MUDGE &amp; SON, PRINTERS,
No. 24 FRANKLIN STREET.
1884.</p>

<pb xml:id="p01" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.001"/>

<p>ORATION.</p>

<p>THE NEGRO AS A POLITICAL PROBLEM.</p>

<p>Mr. President, Ladies and Gentlemen:
From the waters of the Potomac to the liberty-
crowned dome of the Capitol of the nation the bells of
liberty have been ringing. The prayer of gratitude has
been said, and the dirge has been sung at the tomb of
slavery. The stirring strains of martial music, the
swinging battalions of troops, the citizens in holiday at-
tire, the bright faces and glad voices of the day, proclaim
this an occasion of more than ordinary interest. And
now, at the close of this anniversary day, while the
pride, pomp, and circumstance of the occasion pass to
their place in history, let us turn to the muse of medita-
tion. Under this sacred shelter, whose platform has
been the fortress of every honest and humane interest,
we may find all the conditions friendly to reflection and
instruction. Experience holds in lifted hand the flam-
ing torch of knowledge, while our hearts know full
well the serious lessons this day would teach us. There
are but two rational reasons for going back into the
past: one is where we can gather the fadeless flowers</p>

<pb xml:id="p02" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.002"/>

<p>2

of memory whose aroma may yet cheer the present ;
the other is where the bitter herbs of experience may
act as a tonic upon a debilitated moral effort amid the
living issues of the present.
Few, indeed, and odorless and colorless, are the flowers of memory that we as a race care to turn back and
pluck. Passion flowers innumerable we might find.
But were we to turn and touch them, every stamen and
petal would instantly become vocal with a thousand
tongues. They would tell the story of tribes cheated,
villages burned, and murder perpetrated by the remorseless hand of gain. They would relate the story
of the middle passage, of young men and innocent
maidens, of old men and helpless women, forced into
the horrible middle passage; how that the ocean
became a voracious sepulchre for hundreds of thousands of the hapless victims of the slave-trade, and will
forever chant a ceaseless requiem over their watery
grave; they would voice the deep plaint of innocent
womanhood led into captivity, of broken hearts and
sundered families; they Would tell the long and mournful story of a race's wrongs and sufferings, — of hope
and piety, love and fear ; we should hear how the race
was mobbed in the Korth and sold at the South ; how
malice and vengeance, lash, knife, gun, dungeon, fire,
water, and insanity, performed their hateful work. God
forbid that we should undertake so dreadful a task!
For were we thus to review the past we would find little else save a cemetery. And as we walked abroad we
should find naught but graves of buried rights, hopes,</p>

<pb xml:id="p03" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.003"/>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>