<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>
George W. Williams, "The Negro as a Political Problem" (1884)
</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0013</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">1862--Emancipation Day--1884; The Negro as a Political Problem</title>
<title level="m">Apropos of Africa: Sentiments of Negro American Leaders on Africa from the 1800s to the 1950s</title>
<author n="Williams, George W.">George W. Williams</author>
<editor/>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<publisher>A. Mudge &amp; Son, printers, 1884</publisher>
<date when="1884">1884</date>
<biblScope unit="page">44-47</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Book</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019" who="sab">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p000" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.000"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>1862--Emancipation Day--1884</p>

<p>The Negro as a Political Problem.</p>

<p>Oration
by the
Hon. George W. Williams,
of Massachusettes,
at the
Asbury Church, Washington, D.C.,
April 16, 1884.</p>

<p>"From every hill instinct with life is sent<lb/>
Gratitude--a mental sacrament,<lb/>
That from their neck they loosen'd felt the yoke--<lb/>
That the first link in slavery's chain was broke."</p>

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.001"/>

<p>Oration.</p>

<p>The Negro as a Political Problem.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Mr. President, Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>

<p>From the waters of the Potomac to the liberty-crowned 
dome of the Capitol of the nation the bells of
liberty have been ringing. The prayer of gratitude has
been said, and the dirge has been sung at the tomb of
slavery. The stirring strains of martial music, the
swinging battalions of troops, the citizens in holiday attire, 
the bright faces and glad voices of the day, proclaim
this an occasion of more than ordinary interest. And
now, at the close of this anniversary day, while the
pride, pomp, and circumstance of the occasion pass to
their place in history, let us turn to the muse of meditation. 
Under this sacred shelter, whose platform has
been the fortress of every honest and humane interest,
we may find all the conditions friendly to reflection and
instruction. Experience holds in lifted hand the flaming 
torch of knowledge, while our hearts know full
well the serious lessons this day would teach us. There
are but two rational reasons for going back into the
past: one is where we can gather the fadeless flowers</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.002"/>

<p>2

of memory whose aroma may yet cheer the present;
the other is where the bitter herbs of experience may
act as a tonic upon a debilitated moral effort amid the
living issues of the present.</p>

<p>Few, indeed, and odorless and colorless, are the flowers 
of memory that we as a race care to turn back and
pluck. Passion flowers innumerable we might find.
But were we to turn and touch them, every stamen and
petal would instantly become vocal with a thousand
tongues. They would tell the story of tribes cheated,
villages burned, and murder perpetrated by the remorseless 
hand of gain. They would relate the story
of the middle passage, of young men and innocent
maidens, of old men and helpless women, forced into
the horrible middle passage; how that the ocean
became a voracious sepulchre for hundreds of thousands 
of the hapless victims of the slave-trade, and will
forever chant a ceaseless requiem over their watery
grave; they would voice the deep plaint of innocent
womanhood led into captivity, of broken hearts and
sundered families; they would tell the long and mournful 
story of a race's wrongs and sufferings,--of hope
and piety, love and fear; we should hear how the race
was mobbed in the North and sold at the South; how
malice and vengeance, lash, knife, gun, dungeon, fire,
water, and insanity, performed their hateful work. God
forbid that we should undertake so dreadful a task!
For were we thus to review the past we would find little 
else save a cemetery. And as we walked abroad we
should find naught but graves of buried rights, hopes,

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.003"/>

and loves; of manly aspirations foully murdered, and 
pious protests cruelly strangled. Over such terrible 
things we must let the pall drop. We must turn only 
to those facts of history that may act as a tonic and 
inspiration for the discharge of duties present and 
future.</p> 

<p>SLAVERY IN THIS DISTRICT 
was always an anomaly. The District was ceded to 
the United States government by Maryland and Virginia; 
but the portion belonging to Virginia was subsequently 
ceded back to that State. Thus the District 
was ceded entirely by Maryland. This was consummated 
in 1790, and comprised sixty-four square miles. 
In 1634 the Colony of Maryland was formed out of a 
portion of the territory belonging to Virginia. And 
Maryland, as the other Southern Colonies, held slaves 
until the war for the Union destroyed the institution. 
When Congress appointed a committee to secure a permanent 
seat for the government, instructions were also 
given to provide a place where it should have authority 
also. This was done; and in December, 1800, the Congress 
of the United States moved into the District.</p>
 
<p>In the articles of concession, the people then living 
in the District of Columbia did not reserve any vested 
rights. They had no indefeasible possessory right to 
slave property. There was nothing in the Constitution 
justifying the existence of the evil at the very seat of 
the American government. So, then, the crime was 
permitted for more than sixty years.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.004"/>

<p>The following table exhibits the number of free and bond persons of color in the District for the space of six decades:--</p>
 
<table>
<row>
<cell>Year.</cell>
<cell>Free Negroes.</cell>
<cell>Slave Negroes.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1800</cell>
<cell>490</cell>
<cell>3,244</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1810</cell>
<cell>1,527</cell>
<cell>5,395</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1820</cell>
<cell>2,758</cell>
<cell>6,377</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1830</cell>
<cell>4,604</cell>
<cell>6,119</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1840</cell>
<cell>6,499</cell>
<cell>4,694</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1850</cell>
<cell>10,059</cell>
<cell>3,687</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1860</cell>
<cell>11,131</cell>
<cell>3,181</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>In 1870 there were 43,404 Negroes in the District; 
and in 1880, 59,596.</p>
 
<p>That it was clearly within the power of Congress to 
abolish it no clear-headed statesman ever doubted. It 
was tolerated in the States because the people had the 
right to support it by State Constitution, or abolish it 
by amendment. But all government territory was 
under the immediate and absolute control of Congress.
If it were claimed by Northern apologists that the 
Union could not have been formed except slavery were 
allowed in the Southern States, there was certainly no 
good excuse for tolerating the crime in the District of 
Columbia. And yet for more than two generations 
slavery built its altars under the aegis of the American 
Capitol; the slave-hound bayed his human victims, and 
the black shadow of the accursed institution sent a chill 
of death through thousands of hearts.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p005" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.005"/>

<p>In 1800, as we have shown, there were 3,244 slaves in 
the District of Columbia. Ten years later the slave 
population had increased to 5,3^)5, in 1820 it was 6,877, 
in 1830 it was 6,119, in 1840 it was 4,694, in 1850 it 
was 3,687, and in 1860 there were only 3,186. By these 
figures we see that at the end of six decades there were 
less slaves in the District than there were at the beginning 
of the century. The largest number was in 1820, 
6,377. This was the year in which the Missouri Compromise 
occasioned so much excitement. From that 
year down to the breaking out of the Rebellion, the 
slave population was on a steady decrease. Slavery, 
existing within the District without sanction of law, 
attracted the attention of anti-slavery men from the beginning. 
In 1827 William Lloyd Garrison began his career 
as an anti-slavery agitator by addressing a petition 
to Congress for the abolition of slavery in the District 
of Columbia. The friends of freedom saw the glaring 
inconsistency of allowing the slave-trade to go on at 
the capital of a free republic, and thus they felt it to be 
a patriotic duty to labor for the abolition of the evil in 
the District. But the influence of the South was overwhelming. 
Avarice and cotton were more than a match 
for humanity, and the clank of the slaves' chains was 
heard in your streets. Justice tarried; the nation 
halted at its plain, constitutional duty, and failed to use 
its authority. The years flew apace, until at last even-handed 
justice lifted the bitter chalice of war to the 
nation's lips.</p>
 
<p>The shock of embattled arms, that had been the nation's

<pb xml:id="p006" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.006"/>

lullaby, was heard in dreadful reverberations 
throughout the land. A year of an unbroken series 
of Union disasters humbled the national pride. While 
the nation was struggling and gasping for life, while 
all the powers of Congress were invoked to tear, one 
by one, the steel fingers of armed rebellion from the 
nation's throat, in the slave marts of the capital bonds-men, 
with brows beaded with the sweat of unrequited 
toil, lifted their pinioned hands to yon goddess of liberty 
in vain. The heart of the nation was as hard as 
the brazen images on the Capitol that had witnessed for 
years that the Constitution of this great Republic was a 
tissue of lies. The national treasury was depleted; the 
bonds were depreciated; the commerce that had 
whitened all seas had largely disappeared; the workshops 
were deserted; treason lurked in the high places; 
the rebel forces were closing in upon the capital, and 
the red fields of inglorious conflict admonished the 
Congress to wipe the foul stain of slavery from the 
District of Columbia.</p>

<p>THE MORAL EFFECT 
of emancipation in the District of Columbia was marked. 
Anti-slavery men regarded this as the entering wedge. 
It was the thermometer of Congressional patriotism; it 
was the glorious reward of patient and consistent labor; 
it was the answer to agonizing prayers,--a prophecy of 
victory, long delayed, for the cause of the Union. It 
became the theme of the pulpit, the topic of editorial

<pb xml:id="p007" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.007"/>

 discussion, the inspiration of our army, the bright star of a nation's hope, suddenly breaking into a long night of distress and perplexity. 

From field and mountain, from cabin and cot, from hamlet and village, the long, dark stream of eager freed-men poured into the capital of the Kepublic. In the more evil days they shrank from the name of Washing-ton as from some deadly reptile. Washington was the place where legal chains were forged for their unwilling limbs. Under the goddess of liberty laws had been enacted that charged every power of the government to hunt down, at all hazards, and regardless of cost, the fugitive flying for life, and hurry him back to the hell of slavery. Under the dome of that Capitol a Chief Justice had declared that " a Kegro had no rights that a white is bound to respect." ISTo l^^egro had been allowed to walk under the shadow of the Capitol or darken its door, except as nurse or servant to some Southern slave•holder. 
Horrible indeed were the thoughts of Washington to the poor slaves beyond its borders. But the news of emancipation had come to them in their dark Isle of Patmos, and was heard above the mad storm of civil war. Washington was transformed from a prison to a castle. To the poor fugitive and bondman it seemed now to be the only secure place in all the land. It stood as a lone island in the midst of an angry sea, and every wave of rebellion seemed anxious to devour it. But there it stood, amid the boom of cannon, the glare of the lightnings of war, safe even amidst the

</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>