<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Pauline E. Hopkins - Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self. (1902-1903)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0095</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>

<bibl n="1" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.001">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1902-11">November 1902</date>
<biblScope unit="page">29-40</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="2" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.002">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1902-11">December 1902</date>
<biblScope unit="page">102-113</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="3" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.003">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1903-01">January 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">191-200</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="4" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.004">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1903-02">February 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">264-272</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="5" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.005">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1903-03">March 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">339-348</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="6" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.006">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1903-03">May 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">423-432</biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Fiction</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-12" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.001">

<pb facs="p29"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Chapter I.</p>

<p>The recitations were over for the day.
It was the first week in November and it
had rained about every day the entire
week; now freezing temperature added
to the discomforture of the dismal season.
The lingering equinoctial whirled the
last clinging yellow leaves from the trees
on the campus and strewed them over the

deserted paths, while from the leaden sky
fluttering snow-white flakes gave an unexpected 
touch of winter to the scene.</p>

<p>The east wind for which Boston and
vicinity is celebrated, drove the sleet
against the window panes of the room in
which Reuel Briggs sat among his books
and the apparatus for experiments. The
room served for both living and sleeping.
Briggs could have told you that the bare-

<pb facs="p30"/>

ness and desolateness of the apartment
were like his life, but he was a reticent
man who knew how to suffer in silence.
The dreary wet afternoon, the cheerless
walk over West Boston bridge through
the soaking streets had but served to
emphasize the loneliness of his position,
and morbid thoughts had haunted him all
day: To what use all this persistent hard
work for a place in the world&#8212;clothes,
food, a roof? Is suicide wrong? he asked
himself with tormenting persistency.
From out the storm, voices and hands
seemed beckoning him all day to cut the
Gordian knot and solve the riddle of
whence and whither for all time.</p>

<p>His place in the world would soon be
filled; no vacuum remained empty; the
eternal movement of all things onward
closed up the gaps, and the wail of the
newly-born augmented the great army of
mortals pressing the vitals of mother
Earth with hurrying tread. So he had
tormented himself for months, but the
courage was yet wanting for strength to
rend the veil. It had grown dark early.
Reuel had not stirred from his room since
coming from the hospital&#8212;had not eaten
nor drank, and was in full possession of
the solitude he craved. It was now five
o'clock. He sat sideways by the bare
table, one leg crossed over the other. His
fingers kept the book open at the page
where he was reading, but his attention
wandered beyond the leaden sky, the
dripping panes, and the sounds of the
driving storm outside.</p>

<p>He was thinking deeply of the words he
had just read, and which the darkness had
shut from his gaze. The book was called
"The Unclassified Residuum," just published 
and eagerly sought by students of
mysticism, and dealing with the great
field of new discoveries in psychology.
Briggs was a close student of what might
be termed "absurdities" of supernatural
phenomena or mysticism, best known to
the every-day world as "effects of the

imagination," a phrase of mere dismissal,
and which it is impossible to make precise; 
the book suited the man's mood.
These were the words of haunting significance:</p>

<p>"All the while, however, the phenomena 
are there, lying broadcast over the
surface of history. No matter where
you open its pages, you find things recorded 
under the name of divinations,
inspirations, demoniacal possessions, apparitions,
trances, ecstasies, miraculous
healing and productions of disease, and
occult powers possessed by peculiar individuals 
over persons and things in their
neighborhood.</p>

<p>"The mind-curers and Christian scientists, 
who are beginning to lift up their
heads in our communities, unquestionably
get remarkable results in certain cases.
The ordinary medical man dismisses
them from his attention with the
cut-and-dried remark that they are
'only the effects of the imagination.' But
there is a meaning in this vaguest of
phrases.</p>

<p>"We know a non-hysterical woman
who in her trances knows facts which
altogether transcend her <hi rend="italics">possible</hi> normal
consciousness, facts about the lives of
people whom she never saw or heard of
before. I am well aware of all the
liabilities to which this statement exposes
me, and I make it deliberately, having
practically no doubt whatever of its
truth."</p>

<p>Presently Briggs threw the book down,
and, rising from his chair, began pacing
up and down the bare room.</p>

<p>"That is it," at length he said aloud.
"I have the power, I know the truth of
every word&#8212;of all M. Binet asserts, and
could I but complete the necessary experiments, 
I would astonish the world.
O Poverty, Ostracism! have I not
drained the bitter cup to the dregs!" he
apostrophized, with a harsh, ironical
laugh.</p>

<pb facs="p31"/>

<p>Mother Nature had blessed Reuel
Briggs with superior physical endowments, 
but as yet he had never had reason 
to count them blessings. No one
could fail to notice the vast breadth of
shoulder, the strong throat that upheld
a plain face, the long limbs, the sinewy
hands. His head was that of an athlete,
with close-set ears, and covered with an
abundance of black hair, straight and
closely cut, thick and smooth; the nose
was the aristocratic feature, although
nearly spoiled by broad nostrils, of this
remarkable young man; his skin was
white, but of a tint suggesting olive, an
almost sallow color which is a mark of
strong, melancholic temperaments. His
large mouth concealed powerful long
white teeth which gleamed through lips
even and narrow, parting generally in a
smile at once grave, genial and singularly
sweet; indeed Briggs' smile changed
the plain face at once into one that interested 
and fascinated men and women.
True there were lines about the mouth
which betrayed a passionate, nervous
temperament, but they accorded well
with the rest of his strong personality.
His eyes were a very bright and piercing
gray, courageous, keen and shrewd.
Briggs was not a man to be despised
physically or mentally.</p>

<p>None of the students associated together 
in the hive of men under the fostering 
care of the benign mother knew
aught of Reuel Briggs's origin. It was
rumored at first that he was of Italian
birth, then they guessed he was a Japanese, 
but whatever land claimed him as
a son, all voted him a genius in his scientific
studies, and much was expected
of him at graduation. He had no money,
for he was unsocial and shabby to the
point of seediness, and apparently no relatives, 
for his correspondence was limited
to the letters of editors of well known local 
papers and magazines. Somehow he

lived and paid his way in a third-rate
lodging-house near Harvard square, at
the expense of the dull intellects or the
idle rich, with which a great university
always teems, to whom Briggs acted as
"coach," and by contributing scientific
articles to magazines on the absorbing
subject of spiritualistic phenomena. A
few of his articles had produced a pro
found impression. The monotonous
pacing continued for a time, finally ending 
at the mantel, from whence he abstracted 
a disreputable looking pipe and
filled it.</p>

<p>"Well," he soliloquized, as he reseated
himself in his chair, "Fate has done her
worst, but she mockingly beckons me on
and I accept her challenge. I shall not
yet attempt the bourne. If I conquer, it
will be by strength of brain and will-power. 
I shall conquer; I must and
will."</p>

<p>The storm had increased in violence;
the early dusk came swiftly down, and
at this point in his revery the rattling
window panes, as well as the whistle and
shriek of gusts of moaning wind, caught
his attention. "Phew! a beastly night."
With a shiver, he drew his chair closer to
the cylinder stove, whose glowing body
was the only cheerful object in the bare
room.</p>

<p>As he sat with his back half-turned to
catch the grateful warmth, he looked out
into the dim twilight across the square
and into the broad paths of the campus,
watching the skeleton arms of giant trees
tossing in the wind, and the dancing
snow-flakes that fluttered to earth in their
fairy gowns to be quickly transformed into 
running streams that fairly overflowed
the gutters. He fell into a dreamy state
as he gazed, for which he could not account. 
As he sent his earnest, penetrating 
gaze into the night, gradually the
darkness and storm faded into tints of
cream and rose and soft moist lips. 

<pb facs="p32"/>

Silhouetted against the background of lowering 
sky and waving branches, he saw
distinctly outlined a fair face framed in
golden hair, with soft brown eyes, deep
and earnest&#8212;terribly earnest they
seemed just then&#8212;rose-tinged baby lips,
and an expression of wistful entreaty. O
how real, how very real did the passing
shadow appear to the gazer!</p>

<p>He tried to move, uneasily conscious
that this strange experience was but "the
effect of the imagination," but he was
powerless. The unknown countenance
grew dimmer and farther off, floating
gradually out of sight, while a sense of
sadness and foreboding wrapped him
about as with a pall.</p>

<p>A wilder gust of wind shook the window 
sashes. Reuel stared about him in
a bewildered way like a man awakening
from a heavy sleep. He listened to the
wail of the blast and glanced at the fire
and rubbed his eyes. The vision was
gone; he was alone in the room; all was
silence and darkness. The ticking of the
cheap clock on the mantel kept time
with his heart-beats. The light of his
own life seemed suddenly eclipsed with
the passing of the lovely vision of Venus.
Conscious of an odd murmur in his
head, which seemed to control his movements, 
he rose and went toward the window 
to open it; there came a loud knock
at the door.</p>

<p>Briggs did not answer at once. He
wanted no company. Perhaps. the
knocker would go away. But he was
persistent. Again came the knock ending 
in a double rat-tat accompanied by
the words:</p>

<p>"I know you are there; open, open,
you son of Erebus! You inhospitable
Turk!"</p>

<p>Thus admonished Briggs turned the
key and threw wide open the door.</p>

<p>"It's you, is it? Confound you, you're
always here when you're not wanted,"
he growled.</p>

<p>The visitor entered and closed the
door behind him. With a laugh he stood
his dripping umbrella back of the stove
against the chimney-piece, and immediately 
a small stream began trickling
over the uncarpeted floor; he then relieved 
himself of his damp outer garments.</p>

<p>"Son of Erebus, indeed, you ungrateful 
man. It's as black as Hades in this
room; a light, a light! Why did you
keep me waiting out there like a
drowned rat?"</p>

<p>The voice was soft and musical.
Briggs lighted the student lamp. The
light revealed a tall man with the beautiful 
face of a Greek God; but the sculptured 
features did not inspire confidence.
There was that in the countenance of
Aubrey Livingston that engendered
doubt. But he had been kind to Briggs,
was, in fact, his only friend in the college,
or, indeed, in the world for that matter.</p>

<p>By an act of generosity he had helped
the forlorn youth, then in his freshman
year, over obstacles which bade fair to
end his college days. Although the
pecuniary obligation was long since paid,
the affection and worship Reuel had conceived 
for his deliverer was dog-like in
its devotion.</p>

<p>"Beastly night," he continued, as he
stretched his full length luxuriously in
the only easy chair the room afforded.
"What are you mooning about all alone
in the darkness?"</p>

<p>"Same old thing," replied Briggs
briefly.</p>

<p>"No wonder the men say that vou
have a twist, Reuel."</p>

<p>"Ah, man! but the problem of whence
and whither! To solve it is my life; I
live for that alone; let'm talk."</p>

<p>"You ought to be re-named the
'Science of Trance-States,' Reuel. How
a man can grind day and night beats
me." Livingston handed him a cigar
and for a time they smoked in silence.

<pb facs="p33"/>

At length Reuel said:</p>

<p>"Shake hands with Poverty once,
Aubrey, and you will solve the secret of
many a student's success in life."</p>

<p>"Doubtless it would do me good," replied
Livingston with a laugh, "but just
at present, it's the ladies, bless their
sweet faces who disturb me, and not
delving in books nor weeping over ways
and means. Shades of my fathers, forbid
that I should ever have to work!</p>

<p>"Lucky dog!" growled Reuel, enviously, 
as he gazed admiringly at the handsome 
face turned up to the ceiling and
gazing with soft caressing eyes at the
ugly whitewashed wall through rings of
curling smoke. "Yet you have a greater
gift of duality than I," he <sic>addded</sic> dreamily. 
"Say what you will; ridicule me, torment 
me, but you know as well as I that
the wonders of a material world cannot
approach those of the undiscovered
country within ourselves&#8212;the hidden self
lying quiescent in every human soul."</p>

<p>"True, Reuel, and I often wonder what
becomes of the mind and morals, distinctive 
entities grouped in the republic
known as man, when death comes. Good
and evil in me contend; which will gain
the mastery? Which will accompany me
into the silent land?"</p>

<p>"Good and evil, God and the devil,"
suggested Reuel. "Yes, sinner or saint,
body or soul, which wins in the life
struggle? I am not sure that it matters
which," he concluded with a shrug of his
handsome shoulders. "I should know if
I never saw you again until the struggle
was over. Your face will tell its own tale
in another five years. Now listen to
this:" He caught up the book he had
been reading and rapidly turning the
leaves read over the various passages
that had impressed him.</p>

<p>"A curious accumulation of data; the
writer evidently takes himself seriously,"
Livingston commented.</p>

<p>"And why not?" demanded Reuel.

"You and I know enough to credit the
author with honest intentions.</p>

<p>"Yes; but are we prepared to go so
far?"</p>

<p>"This man is himself a mystic.
gives his evidence clearly enough."</p>

<p>"And do you credit it?"</p>

<p>"Every word! Could I but get the
necessary subject, I would convince you;
I would go farther than M. Binet in unveiling 
the vast scheme of compensation
and retribution carried about in the vast
recesses of the human soul."</p>

<p>"Find the subject and I will find the
money," laughed Aubrey.</p>

<p>"Do you mean it, Aubrey? Will you
join me in carrying forward a search for
more light on the mysteries of
existence?"</p>

<p>"I mean it. And now, Reuel, come
down from the clouds, and come with me
to a concert."</p>

<p>"Tonight?"</p>

<p>"Yes, 'tonight,'" mimicked the other.
"The blacker the night, the greater the
need of amusement. You go out too
little."</p>

<p>"Who gives the concert?"</p>

<p>Well, it's a new departure in the
musical world; something Northerners
know nothing of; but I who am a
Southerner, born and bred, or as the vulgar 
have it, 'dyed in the wool,' know and
understand Negro music. It is a jubilee
concert given by a party of Southern
colored people at Tremont Temple. I
have the tickets. Redpath has them in 
charge."</p>

<p>"Well, if you say so, I suppose I must."
Briggs did not seem greatly impressed.</p>

<p>"Coming down to the practical, Reuel,
what do you think of the Negro problem? 
Come to think of it, I have never
heard you express an opinion about it.
I believe it is the only burning question
in the whole category of live issues and
ologies about which you are silent."</p>

<pb facs="p34"/>

<p>"I have a horror of discussing the woes
of unfortunates, tramps, stray dogs and
cats and Negroes&#8212;probably because I
am an unfortunate myself."</p>

<p>They smoked in silence.</p>

<p>Chapter II.</p>

<p>The passing of slavery from the land
marked a new era in the life of the nation.
The war, too, had passed like a dream of
horrors, and over the resumption of normal 
conditions in business and living, the
whole country, as one man, rejoiced and
heaved a deep sigh of absolute content.</p>

<p>Under the spur of the excitement occasioned 
by the Proclamation of Freedom, 
and the great need of schools for
the blacks, thousands of dollars were
contributed at the North, and agents
were sent to Great Britain, where
generosity towards the Negroes was
boundless. Money came from all directions, 
pouring into the hands of philanthropists, 
who were anxious to prove that
the country was able, not only to free the
slave, but to pay the great debt it owed
him,&#8212;protection as he embraced freedom, 
and a share in the great Government 
he had aided to found by sweat and
toil and blood. It was soon discovered
that the Negro possessed a phenomenal
gift of music, and it was determined to
utilize this gift in helping to support
educational institutions of color in the
Southland.</p>

<p>A band of students from Fisk University 
were touring the country, and those
who had been fortunate enough to listen
once to their matchless untrained voices
singing their heartbreaking minor music
with its grand and impossible intervals
and sound combinations, were eager to
listen again and yet again.</p>

<p>Wealthy and exclusive society women
everywhere vied in showering benefits
and patronage upon the new prodigies
who had suddenly become the pets of

the musical world. The Temple was a
blaze of light, and crowded from pit to
dome. It was the first appearance of the
troupe in New England, therefore it
was a gala night, and Boston culture was
out in force.</p>

<p>The two friends easily found their
seats in the first balcony, and from that
position idly scanned the vast audience
to beguile the tedious waiting. Reuel's
thoughts were disturbed; he read over
the program, but it carried no meaning
to his pre-occupied mind; he was uneasy;
the face he had seen outlined in the
twilight haunted him. A great nervous
dread of he knew not what possessed
him, and he actually suffered as he sat
there answering at random the running
fire of comments made by Livingston on
the audience, and replying none too
cordially to the greetings of fellow-students, 
drawn to the affair, like himself, by
curiosity.</p>

<p>"Great crowd for such a night," observed 
one. "The weather matches your
face, Briggs; why didn't you leave it outside? 
Why do you look so down?"</p>

<p>Reuel shrugged his shoulders.</p>

<p>"They say there are some pretty girls
in the troupe; one or two as white as
we, continued the speaker unabashed by
Reuel's surliness.</p>

<p>"They range at home from alabaster
to ebony," replied Livingston. "The results
of amalgamation are worthy the
careful attention of all medical experts.</p>

<p>"Don't talk shop, Livingston," said
Briggs peevishly.</p>

<p>"You are really more disagreeable
than usual," replied Livingston, pleasantly. 
"Do try to be like the other fellows,
for once, Reuel."</p>

<p>Silence ensued for a time, and then
the irrepressible one of the party remarked: 
"The soprano soloist is great;
heard her in New York." At this
there was a general laugh among the
men. Good natured Charlie Vance was

<pb facs="p35"/>

generally "stuck" once a month with the
"'loveliest girl, by jove, you know."</p>

<p>"That explains your presence here,
Vance; what's her name?"</p>

<p>"Dianthe Lusk."</p>

<p>"Great name. I hope she comes up to
it,&#8212;the flower of Jove."</p>

<p>"Flower of Jove, indeed! You'll say
so when you see her," cried Charlie with
his usual enthusiasm.</p>

<p>"What! again, my son? 'Like Dian's
kiss, unmasked, unsought, Love gives itself'" 
quoted Livingston, with a smile on
his handsome face.</p>

<p>"Oh, stow it! Aubrey, even your cold
blood will be stirred at sight of her exquisite 
face; of her voice I will not speak;
I cannot do it justice."</p>

<p>"If this is to be the result of emancipation, 
I for one vote that we ask Congress 
to annul the Proclamation," said
Reuel, drily.</p>

<p>Now conversation ceased; a famous
local organist began a concert on the
organ to occupy the moments of waiting.
The music soothed Reuel's restlessness.
He noticed that the platform usually occupied 
by the speaker's desk, now held a
number of chairs and a piano. Certainly,
the assiduous advertising had brought
large patronage for the new venture, he
thought as he idly calculated the financial 
result from the number in the
audience.</p>

<p>Soon the hot air, the glare of lights,
the mingling of choice perfumes emanating 
from the dainty forms of elegantly attired women, 
acted upon him as an intoxicant. 
He began to feel the pervading 
excitement&#8212;the flutter of expectation, 
and presently the haunting face left
him.</p>

<p>The prelude drew to a close; the last
chord fell from the fingers of the artist: a
line of figures&#8212;men and women&#8212;dark in
hue, and neatly dressed in quiet evening
clothes, filed noiselessly from the anterooms 
and filled the chairs upon the

platform. The silence in the house was
painful. These were representatives of
the people for whom God had sent the
terrible scourge of blood upon the land
to free from bondage. The old abolitionists 
in the vast audience felt the blood
leave their faces beneath the stress of
emotion.</p>

<p>The opening number was "The Lord's
Prayer." Stealing, rising, swelling,
gathering, as it thrilled the ear, all the
delights of harmony in a grand minor cadence 
that told of deliverance from bondage 
and homage to God for his wonderful
aid, sweeping the awed heart with an ecstasy 
that was almost pain; breathing,
hovering, soaring, they held the vast multitude 
in speechless wonder.</p>

<p>Thunders of applause greeted the
close of the hymn. Scarcely waiting for
a silence, a female figure rose and came
slowly to the edge of the platform and
stood in the blaze of lights with hands
modestly clasped before her. She was
not in any way the preconceived idea of
a Negro. Fair as the fairest woman in
the hall, with wavy bands of chestnut
hair, and great, melting eyes of brown,
soft as those of childhood; a willowy
figure of exquisite mould, clad in a
sombre gown of black. There fell a
voice upon the listening ear, in celestial
showers of silver that passed all conceptions, 
all comparisons, all dreams ; a voice
beyond belief&#8212;a great soprano of unimaginable 
beauty, soaring heavenward
in mighty intervals.</p>

<p>"Go down, Moses, way down in Egypt's
land,<lb/>
Tell ol' Pharaoh, let my people go."<lb/>
sang the woman in tones that awakened
ringing harmonies in the heart of every
listener.</p>

<p>"By Jove!" Reuel heard Livingston
exclaim. For himself he was dazed,
thrilled; never save among the great
artists of the earth, was such a voice
heard alive with the divine fire.</p>

<pb facs="p36"/>

<p>Some of the women in the audience
wept; there was the distinct echo of a
sob in the deathly quiet which gave
tribute to the power of genius. Spellbound 
they sat beneath the outpoured
anguish of a suffering soul. All the
horror, the degredation from which a
race had been delivered were in the
pleading strains of the singer's voice.
It strained the senses almost beyond endurance. 
It pictured to that self-possessed, 
highly-cultured New England
assemblage as nothing else ever had, the
awfulness of the hell from which a people
had been happily plucked.</p>

<p>Reuel was carried out of himself; he
leaned forward in eager contemplation of
the artist; he grew cold with terror and
fear. Surely it could not be&#8212; he must be
dreaming! It was incredible! Even as
he whispered the words to himself the
hall seemed to grow dim and shadowy;
the sea of faces melted away; there be
fore him in the blaze of light&#8212;like a
lovely phantom&#8212;stood a woman wearing
the face of his vision of the afternoon!</p>

<p>Chapter III.</p>

<p>It was Hallow-eve.</p>

<p>The north wind blew a cutting blast
over the stately Charles, and broke the
waves into a miniature flood; it swept the
streets of the University city, and danced
on into the outlying suburbs tossing the
last leaves about in gay disorder, not
even sparing the quiet precincts of
Mount Auburn cemetery. A deep, clear,
moonless sky stretched overhead, from
which hung myriads of sparkling stars.</p>

<p>It Mount Auburn, where the residences 
of the rich lay far apart, darkness
and quietness had early settled down.
The main street seemed given over to
the duskiness of the evening, and with
one exception, there seemed no light on
earth or in heaven save the cold gleam of
the stars.</p>

<p>The one exception was in the home
of Charlie Vance, or "Adonis," as he was
called by his familiars. The Vance
estate was a spacious house with rambling 
ells, tortuous chimney-stacks, and
corners, eaves and ledges; the grounds
were extensive and well kept telling
silently of the opulence of its owner. Its
windows sent forth a cheering light. Dinner 
was just over.</p>

<p>Within, on an old-fashioned hearth,
blazed a glorious wood fire, which gave
a rich coloring to the oak-panelled walls,
and fell warmly on a group of young
people seated and standing, chatting
about the fire. At one side of it, in a
chair of the Elizabethan period, sat the
hostess, Molly Vance, only daughter of
James Vance, Esq., and sister of
"Adonis," a beautiful girl of eighteen.</p>

<p>At the opposite side, leaning with
folded arms against the high carved mantel, 
stood Aubrey Livingston; the beauty
of his fair hair and blue eyes was never
more marked as he stood there in the
gleam of the fire and the soft candle
light. He was talking vivaciously, his
eyes turning from speaker to speaker, as
he ran on, but resting chiefly with pride
on his beautiful betrothed, Molly Vance.</p>

<p>The group was completed by two or
three other men, among them Reuel
Briggs, and three pretty girls. Suddenly
a clock struck the hour.</p>

<p>"Only nine," exclaimed Molly. "Good
people, what shall we do to wile the
tedium of waiting for the witching hour?
Have any one of you enough wisdom to
make a suggestion?"</p>

<p>"Music," said Livingston.</p>

<p>"We don't want anything so commonplace."</p>

<p>"Blind Man's Buff," suggested
"Adonis."</p>

<p>"Oh! please not that, the men are so
rough!"</p>

<p>"Let us," broke in Cora Scott, "tell
ghost stories."</p>

<pb facs="p37"/>

<p>"Good, Cora! yes, yes, yes."</p>

<p>"No, no!" exclaimed a chorus of
voices.</p>

<p>"Yes, yes," laughed Molly, gaily, clapping 
her hands. "It is the very thing.
Cora, you are the wise woman of the
party. It is the very time, tonight is the
new moon, and we can try our projects
in the Hyde house."</p>

<p>"The moon should be full to account
for such madness," said Livingston.</p>

<p>"Don't be disagreeable, Aubrey," replied 
Molly. "The 'ayes' have it.
You're with me, Mr. Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Of course, Miss Vance," answered
Reuel, "to go to the North Pole or
Hades&#8212;only please tell us where is
'Hyde house.'"</p>

<p>"Have you never heard? Why it's the
adjoining estate. It is reputed to be
haunted, and a lady in white haunts the
avenue in the most approved ghostly
style."</p>

<p>"Bosh!" said Livingston.</p>

<p>"Possibly," remarked the laughing
Molly, "but it is the 'bosh' of a century."</p>

<p>"Go on, Miss Vance; don't mind
Aubrey. Who has seen the lady?"</p>

<p>"She is not easily seen," proceeded
Molly, "she only appears on Hallow-eve,
when the moon is new, as it will be tonight. 
I had forgotten that fact when I
invited you here. If anyone stands, to-
night, in the avenue leading to the house,
he will surely see the tall veiled figure
gliding among the old hemlock trees."</p>

<p>One or two shivered.</p>

<p>"If, however, the watcher remain, the
lady will pause, and utter some sentence
of prophecy of his future."</p>

<p>"Has any one done this?" queried
Reuel.</p>

<p>"My old nurse says she remembers
that the lady was seen once."</p>

<p>"Then, we'll test it again tonight!" exclaimed 
Reuel, greatly excited over the
chance to prove his pet theories.</p>

<p>"Well, Molly, you've started Reuel off

on his greatest hobby; I wash my hands
of both of you."</p>

<p>"Let us go any way!" chorused the
venturesome party.</p>

<p>"But there are conditions," exclaimed
Molly. "Only one person must go at a
time."</p>

<p>Aubrey laughed as he noticed the consternation 
in one or two faces.</p>

<p>"So," continued Molly, "as we cannot
go together, I propose that each shall
stay a quarter of an hour, then whether
successful or not, return and let another
take his or her place. I will go first."</p>

<p>"No&#8212;" it was Charlie who spoke&#8212;"I
put my veto on that, Molly. If you are
mad enough to risk colds in this mad
freak, it shall be done fairly. We will
draw lots."</p>

<p>"And I add to that, not a girl leave
the house; we men will try the charm
for the sake of your curiosity, but not a
girl goes. You can try the ordinary
Hallow-eve projects while we are away."</p>

<p>With many protests, but concealed relief, 
this plan was reluctantly adopted by
the female element. The lots were prepared 
and placed in a hat, and amid much
merriment, drawn.</p>

<p>"You are third, Mr. Briggs," exclaimed 
Molly who held the hat and
watched the checks.</p>

<p>"I'm first," said Livingston, "and
Charlie second."</p>

<p>"While we wait for twelve, tell us the
story of the house, Molly," cried Cora.</p>

<p>Thus adjured, Molly settled herself
comfortably in her chair and began:
"Hyde House is nearly opposite the cemetery,
and its land joins that of this house;
it is indebted for its ill-repute to one of
its owners, John Hyde. It has been
known for years as a haunted house, and
avoided as such by the superstitious. It
is low-roofed, rambling, and almost entirely 
concealed by hemlocks, having an
air of desolation and decay in keeping
with its ill-repute. In its dozen rooms

<pb facs="p38"/>

were enacted the dark deeds which gave
the place the name of the 'haunted
house.'</p>

<p>"The story is told of an unfaithful husband, 
a wronged wife and a beautiful
governess forming a combination which
led to the murder of a guest for his
money. The master of the house died
from remorse, under peculiar circumstances. 
These materials give us the
plot for a thrilling ghost story."</p>

<p>"Well, where does the lady come in?"
interrupted "Adonis."</p>

<p>There was a general laugh.</p>

<p>"This world is all a blank without the
ladies for Charlie," remarked Aubrey.
"Molly, go on with your story, my
child."</p>

<p>"You may all laugh as much as you
please, but what I am telling you is be-
lieved in this section by every one. aA
local magazine speaks of it as follows, as
near as I can remember:</p>

<p>"'A most interesting story is told by
a woman who occupied the house for a
short time. She relates that she had no
sooner crossed the threshold than she
was met by a beautiful woman in flowing
robes of black, who begged permission
to speak through her to her friends. The
friends were thereupon bidden to be present 
at a certain time. When all were assembled 
they were directed by invisible
powers to kneel. Then the spirit told the
tale of the tragedy through the woman.
The spirit was the niece of the murderer,
and she was in the house when the
crime was committed. She discovered 
blood stains on the door of
the woodshed, and told her uncle
that she suspected him of murdering 
the guest, who had mysteriously
disappeared. He secured her promise
not to betray him. She had always kept
the secret. Although both had been
dead for many years, they were chained
to the scene of the crime, as was the

governess, Who was the man's partner in
guilt. The final release of the niece from
the place was conditional on her making
a public confession. This done she
would never be heard from again. And
she never was, except on Hallow-eve,
when the moon is new.'"</p>

<p>"Bring your science and philosophy to
bear on this, Reuel. Come, come, man,
give us your opinion," exclaimed Aubrey.</p>

<p>"Reuel doesn't believe such stuff; he's
too sensible," added Charlie.</p>

<p>"If these are facts, they are only for
those who have a mental affinity with
them. I believe that if we could but
strengthen our mental sight, we could
discover the broad highway between this
and the other world on which both good
and evil travel to earth," replied Reuel.</p>

<p>"And that 'irst highway was beaten
out of choas by Satan, as Milton has it,
eh, Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Have it as you like, Smith. No matter. 
For my own part, I have never believed 
that the whole mental world is
governed by the faculties we understand,
and can reduce to reason or definite feeling. 
But I will keep my ideas to myself: 
one does not care to be laughed at."</p>

<p>The conversation was kept up for an-
other hour about indifferent subjects, but
all felt the excitement underlying the
frivolous chatter. At quarter before
twelve, Aubrey put on his ulster with the
words: "Well, here goes for my lady."
The great doors were thrown open, and
the company grouped about him to see
him depart.</p>

<p>"Mind, honor bright, you go," laughed
Charlie.</p>

<p>"Honor bright," he called back.</p>

<p>Then he went on beyond the flood of
light into the gloom of the night. Muffled 
in wraps and ulsters they lingered
on the piazzas waiting his return.</p>

<p>"Would he see anything?"</p>

<pb facs="p39"/>

<p>"Of course not!" laughed Charlie and
Bert Smith. 'Still, we bet he'll be sharp
to his time."</p>

<p>They were right. Aubrey returned at
five minutes past twelve, a failure.</p>

<p>Charlie ran down the steps briskly, but
in ten minutes came hastening back.</p>

<p>"Well," was the chorus, "did you see
it?"</p>

<p>"I saw something&#8212;a figure in the
trees!"</p>

<p>"And you did not wait?" said Molly,
scornfully.</p>

<p>"No, I dared not; I own it."</p>

<p>"It's my turn; I'm third," said Reuel.</p>

<p>"Luck to you, old man," they called as
he disappeared in the darkness.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs was a brave man. He
knew his own great physical strength and
felt no fear as he traversed the patch
of woods lying between the two estates.
As he reached the avenue of hemlocks
he was not thinking of his mission, but
of the bright home scene he had just left
&#8212;of love and home and rest&#8212;such a life
as was unfolding before Aubrey Livingston 
and sweet Molly Vance.</p>

<p>"I suppose there are plenty of men in
the world as lonely as I am," he mused;
"but I suppose it is my own fault. A
man though plain and poor can generally 
manage to marry; and I am both. But
I don't regard a wife as one regards
bread&#8212;better sour bread than starvation; 
better an uncongenial life-companion 
than none! What a frightful mistake! 
No! The woman I marry must
be to me a necessity, because I love her;
because so loving her, 'all the current of
my being flows to her,' and I feel she is
my supreme need."</p>

<p>Just now he felt strangely happy as
he moved in the gloom of the hemlocks,
and he wondered many times after that
whether the spirit is sometimes mysteriously 
conscious of the nearness of its
kindred spirit; and feels, in anticipation,

the "sweet unrest" of the master-passion
that rules the world.</p>

<p>The mental restlessness of three weeks
before seemed to have possession of him
again. Suddenly the "restless, unsatisfied 
longing," rose again in his heart.
He turned his head and saw a female
figure just ahead of him in the path, coming 
toward him. He could not see her
features distinctly, only the eyes&#8212;large,
bright and dark. But their expression!
Sorrowful, wistful—almost imploring&#8212;
gazing straightforward, as if they saw
nothing&#8212;like the eyes of a person entirely 
absorbed and not distinguishing one
object from another.</p>

<p>She was close to him now, and there
was a perceptible pause in her step. Suddenly 
she covered her face with her
clasped hands, as if in uncontrollable
grief. Moved by a mighty emotion,
Briggs addressed the lonely figure:</p>

<p>"You are in trouble, madam; may I
help you?"</p>

<p>Briggs never knew how he survived
the next shock. Slowly the hands were
removed from the face and the moon
gave a distinct view of the lovely features 
of the jubilee singer&#8212;Dianthe
Lusk.</p>

<p>She did not seem to look at Briggs,
but straight before her, as she said in a
low, clear, passionless voice:</p>

<p>"You can help me, but not now; tomorrow."</p>

<p>Reuel's most prominent feeling was
one of delight. The way was open to
become fully acquainted with the woman
who had haunted him sleeping and waking, 
for weeks past.</p>

<p>"Not now! Yet you are suffering.
Shall I see you soon? Forgive me&#8212;but
oh! tell me&#8212;"</p>

<p>He was interrupted. The lady moved
or floated away from him, with her face
toward him and gazing steadily at him.</p>

<p>He felt that his whole heart was in his

<pb facs="p40"/>

eyes, yet hers did not drop, nor did her
cheek color.</p>

<p>"The time is not yet," she said in the
same, clear, calm, measured tones, in
which she had spoken before. Reuel
made a quick movement toward her, but
she raised her hand, and the gesture forbade 
him to follow her. He paused involuntarily, 
and she turned away, and
disappeared among the gloomy hemlock
trees.</p>

<p>He parried the questions of the merry
crowd when he returned to the house,
with indifferent replies. How they
would have laughed at him&#8212;slave of a
passion as sudden and romantic as that
of Romeo for Juliet; with no more
foundation than the "presentments" in
books which treat of the "occult." He
dropped asleep at last, in the early morning 
hours, and lived over his experience
in his dreams.</p>

<p>Chapter IV.</p>

<p>Although not yet a practitioner, Reuel
Briggs was a recognized power in the
medical profession. In brain diseases he
was an authority.</p>

<p>Early the next morning he was
aroused from sleep by imperative knocking 
at his door. It was a messenger

from the hospital. There had been a
train accident on the Old Colony road,
would he come immediately?</p>

<p>Scarcely giving himself time for a cup
of coffee, he arrived at the hospital almost
as soon as the messenger.</p>

<p>The usual silence of the hospital was
broken; all was bustle and movement,
without confusion. It was a great call
upon the resources of the officials, but
they were equal to it. The doctors
passed from sufferer to sufferer, dressing
their injuries; then they were borne to
beds from which some would never rise
again.</p>

<p>"Come with me to the women's ward,
Doctor Briggs," said a nurse. "There is
a woman there who was taken from the
wreck. She shows no sign of injury, but
the doctors cannot restore her to consciousness. 
Doctor Livingston pronounces 
her dead, but it doesn't seem
possible. So young, so beautiful. Do
something for her, Doctor."</p>

<p>The men about a cot made way for
Reuel, as he entered the ward. "It's no
use Briggs," said Livingston to him in
reply to his question. "Your science
won't save her. The poor girl is already
cold and stiff."</p>

<p>He moved aside disclosing to Reuel's
gaze the lovely face of Dianthe Lusk!</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.002">

<pb facs="p102"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Chapter IV. (Concluded.)</p>

<p>The most marvellous thing to watch is
the death of a person. At that moment
the opposite takes place to that which
took place when life entered the first unit,
after nature had prepared it for the inception 
of life. How the vigorous life
watches the passage of the liberated life
out of its earthly environment! What a
change is this! How important the
knowledge of whither life tends! Here is
shown the setting free of a disciplined
spirit giving up its mortality for immortality,
&#8212;the condition necessary to know
God. Death! There is no death. Life
is everlasting, and from its reality can
have no end. Life is real and never
changes, but preserves its identity eternally 
as the angels, and the immortal
spirit of man, which are the only realities 
and continuities in the universe, God
being over all, Supreme Ruler and Divine 
Essence from whom comes all life.
Somewhat in this train ran Reuel's
thoughts as he stood beside the seeming
dead girl, the cynosure of all the medical
faculty there assembled.</p>

<p>To the majority of those men, the case
was an ordinary death, and that was all
there was to it. What did this young upstart 
expect to make of it? Of his skill
and wonderful theories they had heard
strange tales. but they viewed him coldly
as we are apt to view those who dare to
leave the beaten track of conventionality.</p>

<p>Outwardly cool and stolid, showing no
sign of recognition, he stood for some
seconds gazing down on Dianthe; every
nerve quivered, every pulse of his body
throbbed. Her face held for him a wonderful 
charm. an extraordinary fascination. 
As he gazed he knew that once
more he beheld what he had vaguely

sought and yearned for all his forlorn
lite. His whole heart went out to her;
destiny, not chance, had brought him to
her. He saw, too, that no one knew her,
none had a clue to her identity; he determined 
to remain silent for the present,
and immediately he sought to impress
Livingston to do likewise.</p>

<p>His keen glance swept the faces of the
surrounding physicians. "No, not one,"
he told himself, "holds the key to unlock
this seeming sleep of death." He alone
could do it. Advancing far afield in the
mysterious regions of science, he had
stumbled upon the solution of one of
life's problems: <hi rend="italics">the reanimation of the
body after seeming death</hi>.</p>

<p>He had hesitated to tell of his discovery 
to any one; not even to Livingston
had he hinted of the daring possibility,
fearing ridicule in case of a miscarriage
in his calculations. But for the sake of
this girl he would make what he felt to be
a premature disclosure of the results of
his experiments. Meantime, Livingston,
from his place at the foot of the cot,
watched his friend with fascinated eyes.
He, too, had resolved. contrary to his first
intention, not to speak of his knowledge
of the beautiful patient's identity. Curiosity 
was on tiptoe; expectancy was in
the air. All felt that something unusual
was about to happen.</p>

<p>Now Reuel, with gentle fingers,
touched rapidly the clammy brow, the icy,
livid hands. the region of the pulseless
heart. No breath came from between
the parted lips; the life-giving organ was
motionless. As he concluded his examination, 
he turned to the assembled doctors:</p>

<p>"As I diagnose this case, it is one of
suspended animation. This woman has
been long and persistently subjected to

<pb facs="p103"/>

mesmeric influences, and the nervous
shock induced by the excitement of the
accident has thrown her into a cataleptic
sleep."</p>

<p>"But, man!" broke from the head physician 
in tones of exasperation, "rigor
mortis in unmistakable form is here. The
woman is dead!"</p>

<p>At these words there was a perceptible
smile on the faces of some of the students
&#8212;associates who resented his genius
as a personal affront, and who considered
these words as good as a reprimand for
the daring student, and a settler of his
pretensions. Malice and envy, from Adam's 
time until today, have loved a shining 
mark.</p>

<p>But the reproof was unheeded. Reuel
was not listening. Absorbed in thoughts
of the combat before him, he was oblivious 
to all else as he bent over the lifeless
figure on the cot. He was full of an earnest 
purpose. He was strung up to a
high tension of force and energy. As he
looked down upon the unconscious girl
whom none but he could save from the
awful fate of a death by post-mortem,
and who by some mysterious mesmeric
affinity existing between them, had drawn
him to her rescue, he felt no fear that he
should fail.</p>

<p>Suddenly he bent down and took both
cold hands into his left and passed his
right hand firmly over her arms from
shoulder to wrist. He repeated the movements 
several times; there was no response 
to the passes. He straightened
up, and again stood silently gazing upon
the patient. Then, like a man just
aroused from sleep, he looked across the
bed at Livingston and said abruptly:</p>

<p>"Dr. Livingston, will you go over to
my room and bring me the case of vials
in my medicine cabinet? I cannot leave
the patient at this point."</p>

<p>Livingston started in surprise as he replied: 
"Certainly, Briggs, if it will help
you any."</p>

<p>"The patient does not respond to anv
of the ordinary methods of awakening.

She would probably lie in this sleep for
months, and death ensue from exhaustion, 
if stronger remedies are not used to
restore the vital force to a normal condition."</p>

<p>Livingston left the hospital; he could
not return under an hour; Reuel took up
his station by the bed whereon was
stretched an apparently lifeless body, and
the other doctors went the rounds of the
wards attending to their regular routine
of duty. The nurses gazed at him curiously; 
the head doctor, upon whom the
young student's earnestness and sincerity 
had evidently made an impression,
came a number of times to the bare little
room to gaze upon its silent occupants,
but there was nothing new. When Livingston
returned, the group again gathered 
about the iron cot where lay the patient.</p>

<p>"Gentlemen," said Reuel, with quiet
dignity, when they were once more assembled, 
"will you individually examine
the patient once more and give your verdicts ?"</p>

<p>Once more doctors and students carefully 
examined the inanimate figure in
which the characteristics of death were
still more pronounced. On the outskirts
of the group hovered the house-surgeon's
assistants ready to transport the body to
the operating room for the post-mortem.
Again the head physician spoke, this time
impatiently.</p>

<p>"We are wasting our time, Dr. Briggs;
I pronounce the woman dead. She was
past medical aid when brought here."</p>

<p>"There is no physical damage, apparent 
or hidden, that you can see, Doctor?"
questioned Reuel, respectfully.</p>

<p>"No; it is a perfectly healthful organism, 
though delicate. I agree entirely
with your assertion that death was induced 
by the shock."</p>

<p>"Not <hi rend="italics">death</hi>, Doctor," protested Briggs.</p>

<p>"Well, well, call it what you like&#8212;call
it what you like, it amounts to the same
in the end," replied the doctor testily.</p>

<pb facs="p104"/>

<p>"Do you all concur in Doctor Hamilton's 
diagnosis?" Briggs included all
the physicians in his sweeping glance.
There was a general assent.</p>

<p>"I am prepared to show you that in
some cases of seeming death&#8212;or even
death in reality&#8212;consciousness may be
restored or the dead brought back to life.
I have numberless times in the past six
months restored consciousness to dogs
and cats after rigor mortis had set in, he
declared calmly.</p>

<p>"Bosh!" broke from a leading surgeon.
In this manner the astounding statement,
made in all seriousness, was received by
the group of scientists mingled with an
astonishment that resembled stupidity.
But in spite of their scoffs, the young student's 
confident manner made a decided
impression upon his listeners, unwilling
as they were to be convinced.</p>

<p>Reuel went on rapidly; his eyes kindled; 
his whole person took on the majesty 
of conscious power, and pride in the
knowledge he possessed. "I have found
by research that life is not dependent upon 
organic function as a principle. It
may be infused into organized bodies
even after the organs have ceased to perform 
their legitimate offices. Where
death has been due to causes which have
not impaired or injured or destroyed tissue 
formation or torn down the structure
of vital organs, life may be recalled when
it has become entirely extinct, which is
not so in the present case. This I have
discovered by my experiments in animal
magnetism."</p>

<p>The medical staff was fairly bewildered. 
Again Dr. Hamilton spoke:</p>

<p>"You make the assertion that the dead
can be brought to life, if I understand
your drift, Dr. Briggs, and you expect
us to believe such utter nonsense." He
added significantly, "My colleagues and
I are here to be convinced."</p>

<p>"If you will be patient for a short time
longer, Doctor, I will support my assertion 
by action. The secret of life lies in

what we call volatile magnetism&#8212;it exists 
in the free atmosphere. You, Dr.
Livingston, understand my meaning; do
you see the possibility in my words?" he
questioned, appealing to Aubrey for the
first time.</p>

<p>I have a faint conception of your
meaning, certainly, replied his friend.</p>

<p>"This <sic>subtile</sic> magnetic agent is constantly 
drawn into the body through the
lungs, absorbed and held in bounds until
chemical combination has occurred
through the medium of mineral agents
always present in normal animal tissue
When respiration ceases this magnetism
cannot be drawn into the lungs. It must
be artificially supplied. This, gentlemen,
is my discovery. I supply this magnetism. 
I have it here in the case Dr. Livingston 
has kindly brought me." He
held up to their gaze a small phial
wherein reposed a powder. Physicians
and students, now eager listeners, gazed
spell-bound upon him, straining their ears
to catch every tone of the low voice and
every change of the luminous eyes; they
pressed forward to examine the contents
of the bottle. It passed from eager hand
to eager hand, then back to the owner.</p>

<p>"This compound, gentlemen, is an exact 
reproduction of the conditions existing 
in the human body. It has common
salt for its basis. This salt is saturated
with oleo resin and then exposed for several 
hours in an atmosphere of free ammonia. 
The product becomes a powder,
and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> brings back the seeming dead to
life."</p>

<p>"Establish your theory by practical
demonstration, Dr. Briggs, and the
dreams of many eminent practitioners
will be realized," said Dr. Hamilton,
greatly agitated by his words.</p>

<p>"Your theory smacks of the supernatural, 
Dr. Briggs, charlatanism, or dreams
of lunacy," said the surgeon. "We leave
such assertions to quacks, generally, for
the time of miracles is past."</p>

<p>"The supernatural presides over man's

<pb facs="p105"/>

formation always," returned Reuel, quietly. 
"Life is that evidence of supernatural 
endowment which originally entered
nature during the formation of the units
for the evolution of man. Perhaps the
superstitious masses came nearer to solving 
the mysteries of creation than the favored 
elect will ever come. Be that as it
may, I will not contend. I will proceed
with the demonstration."</p>

<p>There radiated from the speaker the
potent <sic>pressence</sic> of a truthful mind, a
pure, unselfish nature, and that inborn
dignity which repels the shafts of lower
minds as ocean's waves absorb the drops
of rain. Something like respect mingled
with awe hushed the sneers, changing
them into admiration as he calmly proceeded 
to administer the so-called life-giving 
powder. Each man's wat.h was
in his hand; one minute passed&#8212;another
&#8212;and still another. The body remained
inanimate.</p>

<p>A cold smile of triumph began to
dawn on the faces of the older members
of the profession, but it vanished in its
incipiency, for a tremor plainly passed
over the rigid form before them. Another 
second&#8212;another convulsive movement
of the chest!</p>

<p>"She moves!" cried Aubrey at last,
carried out of himself by the strain on his
nerves. "Look, gentlemen, she breathes!
<hi rend="italics">She is alive</hi>; Briggs is right! Wonderful!
Wonderful!"</p>

<p>"We said there could not be another
miracle, and here it is!" exclaimed Dr.
Hamilton with strong emotion.</p>

<p>Five minutes more and the startled
doctors fell back from the bedside at a
motion of Reuel's hand. A wondering
nurse, with dilated eyes, unfolded a
screen, placed it in position and came and
stood beside the bed opposite Reuel.
Holding Dianthe's hands, he said in a
low voice: "Are you awake?" Her eyes
unclosed in a cold, indifferent stare which
gradually changed to one of recognition.
She looked at him&#8212;she smiled, and said

in a weak voice, "Oh, it is you; I dreamed
of you while I slept."</p>

<p>She was like a child&#8212;so trusting that
it went straight to the young man's heart.
and for an instant a great lump seemed
to rise in his throat and choke him. He
held her hands and chafed them, but
spoke with his eyes only. The nurse said
in a low voice: "Dr. Briggs, a few spoonfuls 
of broth will help her?"</p>

<p>"Yes, thank you, nurse; that will be
just right." He drew a chair close beside
the bed, bathed her face with water
and pushed back the tangle of bright
hair. He felt a great relief and quiet joy
that his experiment had been successful.</p>

<p>"Have I been ill? Where am I?" she
asked after a pause, as her face grew
troubled and puzzled.</p>

<p>"No, but you have been asleep a long
time; we grew anxious about you. You
must not talk until you are stronger."</p>

<p>The muse returned with the broth;
Dianthe drank it eagerly and called for
water, then with her hand still clasped
in Reuel's she sank into a deep sleep,
breathing softly like a tired child.
It was plain to the man of science that
hope for the complete restoration of her
faculties would depend upon time, nature
and constitution. Her effort to collect
her thoughts was unmistakable. In her
sleep, presently, from her lips fell incoherent 
words and phrases; but through it
all she clung to Reuel's hand, seeming to
recognize in him a friend.</p>

<p>A little later the doctors filed in noiselessly 
and stood about the bed gazing
down upon the sleeper with awe, listening 
to her breathing, feeling lightly the
fluttering pulse. Then they left the quiet
house of suffering, marvelling at the miracle 
just accomplished in their presence.
Livingston lingered with Briggs after
the other physicians were gone.</p>

<p>"This is a great day for you, Reuel,"
he said, as he laid a light caressing hand
upon the other's shoulder.</p>

<p>Reuel seized the hand in a quick convulsive

<pb facs="p106"/>

clasp. "True and tried friend, do
not credit me more than I deserve. No
praise is due me. I am an instrument&#8212;
how I know not&#8212;a child of circumstances. 
Do you not perceive something
strange in this case? Can you not deduce
conclusions from your own intimate
knowledge of this science?"</p>

<p>"What can you mean, Reuel?"</p>

<p>"I mean&#8212;it is a <hi rend="italics">dual</hi> mesmeric trance!
The girl is only partly normal now. Binet
speaks at length of this possibility in his
treatise. We have stumbled upon an
extraordinary case. It will take a year to
restore her to perfect health."</p>

<p>"In the meantime we ought to search
out her friends."</p>

<p>"Is there any hurry, Aubrey?" pleaded
Reuel, anxiously.</p>

<p>"Why not wait until her memory returns; 
it will not be long, I believe, although 
she may still be liable to the
trances."</p>

<p>"We'll put off the evil day to any date
you may name, Briggs; for my part, I
would preserve her incognito indefinitely."</p>

<p>Reuel made no reply. Livingston was
not sure that he heard him.</p>

<p>Chapter V.</p>

<p>The world scarcely estimates the service 
rendered by those who have unlocked 
the gates of sensation by the revelations 
of science: and yet it is to the
clear perception of things which we obtain 
by the study of nature's laws that
we are enabled to appreciate her varied
gifts. The scientific journals of the next
month contained wonderful and <hi rend="italics">wondering</hi> (?) accounts of the now celebrated
case,&#8212;re-animation after seeming death.
Reuel's lucky star was in the ascendant;
fame and fortune awaited him; he had
but to grasp them. Classmates who had
once <sic>ingored</sic> him now sought familiar association, 
or else gazed upon him with
awe and reverence. "How did he do it?"

was the query in each man's mind, and
then came a stampede for all scientific
matter bearing upon animal magnetism.</p>

<p>How often do we look in wonder at the
course of other men's lives, whose paths
have diverged so widely from the beaten
track of our own, that, unable to comprehend 
the one spring upon which, perhaps,
the whole secret of the diversity hinged,
we have been fain to content ourselves
with summing up our judgment in the
common phrase, "Well, it's very strange;
what odd people there are in the world.
to be sure!"</p>

<p>Many times this trite sentence was uttered 
during the next few months, generally 
terminating every debate among
medical students in various colleges.</p>

<p>Unmindful of his growing popularity,
Reuel devoted every moment of his spare
time to close study of his patient. Although 
but a youth, the scientist might
have passed for any age under fifty, and
life for him seemed to have taken on a
purely mechanical aspect since he had become 
first in this great cause. Under pretended 
indifference to public criticism.
throbbed a heart of gold, sensitive to a
fault; desiring above all else the well-being 
of all humanity: his faithfulness to
those who suffered amounted to complete
self-sacrifice. Absolutely free from the
vices which beset most young men of his
age and profession, his daily life was a
white, unsullied page to the friend admitted 
to unrestricted intercourse, and
gave an irresistible impetus to that friendship, 
for Livingston could not but admire
the newly developed depths of nobility
which he now saw unfolding day by day
in Reuel's character. Nor was Livingston 
far behind the latter in his interest
in all that affected Dianthe. Enthused by
its scientific aspect, he vied with Reuel in
close attention to the medical side of the
case, and being more worldly did not neglect 
the material side.</p>

<p>He secretly sought out and obtained
the address of the manager of the jubilee

<pb facs="p107"/>

singers and to his surprise received
the information that Miss Lusk had left
the troupe to enter the service of a traveling 
magnetic physician&#8212;a woman&#8212;for
a large salary. They (the troupe) were
now in Europe and had heard nothing
of Miss Lusk since.</p>

<p>After receiving this information by
cable, Livingston sat a long time smoking 
and thinking: people often disappeared 
in a great city, and the police
would undoubtedly find the magnetic
physician if he applied to them. Of
course that was the sensible thing to do,
but then the publicity, and he hated that
for the girl's sake. Finally he decided to
compromise the matter by employing a
detective. With him to decide that it was
expedient to do a certain thing was the
same as to act; before night the case was
in the hands of an expert detective who
received a goodly retainer. Two weeks
from that day&#8212;it was December twenty-fourth
&#8212;before he left his boarding place,
the detective was announced. He had
found the woman in a small town near
Chicago. She said that she had no knowledge 
of Miss Lusk's whereabouts. Dianthe 
had remained with her three weeks,
and at the end of that time had mysteriously 
disappeared; she had not heard of
her since.</p>

<p>Livingston secured the woman's name
and address, gave the man a second check
together with an admonition to keep silence 
concerning Miss Lusk. That closed
the episode. But of his observations and
discoveries, Aubrey said nothing, noting
every phase of this strange happening in
silence.</p>

<p>Strangely enough, none of the men
that had admired the colored artist who
had enthralled their senses by her wonderful 
singing a few weeks before, rec-
ognized her in the hospital waif consecrated 
to the service of science. Her incognito 
was complete.</p>

<p>The patient was now allowed the freedom 
of the corridors for exercise, and

was about her room during the day. The
returns of the trance-state were growing
less regular, although she frequently fell
into convulsions, thereby enduring much
suffering, sometimes lying for hours in a
torpid state. Livingston had never happened 
to be present on these occasions,
but he had heard of them from eye-witnesses. 
One day he entered the room
while one was occurring. His entrance
was unnoticed as he approached lightly
over the uncarpeted floor, and stood
transfixed by the scene before him.</p>

<p>Dianthe stood upright, with closed
eyes, in the middle of the room. Only the
movement of her bosom betrayed breath.
The other occupants of the room preserved 
a solemn silence. She addressed
Reuel, whose outstretched arms were extended 
as if in blessing over her head.</p>

<p>"Oh! Dearest friend! hasten to cure
me of my sufferings. Did you not promise 
at that last meeting? You said to me,
'You are in trouble and I can help you.'
And I answered, 'The time is not yet.' Is
it not so?"</p>

<p>"Yes," replied Reuel. "Patience a
while longer; all will be well with you."</p>

<p>"Give me the benefit of your powerful
will," she continued. "I know much but
as yet have not the power to express it;
I see much clearly, much dimly, of the
powers and influences behind the Veil,
and yet I cannot name them. Some time
the full power will be mine; and mine
shall be thine. In seven months the sick
will be restored&#8212;she will awake to
worldly cares once more." Her voice
ceased; she sank upon the cot in a recumbent 
position. Her face was pale;
she appeared to sleep. Fifteen minutes
passed in death-like stillness, then she
extended her arms, stretched, yawned,
rubbed her eyves&#8212;awoke.</p>

<p>Livingston listened and looked in a
trance of delight, his keen artistic sense
fully aroused and appreciative, feeling
the glamour of her presence and ethereal
beauty like a man poring over a poem

<pb facs="p108"/>

that he has unexpectedly stumbled upon,
losing himself in it, until it becomes, as
it were, a part of himself. He felt as he
watched her that he was doing a foolish
thing in thus exposing himself to temptation 
while his honor and faith were
pledged to another. But then, foolishness 
is so much better than wisdom, particularly 
to a man in certain stages of life.
And then he fell to questioning if there
could be temptation for him through this
girl&#8212;he laughed at the thought and the
next instant dismay covered him with
confusion, for like a flash he realized that
the mischief was already done.</p>

<p>As we have already hinted, Aubrey
was no saint; he knew that fickleness was
in his blood; he had never denied himself 
anything that he wanted very much
in his whole life. Would he grow to want
this beautiful woman very much? Time
would tell.</p>

<p>* * * *</p>

<p>It was Christmas-time&#8212;a good, sensible
seasonable day before Christmas, with frost
and ice in abundance, and a clear, bright,
wintry sky above. Boston was very full
of people&#8212;mostly suburban visitors&#8212;
who were rushing here and there bent on
emptying their purses on the least provocation. 
Good-nature prevailed among
the pedestrians; one poor wretch stood
shivering, with blue, wan face, on the
edge of the sidewalk, his sightless eyes
staring straight before him, trying to
draw a tune from a consumptive violin
&#8212;the embodiment of despair. He was,
after all, in the minority, to judge by the
hundreds of comfortably-clad forms that
hurried past him, breathing an atmosphere 
of peace and prosperity.</p>

<p>Tomorrow the church bells would ring
out tidings that another Christmas was
born, bidding all rejoice.</p>

<p>This evening, at six o'clock, the two
friends went to dine in a hotel in a fashionable 
quarter. They were due to spend
the night and Christmas day at the Vance
house. As they walked swiftly along

with the elastic tread of youth, they
simultaneously halted before the blind
musician and pressed into his trembling
hand a bountiful gift; then they hurried
away to escape his thanks.</p>

<p>At the hotel Livingston called for a private 
dining room, and after the coffee
was served, he said:</p>

<p>"Tell me, Briggs, what is the link between 
you and your patient. There is a
link, I am sure. Her words while in the
trance made a great impression upon
me."</p>

<p>There was a pause before Reuel replied 
in a low tone, as he rested his arm
on the opposite side of the table and
propped his head up on his hand:</p>

<p>"Forgive me, Aubrey!"</p>

<p>"For what?"</p>

<p>"This playing with your confidence. I
have not been entirely frank with you."</p>

<p>"Oh, well! you are not bound to tell
me everything you know. You surely
have the right to silence about your affairs, 
if you think best."</p>

<p>"Listen, Aubrey. I should like to tell
you all about it. I would feel better.
What you say is true; there is a link; but
I never saw her in the flesh before that
night at the Temple. With all our
knowledge, Aubrey, we are but barbarians 
in our ideas of the beginning, interim
and end of our creation. Why were we
created? for whose benefit? can anyone
answer that satisfactorily?</p>

<p>"'Few things are hidden from the man
who devotes himself earnestly and seriously 
to the solution of a mystery,' Hawthorne 
tells us," replied Aubrey. "Have
not you proved this, Reuel?"</p>

<p>"Well, yes&#8212;or, we prove rather, that
our solution but deepens the mystery or
mysteries. I have surely proved the last.
Aubrey, I look natural, don't I? There is
nothing about me that seems wrong?"</p>

<p>"Wrong! No."</p>

<p>"Well, if I tell you the truth you will
call me a lunatic. You have heard of
people being haunted by hallucinations?"

<pb facs="p109"/>

Aubrey nodded. 'I am one of those persons. 
Seven weeks ago I saw Dianthe
first, but not in the flesh. Hallow-eve I
spoke to her in the garden of the haunted
house, but not in the flesh. I thought 't
strange to be sure, that this face should
lurk in my mind so much of the time;
but I never dreamed what a crisis it was
leading up to. The French and German
schools of philosophy have taught us
that going to places and familiar passages
in books, of which we have had no previous 
knowledge, is but a proof of
Plato's doctrine&#8212;the soul's transmigration, 
and reflections from the invisible
world surrounding us.</p>

<p>"Finally a mad desire seized me to find
that face a living reality that I might
love and worship it. Then I saw her at
the Temple&#8212;I found her at the hospital
&#8212;<hi rend="italics">in the flesh!</hi> My desire was realized."</p>

<p>"And having found her, what then?"
He waited breathlessly for the reply.</p>

<p>"I am mightily pleased and satisfied. I
will cure her. She is charming; and if it
is insanity to be in love with her, I don't
care to be sane."</p>

<p>Livingston did not reply at once. His
face was like marble in its impassiveness.
The other's soft tremulous tones, fearless
yet moist eyes and broken sentences, appeared 
to awaken no response in his
breast. Instead, a far-off gleam came into 
his blue eyes. At last he broke the silence 
with the words:</p>

<p>"You name it well; it is insanity indeed, 
for you to love this woman."</p>

<p>"Why?" asked his friend, constrainedly.</p>

<p>"Because it is not for the best."</p>

<p>"For her or me?"</p>

<p>"Oh, for <hi rend="italics">her</hi> &#8212;!" he finished the
sentence with an expressive gesture.</p>

<p>"I understand you, Aubrey. I should
not have believed it of you. If it were
one of the other fellows; but you are
generally so charitable."</p>

<p>"You forget your own words: 'Tramps,
stray dogs and Negroes &#8212;.'" he

quoted significantly. "Then there 1s your
professional career to be considered,&#8212;you
mean honorable, do you not? &#8212; How
can you succeed if it be hinted abroad that
you are married to a Negress?"</p>

<p>"I have thougnt of all that. I am determined. 
I will marry her in spite of hell
itself! Marry her before she awakens to
consciousness of her identity. I'm not
unselfish; I don't pretend to be. There
is no sin in taking her out of the sphere
where she was born. God and science
helping me, I will give her life and love
and wifehood and maternity and perfect
health. God, Aubrey! you, with all you
have had of life's sweetness, petted idol
of a beautiful world, you who will soon
feel the heart-beats of your wife against
your breast when lovely Molly is eternally
bound to you, what do you know of a
<sic>lonelly</sic>, darkened life like mine? I have
not the manner nor the charm which
wins women. Men like me get love from
them which is half akin to pity, when
they get anything at all. It is but the
shadow. This is my opportunity for happiness; 
I seize it. Fate has linked us together 
and no man and no man's laws
shall part us."</p>

<p>Livingston sipped his wine quietly, intently 
watching Reuel's face. Now he
leaned across the table and stretched out
his hand to Briggs; his eyes looked full
into his. As their hands met in a close
clasp, he whispered a sentence across the
board. Reuel started, uttered an exclamation 
and flushed slowly a dark, dull red.</p>

<p>"How&#8212;where&#8212;how did you know
it?" he stammered.</p>

<p>"I have known it since first we met; but
the secret is safe with me."</p>

<p>Chapter VI.</p>

<p>The scene which met the gaze when an
hour later the young men were ushered
into the long drawing-room of the Vance
house was one well-calculated to remove
all gloomy, pessimistic reasoning.

<pb facs="p110"/>

Warmth, gaiety, pretty women, luxury,&#8212;
all sent the blood leaping through the
veins in delightful anticipation.</p>

<p>Their entrance was greeted by a shout
of welcome.</p>

<p>"Oh, Aubrey! I am so glad you are
come," cried Molly from the far end of
the room. "Fancy tomorrow being
Christmas! Shall we be ready for all that
company tomorrow night and the ballroom, 
dining room and hall yet to be
trimmed? Is it possible to be ready?"</p>

<p>"Not if we stand dwadling in idle talk."
This from "Adonis," who was stretched
full length on the sitting-room sofa, with
a cigarette between his lips, his hands
under his handsome head, surrounded by
a bevy of pretty, chattering girls, prominent 
among whom was Cora Scott, who
aided and <sic>abbetted</sic> Charlie in every piece
of mischief.</p>

<p>Molly curled her lip but deigned no
reply.</p>

<p>Bert Smith, from a corner of the room
where he was about ascending a step-ladder, 
flung a book heavily at Adonis's lazy
figure.</p>

<p>"Don't confuse your verbs," exclaimed
Aubrey. "How can you stand when you
are lying down, and were you ever known
to do anything else but dwadle, Adonis&#8212;
eh?"</p>

<p>"I give it up," said Charlie, sleepily,
kicking the book off the sofa.</p>

<p>"Is this an amateur grocery shop, may
I ask, Miss Vance?" continued Aubrey as
he and Briggs made their way to their
hostess through an avalanche of parcels
and baskets strewn on the tables and the
floor.</p>

<p>Molly laughed as she greeted them.
"No wonder you are surprised. I am
superintending the arrangement of my
poor people's gifts," she explained. "They
must all be sent out tonight. I don't
know what I should have done without all
these good people to help me. But there
are <hi rend="italics">piles</hi> to be done yet. There is the

tree, the charades, etc., etc.," she continued, 
in a plaintive little voice.</p>

<p>"More particularly cetra, cetra," said
Aubrey from Bert's corner where he had
gone to help along the good works of
placing holly wreaths.</p>

<p>"Oh, you, Aubey&#8212;stop being a mag.
pie." Aubrey and Molly were very matter 
of fact lovers.</p>

<p>"Molly," again broke in Charlie, "suppose 
the box from Pierson's has never
come, won't you be up a tree?" and the
speaker opened his handsome eyes wide,
and shook off his cigarette-ash.</p>

<p>Molly maintained a dignified silence toward 
her brother. The firelight danced
and dwelt upon her lovingly. She was so
pretty, so fair, so slender, so graceful.
Now in her gray plush tea-gown, with her
hair piled picturesquely on the top of her
small head, and fixed there with a big
tortoise-shell pin, it would have been difficult 
to find a more delightful object for
the gaze to rest upon.</p>

<p>"We shall have to fall back upon the
wardrobes," she said at length. "You
are a horrid wet-blanket, Charlie! I am
sure I&#8212;"</p>

<p>Her remarks were cut short as the door
opened, and with laughter and shouting
a bevy of young people who had been at
work in another part of the house rushed
in. "It is come; it's all right; don't
worry, Molly!" they sang in chorus.</p>

<p>"Do be quiet all of vou; one can hardly
hear oneself speak!"</p>

<p>The box from the costumer's had arrived; 
the great costume party was saved;
in short, excitement and bustle were in
full swing at Vance Hall as it had been at
Christmas-time since the young people
could remember.</p>

<p>Adonis lifted himself from the sofa
and proposed to open the box of dresses
at once, and trv them on.</p>

<p>"Charlie, you are a brick!&#8212;the very
thing!"</p>

<p>"Oh! yes, yes; let us try them on!"</p>

<p>Molly broke through the eager voices:

<pb facs="p111"/>

"And we have not done the ball-room
yet!" she said reproachfully.</p>

<p>"Oh! bother the ball-room!" declared
Adonis, now thoroughly aroused. "We
have all night. We can't do better than
to don our finery."</p>

<p>Molly sat down with an air of resigned
patience. "I promised Mr. Pierson," she
observed quietly, "that the box should not
be touched until he was here to superintend 
matters."</p>

<p>"Oh, Pierson be blowed!" elegantly observed 
her brother. But Reuel Briggs
suddenly dropped his work, walked over,
and sided with Molly.</p>

<p>"You are quite right, Miss Molly; and
you Charlie and Aubrey and the rest of
you men, if you want to open the box tonight
you must first decorate the ballroom.
Business before pleasure."</p>

<p>"Saved!&#8212;saved! See my brave, true
Knight defends his lady fair." Molly
danced, practising the step she was about
to astonish the company with on Christmas-night. 
"I think I am what the Scotch
call 'fev' she laughed. "I don't know
why I feel so awfully jolly tonight. I
could positively fly from sheer excitement
and delight."</p>

<p>"Don't you know why?" observed Cora.
"I will tell you. It is because this is
your last Christmas as Molly Vance; next
year&#8212;"</p>

<p>"Ah, do not!" interrupted Molly, quickly. 
"Who knows what a year may bring
forth. Is it net so, Dr. Briggs?" she
turned appealingly to Reuel.</p>

<p>"Grief follows joy as clouds the sunlight. 
'Woe! woe! each heart must bleed,
must break,'" was his secret thought as
he bowed gravely. But on his face was a
look of startled perplexity, for suddenly
as she spoke to him it appeared that a
dark veil settled like a pall over the laughing 
face at his side. He shivered.</p>

<p>"What's the matter, Briggs?" called
out Adonis. They had reached the ballroom 
and were standing over the piles
of holly and evergreen, ready for an onslaught
on the walls.</p>

<p>"Don't be surprised if Briggs acts
strangely," continued Charlie. "It is in
order for him to whoop it up in the spirit
line."</p>

<p>"Why, Charlie! What do you mean?"
questioned Molly with an anxious glance
ut Reuel.</p>

<p>"Anything interesting, Charlie?" called
out a jolly girl across the room.</p>

<p>"Briggs is our 'show' man. Haven't
you heard, girls, what a celebrity is with
you tonight? Briggs is a philosopher&#8212;
mesmerism is his specialty. Say, old
man, give the company a specimen of
your infernal art, can't you? He goes the
whole hog, girls; can even raise the
dead."</p>

<p>"Let up, Charlie," said Aubrey in a
low tone. It's no joking matter."</p>

<p>There were screams and exclamations
from the girls. With reckless gaiety
Adonis continued,</p>

<p>"What is to be the outcome of the
great furore you have created, Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Nothing of moment, I hope," smiled
Reuel, good-naturedly. I have been
simply an instrument; I leave results to
the good angels who direct events. What
does Longfellow say about the arrow
and the song?

<q>'Long, lone afterwards, in an oak<lb/>
I found the arrow still unbroke;<lb/>
And the song, from beginning to end,
I found in the heart of a friend.'</q>

May it be so with my feeble efforts."</p>

<p>"But circumstances alter cases. In this
case, the 'arrow' is a girl and a devilish
handsome one, too; and the 'air' is the
whole scientific world. Your philosophy
and mysticism gave way before Beauty.
Argument is a stubborn man's castle, but
the heart is still unconvinced."</p>

<p>"'I mixed those children up, and not
a creature knew it,'" hummed Bert
Smith. "Your ideas are mixed, Don;
stick to the ladies, you understand girls
and horseflesh: philosophy isn't in your
line."</p>

<pb facs="p112"/>

<p>"Oh, sure!" said Adonis unruffled by
his friend's words.</p>

<p>"Charlie Vance," said Molly severely,
"if we have any more <hi rend="italics">swearing</hi> from you
to night, you leave the room until you
learn to practice good manners. I'm surprised 
at your language!"</p>

<p>"Just the same, Briggs is a fraud. I
shall keep my eye on him. It's a case of
beauty and the beast. Oh," he continued
in malicious glee, "wouldn't you girls
turn green with envy, every man jack of
you, if you could see the beauty!"</p>

<p>Thereupon the girls fell to pelting him
with holly wreaths and evergreen festoons, 
much to the enjoyment of Mr.
Vance, who had entered unperceived in
the general melee.</p>

<p>"What is it all about, Dr. Briggs?"
asked Molly in a low voice.</p>

<p>"It is the case of a patient who was in
a mesmeric sleep and I was fortunate
enough to awaken her. She is a waif;
and it will be months before she will be
well and strong, poor girl."</p>

<p>"Do you make a study of mesmerism,
Doctor?" asked Mr. Vance from his armchair 
by the glowing fire.</p>

<p>"Yes sir; and a wonderful science it is."
Before Mr. Vance could continue, Livingston 
said: "If you folks will be still for
about ten minutes, I'll tell you what
happened in my father's house when I
was a very small boy; I can just remember 
it."</p>

<p>"If it's a ghost story, make it strong,
Aubrey, so that not a girl will sleep tonight. 
Won't the dears look pretty blinking 
and yawning tomorrow night? We'll
hear 'em, fellows, in the small hours of
the morning, 'Molly, Molly! I'm so
frightened. I do believe someone is in my
room; may I come in with you, dear?'"</p>

<p>"Charlie, stop your <sic>nonsence</sic>," laughed
his father, and Adonis obediently subsided.</p>

<p>"My father was Dr. Aubrey Livingston
too," began Aubrey, "and he owned a
large plantation of slaves. My father was

deeply interested in the science of medicine, 
and I believe made some valuable
discoveries along the line of mesmeric
phenomena, for some two or three of his
books are referred to even at this advanced 
stage of discovery, as marvellous
in some of their data.</p>

<p>"Among the slaves was a girl who was
my mother's waiting maid, and I have
seen my father throw her into a trance-state 
many times when I was so small that
I had no conception of what he was doing.</p>

<p>"Many a time I have known him to call
her into the parlor to perform tricks of
mind-reading for the amusement of visitors, 
and many wonderful things were
done by her as the record given in his
books shows.</p>

<p>"One day there was a great dinner
party given at our place, and the êlite
of the county were bidden. It was about
two years before the civil war, and our
people were not expecting war; thinking
that all unpleasantness must end in their
favor, they gave little heed to the ominous 
rumble of public opinion that was
arising at the North, but went on their
way in all their pride of position and
wealth without a care for the future.</p>

<p>"Child as I was I was impressed by the
beauty and wit of the women and the
chivalric hearing of the men gathered
about my father's hospitable board on that
memorable day. When the feasting and
mirth began to lag, someone called for
Mira&#8212;the maid&#8212;and my father sent for
her to come and amuse the guests.</p>

<p>"My father made the necessary passes
and from a serious, rather sad Negress,
very mild with everyone, Mira changed to
a gay, noisy, restless woman, full of irony
and sharp jesting. In this case this
peculiar metamorphosis always occurred.
Nothing could be more curious than to
see her and hear her. 'Tell the company 
what you see, Mira,' commanded
my father.</p>

<p>"You will not like it, captain; but if I

<pb facs="p113"/>

must, I must. All the women will be
widows and the men shall sleep in early
graves. They come from the north, from
the east, from the west, they sweep to the
gulf through a trail of blood. Your
houses shall burn, your fields be laid
waste, and a down-trodden race shall rule
in your land. For you, captain, a prison
cell and a pauper's grave."</p>

<p>The dinner-party broke up in a panic.
and from that time my father could not
abide the girl. He finally sold her just
a few months before the secession of the
Confederate States, and that was the last
we ever knew of her."</p>

<p>"And did the prophecy come true about
your father? asked Mr. Vance.</p>

<p>"Too true, sir; my father died while
held as a prisoner of war, in Boston Harbor. 
And every woman at the table was
left a widow. There is only too much
truth in science of mesmeric phenomena.
The world ts a wonderful place."</p>

<p>"Wonderful!" declared his hearers.</p>

<p>"I am thinking of that poor, pretty
creature lying ill in that gloomy hospital
without a friend. Men are selfish! I tell
you what, folks, tomorrow after lunch
we'll make a Christmas visit to the
patients, and carry them fruit and flowers.
As for your beautiful patient, Dr. Briggs,
she shall not be friendless any longer, she

shall come to us at Vance Hall."</p>

<p>"Molly!" broke simultaneously from
Aubrey and Charlie.</p>

<p>"Oh, I mean it. There is plenty of
room in this great house, and here she
shall remain until she is restored to
health."</p>

<p>Expostulation was in vain. The petted
heiress was determined, and when Mr.
Vance was appealed to he laughed and
said, as he patted her hand:</p>

<p>"The queen must have her own."</p>

<p>At length the costumer's box was
opened amidst jest, song and laughter.
The characters were distributed by the
wilful Molly. Thus attired, to the music
of Tannhauser's march, played by one of
the girls on the piano, the gay crowd
marched and counter-marched about the
spacious room.</p>

<p>In the early morning hours, Aubrey
Livingston slept and dreamed of Dianthe
Lusk, and these words haunted his sleep
and lingered with him when he woke:</p>

<p>"She had the glory of heaven in her
voice, and in her face the fatal beauty of
man's terrible sins."</p>

<p>Aubrey Livingston knew that he was
as hopelessly lost as was Adam when he
sold his heavenly birthright for a
woman's smile.</p>

<p>(To be continued.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.003">

<pb facs="p191"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Synopsis of Chapters I to VI.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, a young medical student, interested in
mysticism, sees a face that haunts him. He attends a
concert with his friend Aubrey Livingston, and there
discovers in a negro concert-singer the owner of the
mysterious face. He sees this woman again on Hallow
Eve while playing at charms with a party of young
people at Vance Hall, the home of Livingston's betrothed. 
Early the next morning he is called to attend
the victims of a railroad disaster at the hospital. He
finds among them the girl whose face haunts him, in a
cataleptic sleep which the doctors call death. He succeeds 
in restoring her to consciousness, but with a
complete loss of memory. She loses her identity as a
negress. Reuel falls deeply in love with her.</p>

<p>Chapter VII.</p>

<p>Through days and days, and again
through days and days, over and over
again, Reuel Briggs fought to restore his
patient to a normal condition of health.
Physically, he succeeded ; but mentally his
treatment was a failure. Memory remained 
a blank to the unhappy girl. Her
life virtually began with her awakening
at the hospital. A look of wonder and a
faint smile were the only replies that
questions as to the past elicited from her.
Old and tried specialists in brain diseases
and hypnotic states came from every part
of the Union on bootless errands. It was
decided that nothing could be done; rest,
freedom from every care and time might
eventually restore the poor, violated mind
to its original strength. Thus it was that
Dianthe became the dear adopted daughter 
of the medical profession. Strange to
say, Molly Vance secured her desire, and
wearing the name of Felice Adams.
Dianthe was domiciled under the roof of
palatial Vance hall, and the small annuity
provided by the generous contributions of
the physicians of the country was placed
in the hands of Mr. Vance, Sr., to be expended 
for their protege.</p>

<p>The astonishing nature of the startling
problems he had unearthed, the agitation

and indignation aroused in him by the
heartless usage to which his patient must
have been exposed, haunted Briggs day
and night. He believed that he had been
drawn into active service for Dianthe by
a series of strange <sic>coincidencies</sic>, and the
subtle forces of immortality; what future
acts this service might require he knew
not, he cared not; he registered a solemn
promise to perform all tasks allotted him
by Infinity, to the fullest extent of his
power.</p>

<p>The brilliant winter days merged themselves 
into spring. After one look into
Dianthe's eves, so deep, clear and true,
Molly Vance had surrendered unconditionally 
to the charm of the beautiful
stranger, drawn by an irresistible bond of
sympathy. "Who would believe," she observed 
to Livingston, "that at this stage
of the world's progress one's identity
could be so easily lost and one still be
living. It is like a page from an exciting 
novel."</p>

<p>With the impulsiveness of youth, a
wonderful friendship sprang up between
the two; they rode, walked and shopped
together; in short, became inseparable
companions. The stranger received every
attention in the family that could be given
an honored guest. Livingston and Briggs
watched her with some anxiety; would
she be able to sustain the position of intimate 
friendship to which Molly had
elected her? But both breathed more
freely when they noted her perfect manners, 
the ease and good-breeding displayed 
in all her intercourse with those
socially above the level to which they
knew this girl was born. She accepted
the luxury of her new surroundings as
one to the manner born.</p>

<pb facs="p192"/>

<p>"We need not have feared for her; by
Jove, she's a thorough-bred!" exclaimed
Aubrey one day to Reuel. The latter
nodded as he locked up from his book.</p>

<p>"And why not? Probably the best
blood of the country flows in the poor
girl's veins. Who can tell? Why should
she not be a thorough-bred."</p> 

<p>"True," replied Aubrey, as a slight
frown passed over his face.</p>

<p>"I am haunted by a possibility, Aubrey," 
continued Reuel. "What if memory 
suddenly returns? Is it safe to risk
the unpleasantness of a public reawakening 
of her sleeping faculties? I have
read of such things."</p>

<p>Aubrey shrugged his handsome shoulders. 
"We must risk something for the
sake of science; where no one is injured
by deception there is no harm done."</p>

<p>"Now that question has presented itself
to me repeatedly lately: Is deception
justifiable for any reason? Somehow it
haunts me that trouble may come from
this. I wish we had told the exact truth
about her identity."</p>

<p>"'If 'twere done when 'tis done, then
"twere well it were done quickly" murmured 
Aubrey with a sarcastic smile on
his face. "How you balk at nothing.
Reuel," he drawled mockingly.</p>

<p>"Oh, call me a fool and done with it,
Aubrey: I <sic>supose</sic> I am; but one didn't
make one's self."</p>

<p>Drives about the snow-clad suburbs of
Cambridge with Briggs and Molly, at
first helped to brighten the invalid; then
came quiet social diversions at which
Dianthe was the great attraction.</p>

<p>It was at an afternoon function that
Reuel took courage to speak of his love.
A dozen men buzzed about "Miss Adams"
in the great bay window where Molly had
placed Dianthe, her superb beauty set off
by a simple toilet. People came and went
constantly. Musical girls, generally with
gold eyeglasses on esthetic noses, played
grim classical preparations, which have as
cheerful an effect on a gay crowd as the

perfect, irreproachable skeleton of a bygone 
beauty might have; or articulate,
with cultivation and no voices to speak of,
arias which would sap the life of a true
child of song to render as the maestro intended.</p>

<p>The grand, majestic voice that had
charmed the hearts from thousands of
bosoms, was pinioned in the girl's throat
like an imprisoned song-bird. Dianthe's
voice was completely gone along with her
memory. But music affected her strangely, 
and Reuel watched her anxiously.</p>

<p>Her face was a study in its delicate,
quickly changing tints, its sparkle of
smiles running from the sweet, pure
tremor of the lovely mouth to the switt
laughter of eyes and voice.</p>

<p>Mindful of her infirmity, Reuel led her
to the conservatory to escape the music.
She lifted her eyes to his with a curious
and angelic light in them. She was conscious 
that he loved her with his whole
most loving heart. She winced under the
knowledge, for while she believed in him,
depended upon him and gathered strength
from his love, what she gave in return
was but a slight, cold affection compared
with his adoration.</p>

<p>He brought her refreshments in the
conservatory, and then told his love and
asked his fate. She did not answer at
once, but looked at his plain face, at the
stalwart elegance of his figure, and again
gazed into the dark, true, clever eyes, and
with the sigh of a tired child crept into
his arms, and into his heart for all time
and eternity. Thus Aubrey Livingston
found them when the company had departed. 
So it was decided to have the
wedding in June. What need for these
two children of misfortune to wait?</p>

<p>Briggs, with his new interest in life,
felt that it was good just to be alive. The
winter passed rapidly, and as he threaded
the streets coming and going to his hospital 
duties, his heart sang. No work was
now too arduous; he delighted in the duty
most exacting in its nature. As the spring

<pb facs="p193"/>

came in it brought with it thoughts of the
future. He was almost penniless, and he
saw no way of obtaining the money he
needed. He had not been improvident,
but his lonely life had lived a reckless
disregard of the future, and the value of
money. He often lived a day on bread
and water, at the same time sitting without 
a fire in the coldest weather because
his pockets were empty and he was too
proud to ask a loan, or solicit credit from
storekeepers. He now found himself in
great difficulty. His literary work and
the extra cases which his recent triumph
had brought him, barely sufficed for his
own present needs. Alone in his bachelor
existence he would call this luxury, but it
was not enough to furnish a suitable establishment 
for Dianthe. As the weeks
rolled by and nothing presented itself, he
grew anxious, and finally resolved to consult 
Livingston.</p>

<p>All things had become new to him, and
in the light of his great happiness the very
face of old Cambridge was changed. Fate
had always been against him, and had
played him the shabbiest of tricks, but
now he felt that she might do her worst,
he held a talisman against misfortune
while his love remained to him. Thinking
thus he walked along briskly, and
the sharp wind brought a faint color into
his sallow face. He tried to think and
plan, but his ideas were whirled away <sic>befort</sic> 
they had taken form, and he felt a
giant's power to overcome with each inspiring 
breath of the crisp, cool March
air. Aubrey should plan for him, but he
would accomplish.</p>

<p>Livingston had apartments on Dana
Hill, the most aristocratic portion of
Cambridge. There he would remain till
the autumn, when he would marry Molly
Vance, and remove to Virginia and renew 
the ancient splendor of his ancestral
home. He was just dressing for an evening 
at the theatre when Briggs entered
his rooms. He greeted him with his usual
genial warmth.</p>

<p>"What!" he said gaily, "the great scientist 
here, at this hour?"</p>

<p>Then noticing his visitor's anxious
countenance he added:</p>

<p>"What's the matter?"</p>

<p>"I am in difficulties and come to you
for help," replied Reuel.</p>

<p>"How so? What is it? I am always
anxious to serve you, Briggs."</p>

<p>"I certainly think so or I would not be
here now," said Reuel. "But you are just
going out, an engagement perhaps with
Miss Molly. My business will take some
time&#8212;"</p>

<p>Aubrey interrupted him, shaking his
head negatively. "I was only going out
to wile away the time at the theatre. Sit
down and free your mind, old man."</p>

<p>Thus admonished, Reuel flung himself
among the cushions of the divan, and began 
to state his reasons for desiring assistance; 
when he finished, Livingston
asked:</p>

<p>"Has nothing presented itself?"</p>

<p>"O yes; two or three really desirable
offers which I wrote to accept, but to my
surprise, in each case I received polite regrets 
that circumstances had arisen to prevent 
the acceptance of my valuable services. 
That is what puzzles me. What
the dickens did it mean?"</p>

<p>Aubrey said nothing but continued a
drum solo on the arm of his chair. Finally
he asked abruptly: "Briggs, do you
think anyone knows or suspects your
origin?"</p>

<p>Not a muscle of Reuel's face moved as
he replied, calmly: "I have been wondering 
if such can be the case."</p>

<p>"This infernal prejudice is something
horrible. It closes the door of hope and
opportunity in many a good man's face.
I am a Southerner, but I am ashamed of
my section," he added warmly.</p>

<p>Briggs said nothing, but a dark, dull
red spread slowly to the very roots of his
hair, Presently Aubrey broke the painful
silence.</p>

<p>"Briggs, I think I can help you."</p>

<pb facs="p194"/>

<p>"How ?"</p>

<p>"There's an expedition just about starting 
from England for Africa; its final
destination is, I believe, the site of ancient
Ethiopian cities; its object to unearth
buried cities and treasure which the shifting 
sands of Sahara have buried for centuries. 
This expedition lacks just such a
medical man as you; the salary is large,
but you must sign for two years; that is
my reason for not mentioning it before.
It bids fair to be a wonderful venture and
there will be plenty of glory for those
who return, beside the good it will do to
the Negro race if it proves the success in
discovery that scholars predict. I don't
advise you to even consider this opportunity, 
but you asked for my help and this
is all I can offer at present."</p>

<p>"But Dianthe!" exclaimed Reuel faintly.</p>

<p>"Yes," smiled Aubrey. "Don't I know
how I would feel if it were Molly and I
was in your place? You are like all other
men, Reuel. Passion does not calculate,
and therein lies its strength. As long as
common sense lasts we are not in love.
Now the answer to the question of ways
and means is with you; it is in your
hands. You will choose love and poverty 
I suppose; I should. There are people 
fools enough to tell a man in love to
keep cool. Bah! It is an impossible thing."</p>

<p>"Does true love destroy our reasoning
faculties ?" Reuel asked himself as he sat
there in silence after his friend ceased
speaking. He felt then that he could not
accept this offer. Finally he got upon his
feet, still preserving his silence, and made
ready to leave his friend. When he
reached the door, he turned and said: "I
will see you in the morning."</p>

<p>For a long time after Briggs had gone,
Aubrey sat smoking and gazing into the
glowing coals that filled the open grate.</p>

<p>All that night Reuel remained seated in
his chair or pacing the cheerless room,
conning ways and means to extricate himself 
from his dilemma without having recourse 

to the last extremity proposed by
Aubrey. It was a brilliant opening;
there was no doubt of that; a year&#8212;six
months ago&#8212;he would have hailed it with
delight, but if he accepted it, it would
raise a barrier between his love and him
which could not be overcome&#8212;the ocean
and thousands of miles.</p>

<p>"Oh, no!" he cried, "a thousand times
no! Rather give up my ambitions."</p>

<p>Then growing more rational he gazed
mournfully around the poor room and
asked himself if he could remain and see
his wife amid such surroundings? That
would be impossible. The question then,
resolved itself into two parts: If he remained 
at home, they could not marry,
therefore separation; if he went abroad,
marriage and separation. He caught at
the last thought eagerly. If then they
were doomed to separate, of two evils
why not choose the least? The African
position would at least bind them irrevocably 
together. Instantly hope resumed 
its sway in Reuel's breast so fertile
is the human mind in expedients to calm
the ruffled spirit; he began to estimate
the advantages he would gain by accepting 
the position: He could marry
Dianthe, settle a large portion of his
salary upon her thus rendering her independent 
of charity, leave her in the care
of the Vance family, and return in two
years a wealthy man no longer fearing
poverty. He had never before builded
golden castles, but now he speculated upon 
the possibility of unearthing gems and
gold from the mines of ancient Meroe
and the pyramids of Ethiopia. In the
midst of his fancies he fell asleep. In the
morning he felt a wonderful relief as he
contemplated his decision. Peace had returned 
to his mind. He determined to
see Aubrey at once and learn all the particulars 
concerning the expedition. Providentially, 
Aubrey was just sitting down
to breakfast and over a cup of steaming
coffee Reuel told his decision, ending with
these words: "Now, my dear Aubrey, it

<pb facs="p195"/>

may be the last request I may ever ask
of you, tor who can tell what strange adventures 
may await me in that dark and
unknown country to which Fate has
doomed me?"</p>

<p>Livingston tried to remonstrate with
him.</p>

<p>"I know what I am saying. The
climate is murderous, to begin with, and
there are many other dangers. It is better 
to be prepared. I have no friend but
you."</p>

<p>"Between us, Reuel, oaths are useless;
you may count upon my loyalty to all your
interests," said Aubrey with impressiveness.</p>

<p>"I shall ask you to watch over Dianthe.
I intrust her to you as I would intrust her
to my brother, had I one. This is all I
ask of you when I am in that far country."</p>

<p>With open brow, clear eyes and grave
face, Aubrey Livingston replied in solemn
tones:</p>

<p>"Reuel, you may sail without a fear.
Molly and I will have her with us always
like a dear sister."</p>

<p>Hand clasped in hand they stood a moment 
as if imploring heaven's blessing on
the solemn compact. Then they turned
the conversation on the business of securing 
the position at once.</p>

<p>Chapter VIII.</p>

<p>Reuel was greatly touched during the
next three months by the devotion of his
friend Livingston, whose unselfishness in
his behalf he had before had cause to
notice. Nor was this all; he seemed
capable of any personal sacrifice that the
welfare of Briggs demanded.</p>

<p>Before many days had passed he had
placed the young man in direct communication 
with the English officials in charge
of the African expedition, The salary
was most generous; in fact, all the arrangements 
were highly satisfactory.
Whatever difficulties really existed
melted, as it were, before Aubrey's influence, 

and Reuel would have approached
the time of departure over a bed of roses
but for the pain of parting with Dianthe.</p>

<p>At length the bustle of graduation was
over. The last article of the traveler's
outhit was bought. The morning of the
day of departure was to see the ceremony
performed that would unite the young
people for life. It was a great comfort to
Reuel that Charlie Vance. had decided to
join the party as a tourist for the sake of
the advantages of such a trip.</p>

<p>The night before their departure Aubrey 
Livingston entertained the young
men at dinner in his rooms along with a
number of college professors and other
learned <sic>savans</sic>. The most complimentary
things were said of Reuel in the after-dinner 
toasts, the best of wishes were
uttered together with congratulations on
the marriage of the morrow for they all
admired the young enthusiast. His superiority 
was so evident that none disputed 
it; they envied him, but were not
jealous. The object of their felicitations
smiled seldom.</p>

<p>"Come, for heaven sake shake off your
sadness; he the happy groom upon whom
Tortune, fickle jade, has at last consented
to smile," cried Adonis. So, amid laughter 
and jest, the night passed and the morrow came.</p>

<p>After his guests had departed, Aubrey
Livingston went to the telegraph office
and sent a message:</p>

<p>"To Jim Titus,<lb/>
"Laurel Hill, Virginia:&#8212;<lb/>
"Be on hand at the New York dock,
Trans-Atlantic Steamship Co., on the
first. I will be there to make things right
for you. Ten thousand if you succeed the
first six months.</p>

<p>"A. L."</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>It was noon the next day and the newly 
wedded stood with clasped hands uttering 
their good-byes.</p>

<p>"You must not be unhappy, dear. The
time will run by before you know it, and

<pb facs="p196"/>

I shall be with you again. Meanwhile
there is plenty to occupy you. You have
Molly and Aubrey to take you about. But
pray remember my advice,&#8212;don't attempt 
too much; you're not strong by
any means."</p>

<p>"No, I am not strong!" she interrupted
with a wild burst of tears. "Reuel, if you
knew how weak I am you would not leave
me."</p>

<p>Her husband drew the fair head to his
bosom, pressing back the thick locks with
a lingering lover's touch.</p>

<p>"I wish to God I could take you with
me," he said tenderly after a silence.
Dear girl, you know this grief of yours
would break my heart, only that it shows
how well you love me. I am proud of every 
tear." She looked at him with
expression he could not read; it was full
of unutterable emotion&#8212;love, anguish,
compassion.</p>

<p>"Oh," she said passionately, "nothing
remains long with us but sorrow and regret. 
Every good thing may be gone 
tomorrow&#8212;lost! Do you know, I sometimes 
dream or have waking visions of a
past time in my life? But when I try to
grasp the fleeting memories they leave me
groping in darkness. Can't you help me
Reuel?"</p>

<p>With a laugh he kissed away her
anxieties, although he was dismayed to
know that at most any time full memory
might return. He must speak to Aubrey.
Then he closed her lips with warm lingering 
kisses.</p>

<p>"Be a good girl and pray for your husband's 
safety, that God may let us meet
again and be happy! Don't get excited.
That you <hi rend="italics">must</hi> guard against."</p>

<p>And Reuel Briggs, though his eyes
were clouded with tears, was a happy man
at heart that day. Just that once he
tasted to the full all that there is of happiness 
in human life. Happy is he who is
blessed with even <hi rend="italics">one</hi> perfect day in a
lifetime of sorrow. His last memory of
her was a mute kiss and a low "God bless

you," broken by a sob. And so they
parted.</p>

<p>In the hall below Molly Vance met him
with a sisterly kiss for good-bye; outside
in the carriage sat Mr. Vance, Sr., Charlie
and Aubrey waiting to drive to the depot.</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, Charlie Vance and their
servant, Jim Titus, sailed from New York
for Liverpool, England, on the first day
of July.</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>The departure of the young men made
a perceptible break in the social circle at
Vance Hall. Mr. Vance buried himself
in the details of business and the two
girls wandered disconsolately about the
house and grounds attended by Livingston, 
who was at the Hall constantly
and pursued them with delicate attentions.</p>

<p>By common consent it was determined
that no summer exodus could be thought
of until after the travellers had reached
August, all being well, they would seek
the limit of civilized intercourse in Africa.
While waiting, to raise the spirits of the
family, it was decided to invite a house
party for the remainder of July, and in
the beauties of Bar Harbor. Soon gaiety
and laughter filled the grand old rooms;
the days went merrily by.</p>

<p>Two men were sitting in the billiard 
room lounging over iced punch. Light,
perfumed and golden, poured from the
rooms below upon the summer night, and
the music of a waltz made its way into
the darkness.</p>

<p>"What an odd fish Livingston has
grown to be," said one, relighting a thin,
delicate-looking cigar. "I watched him
out of curiosity a while ago and was
struck at the change in him."</p>

<p>"Ah!" drawled the other sipping the
cooling beverage. "Quite a Priuli on the
whole, eh?"</p>

<p>"Y-e-s! Precisely. And I have fancied
that the beautiful Mrs. Briggs is his
Clarisse. What do you think? She 

<pb facs="p197"/>

shudders every time he draws near, and sinks
to the ground under the steady gaze of
his ye. Odd, isn't it?"</p>

<p>"Deucedly odd! About to marry Miss
Vance, isn't he?"</p>

<p>"That don't count. Love is not always
legitimate. If there's anything in it, it is
only a flirtation probably; that's the
style."</p>

<p>"What you say is true, Skelton. Let's
drink the rest of this stuff and go down
again. I know we're missed already."</p>

<p>When they had swallowed the punch
and descended, the first person they saw
was Livingston leaning against the door
of the salon. His face was abstracted
and in dead repose, there lurked about the
corners of his full lips implacable resolution. 
The waltz was ended.</p>

<p>Some interminable argument was going 
on, generally, about the room. Conversation 
progressed in sharp, brisk sentences, 
which fell from the lips like the
dropping shots of sharpshooters. There
was a call for music. Molly mentally calculated 
her available talent and was about
to give up the idea and propose something
else, when she was amazed to see Dianthe
rise hurriedly from her seat on an ottoman, 
go to the piano unattended and sit
down. Unable to move with astonishment 
she watched in fascination the slender 
white fingers flash over the keys.
There was a strange rigid appearance
about the girl that was unearthly. Never
once did she raise her eves. At the first
sharp treble note the buzz in the room
was hushed at stillness. Livingston
moved forward and rested his arm upon
the piano fastening his gaze upon the
singer's quivering lips.</p>

<p>Slowly. tremulously at first, pealed
forth the notes:</p>

<p>"Go down, Moses, way down in Egypt's
land,<lb/>
Tell ol' Pharaoh, let my people go."</p>

<p>Scarcely was the verse begun when every 
person in the room started suddenly

and listened with eager interest. As the
air proceeded, some grew visibly pale,
and not daring to breathe a syllable,
looked horrified into each other's faces.
"Great heaven!" whispered Mr. Vance to
his daughter, "do you not hear another
voice beside Mrs. Briggs'?"</p>

<p>It was true, indeed. A weird contralto,
veiled as it were, rising and falling upon
every wave of the great soprano, and
reaching the ear as irom some strange
distance. The singer sang on, her voice
dropping sweet and low, the echo follow-
ing it, and at the closing word, she fei!
back i in a dead faint. Mr. Vance caught
her in his arms.</p>

<p>"Mrs. Briggs has the soul of an artiste.
She would make a perfect prima donna
for the Grand Opera," remarked one man
to Molly.</p>

<p>"We are as surprised as anyone,' re-
plied the young girl; "we never knew
that Mrs. Briggs was musical until this
evening. It is a delightful surprise."</p>

<p>They carried her to the quiet, cool library 
away from the glaring lights and
the excitement, and at her request left her
there alone. Her thoughts were painful.
Memory had returned in full save as to
her name. She knit her brow in painful
thought, finally leaning back among her
cushions wearily, too puzzled for further
thought. Presently a step paused beside
her chair. She looked up into Livingston's 
face.</p>

<p>"Are you feeling better?" he asked,
gently taking in his slender wrist and
counting the pulse-beats.</p>

<p>Instead of answering his question, she
began abruptly: "Mr. Livingston, Reuel
told me to trust you implicitly. Can you
and will you tell me what has happened
to me since last I sang the song I have

sung here tonight? I try to recall the
past, but all is confusion and mystery, It
makes my head ache so to think."</p>

<p>Livingston suddenly drew closer to
her.</p>

<pb facs="p198"/>

<p>"Yes, Felice, there <hi rend="italics">is</hi> a story in your
life! I can save you."</p>

<p>"Save me!" exclaimed the girl.</p>

<p>"Yes, and will! Listen to me." In
gentle accents he recounted to her there
in the stillness, with the pulsing music
of the viols beating and throbbing in her
ears like muffled drums, the story of
Dianthe Lusk as we have told it here. At
the close of the tale the white-faced girl
turned to him in despair the more eloquent 
because of her quietness.</p>

<p>"Did Reuel know that I was a Negress?"</p>

<p>"No; no one recognized you but myself."</p>

<p>She hid her face in her hands.</p>

<p>"Who ever suffered such torture as
mine?" she cried, bitterly. "And there is
no rest out of the grave!" she continued.</p>

<p>"Yes, there is rest and security in my
love! Felice, Dianthe, I have learned to
love you!"</p>

<p>She sprang from his touch as if stung.</p>

<p>He continued: "I love you better than
all in the world. To possess you I am
prepared to prove false to my friend&#8212;I
am prepared to save you from the fate
that must be yours if ever Reuel learns
your origin."</p>

<p>"You would have me give up all for
you?" she asked with a shudder.</p>

<p>"Ay, from your husband&#8212;from the
world! We will go where none can ever
find us. If you refuse, I cannot aid you."</p>

<p>"Pity me!"</p>

<p>She sank upon her knees at his feet.</p>

<p>"I give you a week to think it over. I
can love, but cannot pity."</p>

<p>In vain the girl sought to throw off the
numbing influence of the man's presence.
In desperation she tried to defy him, but
she knew that she had lost her will-power
and was but a puppet in the hands of this
false friend.</p>

<p>Chapter IX.</p>

<p>"The Doctor is so good to you about letters; 
so different from poor Charlie. I

can't imagine what he finds to write
about."</p>

<p>It was the first of August, and the last
guest had left the mansion; tomorrow
they started for Bar Harbor. Moliy,
Dianthe and Livingston sat together in
the morning room.</p>

<p>"He tells me the incidents of the journey. 
This is the last letter for three
months," said Dianthe, with a sigh.</p>

<p>"Of course, there is no love-making,"
said Aubrey, lazily letting fall his newspaper, 
and pushing his hands through his
bright hair. He was a sight for gods and
men. His handsome figure outlined
against the sky, as he stood by the window 
in an attitude of listless grace, his
finely-cut face, so rich in color and the
charm of varying expression, turned indolently 
toward the two women to whom
the morning mail had brought its offering.</p>

<p>"Have you ever read one of Reuel's letters?" 
Dianthe said, quietly. "You may
see this 1f you like." A tap sounded on
the door.</p>

<p>"Miss Molly, if you please, the dressmaker 
has sent the things."</p>

<p>"Oh, thank you, Jennie, I'll come at
once!'' and gathering up her letters, Molly 
ran off with a smile and a nod of
apology.</p>

<p>Aubrey stood by the window reading
Reuel's letter. His face was deadly white,
and his breath came quick and short.
He read half the page; then crushed it
in his hand and crossed the room to
Dianthe. She, too, was pale and there
was something akin to fear in the gaze
that she lifted to his face.</p>

<p>"How dare you?" he asked breathlessly; 
"but you are a woman! Not one of
you has any delicacy in her heart! Not
one!"</p>

<p>He tore the letter across and flung it
from him.</p>

<p>"I do not suffer enough," he said in a
suffocated voice. "You taunt me with
this view of conjugal happiness&#8212;with
his <hi rend="italics">right</hi> to love and care for you."</p>

<pb facs="p199"/>

<p>"I did not do it to hurt you," she answered. 
"Do you have no thought for
Molly's sufferings 1f I succumb to your
threats of exposure and weakly allow myself 
to be frightened into committing the
great wrong you contemplate toward two
true-hearted people? I thought you
could realize if you could <hi rend="italics">know</hi> how
Reuel loves and trusts me, and how true
and noble is his nature."</p>

<p>"Do you think I have room to pity
Reuel&#8212;Molly&#8212;while my own pain is
more than I can bear? Without you my
ambition is destroyed, my hope for the
future&#8212;my life is ruined."</p>

<p>He turned from her and going to a distant 
part of the room, threw himself into
a chair and covered his face with his
hands. Against her will, better promptings 
and desires, the unfortunate girl is
drawn by invisible influences across the
room to the man's side. Presently he
holds her in his eager, strong embrace,
his face and tears hidden against her
shoulder. She does not struggle in his
clasp, only looks into the future with the
hopeless agony of dumb despair.</p>

<p>At length he broke the silence. "There
is nothing you can feel, or say to me that
i do not realize&#8212;the sin, the shame, the
lasting disgrace. I know it all. I told
you once I loved you; I tell you now
that I cannot <hi rend="italics">live</hi> without you!"</p>

<p>An hour later Dianthe sat alone in the
pleasant room. She did not realize the
beauty of the lanquid mid-summer day.
She thought of nothing but the wickedness 
of betraying her friends. Her perfect 
features were like marble. The dark
eyes had deep, black circles round them
and gazed wistfully into the far, far distance, 
a land where spirit only could compass 
the wide space. As she sat there in
full possession of all her waking faculties,
suddenly there rose from out the very
floor, as it were, a pale and lovely woman.
She neither looked at Dianthe nor did
she speak; but walked to the table and
opened a book lying upon it and wrote;

then coming back, stood for a moment
fixed; then sank, just as she rose, and
disappeared. Her dress was that of a
servant. Her head was bare; her hair
fell loosely around her in long black
curls. Her complexion was the olive of
mulattoes or foreigners. As the woman
passed from her view, Dianthe rose and
went to the table to examine the book.
she did not feel at all frightened, recognizing 
instantly the hand of mysticism in
this strange occurrence. There on the
open page, she perceived heavy marks in
ink, under-scoring the following quotation 
from the 12th chapter of Luke: "For
there is nothing covered that shall not be
revealed." On the margin, at the end of
this passage was written in a fine female
hand, the single word, "Mira."</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>After luncheon Aubrey proposed that
they go canoeing on the river. The idea
was eagerly embraced and by five o'clock
the large and luxurious canoe floated out
from the boat-house upon the calm
bosom of the lovely Charles rocking soit-
ly to the little waves that lapped her
sides.</p>

<p>The day had been oppressive, but upon
the river a refreshing breeze was blowing
now that the sun had gone down. For
the time all Dianthe's cares left her and
her tortured mind was at peace. Molly
was full of life and jested and sang and
laughed. She had brought her mandolin
with her and gave them soft strains of
delicious waltzes.</p>

<p>On, on they glided under the impetus
of the paddle-strokes in Aubrey's skilful
hands, now past the verdure-clad pine
hills, now through beds of fragrant water-lilies 
getting gradually farther and
farther from the companionship of other
pleasure-seekers. On, into the uninhabited 
portion where silent woods and
long green stretches of pasture-land
added a wild loneliness to the scene.</p>

<p>How lovely was the evening sky with

<pb facs="p200"/>

its white clouds dotting the azure and the
pink tinting of the sunset casting over all
its enlivening glow; how deep, and dark
was the green of the water beneath the
shadowing trees. From the land came
the lowing of cows and the sweet scent
of freshly spread hay.</p>

<p>Suddenly Aubrey's paddle was caught

and held in the meshes of the water-lily
stems that floated all about them. He
leaned far over to extricate it and in a
moment the frail craft was bottom up, its
living freight struggling in the river.
Once, twice, thrice a thrilling call for help
echoed over the darkening land; then all
was still.</p>

<p>(To be continued.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.004">

<pb facs="p264"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Synopsis of Chapters I to X.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, a young medical student, interested in
mysticism, sees a face that haunts him. Me attends a
concert with his friend Aubrey Livingston, and there
discovers in a negro concert-singer the owner of the
mysterious face. He sees this woman again on Hallow
Eve while playing at charms with a party of young
people at Vance Hall, the home of Livingston's betrothed. 
Early the next morning he is called to attend
the victims of a railroad disaster at the hospital. He
finds among them the girl whose face haunts him, in a
cataleptic sleep which the doctors call death. He succeeds 
in restoring her to consciousness, but with a
complete loss of memory. She loses her identity as a
negress. Reuel falls deeply in love with her. He
finally restores her to health and determines to marry
her, but finds his circumstances too straitened Aubrey 
Livingston helps him out by offering to obtain
for him a place in an expedition about to explore the
ancient city of Meroe in Africa. Reuel accepts, but
marries Dianthe before going on a two years' venture.
After his departure Dianthe finds that Livingston is in
love with her, and he acquires a power over her that
she cannot resist. She agrees to fly with him against
her will; but before the time set they with Molly
Vance go out canoeing and are overturned in the river,
and all three are supposed to have been drowned.</p>

<p>Chapter X.</p>

<p>The expedition with which Reuel
Briggs found himself connected was made
up of artists, savans and several men&#8212;
capitalists&#8212;who represented the business
interests of the venture. Before the white
cliffs of the English coast were entirely 
lost to view, Reuel's natural propensities 
for leadership were being fully
recognized by the students about him.
There was an immediate demand for his
professional services and he was kept
busy for many days. And it was the
best panacea for a nature like his&#8212;deep
and silent and self-suppressing. He had
abandoned happiness for duty; he had
stifled all those ominous voices which rose
from the depth of his heart, and said to
him: "Will you ever return? and if you
return will you find your dear one? and,
if you find her, will she not have
changed? will she have preserved your
memory as faithfully as you will preserve
hers?</p>

<p>A thousand times a dav while he performed

his duties mechanically, his fate
haunted him&#8212;the renunciation which
called on him to give up happiness, to
open to mishap the fatal door absence.
All the men of the party were more or
less silent and distrait, even Charlie
Vance was subdued and thoughtful. But
Briggs suffered more than any of them,
although he succeeded in affecting a certain 
air of indifference. As he gradually
calmed down and peace returned to his
mind, he was surprised to feel the resignation 
that possessed him. Some unseen
presence spoke to his inner being words
of consolation and hope. He was shown
very clearly his own inability to control
events, and that his fate was no longer in
his own hands but ordered by a being of
infinite pity and love. After hours spent
in soul-communion with the spirit of
Dianthe, he would sink into refreshing
slumber and away in peace. Her letters
were bright spots, very entertaining and
describing minutely her life and daily occupation 
since his departure. He lived
upon them during the voyage to Tripoli,
sustained by the hope of finding one upon
arriving at that city.</p>

<p>One fine evening when the sun was
setting, they arrived at Tripoli. Their
course lay toward the southward, and
standing on deck, Reuel watched the
scene&#8212;a landscape strange in form,
which would have delighted him and
filled him with transports of joy; now he
felt something akin to indifference.</p>

<p>The ripples that flit the burnished surface 
of the long undulating billows tinkled
continually on the sides of the vessel. He
was aware of a low-lying spectral-pale
band of shore. That portion of Africa
whose nudity is only covered by the fallow 
mantle of the desert gave a most sad

<pb facs="p265"/>

impression to the gazer. The Moors call
it "Bled el Ateusch," the Country of
Thirst; and, as there is an intimate relation 
between the character of a country
and that of its people, Reuel realized
vividly that the race who dwelt here must
be different from those of the rest of the
world.</p>

<p>"Ah! that is our first glimpse of Africa, 
is it?" said Adonis's voice, full of
delight, beside him.</p>

<p>He turned to see his friend offering him
a telescope. "At last we are here. In the
morning we shall set our feet on the enchanted 
ground."</p>

<p>In the distance one could indeed make
out upon the deep blue of the sky the profile 
of Djema el Gomgi, the great mosque
on the shores of the Mediterranean. At a
few cable lengths away the city smiles at
them with all the fascination of a modern 
Cleopatra, circled with an oasis of
palms studded with hundreds of domes
and minarets. Against a sky of amethyst
the city stands forth with a penetrating
charm. It is the eternal enchantment of
the cities of the Orient seen at a distance;
but, alas! set foot within them, the illusion 
vanishes and disgust seizes you. Like
beautiful bodies they have the appearance
of life, but within the worm of decay and
death eats ceaselessly.</p>

<p>At twilight in this atmosphere the city
outlines itself faintly, then disappears in
dusky haze. One by one the stars came
into the sky until the heavens were a
twinkling blaze; the sea murmured even
her soft refrain and slept with the transparency 
of a mirror, flecked here and
there with fugitive traces of phosphorescence.</p>

<p>The two young men stood a long time
on the deck gazing toward the shore.</p>

<p>"Great night!" exclaimed Adonis at
length with a long-drawn sigh of satisfaction. 
"It promises to be better than
anything Barnum has ever given us even
at a dollar extra reserved seat."</p>

<p>Reuel smiled in spite of himself; after

all, Charlie was a home-line warranted to
ward off homesickness. On board there
was the sound of hurrying feet and a
murmur of suppressed excitement, but it
had subsided shortly; an hour later "sleep
and oblivion reigned over all."</p>

<p>In the morning, amid the bustle of departure 
the mail came on board. There
were two letters for Reuel. He seated
himself in the seclusion of the cabin safe
from prying eyes. Travelling across the
space that separated him from America,
his thoughts were under the trees in the
garden of Vance Hall. In the fresh morning 
light he thought he could discern the
dress of his beloved as she came toward
aim between the trees.</p>

<p>Again he was interrupted by Charlie's
jolly countenance. He held an open letter
in his hand. "There, Doc., there's Molly's
letter. Read it, read it; don't have any
qualms of conscience about it. There's a
good bit in it concerning the Madam, see?
I thought you'd like to read it." Then
he sauntered away to talk with Jim Titus
about the supplies for the trip across the
desert.</p>

<p>Jim was proving himself a necessary
part of the expedition. He was a Negro
of the old régime who felt that the Anglo-Saxon 
was appointed by God to rule over
the African. He showed his thoughts in
his obsequious manner, his subservient
"massa," and his daily conversation with
those about him. Jim superintended the
arrangement of the table of the exploring
party, haggled over prices with the hucksters, 
quarreled with the galley cooks and
ended by doing all the cooking for his
party in addition to keeping his eye on
"Massa Briggs." All of this was very
pleasant, but sometimes Reuel caught a
gleam in Jim's furtive black eye which
set him thinking and wondering at the
latter's great interest in himself; but he
accounted for this because of Livingston's
admonitions to Jim to "take care of Dr.
Briggs."</p>

<p>Willing or not, the company of travellers

<pb facs="p266"/>

were made to take part in the noisy
scene on deck when a horde of dirty rascals 
waylaid them, and after many uses
and combination of all sorts over a few
cents, they and their luggage were transported 
to the Custom House. "Ye gods!"
exclaimed Charlie in deep disgust, "what
a jostling, and what a noise."</p>

<p>All the little world about them was in
an uproar, everyone signalling, gesticulating, 
speaking at once. Such a fray
bewilders a civilized man, but those familiar 
with Southern exuberance regard
it tranquilly, well knowing the disorder is
more apparent than real. Those of the
party who were familiar with the scene,
looked on highly amused at the bewilderment 
of the novices.</p>

<p>Most of them had acquired the necessary
art of not hurrying, and under their
direction the examination of the baggage
proceeded rapidly. Presently, following
a robust porter, they had traversed an
open place filled with the benches and
chairs of a "café," and soon the travellers 
were surprised and amused to find
themselves objects of general curiosity.
Coffee and nargiles were there merely as a
pretext, in reality the gathering was in
their honor. The names of the members
of the expedition were known, together
with its object of visiting Meroe of ancient 
fame, the arrival of such respectable
visitors is a great event. Then, too, Tripoli 
is the natural road by which Africa
has been attacked by many illustrious explorers 
because of the facility of communication 
with the country of the Blacks.
Nowhere in northern Africa does the
Great Desert advance so near the sea.
The Atlas range rises from the Atlantic
coast, extending far eastward. This range
loses itself in the gulf of Little Syrta, and
the vast, long-pent-up element, knowing
no more barrier, spreads its yellow, sandy
waves as far as the Nile, enveloping the
last half-submerged summits which form
a rosary of oases.</p>

<p>Under the Sultan's rule Tripoli has remained 

the capital of a truly barbaric
state, virgin of improvements, with just
enough dilapitated abandon, dirt and picturesqueness 
to make the delight of the
artist. Arabs were everywhere; veiled
women looked at the Christians with
melting eyes above their wrappings. Mohammedanism, 
already twelve centuries
old, has, after a period of <sic>inacitivity</sic>,
awakened anew in Africa, and is rapidly
spreading. Very unlike the Christians,
the faithful of today are the same fervid
Faithful of Omar and Mohammed. Incredulity, 
indifference, so widely spread
among other sects are unknown to them.</p>

<p>Supper-time found the entire party
seated on the floor around a well-spread
tray, set on a small box. They had taken
possession of the one living-room of a
mud house. It was primitive but clean,
A post or two supported the thatched ceiling. 
There were no windows. The furniture 
consisted of a few rugs and cushions. 
But the one idea of the party being
sleep, they were soon sunk in a profound
and dreamless slumber.</p>

<p>The next day and the next were spent
in trying to gain an audience with the
Sheik Mohammed Abdallah, and the days
lengthened into weeks and a month finally 
rolled into oblivion. Meantime there
were no letters for Dr. Briggs and Charlie 
Vance. Everyone else in the party
had been blessed with many letters, even
Jim was not forgotten.</p>

<p>Reuel had learned to be patient in the
dolce far miente of the East, but not so
Charlie. He fumed and fretted continually 
after the first weeks had passed. But
promptly at two, one hot afternoon the
Sheik knocked at the door of their hut.
He was a handsome man of forty years
&#8212;tall, straight, with clear brown eyes,
good features, a well-shaped moustache
and well-trimmed black beard. Authority 
surrounded him like an atmosphere.
He greeted the party in French and Arabic 
and invited them to his house where a
feast was spread for them. Presents were

<pb facs="p267"/>

given and received and then they were introduced 
to Ababdis, an owner of camels
who was used to leading parties into the
wilderness. After much haggling over
prices, it was decided to take fifteen camels 
and their drivers. Supplies were to
consist of biscuit, rice, tea, sugar, coffee,
wax candles, charcoal and a copious supply 
of water bags. It was decided not to
start until Monday, after the coming oi
the mail, which was again due. After
leaving Tripoli, it was doubtful when
they would receive news from America
again. The mail came. Again Jim was
the only one who received a letter from
the United States. Reuel handed it to
him with a feeling of homesickness and
a sinking of the heart.</p>

<p>Monday morning found them mounted
and ready for the long journey across the
desert to the first oasis. From the back
of a camel Charlie Vance kept the party
in good humor with his quaint remarks.
"Say, Doc., it's worth the price. How I
wish the pater, your wife and Molly could
see us now. Livingston wouldn't do a
thing to these chocolate colored gentry of
Arabia."</p>

<p>"And Miss Scott? where does she come
in?" questioned Reuel with an assumption 
of gaiety he was far from feeling.</p>

<p>"Oh," replied Charlie, not at all nonplussed. 
"Cora isn't in the picture; I'm
thinking of a houri."</p>

<p>"Same old thing, Charlie&#8212;the ladies?"</p>

<p>"No," said Charlie, solemnly. "It's
business this time. Say, Briggs, the sight
of a camel always makes me a child again.
The long-necked beast is inevitably associated 
in my mind with Barnum's circus
and playing hookey. Pop wants me to
put out my sign and go in for business,
but the show business suits me better. For
instance," he continued with a wave of
his hand including the entire caravan,
"Arabs, camels, stray lions, panthers,
scorpions, serpents, explorers, etc., with a
few remarks by yours truly, to the accompaniment 
of the band&#8212;always the band

you know, would make an interesting
show&#8212;a sort of combination of Barnum
and Kiralfy. The houris would do Kiralfy's 
act, you know. There's money in it."</p>

<p>"Were you ever serious in your life,
Charlie?"</p>

<p>"What the deuce is the need of playing
funeral all the time, tell me that, Briggs,
will you?"</p>

<p>The great desert had the sea's monotony. 
They rode on and on hour after
hour. The elements of the view were
simple. Narrow valleys and plains bounded 
by picturesque hills lay all about them.
The nearer hills to the right had shoulders 
and hollows at almost regular intervals, 
and a sky-line of an almost regular
curve. Under foot the short grass always
seemed sparse, and the low sage-shrubs
rather dingy, but as they looked over the
plain stretching away in every direction,
it had a distinctly green tint. They saw
occasionally a red poppy and a purple iris.
Not a tree was to be seen, nor a rock.
Sometimes the land lay absolutely level
and smooth, with hardly a stone larger
than a bean. The soft blue sky was cloud-
less, the caravan seemed to be the only
living creature larger than a gazelle in
the great solitude. Even Reuel was
aroused to enthusiasm by the sight of a
herd of these graceful creatures skimming 
the plain. High in the air the larks
soared and sang.</p>

<p>As they went southward the hot sun
poured its level rays upon them, and the
song of the drivers was a relief to their
thoughts. The singing reminded travellers 
of Venetian gondoliers, possessing as
it did the plaintive sweetness of the most
exquisite European airs. There was generally 
a leading voice answered by a full
chorus. Reuel thought he had never
heard music more fascinating. Ababdis
would assume the leading part. "Ah,
when shall I see my family again; the
rain has fallen and made a canal between
me and my home. Oh, shall I never see
it more?" Then would follow the chorus

<pb facs="p268"/>

of drivers: "Oh, what pleasure, what delight, 
to see my family again; when I see
my father, mother, brothers, sisters, I will
hoist a flag on the head of my camel for
joy!" About the middle of the week they
were making their way over the Great
Desert where it becomes an elevated plateau 
crossed by rocky ridges, with intervening 
sandy plains mostly barren, but
with here and there a solitary tree, and
sometimes a few clumps of grass. The
caravan was skirting the base of one of
these ridges, which culminated in a cliff
looking, in the distance, like a half-ruined
castle, which the Arabs believed to be enchanted. 
Reuel determined to visit this
cliff, and saying nothing to any one, and
accompanied only by Jim and followed by
the warnings of the Arabs to beware of
lions, they started for the piles of masonry, 
which they reached in a couple of
hours. The moon rose in unclouded
splendor, and Moore's lines came to his
heart:</p>

<q>"O, such a blessed night as this,<lb/>
I often think if friends were near,<lb/>
How we should feel, and gaze with bliss<lb/>
Upon the moonlight scenery here."</q>

<p>He strolled into the royal ruin, stumbling 
over broken carvings, and into hollows 
concealed by luminous plants, beneath 
whose shades dwelt noisome things
that wriggled away in the marvelous
white light. Climbing through what was
once a door, he stepped out on a ledge of
masonry, that hung sheer seven hundred
feet over the plain. Reuel got out his
pipe and it was soon in full blast, while
the smoker set to building castles in the
curls of blue smoke, that floated lightly
into space. Jim with the guns waited for
him at the foot of the hill.</p>

<p>Under the influence of the soothing
narcotic and the spell of the silver moon,
Reuel dreamed of fame and fortune he
would carry home to lay at a little woman's 
feet. Presently his castle-building
was interrupted by a low vail&#8212;not exactly 
the mew of a cat, nor vet the sound of
a lute.</p>

<p>Again the sound.</p>

<p>What could it be?</p>

<p>"Ah, I have it!" muttered Reuel; "it's
the Arabs singing in the camp."</p>

<p>Little did he imagine that within ten
paces of him crouched an enormous
leopard.</p>

<p>Little did he imagine that he was creeping, 
creeping toward him, as a cat
squirms at a bird.</p>

<p>he sat on the ruined ledge of the parapet,
within two feet of the edge: seven
hundred feet below the desert sand glittered 
like molten silver in the gorgeous
moonlight.</p>

<p>He was unarmed, having given Jim his
revolver to hold.</p>

<p>Reuel sat there entirely unconscious of
danger; presently a vague feeling struck
him, not of fear, not of dread, but a feeling 
that if he turned his head he would
see an enemy, and without knowing why,
he slowly turned his head.</p>

<p>Great heavens! what did he see? A
thrill of horror passed through him as his
eves rested upon those of an enormous
brute, glaring like hot coals set in blood-red circles.</p>

<p>Its mouth was wide open, its whiskers
moving like the antennal of a lobster. It
lay on its belly, its hindquarters raised, its
forepaws planted in the tawny sand ready
to spring.</p>

<p>The moon played on the spots of its
body. The dark spots became silvered,
and relapsed into darkness as the animal
breathed, while its tail lashed about, occasionally 
whipping the sand with a peculiar whish.</p>

<p>How was he to withstand its spring?</p>

<p>The weight of its body would send him
over the precipice like a shot.</p>

<p>Strange to say a grim satisfaction came
to him at the thought that the brute must
go down with him. Where could he
hold? Could he clutch at anything? he
asked himself.</p>

<p>He dared not remove his eyes from
those of the leopard. He could not in

<pb facs="p269"/>

fact. But in a sort of introverted glance
he saw that nothing stood between him
and space but a bare, polished wall, that
shone white beneath the moonbeams.</p>

<p>"Was there a loose stone&#8212;a stone that
would crush in the skull of the blood-thirsty 
animal?" Not so much as a pebble
to cast into the depths, for he had already
searched for one to fling over, as people
do when perched on imminences. He
cried for help, "Jim! Jim! O-o-o-h, Jim!"</p>

<p>There came no reply; not the slightest
sound broke the stillness as the scund ot
his cries died away.</p>

<p>Reuel was now cool&#8212;cool as a cucumber
&#8212;so cool that he deliberately placed
himself in position to receive the rush of
the terrific brute. He felt himself moving 
gently back his right foot, shuffling it
back until his heel came again an unevenness 
in the rock, which gave him a sort of
purchase&#8212;something to back it.</p>

<p>He gathered himself together for a supreme 
effort, every nerve being at the
highest condition of tension.</p>

<p>It is extraordinary all the thoughts that
pass like lightning in a second of time,
through the mind, while face to face with
death. Volumes of ideas flashed through
his brain as he stood on the stone ledge,
with eternity awaiting him, knowing that
this would be the end of all his hopes and
fears and pleasant plans for future happiness, 
that he would go down to death
in the embrace of the infuriated animal
before him, its steel-like claws buried in
his flesh, its fetid breath filling his nostrils. 
He thought of his darling love, and
of how the light would go out of her existence 
with his death. He thought of
Livingston, of the fellows who had gathered 
to bid him God speed, of the paragraphs 
in the papers. All these things
came as harrowing pictures as he stood at
bay in the liquid pearl of the silent moon.</p>

<p>The leopard began to move its hind-
quarters from side to side. A spring was
at hand.</p>

<p>Reuel yelled then&#8212;yelled till the walls

of the ruined castle echoed again&#8212;yelled
as if he had 10,000 voices in his throat&#8212;
yelled, as a man only yells when on his
being heard depends his chance for dear
life.</p>

<p>The beast turned its head sharply, and
prepared to spring. For a second Briggs
thought that a pantomime trick might
give him a chance. What if he were to
wait until the animal actually leaped, and
then turn aside?</p>

<p>Carried forward by its own weight and
momentum it would go over the ledge
and be dashed to pieces on the rocks below.</p>

<p>It was worth trying. A drowning man
catches at a straw. Instinctively Reuel
measured his distance. He could step
aside and let the brute pass, but that was
all. The ledge was narrow. He was, unhappily, 
in very good condition. The sea-voyage 
had fattened him, and it was just
a chance that he could escape being carried 
over by the brute.</p>

<p>He accepted the chance.</p>

<p>Then came the fearful moment.</p>

<p>The leopard swayed a little backward!</p>

<p>Then, to his intense delight, he heard a
shout of encouragement in Vance's well-known 
voice, "Coming, Briggs, coming?"</p>

<p>The next moment a hand was laid on
his shoulder from a window above; it was
Charlie, who trembling with anxiety had
crept through the ruin, and, oh, blessed
sight! handed Reuel his revolver.</p>

<p>Briggs made short work of the leopard:
he let him have three barrels&#8212;all in the
head.</p>

<p>Vance had become alarmed for the
safety of his friend, and had gone to the
ruin to meet him. When very nearly
there, he had heard the first cry for help.
and had urged his camel forward. Arrived 
at the castle he had found Jim apparently 
dead with sleep, coiled up on the
warm sand. How he could sleep within
sound of the piercing cries uttered by
Briggs was long a mystery to the two
friends.</p>

<pb facs="p270"/>

<p>Chapter XI.</p>

<p>The caravan had halted for the night.
Professor Stone, the leader of the expedition, 
sat in Reuel's tent enjoying a pipe
and a talk over the promising features of
the enterprise. The nearer they approached 
the goal of their hopes&#8212;the ancient 
Ethiopian capital Meroe&#8212;the greater 
was the excitement among the leaders
of the party. Charlie from his bed of
rugs listened with ever-increasing curtosity 
to the conversation between the two
men.</p>

<p>"It is undoubtedly true that from its
position as the capital of Ethiopia and
the enterpret of trade between the North
and South, between the East and West,
Meroe must have held vast treasures. African 
caravans poured ivory, frankincense
and gold into the city. My theory is that
somewhere under those pyramids we shall
find invaluable records and immense
treasure."</p>

<p>"Your theories may be true, Professor,
but if so, your discoveries will establish
the primal existence of the Negro as the
most ancient source of all that you value
in modern life, even antedating Egypt.
How can the Anglo-Saxon world bear the
establishment of such a theory?" There
was a hidden note of sarcasm in his voice
which the others did not notice.</p>

<p>The learned savan settled his glasses
and threw back his head.</p>

<p>"You and I, Briggs, know that the theories 
of prejudice are swept away by the
great tide of facts. It is a <hi rend="italics">fact</hi> that Egypt
drew from Ethiopia all the arts, sciences
and knowledge of which she was mistress.
The very soil of Egypt was pilfered by
the Nile from the foundations of Meroe.
I have even thought," he continued meditatively, 
"that black was the original color
of man in prehistoric times. You remember 
that Adam was made from the earth;
what more natural than that he should
have retained the color of the earth?
What puzzles me is not the origin of the

Blacks, but of the Whites. Miriam was
made a leper outside the tents for punishment; 
Naaman was a leper until
cleansed. It is a question fraught with
big possibilities which God alone can
solve. But of this we are sure&#8212;all records 
of history, sacred and profane,<sic>,</sic> unite
in placing the Ethiopian as the primal
race."</p>

<p>"Gee whiz!" exclaimed Charlie from
his bed on the floor. "Count me out!"</p>

<p>"Don't touch upon the origin of the
Negro; you will find yourself in a labyrinth, 
Professor. That question has provoked 
more discussion than any other
concerning the different races of man on
the globe. Speculation has exhausted itself, 
yet the mystery appears to remain
unsolved."</p>

<p>"Nevertheless the Biblical facts are
very explicit, and so simple as to force
the very difficulties upon mankind that
Divinity evidently designed to avoid."</p>

<p>"The relationship existing between the
Negro and other people of the world is
a question of absorbing interest. For my
part, I shall be glad to add to my ethnological 
knowledge by anything we may
learn at Meroe." Thus speaking Reuel
seemed desirous of dismissing the subject. 
More conversation followed on indifferent 
subjects, and presently the Professor 
bade them good night and retired
to his own tent.</p>

<p>Reuel employed himself in making en-
tries in his journal, Charlie continued to
smoke, at times evincing by a musical
snore that he was in the land of dreams.
Jim sat at some distance reading a letter
that he held in his hand.</p>

<p>The night was sultry, the curtains of
the tent undrawn; from out the silent solitude 
came the booming call of a lion to
his mate.</p>

<p>Suddenly a rush of balmy air seemed
to pass over the brow of the scribe, and
a dim shadow fell across the tent door.
It was the form of the handsome Negress
who had appeared to Dianthe, and signed
herself "Mira."</p>

<pb facs="p271"/>

<p>There was no fear in Reuel's gaze, no
surprise; it was as if a familiar and welcome 
visitor had called upon him. For a
moment an impulse to spring away into
the wide, wide realms of air, seemed to
possess him; the next, the still, dreamy
ecstasy of a past time; and then he saw
Jim&#8212;who sat directly behind him&#8212;
placed like a picture on his very table. He
saw him knit his brow, contract his lip,
and then, with a face all seamed with discontent, 
draw from his vest a letter, seemingly 
hidden in a private pocket, reading
thus:&#8212;</p>

<p>"Use your discretion about the final act,
but be sure the letters are destroyed. I
have advised the letters sent in your care
as you will probably be detailed for the
mail. But to avoid mishap call for the
mail for both parties. Address me at
Laurel Hill&#8212;Thomas Johnson."</p>

<p>"A. L."</p>

<p>Twice did the visionary scene, passing
<hi rend="italics">behind</hi> the seer, recross his entranced
eyes; and twice did the shadowy finger of
the shining apparition in the tent door
point, letter by letter, to the pictured page
of the billet, which Jim was at that very
moment perusing with his natural, and
Reuel Briggs with his spiritual eyes.
When both had concluded the reading,
Jim put up his letter. The curtains of the
tent slightly waved; a low, long sigh, like
the night's wind wail, passed over the
cold, damp brow of the seer. A shudder,
a blank. He looked out into the desert
beyond. All was still. The stars were
out for him, but the vision was gone.</p>

<p>Thus was explained to Reuel, by mesmeric 
forces, the fact that his letters had
been withheld.</p>

<p>He had not once suspected Jim of perfidy. 
What did it mean? he asked himself. 
The letter was in Livingston's handwriting! 
His head swam; he could not
think. Over and over again he turned
the problem and then, wishing that something 
more definite had been given him,
retired, but not to sleep.</p>

<p>Try as he would to throw it off, the
most minute act of Jim since entering his
service persisted in coming before his inner vision. 
The night when he was attacked 
by the leopard and Jim's tardiness
in offering help, returned with great significance. 
What could he do but conclude 
that he was the victim of a conspiracy.</p>

<p>"There is no doubt about it," was his
last thought as he dropped into a light
doze. How long he slept he could not tell,
but he woke with a wild, shrill cry in his
ears: "Reuel, Reuel, save me!"</p>

<p>Three times it was repeated, clear, distinct, 
and close beside his ear, a pause be-
tween the repetitions.</p>

<p>He roused his sleeping friend. "Charlie, 
Charlie! wake up and listen!"</p>

<p>Charlie, still half asleep, looked with
blinking eyes at the candle with dazzled
sight.</p>

<p>"Charlie, for the love of God wake
up!"</p>

<p>At this, so full of mortal fear were his
words, Adonis shook off his drowsiness
and sat up in bed, wide awake and staring
at him in wonder.</p>

<p>"What the deuce!" he began, and then
stopped, gazing in surprise at the white
face and trembling hands of his friend.</p>

<p>"Charlie," he cried, "some terrible
event has befallen Dianthe, or like a
sword. hangs over our heads. Lister, listen!"</p>

<p>Charlie did listen but heard nothing but
the lion's boom which now broke the stillness.</p>

<p>"I hear nothing, Reuel."</p>

<p>"O Charlie, are you sure?"</p>

<p>"Nothing but the lion. But that ‘Il be
enough if he should take it into his mind
to come into camp for his supper."</p>

<p>"I suppose you are right, for you can
hear nothing, and I can hear nothing now.
But, oh Charlie! it was so terrible, and I
heard it so plainly; though I daresay it
was only my&#8212;Oh God! there it is again!
listen! listen!"</p>

<pb facs="p272"/>

<p>This time Charlie heard&#8212;heard clearly
and unmistakably, and hearing, felt the
blood in his veins turn to ice.</p>

<p>Shrill and clear above the lion's call
rose a prolonged wail, or rather shriek,
as of a human voice rising to heaven in
passionate appeal for mercy, and dying
away in sobbing and shuddering despair.
Then came the words:</p>

<p>"Charlie, brother, save me!"</p>

<p>Adonis sprang to his feet, threw back
the curtain of the tent and looked out.
All was calm and silent, not even a cloud
flecked the sky where the moon's light
cast a steady radiance.</p>

<p>Long he looked and listened; but nothing 
could be seen or heard. But the cry
still rang in his ears and clamored at his
heart; while his mind said it was the effect 
of imagination.</p>

<p>Reuel's agitation had swallowed up his
usual foresight. He had forgotten his
ability to resort to that far-seeing faculty
which he had often employed for Charlie's 
and Aubrey's amusement when at
home.</p>

<p>Charlie was very calm, however, and
soothed his friend's fears, and after several
ineffectual attempts to concentrate his
powers for the exercise of the clairvoyant 
sight of the <sic>hypnotice</sic> trance, was

finally able to exercise the power,</p>

<p>In low, murmuring cadence, sitting
statuesque and rigid beneath the magnetic
spell, Reuel rehearsed the terrible scene
which had taken place two months before
in the United States in the ears of his
deeply-moved friend.</p>

<p>"Ah, there is Molly, poor Molly;
see your father weeps, and the friend
there and they too weep, but where is my
own sweet girl, Dianthe, love, wife! No,
I cannot see her, I do not find the poor
maimed body of my love. And Aubrey !
What! Traitor, false friend! I shall return 
for vengeance.</p>

<p>"Wake me, Charlie," was his concluding 
sentence.</p>

<p>A few upward passes of his friend's
hands, and the released spirit became lord
of its casket once more. Consciousness
returned, and with it memory. In short
whispered sentences Reuel told Vance of
his suspicions, of the letter he read while
it lay in Jim's hand, of his deliberate intention 
to leave him to his fate in the
leopard's claws.</p>

<p>The friends laid their plans,&#8212;they
would go on to Meroe, and then return
instantly to civilization as fast as steam
could carry them, if satisfactory letters
were not waiting them from America.</p>

<p>(To be continued. )</p>


</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.005">

<pb facs="p339"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Synopsis of Chapters I to XI.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, a young medical student, interested in
mysticism, sees a face that haunts him. He attends a
concert with his friend Aubrey Livingston, and there
discovers in a negro concert-singer the owner of the
mysterious face. He sees this woman again on Hallow
Eve while playing at charms with a party of young
people at Vance Hall, the home of Livingston's betrothed. 
Early the next morning he is called to attend
the victims of a railroad disaster at the hospital. He
finds among them the girl whose face haunts him, in a
cataleptic sleep which the doctors call death. He succeeds 
in restoring her to consciousness, but with a
complete loss of memory. She loses her identity as a
negress. Reuel falls deeply in love with her. He
finally restores her to health and determines to marry
her, but finds his circumstances too straitened Aubrey 
Livingston helps him out by offering to obtain
for him a place in an expedition about to explore the
ancient city of Meroe in Africa. Reuel accepts, but
marries Dianthe before going on a two years' venture.
After his departure Dianthe finds that Livingston is in
love with her, and he acquires a power over her that
she cannot resist. She agrees to fly with him against
her will; but before the time set they with Molly
Vance go out canoeing and are overturned in the river,
and all three are supposed to have been drowned.</p>

<p>The expedition reaches Africa. In crossing the Great
Desert Reuel Briggs visits old ruins and is rescued
from a leopard's claws by Vance. They are suspicious
of Jim Titus, who pretended not to hear Briggs' calls
for help. They receive no letters from home after leaving 
England, and one night, by clairvoyant aid, Reuel
reads a letter that Titus has received. That same
night, by mediumistic power, Briggs describes the
overturning of the boat containing Molly, Dianthe and
Aubrey, on the Charles River months before.</p>

<p>Chapter XII.</p>

<p>Late one afternoon two weeks later, the
caravan halted at the edge of the dirty
Arab town which forms the outposts to
the island of Meroe.</p>

<p>Charlie Vance stood in the door of his
tent and let his eyes wander over the landscape 
in curiosity. Clouds of dust swept
over the sandy plains; when they disappeared 
the heated air began its dance
again, and he was glad to re-enter the
tent and stretch himself at full length in
his hammock. The mail was not yet in
from Cairo, consequently there were no
letters; his eyes ached from straining
them for a glimpse of the Ethiopian ruins
across the glassy waters of the tributaries
of the Nile which encircled the island.</p>

<p>It was not a simple thing to come ail
these thousands of miles to look at a pile
of old ruins that promised nothing of interest 

to him after all. This was what
he had come for&#8212;the desolation of an
African desert, and the companionship of
human fossils and savage beasts of prey.
The loneliness made him shiver. It was
a desolation that doubled desolateness,
because his healthy American organization 
missed the march of progress attested
by the sound of hammers on unfinished
buildings that told of a busy future and
cosy modern homeliness. Here there was
no future. No railroads, no churches, no
saloons, no schoolhouses to echo the
voices of merry children, no promise of
the life that produces within the range of
his vision. Nothing but the monotony
of past centuries dead and forgotten save
by a few learned savans.</p>

<p>As he rolled over in his hammock,
Charlie told himself that next to seeing
the pater and Molly, he'd give ten dollars
to be able to thrust his nose into twelve
inches of whiskey and soda, and remain
there until there was no more. Then a
flicker of memory made Charlie smile as
he remembered the jollities of the past
few months that he had shared with Cora
Scott.</p>

<p>"Jolly little beggar," he mentally
termed her. "I wonder what sort of a
fool she'd call me if she could see me now
whistling around the ragged edge of this
solid block of loneliness called a desert."</p>

<p>Then he fell asleep and dreamed he
was boating on the Charles, and that Molly 
was a mermaid sporting in a bed of
water-lilies.</p>

<p>Ancient writers, among them Strabo,
say that the Astabora unites its stream
with the Nile, and forms the island of
Meroe. The most famous historical city
of Ethiopia is commonly called Carthage,
but Meroe was the queenly city of this ancient

<pb facs="p340"/>

people. Into it poured the traffic
of the world in gold, frankincense and
ivory. Diodorus states the island to be
three hundred and seventy-five miles long
and one hundred and twenty-five miles
wide. The idea was borne in upon our
travellers in crossing the Great Desert
that formerly wells must have been established 
at different stations for the convenience 
of man and beast. Professor Stone
and Reuel had discovered traces of a
highway and the remains of cisterns
which must have been marvellous in skill
and prodigious in formation.</p>

<p>All was bustle and commotion in the
camp that night. Permission had been
obtained to visit and explore the ruins
from the Arab governor of the Province.
It had cost money, but Professor Stone
counted nothing as lost that would aid in
the solution of his pet theories.</p>

<p>The leaders of the enterprise sat together 
late that night, listening to the
marvellous tales told by the Professor of
the city's ancient splendor, and examining
closely the chart which had remained hidden 
for years before it fell into his hands.
For twenty-five years this apostle of
learning had held the key to immense
wealth, he believed, in his hands. For
years he had tried in vain to interest the
wealthy and powerful in his scheme for
finding the city described in his chart,
wherein he believed lay the gold mines
from which had come the streams of precious 
metal which made the ancient Ethiopians 
famous.</p>

<p>The paper was in a large envelope
sealed with a black seal formed to resemble 
a lotus flower. It was addressed:</p>

<p>To the student who, having counted
the cost, is resolute to once more
reveal to the sceptical, the ancient
glory of hoary Meroe.</p>

<p>Within the envelope was a faded
parchment which the Professor drew
forth with trembling hands. The little
company drew more closely about the improvised

table and its flickering candle
which revealed the faded writing to be in
Arabic. There was no comment, but
each one listened intently to the reader,
who translated very fully as he went
along.</p>

<p>"Be it known to you, my brother, that
the great and surpassing wealth mentioned 
in this parchment is not to be won
without braving many dangers of a deadly 
nature. You who may read this message, 
then, I entreat to consider well the
perils of your course. Within the mines
of Meroe, four days' journey from the
city toward Arabia, are to be found gold
in bars and gold in flakes, and diamonds,
and rubies whose beauty excels all the
jewels of the earth. For some of them
were hidden by the priests of Osiris that
had adorned the crown of the great Semiramis, 
and the royal line of Queen Candace, 
even from ancient Babylon's pillage
these jewels came, a spectacle glorious beyond 
compare. There, too, is the black
diamond of Senechus's crown (Senechus
who suffered the captivity of Israel by the
Assyrians), which exceeds all imagination 
for beauty and color.</p>

<p>"All these jewels with much treasure
beside you will gain by following my
plain directions.</p>

<p>"Four days' journey from Meroe toward 
Arabia is a city founded by men
from the Upper Nile; the site is near one
of its upper sources, which still has one
uniform existence. This ity is situated
on a forked tributary, which takes its rise
from a range of high, rocky mountains,
almost perpendicular on their face, from
which descend two streams like cataracts,
about two miles apart, and form a triangle,
which holds the inner city. The
outer city occupies the opposite banks on
either side of the streams, which after
joining, form a river of considerable size,
and running some five miles, loses itself
in the surrounding swamps. The cities
are enclosed within two great walls, running

<pb facs="p341"/>

parallel with the streams. There are
also two bridges with gates, connecting
the inner and outer cities; two great gates
also are near the mountain ranges, connecting 
the outer city with the agricultural 
lands outside the walls. The whole
area is surrounded by extensive swamps,
through which a passage known only to
the initiated runs, and forms an impassible 
barrier to the ingress or egress of
strangers.</p>

<p>"But there is another passage known to
the priests and used by them, and this ts
the passage which the chart outlines be-
neath the third great pyramid, leading
directly into the mines and giving access
to the city.</p>

<p>"When Egypt rose in power and sent
her hosts against the mother country,
then did the priests close with skill and
cunning this approach to the hidden city
of refuge, where they finally retired, carrying 
with them the ancient records of
Ethiopia's greatness, and closing forever,
as they thought, the riches of her marvellous 
mines, to the world.</p>

<p>"Beneath the <sic>Sphinx'</sic> head lies the secret 
of the entrance, and yet not all, for
the rest is graven on the sides of the cavern 
which will be seen when the mouth
shall gape. But beware the tank to the
right where dwells the sacred crocodile,
still living, although centuries have rolled
by and men have been gathered to the
shades who once tended on his wants.
And beware the fifth gallery to the right
where abide the sacred serpents with jewelled 
crowns, for of a truth are they terrible.</p>

<p>"This the writer had from an aged
priest whose bones lie embalmed in the
third pyramid above the Sphinx."</p>

<p>With this extraordinary document a
chart was attached, which, while an enigma 
to the others, seemed to be perfectly
clear to Professor Stone.</p>

<p>The letter ended abruptly, and the chart
was a hopeless puzzle to the various eyes

that gazed curiously at the straggling outlines.</p>

<p>"What do you make of it, Professor?"
asked Reuel, who with all his knowledge,
was at sea with the chart. "We have been
looking for mystery, and we seem to have
found it."</p>

<p>"What do I make of it? Why, that we
shall find the treasure and all return home
rich," replied the scholar testily.</p>

<p>"Rubbish!" snorted Charlie with fine
scorn.</p>

<p>"How about the sacred crocodile and
the serpents? My word, gentlemen, if
you find the back door key of the <sic>Sphinx'</sic>
head, there's a chance that a warm welcome 
is awaiting us."</p>

<p>Charlie's words met with approval
from the others, but the Professor and
Reuel said nothing. There was silence
for a time, each man drawing at his pipe
in silent meditation.</p>

<p>"Well, I'm only travelling for pleasure,
so it matters not to me how the rest of
you elect to shuffle off this mortal coil, i
intend to get some fun out of this thing,"
continued Charlie.</p>

<p>There was a shout of laughter from his
companions.</p>

<p>"Pleasure!" cried one. "O Lord!
You've come to the wrong place. This is
business, solid business. If we get out
with our skins it will be something to be
thankful for."</p>

<p>"Well, said Reuel, rousing himself from
a fit of abstraction, "I come out to do
business and I have determined to see the
matter through if all is well at home.
We'll-prove whether there's a hidden city
or not before we leave Africa."</p>

<p>The Professor grasped his hand in
gratitude, and then silence fell upon the
group. The curtains of the tent were
thrown back. Bright fell the moonlight
on the sandy plain, the Nile, the indistinct
ruins of Meroe, hiding all imperfections
by its magic fingers. It was a wonderful
sight to see the full moon looking down

<pb facs="p342"/>

on the ruins of centuries. The weird
light increased, the shadows lengthened
and silence fell on the group, broken only
by the low tones of Professor Stone as he
told in broken sentences the story of ancient 
Ethiopia.</p>

<p>"For three thousand years the world
has been mainly indebted for its advancement 
to the Romans, Greeks, Hebrews,
Germans and Anglo-Saxons; but it was
otherwise in the first years. Babylon and
Egypt&#8212;Nimrod and Mizraim&#8212;both descendants 
of Ham&#8212;led the way, and
acted as the pioneers of mankind in the
untrodden fields of knowledge. The
Ethiopians, therefore, manifested great
superiority over all the nations among
whom they dwelt, and their name became
illustrious throughout Europe, Asia and
Africa.</p>

<p>"The father of this distinguished race
was Cush, the grandson of Noah, an Ethi-
opian.</p>

<p>"Old Chaldea, between the Euphrates
and Tigris rivers, was the first home of
the Cushites. Nimrod, Ham's grandson,
founded Babylon. The Babylonians early
developed the energy of mind which
made their country the first abode of civilization. 
Canals covered the land, serving 
the purposes of traffic, defense and
irrigation. Lakes were dug and stored
with water, dykes built along the banks
of rivers to fertilize the land, and it is not
surprising to learn that from the earliest
times Babylonia was crowded with populous 
cities. This grandeur was brought
about by Nimrod the Ethiopian."</p>

<p>"Great Scott!" cried Charlie, "you
don't mean to tell me that all this was
done by <hi rend="italics">niggers?</hi>"</p>

<p>The Professor smiled. Being English,
he could not appreciate Charlie's horror
at its full value.</p>

<p>"Undoubtedly your Afro-Americans
are a branch of the wonderful and mysterious 
Ethiopians who had a prehistoric
existence of magnificence, the full record
of which is lost in obscurity.</p>

<p>"We associate with the name ‘Chaldea'
the sciences of astronomy and philosophy
and chronology. It was to the Wise Men
of the East to whom the birth of Christ
was revealed; they were Chaldeans&#8212;of
the Ethiopians. Eighty-eight years before 
the birth of Abraham, these people,
known in history as 'Shepherd Kings,'
subjugated the whole of Upper Egypt,
which they held in bondage more than
three hundred years."</p>

<p>"It is said that Egyptian civilization
antedates that of Ethiopia," broke in Reuel. 
"How do you say, Professor?"</p>

<p>"Nothing of the sort, nothing of the
sort. I know that in connecting Egypt
with Ethiopia, one meets with most bitter 
denunciation from most modern scholars. 
Science has done its best to separate
the race from Northern Africa, but the
evidence is with the Ethiopians. If I
mistake not, the ruins of Meroe will prove
my words. Traditions with respect to
Memnon connect Egypt and Ethiopia
with the country at the head of the Nile.
Memnon personifies the ethnic identity of
the two races. Ancient Greeks believed
it. All the traditions of Armenia, where
lies Mt. Ararat, are in accordance with
this fact. The Armenian geography applies 
the name of Cush to four great regions&#8212;Media, 
Persia, Susiana, Asia, or
the whole territory between the Indus and
the Tigris. Moses of Chorene identifies
Belus, king of Babylon with Nimrod</p>

<p>"But the Biblical tradition is paramount 
to all. In it lies the greatest authority 
that we have for the affiliation of
nations, and it is delivered to us very simply 
and plainly: ‘The sons of Ham were
Cush and Mizraim and Phut and Canaan
. . . and Cush begot Nimrod . . .
and the beginning of his kingdom was
Babel and Erech and Accad and Calneh,
in the land of Shinar.' It is the best interpretation 
of this passage to understand
it as asserting that the four races&#8212;
Egyptians, Ethiopians, Libyans and Canaanites&#8212;

<pb facs="p343"/>

were ethnically connected, being 
all descended from Ham; and that
the primitive people of Babylon were a
subdivision of one of these races; namely,
of the Cushite or Ethiopian.</p>

<p>"These conclusions have lately received
important and unexpected confirmation
from the results of linguistic research.
After the most remarkable of Mesopotamian 
mounds had yielded their treasures,
and supplied the historical student with
numerous and copious documents, bearing 
upon the history of the great Assyrian
and Babylonian empires, it was determined 
to explore Chaldea proper, where
mounds of considerable height marked
the site of several ancient cities.
Among unexpected results was the discovery 
of a new form of speech, differing
greatly from the later Babylonian language. 
In grammatical structure this ancient 
tongue resembles dialects of the Turanian 
family, but its vocabulary has been
pronounced to be decidedly Cushite or
Ethiopian; and the modern languages to
which it approaches nearest are thought
to be the Mahen of Southern Arabia and
the Galla of Abyssinia. Thus comparative 
philology appears to confirm old traditions. 
An Eastern Ethiopia instead of
being the invention of bewildered ignorance, 
is rather a reality which it will require 
a good deal of scepticism to doubt,
and the primitive race that bore sway in
Chaldea proper belongs to this ethnic
type. Meroe was the queenly city of this
great people."</p>

<p>"It is hard to believe your story. From
what a height must this people have fallen 
to reach the abjectness of the American 
Negro," exclaimed a listener.</p>

<p>"True," replied the Professor. "But
from what a depth does history show
that the Anglo-Saxon has climbed to the
position of the first people of the earth today."</p>

<p>Charlie Vance said nothing. He had
suffered so many shocks from the shattering

of cherished idols since entering the
country of mysteries that the power of
expression had left him.</p>

<p>"Twenty-five years ago, when I was
still a young man, the camel-driver who
accompanied me to Thebes sustained a fatal 
accident. I helped him in his distress,
and to show his gratitude he gave me the
paper and chart I have shown you tonight. 
He was a singular man, black hair
and eyes, middle height, dark-skinned,
face and figure almost perfect, he was
proficient in the dialects of the region, besides 
being master of the purest and most
ancient Greek and Arabic. I believe he
was a native of the city he described.</p>

<p>"He believed that Ethiopia antedated
Egypt, and helped me materially in fixing
certain data which time has proved to be
correct. He added a fact which the manuscript 
withholds,&#8212;that from lands beyond 
unknown seas, to which many descendants 
of Ethiopia had been borne as
slaves, should a king of ancient line&#8212;an
offspring of that Ergamenes who lived in
the reign of the second Ptolemy&#8212;return
and restore the former glory of the race.
The preservation of this hidden city is for
his reception. This Arab also declared
that Cush was his progenitor."</p>

<p>"That's bosh. How would they know
their future king after centuries of obscurity 
passed in strange lands, and amalgamation 
with other races?" remarked
the former speaker.</p>

<p>"I asked him that question; he told me
that every descendant of the royal line
bore a lotus-lily in the form of a birthmark 
upon his breast."</p>

<p>It might have been the unstable shadows 
of the moon that threw a tremulous
light upon the group, but Charlie Vance
was sure that Reuel Briggs started violently 
at the Professor's words.</p>

<p>One by one the men retired to rest, each
one under the spell of the mysterious
forces of a past life that brooded like a
mist over the sandy plain, the dark Nile

<pb facs="p344"/>

rolling sluggishly along within a short
distance of their camp, and the ruined
city now a magnificent Necropolis. The
long shadows grew longer, painting the
scene into beauty and grandeur. The
majesty of death surrounded the spot and
its desolation spoke in trumpet tones of
the splendor which the grave must cover,
when even the memory of our times shall
be forgotten.</p>

<p>Chapter XIII.</p>

<p>Next morning the camp was carly astir
before the dawn; and before the sun was
up, breakfast was over and the first boatload 
of the explorers was standing on the
site of the ruins watching the <sic>unlfading</sic> of
the apparatus for opening solid masonry
and excavating within the pyramids.</p>

<p>The feelings of every man in the party
were ardently excited by the approach to
the city once the light of the world's civilization. 
The great French writer, Volney, 
exclaimed when first his eyes beheld
the sight, "How are we astonished when
we reflect that to the race of Negroes,
the object of our extreme contempt, we
owe our arts, sciences and even the use of
speech!"</p>

<p>From every point of view rose magnificent 
groups of pyramids rising above pyramids. 
About eighty of them remaining
in a state of partial preservation. The
principal one was situated on a hill two
and a half miles from the river, commanding 
an extensive view of the plain.
The explorers found by a hasty examination 
that most of them could be ascended
although their surfaces were worn quite
smooth. That the pyramids were places
of sepulture they could not doubt. From
every point of view the sepulchres were
imposing; and they were lost in admiration 
and wonder with the first superficial
view of the imposing scene.</p>

<p>One of the approaches or porticoes was

most interesting, the roof being arched in
regular masonic style, with what may be
called a keystone. Belonging without
doubt to the remotest ages, their ruined
and defaced condition was attributed by
the scientists to their great antiquity. The
hieroglyphics which covered the monuments 
were greatly defaced. A knowledge 
of these characters in Egypt was
confined to the priests, but in Ethiopia
they were understood by all showing that
even in that remote time and place learning 
and the arts had reached so high a
state as to be diffused among the common
people.</p>

<p>For a time the explorers wandered
from ruin to ruin, demoralized as to
routine work, gazing in open astonishment 
at the wonders before them. Many
had visited Thebes and Memphis and the
Egyptian monuments, but none had
hoped to find in this neglected corner, so
much of wonder and grandeur. Within
the pyramids that had been opened to the
curious eye, they found the walls covered
with the pictures of scenes from what
must have been the daily life,&#8212;death,
burial, marriage, birth, triumphal processions, 
including the spoils of war.</p>

<p>Reuel noticed particularly the figure
of a queen attired in long robe, tight at
neck and ankles, with closely fitted legs.
The Professor called their attention to the
fact that the entire figure was dissimilar
to those represented in Egyptian sculpture. 
The figure was strongly marked by
corpulency, a mark of beauty in Eastern
women. This rotundity is the distinguishing 
feature of Ethiopian sculpture,
more bulky and clumsy than Egypt, but
pleasing to the eye.</p>

<p>The queen held in one hand the lash
of Osiris, and in the other a lotus flower.
She was seated on a lion, wearing sandals
resembling those specimens seen in Theban 
figures. Other figures grouped about
poured libations to the queen, or carried the
standards graced and ornamented by the

<pb facs="p345"/>

figures of the jackal, ibis and hawk. At
the extremity of each portico was the representation 
of a monolithic temple, above
which were the traces of a funeral boat
filled with figures.</p>

<p>Professor Stone told them that Diodorus 
mentions that some of the Ethiopians 
preserved the bodies of their relatives
in glass cases (probably alabaster), in order 
to have them always before their eyes.
These porticoes, he thought, might have
been used for that purpose. The hair of
the women was dressed in curls above the
forehead and in ringlets hanging on their
shoulders.</p>

<p>One who had visited the chief galleries
of Europe holding the treasures accumulated 
from every land, could not be unmoved 
at finding himself on the site of the
very metropolis where science and art had
their origin. If he had admired the architecture 
of Rome and the magnificent
use they had made of the arch in their
baths, palaces and temples, he would be,
naturally, doubly interested at finding in
desolate Meroe the origin of that discovery. 
The beautiful sepulchres of Meroe
would give to him evidence of the correctness 
of the historical records. And then
it was borne in upon him that where the
taste for the arts had reached such perfection, 
one might rest assured that other
intellectual pursuits were not neglected
nor the sciences unknown. Now, however, 
her schools are closed forever; not
a vestige remaining. Of the houses of
her philosophers, not a stone rests upon
another: and where civilization and learning 
once reigned, ignorance and barbarism 
have reassumed their sway.</p>

<p>This is the people whose posterity has
been denied a rank among the human
race, and has been degraded into a species 
of talking baboons!</p>

<p>"Land of the mighty Dead!<lb/>
There science once display'd<lb/>
And art, their charms;<lb/>
There awful Pharaohs swayed<lb/>

Great nations who obeyed;<lb/>
There distant monarchs laid<lb/>
Their vanquished arms.<lb/>
"They hold us in survey&#8212;</p>

<p>They cheer us on our way&#8212;<lb/>
They loud proclaim,<lb/>
From pyramidal hall&#8212;<lb/>
From Carnac's sculptured wall&#8212;<lb/>
From Thebes they loudly call&#8212;<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">‘Retake your fame!'</hi></p>

<p>"Arise and now prevail<lb/>
O'er all your foes;<lb/>
In truth and righteousness&#8212;<lb/>
In all the arts of peace&#8212;<lb/>
Advance and still increase,<lb/>
Though hosts oppose."</p>

<p>Under the inspiration of the moment,
Charlie, the irrepressible, mounted to the
top of the first pyramid, and from its peak
proceeded to harangue his companions,
lugging in the famous Napoleon's:
"From the heights of yonder Pyramids
forty centuries are contemplating you,"
etc. This was admirably done, and the
glances and grimaces of the eloquent
young American must have outvied in
ugliness the once gracious-countenanced
Egyptian Sphinx.</p>

<p>We may say here that before the excavations 
of the explorers were ended, they
found in two of the pyramids, concealed
treasures,&#8212;golden plates and tables that
must have been used by the priests in
their worship. Before one enormous image 
was a golden table, also of enormous
proportions. The seats and steps were
also of gold, confirming the ancient Chaldean 
records which tell of 800 talents of
metal used in constructing this statue.</p>

<p>There was also a statue of Candace,
seated in a golden chariot. On her knees
crouched two enormous silver serpents,
each weighing thirty talents. Another
queen (Professor Stone said it must be
Dido from certain peculiar figures) carried 
in her right hand a serpent by the
head, in her left hand a sceptre garnished
with precious stones.</p>

<p>All of this treasure was collected finally, 
after indemnifying the government,

<pb facs="p346"/>

and carefully exported to England, where
it rests today in the care of the Society of
Geographical Research.</p>

<p>They never forgot that sunset over
the ancient capital of Ethiopia at the close
of the first day spent on the city’s site, in
the Desert. The awe-inspiring Pyramids
throwing shadows that reminded one of
the geometrical problems of his student
days; the backsheesh-loving Arabs, in the
most picturesque habiliments and attitudes; 
the patient camels, the tawny
sands, and the burnished coppery sunlight! 
They had brought tents with
them, leaving the most of the outfit on the
under the care of Jim
Reuel had desired the
professor to detail for that duty.
Somehow since his adventure in
the ruins with the leopard, and the
mysterious letter-reading, he had felt
a deep-seated mistrust of the docile servant. 
He concluded not to keep him any
nearer his person than circumstances demanded. 
In this resolve Charlie Vance
concurred; the two friends resolved to
keep an eye on Titus, and Ababdis was
sent for the mail.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs had changed much. Harassed 
by anxieties which arose from his
wife’s silence, at the end of two months
he was fast becoming a misanthrope.
Charlie felt anxious as he looked at him
walking restlessly up and down in the
pale moonlight, with fiery eyes fixed on
space. Charlie suppressed his own feelings 
over the silence of his father and sister 
to comfort Reuel.</p>

<p>“You ought not, my dear Briggs, he
would say. “Come, for heaven’s sake
shake off that sadness which may make
an end of you before you are aware.
Then he would add, jestingly, “Decidedly,
you regret the leopard’s claws!”</p>

<p>On this night the excitement of new
scenes had distracted the thoughts of both
men from their homes, and they lay
smoking in their hammocks before the

parted curtains of the tent lazily watching
Ababdis advancing with a bundle in his
hand. It was the long expected mail!</p>

<p>Chapter XIV.</p>

<p>It was some three weeks after this before 
Briggs was able to assume his duties. 
The sudden shock of the news of
his wife’s death over-weighted a brain
already strained to the utmost. More
than once they despaired of his life&#8212;
Professor Stone and Vance, who had put
aside his own grief to care for his friend.
Slowly the strong man had returned to
life once more. He did not rave or protest: 
Fate had no power to move him
more; the point of anguish was passed,
and in its place succeeded a dumb stupidity 
more terrible by far, though far more
blessed.</p>

<p>His love was dead. He himself was
dead for any sensibility of suffering that
he possessed. So for many days longer
he lay in his hammock seemingly without 
a thought of responsibility.</p>

<p>They had carried him back to the camp
across the river, and there he spent the
long days of convalescence. What did
he think of all day as he moved like a
shadow among the men or swung listlessly 
in the hammock? Many of the men
asked themselves that question as they
gazed at Briggs. One thought repeated
itself over and over in his brain, “Many
waters cannot quench love, neither cat
the floods drown it.” “Many waters"&#8212;
“many waters”&#8212;the words whispered
and sung appealingly, invitingly, in his
ears all day and all night. “Many waters, 
many waters.”</p>

<p>One day he heard them tell of the removal 
of the door in the pyramid two and
one-half miles on the hill. They had
found the Sphinx’ head as described in
the manuscript, but had been unable to
move it with any instrument in their possession. 
Much to his regret, Professor

<pb facs="p347"/>

Stone felt obliged to give the matter up
and content himself with the valuable
relics he had found. The gold mines, if
such there were, were successfully hidden
from searchers, and would remain a mystery.</p>

<p>The white orb of the moon was high in
the heavens; the <sic>echoeless</sic> sand gave back
no sound; that night Reuel rose, took his
revolver and ammunition, and leaving a
note for Vance telling him he had gone to
the third pyramid and not to worry, he
rowed himself over to Meroe. He had
no purpose, no sensation. Once he halted 
and tried to think. His love was dead:
&#8212;that was the one fact that filled his
thoughts at first. Then another took its
place. Why should he live? Of course
not; better rejoin her where parting was
no more. He would lose himself in the
pyramid. The manuscript had spoken of
dangers&#8212;he would seek them.</p>

<p>As he went on the moon rose in full
splendor behind him. Some beast of the
night plunged through a thicket along
the path.</p>

<p>The road ascended steadily for a mile
or more, crossing what must have once
been carriage drives. Under the light of
the setting moon the gradually increasing
fertility of the ground shone silver-white.
Arrived at the top of the hill, he paused
to rest and wipe the perspiration from his
face. After a few minutes’ halt, he
plunged on and soon stood before the entrace 
of the gloomy chamber; as he
stumbled along he heard a low, distinct
hiss almost beneath his feet. Reuel
jumped and stood still. He who had been
desirous of death but an hour before
obeyed the first law of nature. Who can
wonder? It was but the re-awakening
of life within him, and that care for what
has been entrusted to us by Omnipotence,
will remain until death has numbed our
senses.</p>

<p>The dawn wind blew all about him. He
would do no more until the dawn. Presently 

the loom of the night lifted and he
could see the outlines of the building a
few yards away. From his position he
commanded the plain at his feet as level
as a sea. The shadows grew more distinct, 
then without warning, the red dawn
shot up behind him. The sepulchre before 
him flushed the color of blood, and
the light revealed the horror of its emptiness.</p>

<p>Fragments of marble lay about him. It
seemed to the lonely watcher that he
could hear the sound of the centuries
marching by in the moaning wind and
purposeless dust.</p>

<p>The silence and sadness lay on him like
a pall and seemed to answer to the desolation 
of his own life.</p>

<p>For a while he rambled aimlessly from
wall to wall examining the gigantic resting 
place of the dead with scrupulous
care. Here were ranger great numbers
of the dead in glass cases; up and up they
mounted to the vaulted ceiling. His taper
flickered in the sombreness, giving
but a feeble light. The air grew cold and
damp as he went on. Once upon a time
there had been steps cut in the granite
and leading down to a well-like depression 
near the center of the great chamber.
Down he went holding the candle high
above his head as he carefully watched
for the Sphinx’ head. He reached a
ledge which ran about what was evidently
once a tank. The ledge ran only on one
side. He looked about for the Sphinx;
unless it was here he must retrace his
steps, for the ledge ran only a little way
about one side of the chamber.</p>

<p>He was cold and damp, and turned
suddenly to retrace his steps, when just in
front of him to the left the candle’s light
fell full on the devilish countenance of the
Ethiopian Sphinx.</p>

<p>He moved quickly toward it; and then
began an examination of the figure. As
he stepped backward his foot crushed
through a skull; he retreated with a shudder.

<pb facs="p348"/>

He saw now that he stood in a space
of unknown dimensions. He fancied he
saw rows of pillars flickering drunkenly
in the gloom. The American man is familiar 
with many things because of the
range of his experience, and Reuel Briggs
was devoid of fear, but in that moment he
tasted the agony of pure, physical terror.

For the first time since he received his letters 
from home, he was himself again
filled with pure, human nature. He
turned to retrace his steps; something
came out of the darkness like a hand,
passed before his face emitting a subtle
odor as it moved; he sank upon the
ground and consciousness left him.</p>

<p>(To be continued.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.006">

<pb facs="p423"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Synopsis of Chapters I. TO XII.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, a young medical student, interested in
mysticism, sees a face that haunts him. He attends a
concert with his friend Aubrey Livingston, and there
discovers in a negro concert-singer the owner of the
mysterious face. He sees this woman again on Hallow
Eve while playing at charms with a party of young
people at Vance Hall, the home of Livingston's betrothed.
Early the next morning he is called to attend
the victims of a railroad disaster at the hospital. He
finds among them the girl whose face haunts him, in a
cataleptic sleep which the doctors call death. He succeeds
in restoring her to consciousness, but with a
complete loss of memory. She loses her identity as a
negress. Reuel falls deeply in love with her. He
finally restores her to health and determines to marry
her, but finds his circumstances too straitened. Aubrey
Livingston helps him out by offering to obtain
for him a place in an expedition about to explore the
ancient city of Meroe in Africa. Reuel accepts, but
marries Dianthe before going on a two years’ venture.
After his departure Dianthe finds that Livingston is in
love with her, and he acquires a power over her that
she cannot resist. She agrees to fly with him against
her will; but before the time set, they, with Molly
Vance, go out canoeing and are overturned in the river,
and all three are supposed to have been drowned.</p>

<ab>The expedition reaches Africa. In crossing the Great
Desert Reuel Briggs visits old ruins and is rescued
from a leopard’s claws by Vance. They are suspicious
of Jim Titus, who pretended not to bear Briggs’ calls
for help. They receive no letters from home after leaving
England, and one night, by clairvoyant aid, Reuel
reads a letter that Titus has received. That same
night, by mediumistic power, Briggs describes the
overturning of the boat containing Molly, Dianthe and
Aubrey, on the Charles River months before. The
caravan reaches Meroe, and letters reveal the death of
Dianthe and Molly. Reuel is sick for some weeks,
and when he returns to health finds the expedition
about to give up its search for treasure and return
home. Wanders out one night while the camp is
asleep and goes to the last pyramid. While exploring
it he becomes unconscious.</ab>

<p>&#8212;</p>

<p>From profound unconsciousness,
deep, merciful, oblivious to pain and
the flight of time, from the gulf of the
mysterious shadows wherein earth and
heaven are alike forgotten, Reuel awoke
at the close of the fourth day after his
entrance into the Great Pyramid. That
Lethean calm induced by narcotic odors,
saved his reason. Great pain, whether
physical or mental, cannot last long, and
human anguish must find relief or take
it.</p>

<p>A soft murmur of voices was in his
ears as he languidly unclosed his eyes
and gazed into the faces of a number of
men grouped about the couch on which

he lay, who surveyed him with looks of
respectful admiration and curiosity
mingled with awe. One of the group
appeared to be in authority, for the others 
listened to him with profound respect 
as they conversed in low tones,
and were careful not to obtrude their
opinions.</p>

<p>Gradually his senses returned to him,
and Reuel could distinguish his surroundings. 
He gazed about him in
amazement. Gone were all evidences of
ruin and decay, and in their place was
bewildering beauty that filled him with
dazzling awe. He reclined on a couch
composed of silken cushions, in a room
of vast dimensions, formed of fluted columns 
of pure white marble upholding a
domed ceiling where the light poured in
through rose-colored glass in soft prismatic 
shades which gave a touch of
fairyland to the scene.</p>

<p>The men beside him were strangers,
and more unreal than the vast chamber.
Dark-visaged, he noticed that they
ranged in complexion from a creamy
tint to purest ebony; the long hair which
fell upon their shoulders, varied in texture
from soft, waving curls to the crispness 
of the most pronounced African
type. But the faces into which he gazed
were perfect in the cut and outline of
every feature; the forms hidden by soft
white drapery, Grecian in effect, were
athletic and beautifully moulded. Sandals 
covered their feet.</p>

<p>The eyes of the leader followed
Reuel’s every movement.</p>

<p>“Where am I?” cried Briggs impetuously, 
after a hurried survey of the situation.</p>

<pb facs="p424"/>

<p>Immediately the leader spoke to his
companions in a rich voice, commanding, 
but with all the benevolence of a
father.</p>

<p>"Leave us," he said. "I would be
alone with the stranger.”</p>

<p>He spoke in ancient Arabic known
only to the most profound students of
philology. Instantly the room was
cleared, each figure vanished behind the
silken curtains hanging between the colummns 
at one side of the room.</p>

<p>“How came I here?” cried Reuel
again.</p>

<p>“Peace,” replied the leader, extending
his arms as if in benediction above the
young man’s head. “You have nothing
to fear. You have been brought hither
for a certain purpose which will shortly
be made clear to you; vou shall return
to your friends if you desire so to do,
after the council has investigated your
case. But why, my son, did you wander
at night about the dangerous passages
of the pyramid? Are you, too, one of
those who seek for hidden treasure?”</p>

<p>In years the speaker was still young,
not being over forty despite his patriarchal 
bearing. The white robe was infinitely 
becoming, emphasizing breadth
of shoulder and chest above the silver-clasped 
arm’s-eye like nothing he had
seen save in the sculptured figures of
the ruined cities lately explored. But
the most striking thing about the man
was his kingly countenance, combining
force, sweetness and dignity in every
feature. The grace of a perfect life invested 
him like a royal robe. The musical 
language flowed from his lips in
sonorous accents that charmed the
scholar in his listener, who, to his own
great surprise and delight, found that
conversation between them could be
carried on with ease. Reuel could not
repress a smile as he thought of the astonishment 
of Professor Stone if he
could hear them rolling out the ancient

Arabic tongue as a common carrier of
thought. It seemed sacrilegious.</p>

<p>“But where am I?” he persisted, determined 
to locate his whereabouts.</p>

<p>“You are in the hidden city Telassar.
In my people you will behold the direct
descendants of the inhabitants of Meroe.
We are but a remnant, and here we wait
behind the protection of our mountains
and swamps, secure from the intrusion
of a world that has forgotten, for the
coming of our king who shall restore to
the Ethiopian race its ancient glory. I
am Ai, his faithful prime minister.”</p>

<p>Hopelessly perplexed by the words of
the speaker, Reuel tried to convince
himself that he was laboring under a
wild hallucination; but his senses all
gave evidence of the reality of his situation. 
Somewhere in Milton he had read
lines that now came faintly across his
memory:</p>

<p>“Eden stretched her lines<lb/>
From Auran eastward to the royal tow’rs<lb/>
Of great Seleucia, built by kings,<lb/>
Or where the sons of Eden long before<lb/>
Dwelt in Telassar.</p>

<p>Something of his perplexity Ai must
have read in his eves, for he smiled as
he said, “Not Telassar of Eden, but so
like to Eden’s beauties did our ancestors
find the city that thus did they call it.”</p>

<p>“Can it be that you are an Ethiopian
of those early days, now lost in obscurity? 
Is it possible that a remnant of that
once magnificent race yet dwells upon
old mother Earth? You talk of having
lived at Meroe; surely, you cannot mean
it. Were it true, what you have just uttered, 
the modern world would stand
aghast.”</p>

<p>Ai bowed his head gravely. “It is
even so, incredible though it may seem
to you, stranger. Destroyed and abased
because of her idolatries, Ethiopia’s arrogance

<pb facs="p425"/>

and pride have been humbled in
the dust. Utter destruction has come
upon Meroe the glorious, as was predicted. 
But there was a hope held out
to the faithful worshippers of the true
God that Ethiopia should stretch forth
her hand unto Eternal Goodness, and
that then her glory should again dazzle
the world. I am of the priestly caste,
and the office I hold descends from father 
to son, and has so done for more than
six thousand years before the birth of
Christ. But enough of this now; when
you are fully rested and recovered from
the effect of the narcotics we were
forced to give you, I will talk with you,
and I will also show you the wonders of
our hidden city. Come with me.”</p>

<p>Without more speech he lifted one of
the curtains at the side of the room, revealing 
another apartment where running 
water in marble basins invited one
to the refreshing bath. Attendants
stood waiting, tall, handsome, dark-visaged, 
kindly, and into their hands he
resigned Reuel.</p>

<p>Used as he was to the improvements
and luxuries of life in the modern Athens, 
he could but acknowledge them as
poor beside the combination of Oriental
and ancient luxury that he now enjoyed.
Was ever man more gorgeously housed
than this? Overhead was the tinted
glass through which the daylight fell in
softened glow. In the air was the perfume 
and lustre of precious incense, the
flash of azure and gold, the mingling of
deep and delicate hues, the gorgeousness 
of waving plants in blossom and tall
trees&#8212;palms, dates, orange, mingled
with the gleaming statues that shone
forth in brilliant contrast to the dark
green foliage. The floor was paved with
varied mosaic and dotted here and there
with the skins of wild animals.</p>

<p>After the bath came a repast of fruit,
game and wine, served him on curious
golden dishes that resembled the specimens 
taken from ruined Pompeii. By

the time he had eaten night had fallen,
and he laid himself down on the silken
cushions of his couch, with a feeling of
delicious languor and a desire for repose. 
His nerves were in a quiver of
excitement and he doubted his ability
to sleep, but in a few moments, even
while he doubted, he fell into a deep
sleep of utter exhaustion.</p>

<p>Chapter XV.</p>

<p>When he arose in the morning he
found that his own clothing had been
replaced by silken garments fashioned
as were Ai’s with the addition of golden
clasps and belts. In place of his revolver 
was a jewelled dagger literally
encrusted with gems.</p>

<p>After the bath and breakfast, Ai entered 
the room with his noiseless tread,
and when the greetings had been said,
invited him to go with him to visit the
public buildings and works of Telassar.
With a swift, phantomlike movement,
Ai escorted his guest to the farther end
of the great hall. Throwing aside a curtain 
of rich topaz silk which draped the
large entrance doors he ushered him
into another apartment opening out on
a terrace with a garden at its foot&#8212;a
garden where a marvellous profusion of
flowers and foliage ran riot amid sparkling 
fountains and gleaming statuary.</p>

<p>Through a broad alley, lined with majestic 
palms, they passed to the extreme
end of the terrace, and turning faced
the building from which they had just
issued. A smile quivered for a moment
on Ai’s face as he noted Reuel’s ill-concealed 
amazement. He stood for a moment 
stock-still, overcome with astonishment 
at the size and splendor of the
palace that had sheltered him over night.
The building was dome-shaped and of
white marble, surrounded by fluted columns, 
and fronted by courts where
fountains dashed their spray up to the
blue sky, and flowers blushed in myriad

<pb facs="p426"/>

colors and birds in gorgeous plumage
flitted from bough to bough.</p>

<p>It appeared to Reuel that they were
on the highest point of what might be
best described as a horse-shoe curve
whose rounded end rested on the side of
a gigantic mountain. At their feet
stretched a city beautiful, built with an
outer and inner wall. They were in the
outer city. Two streams descended like
cataracts to the plain below, at some
distance from each other, forming a triangle 
which held another city. Far in
the distance like a silver thread, he
could dimly discern where the rivers
joined, losing themselves in union. As he
gazed he recalled the description of the
treasure city that Professor Stone had
read to the explorers.</p>

<p>As far as the eye could reach stretched
fertile fields; vineyards climbed the
mountain side. Again Reuel quoted
Milton in his thoughts, for here was the
very embodiment of his words:</p>

<p>“Flowers of all hue, and without thorn
the rose,<lb/>
Another side, umbrageous grots and
caves<lb/>
Of cool recess, o’er which the mantling
vine<lb/>
Lays forth her purple grape, and gently
creeps<lb/>
Luxuriant; meanwhile murmuring
waters fall<lb/>
Down the slope hills, dispersed, or in
a lake,<lb/>
That to the fringed bank with myrtle
crown’d<lb/>
Her crystal mirror holds, unite their
streams.<lb/>
The birds their choir apply; airs, vernal
airs,<lb/>
Breathing the smell of field and grove,
attune<lb/>
The trembling leaves, while universal
Pan,<lb/>
Knit with the Graces and the Hours in
dance,<lb/>
Led on th’ eternal spring.</p>

<p>Far below he could dimly discern
moving crowds; great buildings reared
their stately heads towards a sky so blue
and bewildering beneath the sun’s bright
rays that the gazer was rendered speechless 
with amazement. Shadowy images
of past scenes and happenings flitted
across his brain like transient reflection
of a past perfectly familiar to him.</p>

<p>“Do you find the prospect fair?” asked
Ai at length, breaking the settled silence.</p>

<p>“Fairer than I can find words to express; 
and yet I am surprised to find that
it all seems familiar to me, as if somewhere 
in the past I had known just such
a city as this.”</p>

<p>Ai smiled a smile of singular sweet-
ness and content; Reuel could have
sworn that there was a degree of satisfaction 
in his pleasure.</p>

<p>“Come, we will go down into the city.
You who know the wonders of modern
life at its zenith, tell me what lesson you
learn from the wonders of a civilization
which had its zenith six thousand years
before Christ’s birth.”</p>

<p>“Six thousand years before Christ!”
murmured Reuel in blank stupidity.</p>

<p>"Aye; here in Telassar are preserved
specimens of the highest attainments the
world knew in ancient days. They tell
me that in many things your modern
world is yet in its infancy.”</p>

<p>“How!” cried Reuel, “do you then
held communion with the world outside
your city?”</p>

<p>“Certain members of our Council are
permitted to visit outside the gates. Do
you not remember Ababdis?”</p>

<p>“Our camel-driver?”</p>

<p>Ai bowed. "He is the member who
brought us news of your arrival, and
the intention of the expedition to find
our city for the sake of its treasure.”</p>

<p>More and more mystified bv the
words and manner of his guide, Reuel
made no reply. Presently they entered
a waiting palanquin and were borne
swiftly toward the city. The silken curtains 
were drawn one side, and he could

<pb facs="p427"/>

drink in the curious sights. They soon
left the country behind them and entered 
a splendid square, where stately
homes were outlined against the dense
blue of the sky. A statue of an immense
sphinx crouched in the center of the
square, its giant head reaching far into
the ethereal blue. Fountains played on
either side, dashing their silvery spray
beyond the extreme height of the head.
Under umbrageous trees were resting-places, 
and on the sphinx was engraved
the words: “That which hath been, is
now; and that which is to be, hath already 
been; and God requireth that
which is past.”</p>

<p>Suddenly a crowd of men surged into
the square, and a deep-toned bell sounded 
from a distance. Swiftly sped the
bearers, urged forward by the general
rush. The booming of the bell continued. 
They reached the end of the avenue 
and entered a side street, through
a court composed of statues. They
paused before a stately pile, towering in
magnificence high in the heavens, a
pile of marvellously delicate architecture
worked in stone. The entrance was of
incomparable magnificence. Reuel
judged that the four colossal statues before 
it represented Rameses the Great.
They were each sculptured of a single
block of Syene granite of mingled red
and black. They were seated on cubical
stones. The four Colosses sitting there
before that glittering pile produced a
most imposing effect.</p>

<p>The steps of the temple were strewn
with flowers; the doors stood open, and
music from stringed instruments vibrated 
upon the air. The bearers stopped
at a side entrance, and at a sign from Ai,
Reuel followed him into the edifice.</p>

<p>All was silence, save for the distant
hum of voices, and the faint sound of
music. They halted before a curtain
which parted silently for their entrance.
It was a small room, but filled with a
light of soft colors; when Reuel could

command his gaze, he beheld about
twenty men prostrated before him.
Presently they arose and each filed past
him, reverently touching the hem of his
white robe. Among them was Ababdis,
so transformed by his gorgeous robes of
office as to be almost unrecognizable.</p>

<p>Ai now assumed an azure robe embroidered 
in silver stars and crescents
that formed a sunburst in shape of a
Grecian cross. He then advanced
towards Reuel bearing on a silken cushion 
a magnificent crown, where the principal 
aigrette was shaped as a cross set
with gems priceless in value. Astounded
at the sight, the young man stood motionless 
while it was adjusted by golden
chains about his head. The gems blazed
with the red of the ruby, the green of
the emerald, the blue of the sapphire,
the yellow of the topaz, the cold white
of priceless diamonds. But dulling all
the glories of precious stones, peerless in
their own class, lay the center ornament&#8212;
the black diamond of Senechus’s
crown, spoken of in Professor Stone’s
record. A white robe of silken stuff was
added to his costume, and again his
companions filed past him in deepest
reverence. Reuel was puzzled to understand 
why so great homage was paid
to him. While he turned the thought
in his mind, a bugle sounded somewhere
in the distance, sweet and high. Instantly, 
he felt a gliding motion as if
the solid earth were slipping from beneath 
his feet, the curtains before him
parted silently, and he found himself
alone on a raised platform in the center
of a vast auditorium, crowded with humanity. 
Lights twinkled everywhere;
there was the fragrance of flowers, there
were columns of marble draped in amber, 
azure and green, and glittering
lamps encrusted with gems and swung
by golden chains from the sides of the
building. A blazing arch formed of
brilliant lamps raised like a gigantic bow

<pb facs="p428"/>

in the heavens and having in its center
the words<lb/>
“HAIL! ERGAMENES!”<lb/>
in letters of sparkling fire, met his startled 
gaze. Then came a ringing shout
from the throats of the assembled multitude, 
“Ergamenes! Ergamenes!” Again
and again the throng lifted up the joyous 
cry. Presently as Reuel stood there
undecided what to do—not knowing
what was expected of him, as silently as
he had come, he felt the motion of the
platform where he stood. The crowd
faded from sight, the curtains fell; once
more he stood within the little room,
surrounded by his companions.</p>

<p>“Ababdis, Ai,” he demanded, sternly,
“What is the meaning of this strange
happening, more like a scene from the
Arabian Nights? Who is Ergamenes?”</p>

<p>“Thou art Ergamenes&#8212;the long-looked-for 
king of Ethiopia, for whose
reception this city was built! But we
will return to the palace, now that the
people have satisfied somewhat their
curiosity. At supper you shall know
more.”</p>

<p>Once more the bearers carried them
swiftly beyond the confines of the city,
and soon the palace walls rose before
them. Reuel had hardly collected his
scattered wits before he found himself
seated at table and on either side of the
board the Council reclined on silken
cushions. His own seat was raised and
placed at the head of the table. There
was no talking done while what seemed
to be a solemn feast was in progress.
Servants passed noiselessly to and fro
attending to their wants, while from an
alcove the music of stringed instruments
and sweetest vocal numbers was borne
to their ears.</p>

<p>After supper, they still reclined on the
couches. Then from the hidden recesses
the musicians came forth, and kneeling
before Reuel, one began a song in blank
verse, telling the story of Ergamenes
and his kingdom.</p>

<p>“Hail! oh, hail, Ergamenes!<lb/>
The dimmest sea-cave below thee,<lb/>
The farthest sky-arch above,<lb/>
In their innermost stillness know thee,<lb/>
And heave with the birth of Love.<lb/>
“All hail!<lb/>
We are thine, all thine, forevermore;<lb/>
Not a leaf on the laughing shore,<lb/>
Not a wave on the heaving sea,<lb/>
Nor a single sigh<lb/>
In the boundless sky,<lb/>
But is vowed evermore to thee!”</p>

<p>“Son of a fallen dynasty, outcast of a
sunken people, upon your breast is a
lotus lily, God’s mark to prove your race
and descent. You, Ergamenes, shall
begin the restoration of Ethiopia. Blessed 
be the name of God for ever and ever,
for wisdom and might are His, and He
changeth the times and seasons; He removeth 
kings and countries, and setteth
them up again; He giveth wisdom unto
the wise, and knowledge to them that
know understanding! He revealeth the
deep and secret things; He knoweth
what is in the darkness, and the light
dwelleth with Him!</p>

<p>“Great were the sins of our fathers,
and the white stranger was to Ethiopia
but a scourge in the hands of an offended 
God. The beautiful temples of
Babylon, filled with vessels of silver and
gold, swelled the treasures of the false
god Bel. Babylon, where our monarchs
dwelt in splendor, once the grandest city
to be found in the world. Sixty miles
round were its walls, of prodigious
height, and so broad that seven chariots
could be driven abreast on the summit!
One hundred gates of solid brass gave
entrance into the city, guarded by lofty
towers. Beautiful buildings rose within,
richly adorned and surrounded by gardens. 
One magnificent royal palace
was girdled by three walls, the outermost 
of which was seven miles and a
half in compass. In its grounds rose the
far-famed hanging gardens, terraces

<pb facs="p429"/>

built one above another to the height
of three hundred and fifty feet, each terrace 
covered with thick mould, and
planted with flowers and shrubs, so that
the skill of man created a verdant hill on
a plain. Nearly in the centre rose the
lofty temple of Belus, the tower of Babel, 
whose builders had hoped to make
its summit touch the very skies. Mil-
lions of dollars in gold were gathered in
the chambers of the temple. The
wealth, power and glory of the world
were centered in the mighty city of
Babylon.</p>

<p>“On the throne of this powerful city
sat your forefathers, O Ergamenes!”</p>

<p>Part of the story had been given in
recitative, one rich voice carrying
grandly the monotonous notes to the
accompaniment of the cornet, flute,
sackbut, dulcimer and harp. Reuel had
listened to the finest trained voices attempting 
the recitative in boasted musical circles, but never in so stately and
impressive a manner as was now his
privilege to hear. They continued the
story.</p>

<p>“And Meroe, the greatest city of them
all, pure-blooded Ethiopian. Once the
light of the world’s civilization, now a
magnificent Necropolis.</p>

<p>“Standing at the edge of the Desert,
fertile in soil, rich in the luxuries of for-
eign shores; into her lap caravans
poured their treasures gathered from
the North, South, East and West. All
Africa poured into this queenly city
ivory, frankincense and gold. Her colossal 
monuments were old before Egypt
was; her wise men monopolized the
learning of the ages, and in the persons
of the Chaldeans have figured conspicuously 
the wisdom of ages since Meroe
has fallen.</p>

<p>“Mother of ancient warfare, her
horsemen and chariots were the won-
der and terror of her age; from the
bows of her warriors, the arrows sped
like a flight of birds, carrying destruction

to her foes,&#8212;a lamb in peace, a lion
in time of war.”</p>

<p>Once more the measure changed, and
another voice took up the story in verse.</p>

<p>“Who will assume the bays<lb/>
That the hero wore?<lb/>
Wreaths on the Tomb of Days<lb/>
Gone evermore!<lb/>
Who shall disturb the brave<lb/>
Or one leaf of their holy grave?<lb/>
The laurel is vow’d to them,<lb/>
Leave the bay on its sacred stem!<lb/>
But hope, the rose, the unfading rose,<lb/>
Alike for slave and freeman grows!</p>

<p>“On the summit, worn and hoary,<lb/>
Of Lybia’s solemn hills,<lb/>
The tramp of the brave is still!<lb/>
And still is the poisoned dart,<lb/>
In the pulse of the mighty hearts,<lb/>
Whose very blood was glory!</p>

<p>Who will assume the bays<lb/>
That the hero wore?<lb/>
Wreaths on the Tomb of Days<lb/>
Gone evermore!”</p>

<p>Upon Reuel a strange force seemed
working. If what he heard were true,
how great a destiny was his! He had
carefully hidden his Ethiopian extraction 
from the knowledge of the world.
It was a tradition among those who had
known him in childhood that he was
descended from a race of African kings.
He remembered his mother well. From
her he had inherited his mysticism and
his occult powers. The nature of the
mystic within him was, then, but a
dreamlike devotion to the spirit that
had swayed his ancestors; it was the
shadow of Ethiopia's power. The lotus
upon his breast he knew to be a birthmark. 
Many a night he had been
aroused from childhood’s slumbers, to
find his mother bending above him, candle 
in hand, muttering broken sentences
of prayer to Almighty God as she examined

<pb facs="p430"/>

his bosom by the candle’s rays.
He had wondered much; now he
guessed the rest. Once more the clanging 
strings of the instruments chained
his attention. The recitative was resumed.</p>

<p>“The Most High ruleth in the kingdom 
of men, and giveth it to whomsoever 
He will. He delivereth and rescueth, 
and He worketh signs and wonders
in heaven and in earth. Pre-eminent in
peace, invincible in war—once the masters 
of mankind, how have we fallen
from our high estate!</p>

<p>“Stiff-necked, haughty, no conscience
but that of intellect, awed not by God’s
laws, worshipping Mammon, sensual,
unbelieving, God has punished us as he
promised in the beginning. Gone are
our ancient glories, our humbled pride
cries aloud to God in the travail of our
soul. Our sphinx, with passionless features, 
portrays the dumb suffering of
our souls</p>

<p>Their look, with the reach of past ages,
was wise,<lb/>
And the soul of eternity thought in their
eyes.</p>

<p>“By divine revelation David beheld
the present time, when, after Christ’s
travail for the sins of humanity, the time
of Ethiopia’s atonement being past,
purged of idolatry, accepting the One
Only God through His Son Jesus, suddenly 
should come a new birth to the
descendants of Ham, and Ethiopia
should return to her ancient glory! Ergamenes, 
all hail!</p>

<p>“You come from afar<lb/>
From the land of the stranger,<lb/>
The dreadful in war,<lb/>
The daring in danger;<lb/>
Before him our plain<lb/>
Like Eden is lying;<lb/>
Behind him remain<lb/>
But the wasted and dying.</p>


<p>“The weak finds not ruth,<lb/>
Nor the patriot glory;<lb/>
No hope for the youth,<lb/>
And no rest for the hoary:<lb/>
O'er Ethiop’s lost plains<lb/>
The victor’s sword flashes,<lb/>
Her sons are in chains,<lb/>
And her temples in ashes!</p>

<p>“Who will assume the bays<lb/>
That the hero wore?<lb/>
Wreaths on the Tomb of Days<lb/>
Gone evermore!”</p>

<p>Upon his companions the song of the
past of Ethiopia had a strange effect.
Soothing at times, at times exciting,
with the last notes from the instruments
the company sprang to their feet; with
flashing dark eyes, faces reflecting inward 
passions, they drew their short,
sabrelike arms and circled about
Reuel’s throne with the shout “Ergamenes! 
Ergamenes!”</p>

<p>Chapter XVI.</p>

<p>Once more Reuel found himself alone
with Ai. It was far into the night, but
he felt sleepless and restless. At last
Ai broke a long silence:</p>

<p>“Tell me of the country from which
you come, Ergamenes. Is it true that
the Ethiopian there is counted less than
other mortals?”</p>

<p>“It is true, Ai,” replied Reuel. “There,
the dark hue of your skin, your waving
hair with its trace of crispness, would
degrade you below the estate of any man
of fair hue and straight locks, belonging
to any race outside the Ethiopian, for it
is a deep disgrace to have within the
veins even one drop of the blood you
seem so proud of possessing.”</p>

<p>“That explains your isolation from
our race, then?”</p>

<p>Reuel bowed his head in assent, while
over his face passed a flush of shame.
He felt keenly now the fact that he had
played the coward’s part in hiding his

<pb facs="p431"/>

origin. What though obstacles were
many, some way would have been
shown him to surmount the difficulties
of caste prejudice.</p>

<p>“And yet, from Ethiopia came all the
arts and cunning inventions that make
your modern glory. At our feet the
mightiest nations have worshipped, paying 
homage to our kings, and all nations 
have sought the honor of alliance
with our royal families because of our
strength, grandeur, riches and wisdom.
Tell me of all the degradation that has
befallen the unfortunate sons of Ham.”</p>

<p>Then in the deep, mysterious silence
of the night, Reuel gave in minutest detail 
the story of the Negro, reciting with
dramatic effect the history of the wrongs
endured by the modern Ethiopian.</p>

<p>To his queries as to the history of
these mountain-dwelling Ethiopians, Ai
gave the following reply:</p>

<p>“We are a singular people, governed
by a female monarch, all having the
same name, Candace, and a Council of
twenty-five Sages, who are educated for
periodical visits to the outer world.
Queen Candace is a virgin queen who
waits the coming of Ergamenes to inaugurate 
a dynasty of kings. Our virgins 
live within the inner city, and from
among them Candace chooses her successor 
at intervals of fifteen years.</p>

<p>“To become a Sage, a man must be
married and have at least two children;
a knowledge of two out-world languages,
and to pass a severe examination by the
court as to education, fitness and ability.
After an arduous preparation they are
initiated into the secrets of this kingdom. 
They are chosen for life. The
inner city is the virgins’ court, and it is
adorned with beautiful gardens, baths,
schools and hospitals. When a woman
marries she leaves this city for the outer
one.</p>

<p>“We have a great temple, the one you
entered, dedicated to the Supreme or
Trinity. It is a masterpiece of beauty

and art. The population assembles
there twice a year for especial service.
It seats about 12,000 persons. The
Sages have seen nothing equal to it in
the outer world.</p>

<p>Octagonal in shape, with four wings
or galleries, on opposite sides; the intervening 
spaces are filled with great prism
columns, twenty-five feet high, made of
a substance like glass, malleable, elastic
and pure. The effect is gorgeous. The
decorations of the hall are prepared
natural flowers; that is, floral garlands
are subjected to the fumes of the crystal
material covering them like a film and
preserving their natural appearance.
This is a process handed down from the
earliest days of Ethiopian greatness. I
am told that the modern world has not
yet solved this simple process,” he said,
with a gentle smile of ridicule.</p>

<p>“We preserve the bodies of our most
beautiful women in this way. We sus-
pend reflecting plates of the crystal ma-
terial arranged in circles, pendant from
the ceiling of the central hall, and thus
the music of the instruments is repeated
many times in sweetest harmony.</p>

<p>“We have services at noon every seventh 
day, chiefly choral, in praise of the
attributes of the Supreme. Our religion
is a belief in One Supreme Being, the
center of action in all nature. He distributed 
a portion of Himself at an early
age to the care of man who has attained
the highest development of any of His
terrestrial creatures. We call this ever-living 
faculty or soul Ego.</p>

<p>“After its transition Ego has the power 
of expressing itself to other bodies,
with like gift and form, its innate feeling; 
and by law of affinity, is ever striving 
to regain its original position near
the great Unity; but the physical attractions 
of this beautiful world have such
a fascination on the organism of man
that there is ever a contention against
the greater object being attained; and
unless the Ego can wean the body from

<pb facs="p432"/>

gross desires and raise it to the highest
condition of human existence, it cannot
be united to its Creator. The Ego preserves 
its individuality after the dissolution 
of the body. We believe in re-incarnation 
by natural laws regulating material 
on earth. The Ego can never be
destroyed. For instance, when the body
of a good man or woman dies, and the
Ego is not sufficiently fitted for the
higher condition of another world, it is
re-associated with another body to complete 
the necessary fitness for heaven.”</p>

<p>“What of the Son of man? Do you
not know the necessity of belief in the
Holy Trinity? Have not your Sages

brought you the need of belief in God's
Son?" Ai looked somewhat puzzled.</p>

<p>“We have heard of such a God, but
have not paid much attention to it. How
beheve vou, Ergamenes?”</p>

<p>“In Jesus Christ, the Son of God,”
replied Reuel solemnly.</p>

<p>“O Ergamenes, your belief shall be
ours; we have no will but yours. Deign
to teach your subjects.”</p>

<p>When at last Reuel closed his eves in
slumber, it was with a feeling of greater
responsibility and humility than he had
ever experienced. Who was he that so
high a destiny as lay before him should
be thrust upon his shoulders?</p>

<p>(To be concluded.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
