<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0208">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from John E. Taylor</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0208</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from John E. Taylor</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date/>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>


<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Taylor, John E.</persName>
<roleName>Acting United States Consul</roleName>
<placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<date/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName></persName>
<roleName></roleName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-09" who="#lkw"> Encoding</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls"> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="3"/>

<!-- <p>Microcopy No. T-438 DESPATCHES FROM UNITED STATES CONSULS IN SIERRA LEONE, 1858-1906 Roll 1 Volume 1 February 22, 1858- March 28,1881 THE NATIONL ARCHIVES NATIONAL ARCHIVES AND RECORDS SERVICE GENERAL SERVICES ADMINISTRATION Washington: 1960</p>

<p>Vol. 1 Sierra Leone Feb. 22, 1858 June 30 1882</p> -->

<p>You will at once see Sir, that the position which I now hold Acting Consul an Acting for and without  appointment from the United States Government, but merely by the nomination of the Commodore before-named invests me in strict law with no actual legal authority. I am recognized as Acting counsul by the local Government, as it seems to me, merely through courtesy, and I cannot close my eyes to the fact, that, had I attempted to make any stand in opposition to the Government in recent cases of aggresion by British Cruizers on American Vessels in the Coast, any further recognition whatever of me even through courtesy would have at once ceased.</p> 

<p>As you are aware, the several vessels seized on the Coast  on the alleged ground of being engaged in the Slave Trade are all sent  to the Colony for adjudication, or, I should rather observe for condemnation.</p>

<p>I stake the liberty of enclosing for your inspection a List of the Prizes taken by H. R. Majestys Cruizers and sent into this Port. I will also mention that during the period I have been Acting Counsel there have arrived in this Port  no fewer than 120 American Vessels comprizing a Tonnage of over 25000 Tons, and with crews consisting of 1100 men, exclusive of three United States Ships of War. </p>

<p>You will have in mind for, that the British Government do not fail, to

<pb facs="4"/>

maintin a Consul at Liberia, and it is I am sure almost unnecessary for me to remark in Point of Comparison with Sierra Leone, Liberia sinks into insignificance. </p>

<p>Under the circumstances I have disclosed to you I venture to submit, for your consideration my lengthened service as Acting Consul and the inadequacy of pay I have received through fees alone and which have been considerably reduced by recent Acts of Congress.</p>

<p>I earnestly trust Sir, that you will see the urgent necessity for appointing a Consul at this place, and that in the exercise of your patronage, you will be pleased to confer such appointment on me with such salary as you may think proper to maintain the dignity of our great nation. </p>

<closer><salute>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
With high respects,<lb/>
Your most obdt humble Servant</salute>
<signed>Jno E Taylor<lb/>
Acting United States Consul.</signed></closer>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>



