<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0904">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward, December 31, 1862</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0904</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 2</biblScope>
<date when="1862-12-31">December 31, 1862</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Slavery and Slave Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2769891">Baikie, William Balfour, 1825-1864</term>
<term>Barbour, J. G. J.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51556067">Benson, Stephen Allen, 1816-1865</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29832058">Burton, Richard Francis, 1821-1890</term>
<term>Campbell, Benjamin</term>
<term>Clegg</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39456173">Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76392240">Crummell, Alexander, 1819-1898</term>
<term>Davis, Francis William</term>
<term>Deputie, Charles</term>
<term>Hewett, J. F. Napier</term>
<term>Johnson, John D.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term>Manna</term>
<term>May, D. J.</term>
<term>McLeod, Lyons</term>
<term>Pinkus, Henry</term>
<term>Ralston, Gerard</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/63021631">Roberts, Joseph J. (Joseph Jenkins), 1809-1876</term>
<term>Ross, R.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4139159820944514000003">Russell, John Russell, Earl, 1792-1878</term>
<term>Townsend, Henry</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abeokuta (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Careysburg (Liberia)</term>
<term>Cape Mount River</term>
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Egypt</term>
<term>Elmina (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Gallinas River</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Lagos (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Little Sess (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Montserrado (Liberia)</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
<term>Yorubaland</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Spain</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Kroo</term>
<term>Gallinas</term>
<term>Niffaw</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hanson, Abraham</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1862-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-04-16"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-05" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0078.jpg"/>

<p>No. 7.</p>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency,<lb/>
Monrovia, Dec 31st., 1862.</p>

<p>To the Honorable William H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State of U.S. of A.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to
enclose herein, duplicate copies of the Message
of His Excellency, S. A. Benson, President of Liberia,
to the Legislature.</p>

<p>I also have the honor to enclose duplicate
copies of a "Prospectus" of a plan for
the promotion and extension of Commerce, between
Great Britain, and the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>I have the honor to remain,<lb/>
With Sincere Respect,<lb/>
Your very Obedient Servt.<lb/>
Abm Hanson,<lb/>
U.S. Com. Agent.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0079.jpg"/>

<note>U.S. Commercial Agency
Monrovia December 31, 1862<lb/>
Abm Hanson Com. Agent</note>

<note>No 7<lb/>
2 Enclosures<lb/>
Received</note>

<note>Annual Message of
President to Legislature of Liberia</note>

<note>Prospectus of a scheme 
of British capitalists for
enlargement of their commerce
with that coast of Africa</note>

<note>Received at Statistical Office May 16/63</note>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0080.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<note>Copy of the Original Prospectus as published in England.</note>

<head type="main">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Incorporated under the Joint Stock Companies' Act of 1856 and 1857, whereby the liability of the Shareholders is limited to the amount of their Subscriptions.</p>

<p>CAPITAL £250,000, in 25,000 SHARES of £10 Each.</p>

<p>FIRST ISSUE 12,500 SHARES.</p>

<p>£1 to be paid on application, and £1 10s. on allotment. The holders of such first Shares to have the preference, pro rata, in all further issues. No call to exceed £2 10s. per Share, nor to be made except at an interval of at least three months from any previous Call.</p>

<p>If no allotment be made, the Deposit will be returned in full.</p>

<list>
<head>Directors.</head>
<item>Thomas Bazley, Esq., M.P., Manchester.</item>
<item>Thomas Bradshaw, Esq., Temple.</item>
<item>George Braginton, Esq., Torrington, Devon.</item><item>Thomas Briggs, Esq., Prestwich Park, Manchester.</item>
<item>Henry Brownrigg, Esq., 33, Lime Street, E.C.</item>
<item>Thomas Clegg, Esq., Manchester.</item>
<item>Frederic Doulton, Esq., M.P., Lambeth.</item>
<item>Ambrose Emerson, Esq. (Messrs. Newby, Carson &amp; Co., Gresham House, E.C.)</item>
<item>Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, F.R.G.S., J.P., Cardiff.</item>
<item>Gerard Ralston, Esq., Consul-General for Liberia, 21, Tokenhouse Yard, E.C.</item>
<item>(with power to add.)</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Bankers.</head>
<item>The London and Westminster Bank, Lothbury, E.C.</item>
<item>Solicitors. Messrs. Cotterill &amp; Sons, 32, Throgmorton Street.</item>
<item>Brokers. Messrs. Huggins &amp; Rowsell, 1, Threadneedle Street.</item>
<item>General Manager. J. B. Langley, Esq.</item>
<item>Secretary. F. W. Stone, Esq.</item>
<item>Shipping and Insurance Agent. Charles Kitto, Esq.</item>
<item>Temporary Offices. 41, Gresham House, E.C.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Prospectus.</head>

<p>The object of the Company is–To establish Trading Stations, Factories, and Depots on the Coast of Western Africa, and by means of organized Agencies, to bring down and collect for shipment at such stations, the valuable products of the Interior; to import Goods, and introduce Machinery for cleaning and pressing Cotton, and for other purposes; and generally to enter into Commercial relations with the Native Traders, by means of barter traffic or otherwise; and thereby to open up, in exchange for British manufactures, a practically illimitable market for Cotton and other products–and to secure their transmission to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>The capabilities of Africa to meet the commercial requirements of Europe are evidenced in the variety of its productions, and the increasing extent of its trading operations; and it has long been a matter of surprise, that the encouragement of Native industry should have been left to associations of a philanthropic character, or to a few Merchants intent upon the enormous profit which exclusive dealings with the Natives incontestably afford.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0081.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Cotton.</head>

<p>The cultivation of the Cotton Plant, and the employment of African labour on its native soil, have already been sufficiently tested. There is abundance of labour seeking employment, a fertile soil well adapted for its growth, and a population actively alive to what will benefit themselves. <hi rend="italics">No expensive or uncertain experiments are required to test the ability or the will of the Natives to supply this country with cheap and good cotton.</hi> The testimony of the officers of the Niger expedition concurs with, and confirms, the evidence of Dr. Livingstone, and other African travellers, that indigenous Cotton is growing in abundance throughout vast districts, covering many thousands of miles of territory, and only waits to be gathered. Some Tribes of the Natives are largely engaged in manufacturing Cotton into clothing for their own use. It is calculated that more than 200,000 pieces of these cloths are annually exported from Africa into the Brazils. In fact, only buyers on the spot are wanted to take from the Natives what they have to offer, giving in exchange manufactured goods suitable to their requirements.</p>

<p>In a letter from Dr. Balfour Bakie, in command of the Niger Expedition, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, which Lord Russell caused to be inserted in the <hi rend="italics">London Gazette</hi> of August 29th, 1862, he emphatically urges his Lordship "to call attention, in England, to the peculiar eligibility of this portion of Central Africa (Bida Nusse), as a Cotton field." Again, speaking of Sudan, and the Yoruba country, he proceeds to say–Here Cotton is already in abundance, and cultivated by a people able and willing to work, and accustomed to its habits and rearing; nothing is required but increased demand, means of purchase, cleaning and shipment. The rest would speedily follow."</p>

<p>Another practical authority–Mr. Clegg, of Manchester, who has an establishment at Abeokuta, states–"for very many years my instructions have been to cease buying Cotton, when more than a halfpenny per pound in the Seed, and my young Africans have again and again written to say, that at that price for more was brought to them than they could buy."</p>

<p>Mr. I. Lyons McLeod, Hon. Secretary to the African Aid Society, in a Letter to the <hi rend="italics">Times</hi>, March 28th, 1861, writes–"It is a well-attested fact, that from Western Africa (shipping port Lagos), Cotton in abundance maybe purchased at 2d. per lb., and allowing for exorbitant overcharge for cleaning freight, &amp;c., it may be sold from the same locality in Liverpool at 4½d. per lb. This Cotton is equal in quality to New Orleans at 6½d. per lb., proving beyond doubt, that from Western Africa, which is nearer to our shores than the Cotton districts of America, we may obtain the same amount of Cotton for £20,000,000, for which we are paying the Slaveholders of the United States £30,000,000. In Western Africa–the Yoruba Country, and along the valley of the Niger," (the localities above referred to by Dr. Balfour Bakie)–"the Natives are ready to supply any amount of Cotton for Manchester and Glasgow Manufacturers."</p>

<p>These testimonies appear to demand the most serious attention and consideration at the present crisis.</p>

<p>The supply of Cotton from the Southern States (which till a recent date formed 80 per cent. of our consumption), cannot be fully renewed for several years; part of the crop of 1861 has been burned, and the remainder may never reach us. In 1862, it is believed, that only about one-fourth of the usual crop has been sown, and it is not likely that a larger area can be placed under Cotton Culture in 1863; so that, if the Civil War were to be ended by any means to-morrow, the full supply of American Cotton could not be resumed till September, 1864. Till that date, the price of middling and ordinary Orleans are not likely to fall below One Shilling per pound.</p>

<p>There is abundant evidence to show that India cannot for many years supply the quantity or quality required. The Egyptian supply is the only one which might be supposed likely to compete with that imported from West Africa; but the Egyptian Cotton imported into England has never hitherto reached 200,000 bales in any one year, and if doubled (which it cannot be for two or three years), it will not suffice to make up the deficiency created by the reduced supplies of ordinary Americans. Besides, the average price of <sic>Egytian</sic> Cotton has been 8d. per pound for several years. African Cotton, equal to middling Orleans, can be delivered in Liverpool, at a cost to the Importer of Fourpence Halfpenny per pound. In the seed, in Africa, it may be procured in unlimited quantities at about one Halfpenny per pound; cleaned Cotton about Threepence. Payments being made in barter, the profits on the Goods reduce the cost price of the Cotton considerably.</p>

<p>It is not the intention of the "West Africa Company" to become <hi rend="italics">Cultivators of Cotton</hi>; the Company will simply be <hi rend="italics">Purchasers of Cotton</hi>, which will be brought down to their Stations by the Native Traders, and thence Shipped to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>Several well-known Firms, having used African Cotton in their Manufactories, are able to report favourably of its quality working.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0082.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">General Trade.</head>

<p>The Company will not, however, depend on Cotton alone for realising the good dividend on the capital employed. The interchange of commodities will be widened to the largest possible extent, so as to include every other product of Africa, which will pay an enhanced value in this country. These products, which consist chiefly of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, Gold Dust, Ivory, Hides, Indigo, Copper, Ground Nuts, Pepper, Arrowroot, Gums, Dye Woods, Ostrich Feathers, Timber for Shipbuilding, and other articles of commerce, equally suitable to the requirements of our markets, will also be made the media of trade, so as to suit the industry and keen trading instincts of the various classes of Native producers. The fact that the production of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, and other valuable articles, is in excess of the local demand, can be shown by the latest and most indubitable authorities. The Rev. Samuel Crowther, writing to the Church Missionary Society lately, states, "at the Delta of the Niger alone, millions' worth, in red Oil and black Oil from the kernels of the Palm nut, rot away annually for want of inducement to collect them."* From an official document received through the Board of Trade, it appears that in 1856 upwards of 220,000 tons of these kernels, from which Oil of the value of £3,789,000 might have been extracted, were actually thrown away on the coast. The amount thus lost represents in actual value a sum of upwards of a Million Sterling more than all the tallow exported from Russia in that year; and when it is considered that the tallow was paid for in cash, and that the bulk of the trade with Africa may be carried on by barter of the manufactures of Manchester, Glasgow, Birmingham, the Potteries, and Sheffield, it is impossible to overrate the benefits which will accrue to this country by developing the resources of Western Africa.</p>

<p>As there is no currency in the Country, trade is conducted by means of barter, so that a market for English productions will be opened at every point from which the Company draws its supplies of raw materials; a profit both ways will thus be obtained by the Company, viz: Upon the goods sold in Africa, and <hi rend="italics">vice versá</hi>, upon the Cotton, Palm Oil, &amp;c., imported and sold in the English markets.</p>

<p>The "West Africa Company," will commence operations under peculiarly favorable circumstances, owing to the fact that their Agencies on the West Coast of Africa are already organized; and competent acclimatised persons, native merchants and others, at Abeokuta, Elmina, Lagos, Cape Palmas, and in the Niger river, are ready to act in behalf of the Company the moment it commences business.</p>

<p>From the foregoing statements, taken together with the fact that this Company will possess unusual facilities for successful mercantile operations, owing to its large Capital and connexions, it is confidently expected that its transactions will produce very handsome dividends. Persons having a knowledge of the Africa trade will readily <sic>undrestand</sic>that to name what would be a probable rate of interest on the Capital worked, would, to the uninitiated, bear the stamp of exaggeration. The Directors, however, feel assured that the Company will eventually assume such dimensions as to invest it with a most important character; and that the development of the resources of Africa will do more than anything else to hasten the extinction of the Foreign Slave Trade, an event not more desirable to philanthropy than to commerce.</p>

<p>* See African Aid Society's Report for 1862, page 10, and generally in confirmation of the statements herein, the Annual Reports of the Cotton Supply Association; "The Cotton Plant and Countries adapted to its Culture," pages 5-15, &amp;c.; D. J. May, Esq., R. N., (Niger Expedition), and the Reports of Mr. Consul Burton; Mr. Davis, Surgeon to the Niger Expedition; ratified as they are by Mr. Consul Campbell; the Rev. Mr. Townsend, of Abeokuta; Dr. R. Ross, Esq.; and by Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, in his recent work "European Settlements on the West Coast of Africa."</p>

<p>Application for Shares may be made in the accompanying form to the Brokers, Messrs. Huggins &amp; Roswell, 1, Threadneedle Street, London, E.C., or to the Secretary, at the Temporary Offices of the Company, 41, Gresham House, E.C.</p>

<p>[For Special Notice addressed to the Residents on the West Coast of Africa, see over.]</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0083.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Capital £250,000, in 25,000 Shares of £10 each.<lb/>
First Issue 12,500 Shares.</p>

<p>Prospectus.</p>

<p>S. Straker &amp; Sons, Printers, 20, Bishopsgate Within &amp; 25, Leadenhall Street.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<p>Coast Allotment.]</p>

<p>SPECIAL NOTICE</p>

<p>To the Merchants, Capitalists, and others on the<lb/>
West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>The Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," established in England by Act of Parliament limiting the liability of each Shareholder to the amount of his Subscriptions, have <hi rend="italics">resolved to reserve 2,500 Shares for the Capitalists on the West Coast.</hi> Mr. William Grant, of Kissy Road, Sierra Leone, and Captain Davis, of Lagos, are acquainted with the Directors; and copies of the Articles of Association, under which the Company is incorporated by law, are in the hands of the former.</p>

<p>Form of Application for Shares.</p>

<p>To the Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," (in England).</p>

<p>Gentlemen,–Having remitted by Draft on &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; the Sum of &#160; &#160; &#160; sterling, I request you to allot me &#160; &#160; &#160; Shares in the Company; and I agree to accept the same or any less number that may be allotted to use me, and to comply with all the rules and regulations of the Company.</p>

<p>Name</p>

<p>Address</p>

<p>Occupation</p>

<p>Date</p>

<p>[The applicant should enclose his application with the Draft addressed to "J. B. Langley, Esq., General Manager West Africa Company, 41, Gresham House, London, England," or in lieu thereof he should forward instructions to his Agent in England <unclear>to</unclear> make application on his behalf, and to pay the deposit (£1 per Share on application, and £1 10s. on allotment). It will be <unclear>necessary</unclear> in case of remittances direct from the Coast that the whole of the deposit, £2 10s. per Share, should be seat at once.]</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0084.jpg"/>

<head type="main">Message of the President of the Republic of Liberia to the Legislature, at the Commencement of their Session December 1862.</head>

<head type="sub">Monrovia: G. Killian, Printer, Liberia Herald Office. 1862</head>

<pb n="Roll2-0086.jpg"/>

<head type="sub">Message.</head>

<p>To the Honorable–The Senate, and the House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>Gentlemen,</p>

<p>Nearly nine months absence from the Republic this year, and having returned only a few days previously to the opening of your Session, have rendered me almost entirely dependent on my constitutional substitute, for data–on the home affairs of our common country, which I have not had sufficient time to consider, and put in that shape, by amplification, as we have mutually desired. I shall therefore make communication to you from time to time during the Session, on such matters as I shall deem promotive of the interests of the country.</p>

<p>I have first, to invite the attention of the Legislature to the manifold disturbances and outrages committed by the Little Sess Fishermen. The peace and quietude of our leeward coast have been sadly disturbed by them during the past year. They have been accused, of not only having made war upon, and killed several of the Niffaw people without reasonable cause–as was ascertained by the Secretary of the Treasury during his visit of investigation to the leeward this year, but have also monopolized, all the portering business along the coast, such as the shipping and unshipping of goods, and the usual services performed by Kroomen on board of trading ships. Fishermen connected with other tribes are compelled to forego the benefits which they would derive from such employment, through fear of the treachery, jealousy and illwill of the Little Sess Fishermen, who are very numerous and live on nearly every part of our coast as adventurers. I indulge the hope that the Legislature will, during the present Session, devise some plan, by which the turbulence of this tribe may be restrained so that order and peace may again be restored along the coast.</p>

<p>On the 19th of April, the Government Schooner Quail arrived from

<pb n="Roll2-0087.jpg"/>

the leeward counties bringing with her the Commissioners appointed under the Act passed at your last Session, authorizing the appointment of commissioners to select a site in the interior for the seat of Government.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the dry season was far advanced, they were, nevertheless commissioned and sent on their mission. After an absence of some seventeen days, they returned to this city having in their tour selected two sites in the vicinity of Bees' Mountain in the rear of the Junk Country, either one of which will, they think, meet the object contemplated.</p>

<p>Intelligence was received on the 17th, of April of the return to the Gallinas, in another vessel, of the Captain of the Spanish slave schooner Bueneventura Cubana, which was seized in that river by the Quail June 1861, and which was subsequently wrested from her by H. B. M. S. Torch. The object of the return of the Spanish Captain to the Gallinas, was to procure the slaves purchased with the cargo brought out in the Bueneventura Cubana. The advice boat, steamer Seth <sic>Grosvernor</sic> was immediately dispatched to the Gallinas, with the Secretary of the Treasury in her, with instructions to arrest, seize and bring to this city for adjudication and trial, all vessels and persons that he might find there, engaged in the slave Trade. His visit resulted in an interview with Prince Manna, the native Chief of Gallinas, the Slaver to take off a single slave from the Gallinas. As the steamer passed out of the Gallinas river, a glimpse of the Spanish vessel was descried wide in the offing. I am happy to be able to inform the Legislature, that the two voyages of the spanish Captain to our coast for a cargo of slaves, were entirely frustrated through the <sic>vigilence</sic> of this Government, and that every exertion will be used to prevent the native chiefs living within our Jurisdiction from holding out inducements to the slave dealer to approach our coast.</p>

<p>The Educational interest has had and will continue to have special attention. The Common day schools authorized at the last Session to be increased and put in operation in each county, were established as early as the several School Committees could engage teachers and procure books. They number in the aggregate sixteen schools, to be increased by the number to be established in Grand Bassa County. Books are very much needed.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the long and almost unprecedented dry season this year, occasioning the loss of a large number of early crops of grain, and the resowing of others: succeeded suddenly by a heavy and incessant rainy season, causing great damage to the maturing plantations of various products, especially to those of cotton, scores of acres of which were destroyed–yet, the agricultural interest is of an encouraging character, admitting of a fair comparison with that of last year. The sugar cane crops increased on the St. Paul's, and the quantity augmented by that grown in the leeward Counties. It

<pb n="Roll2-0088.jpg"/>

affords me much pleasure to be able to say that the people of Liberia are paying more attention than ever to the cultivation of the soil, and to the rich products which so readily find a market in foreign countries.</p>

<p>The Government has, during the year imported six sugar mills, which have been judiciously distributed among the several Counties; and it is the intention to import others for the convenience of our farmers, so soon as it shall be practicable.</p>

<p>The actual revenue of the country is insufficient to meet the demands of government since so many public enterprises have been put on foot. The report of the Secretary of the Treasury will clearly demonstrate this. I invite the special attention of the Legislature to this subject; and I shall be happy to meet their wishes in any reasonable measures they may adopt for increasing the revenue of the country.</p>

<p>The receipts from all sources including recaptive African funds during the fiscal year ending 30 September 1862, were–$138-016-42</p>

<p>Total amount of <sic>disbursments</sic> for the same time was. $138.499-29</p>

<p>I will add in this connection that it is my firm purpose during the remaining year of my incumbency to employ every effort to liquidate all demands now against, and such as may be incurred up to the close of the fiscal year by government, in order that my successor may, on his induction, be relieved of unpleasant pecuniary embarrassments. To effect this, retrenchment will be indispensable; and as a consequence, several public enterprises must cease, until that object shall have been secured.</p>

<p>And I have to earnestly request, that you will cause your appropriation for the fiscal year to harmonize with this policy.</p>

<p>Under the appropriation made at your last session with a view to develop the iron resources in the vicinity of Careysburg, advances have been made from the Treasury, to Charles Deputie Esqr., of Careysburg, who, has succeeded, it is said, in demonstrating that the iron ore near that settlement is of superior quality. Samples of the iron smelted from the ore has been submitted to the government. No formal report, however, has as yet been received from him to enable the government to determine upon the propriety of making further advances for that object.</p>
    
<p>Specimens of ore found on the little Cape Mount river by Mr. J. G. J. Barbour and by him forwarded to the United States to be tested, were, on examination, said to be a rich quality of Coal. See Liberia Herald August 6th, 1862.</p>

<p>A revision of some of the Judiciary Acts is very necessary, in order to define more clearly the Jurisdiction of the Courts. The Attorney General will readily designate to you those conflicting laws, which, as long as they remain will keep up a conflict between the superior and inferior Courts.</p>

<p>Abraham Hanson Esqr. was received Sept. 2nd, 1862, and acknowledged as United States Commercial agent for Monrovia.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0089.jpg"/>

<p>By virtue of a resolution adopted by the Legislature of Liberia at their last session, granting the President of Liberia leave of absence from the Republic during the year 1862, or longer, should he deem it necessary for the restoration of his health, and vesting him with special authority, during his absence, to enter into any arrangements, and to transact any business he might deem promotive of the interest of Liberia, I embarked from this place on the 11th, of March, for Europe via Harper, and arrived in Liverpool on the 11th, of April.</p>

<p>Before leaving Liberia, I had determined that i would extend my visit to the U.S. within a few weeks after my arrival in England, provided my progress in the despatch of the more important public business in Europe, and letters I might receive in England from the U. States should justify it. The many difficulties, and at times sore humiliations we had long been subject to in the enforcement of our Commercial, Revenue and Navigation laws; and in our attempts to suppress the nefarious foreign <sic>trafic</sic> in human flesh and blood with the aborigines within our jurisdiction, rendered the definite and permanent adjustment with H. M. Government of our territorial claims, and boundaries, of paramount importance. Consequently, though I received several letters in Europe from the U.S., urging me to extend my visit to that country; and I felt as certain then as I do now, that I would have had a cordial reception by numerous friends and acquaintances there; and that becoming courtesy would have been accorded by the officials of that Republic, yet, I could not see that much good would have resulted from my visit in the present unhappy state of affairs there. I therefore felt unwilling to defer the adjustment of the more important business in England, in order to make a visit of doubtful utility to the United States, especially as my business there could be transacted equally as well by correspondence from England.</p>

<p>In less than a fortnight after my arrival in England, I presented in person to H. M. Minister of Foreign affairs, and respectfully pressed the same by argument, a memorandum of the several matters I wished to adjust and have a clear understanding on between the two governments before my departure from England.</p>

<p>The first subject was the full recognition of our territorial claims, and fixing the boundaries, especially of that part of our territory, lying conterminously with territory claimed by H. M. Government. I shall transmit to you on the 8th, inst, copies of the correspondence, with explanatory remarks on the action I had with H. M. Government on that subject during my absence, by which it will appear that H. M. Government have magnanimously acknowledged the just claims of the Government of Liberia to the territory comprehended between the San Pedro river on the S. E. to the river Shebar on the N. W. with the understanding however, that the N. W. boundary cannot be definitively described and laid down, until a survey of the river Jong, and ascertainment shall have been thereby made, whether its course and

<pb n="Roll2-0090.jpg"/>

extent interiorward are sufficient to give us a N. western boundary of some sixty miles interiorward, otherwise a line as you will see delineated on the map which accompanied the despatch of July 5th, from the Foreign office, is to be run due north from its head to complete the sixty miles.</p>

<p>A report of the survey, fixing this definitive N. Western boundary was expected from the governor of Sierra Leone in October; and I had hoped, and signified the same to H. M. Government, that it would have arrived timely to have had it accurately laid down by H. M. Government on an authentic map before my embarkation, so that I might be able to bear home with me in that form the evidence of a correct and definitive adjustment of our N. Western boundary, which would have rendered extinct, the last vestige of a possibility of future misunderstandings between the two governments growing out of questions of political jurisdiction in that direction. H. M. Minister of Foreign Affairs was absent on the Continent a few days previously to, and up to the day of my leaving London to embark at Liverpool, having been detained there as I learned by stress of weather. I have directed Consul General Ralston to bring the subject to His Lordship's notice as early as possible after his return to London, a report on which I am confidently expecting by the mail to arrive this month.</p>

<p>The second subject introduced in the memorandum was, that H. M. Government assume all responsibility toward the Spanish Government, not only for the destruction of the Spanish slaver Bueneventura Cubana in 1861 by H. M. S. Torch, but also of the original capture made by the Liberian Government Schooner Quail, since the action of the Commander of the Torch, prevented the prize from being brought to the proper port for formal adjudication.</p>

<p>Third, that such an apology be tendered for the conduct of the Commander of H.M.S. Torch, as H. M. Government might think justly due to the Government of Liberia: and that such prize money be tendered to the captors,–the officers and crew of the Quail,–as H. M. Government might regard justly due them.</p>

<p>The 4th, subject contained in the memorandum was, Notification to H. M. Government, that the Government of Liberia intended the passage of a law that would restrict the operations of all foreign vessels within our jurisdiction to the six ports of entry now, and others that may be hereafter constituted: and that a reasonable time would be allowed before the commencement of its enforcement. In introducing this latter subject, no doubt was intimated by me of our perfect right to make the restriction. The position was reasonably assumed of our perfect right to do so. But as H. M. subjects had for sometime previously to our declaration of independence, traded indiscriminately on the coast, which has continued under regulations ordained by the Government of Liberia since the declaration of independence in 1847, courtesy rendered it not amiss to acquaint H. M. Government of the contemplated restriction. I was particularly induced to adopt this

<pb n="Roll2-0091.jpg"/>

course in order to obviate in the future if possible, the sore humiliations inflicted on us at times by H. M. Cruisers when attempting to enforce our Navigation, Revenue and Commercial laws. These humiliations at any time and under any circumstances have been sorely grievous to us and highly detrimental to our interest; among other evils, causing us to lose prestige with the <sic>aborignes</sic> residing within our dominions, whom we are endeavoring to bring under the influence of law and order, and to thoroughly identify with us in a common body politic.</p>

<p>By reference to copies of correspondence and statements of interviews I had with H. M. Government during my absence, which I hope to be able to transmit to you on the 8th inst, you will perceive that the several matters embodied in the <sic>momorandum</sic> have to a considerable extent been met in a just and generous spirit by H. M. Government, so that the adjustment of them may be regarded upon the whole as having so far resulted satisfactorily. And it affords me great pleasure to be able to add, that H. M. Minister of Foreign Affairs was pleased to express in person every assurance of the best feelings of H. M. Government, as well as of himself individually, for the welfare and success of Liberia.</p>

<p>Having after the elapse of a few months in England, become convinced of the improbability of extending my visit to the United States, I addressed a despatch to that Government in July, proposing the negotiation of a treaty between the two governments. The subsequent correspondence and action on that subject, resulted in the conclusion of a treaty between the two governments, which was duly signed in London on the 21st, of October, by Hon. C. F. Adams, United States Minister to the Court of St. James, (specially authorized) and myself. As this treaty (and if required explanatory documents of it) will be transmitted in a day or two to the Senate for ratification. I need say no more at present on that subject, than that I regard the treaty as being very fair and satisfactory. And through the Government of the United States did not favor stipulating <hi rend="italics">by treaty</hi> on the subject of immigration to Liberia, nor respecting recaptured Africans, but <sic>prefered</sic> those subjects being left opened to future circumstances, and acts of Congress, and contracts that may in future be based upon such acts of Congress, yet I had every assurance given me of the good feelings and best wishes of the administration, and of their favorable impression toward Liberia in connection with those subjects. Recaptive Africans taken on this coast by American cruisers, will, as usual be brought to Liberia.</p>

<p>Respecting the destination of the vast majority of colored persons (African descent) in the United States, I feel no uneasiness whatever. I have not a particle of doubt that there will be a great and voluntary immigration of them to Liberia, and Liberia wishes, and will accept none other than those who will come voluntarily. Various circumstances rapidly converging to a point will ere long cause a

<pb n="Roll2-0092.jpg"/>

greater influx of them than perhaps, it will be considered prudent to admit within a given time; I feel no less certain now than I felt years ago, that our Anglo saxon friends in America have been, are, and will become increasingly dependent on Liberia, as affording the only satisfactory home as yet for those whom they have of late strangely charged with being the cause of the lamentable sanguinary contest now waging in that great country: at least as much so as Liberia is dependent on them for the encouragement of immigration hither.</p>

<p>The truth, that Africa for a long time at least, will prove the only place to which they can move to find a satisfactory home, will increasingly force itself upon both colored and white until it shall become irresistible. Liberia can gain nothing by impatience on this subject. The basis of our national and individual progress, respect and influence having been greatly expanded and deepened by the treaty recently negotiated with the United States Government, let our citizens nerve up and exert every power of body and mind, that they may with a becoming manly spirit render our country increasingly attractive by their industry and progress in the pursuits of civilized life, and we need entertain no fears that we shall not have sufficient voluntary immigration in the future.</p>

<p>Pursuant to the resolution of the Legislature passed at the last session, providing for the appointment of Commissioners for this Government to present to the colored people of the United States the advantages and claims of Liberia, I appointed as such at an early a day as was practicable, J. D. Johnson Esqr. and Professors Crummell and Blyden, who have informed me from time to time by letter that they were zealously prosecuting their mission in the United States.</p>

<p>Their absence as yet from home, and not having received their formal reports, I am disappointed in being able to communicate the substance of them to you at the opening of your Session. I have no doubt their reports will be supplied timely to enable me to transmit them to you before the close of this month.</p>

<p>I have specially to acknowledge the efficient services of J. D. Johnson Esqr. who was Commissioned early this year,–and before he entered upon the duties of a Commissioner to the colored people of the United States–to afford all necessary information respecting Liberia to the government of the United States preparatory to their recognition of the independence of this Republic; which services no doubt contributed much to the Establishment of Diplomatic Relations between the two countries.</p>

<p>After ascertaining the improbability of extending my visit to the United States, I Commissioned the Hon. J. J. Roberts in June, who purposed leaving England for American early in July, vesting him with full authority to amicably adjust all accounts and business matters between the American Colonization Society and this Government, especially those respecting recaptive Africans landed here within the

<pb n="Roll2-0093.jpg"/>

last 2½ years, so that our Commissioner might be able to present on his return, a correct and satisfactory statement of items, and of the balance due this government up to the date of adjustment.</p>

<p>I was very desirous that this should have been done to enable me to place the Secretary of the Treasury in possession of it in a completed form timely for his annual report.</p>

<p>The Secretary of the Treasury to whom I have transmitted the Commissioners report, will inform you that the object of the mission has not been secured. Nor is it likely to be soon unless the American Colonization Society in whom we have the greatest confidence, and for whom we entertain the highest respect, will at their ensuing annual meeting take such action in the premises, of which I have no doubt, as will relieve this government from having to apply in future on this subject to a source, that is–to say the least–peculiarly unpleasant to us.</p>

<p>The fourth quarter's payment to be made by the United States Government on account of Recaptive Africans is yet delayed in consequence of <sic>alledged</sic> omissions in the Certificates issued in favor of this government by the United States Agent for Liberated Africans. I am informed by the Secretary of State that the necessary measures have been adopted months ago to supply the main omission, and I have no doubt that the matter will be satisfactorily settled in a short time.</p>

<p>Before and after leaving home this year, I indulged the hope that the civil war in the United States would have subsided ere this, which would have afforded me an opportunity–though a subordinate consideration–of procuring very cheaply while abroad all the arms and munitions of war we would likely require for many years. but as this has not been the case, and there is at present no very pressing need of them, I have deferred the procuring of them to a more favorable time.</p>

<p>I have however instructed our Agent in the United States to purchase conditionally (as you will perceive by the copies of the letter of instructions, and description of the vessel, which I will transmit in a day or two for your approval–a small Steamer not exceeding two hundred tons, and with heavier and more complete armament than that of the Quail. I have authorized him in case he shall procure her to make the necessary arrangements and expenditures for sending her out without delay, to arrive if possible before the close of the April ensuing, for all which I have to ask an adequate appropriation.</p>

<p>While in England I contracted for, at the suggestion of the Secretary of the Treasury, two light house lamps and fixtures, for the light house of this place and of Harper.</p>

<p>The lamps are to be out in all of this month, and are said to possess every important modern improvement. The Secretary of Treasury will transmit to you an estimate of their cost and charges for which I have to ask an adequate appropriation.</p>

<p>Very soon after my arrival in England, and subsequently thereto, I had conferences and correspondence with a gentleman of high character and respectability in London, Mr. Henry Pinkus, who was desirous of organizing an institution to be styled the London and Liberian

<pb n="Roll2-0094.jpg"/>

Banking and commercial Institution. The object contemplated by this institution you will find to a great extent set forth in the copies of correspondence I had with, and documents from him, which I will in a few days transmit to you. I recommend that no conclusive nor even definite action be taken on the application for a charter until the arrival of the Hon. J. J. Roberts, to whom as the contemplated chief manager of the interests of the institution in Liberia, I requested Mr. Pinkus, (owing to the pressure of duties upon me at the time) to make all further communication on the subject, so that he might be able to afford the Legislature all necessary information on the subject, that may not be contained in the correspondence and documents aforesaid; and which I shall transmit simply that you may be able to give the subject as much thought as possible before consummating action thereon. You will find my own views (which have since undergone, no change) embodied to some extent in my correspondence with him; And whenever I have hesitated to give a definite expression of approval to any special proposal, it was simply as you will perceive, because I was unwilling to commit myself on any important point upon which, for want of more time for reflection, my mind was not clear.</p>

<p>Upon the whole, I think very highly of the contemplated institution, and believe that it can be organized and conducted under a charter, in a manner that will prove safe and highly beneficial to Liberia, and satisfactorily remunerative to the investors.</p>

<p>Considering the ready employment that such a company will proffer to successive companies of immigrants whose arrival in the future, may reasonably be expected in great numbers, the facility and accommodation it will afford to the mercantile and agricultural interests of the country. In a word, the great impetus it will give to every branch of industry and to the rapid development of the resources of the country which can not be done effectively without skill and capital; I cannot regard such an institution, guardedly, yet liberally chartered, otherwise than the great desideratum; and I cannot hesitate to believe, that you will, whenever you shall take action on the subject, meet the wishes of the directors in a just, liberal and enlightened spirit. I shall no doubt have occasion to communicate with you more definitely on this subject.</p>

<p>Upon inquiry, I ascertained that I could have made arrangements in England to have a pier or break water built out ⅛ or ⅙ of a mile in Montserrado roads, on terms not very pressing. But I was unwilling to and consequently did not negotiate such an arrangement, involving so large an expenditure in the absence of Legislative opinion on the subject. I am in possession of plans and estimates which if desired I will lay before the Legislature for their consideration.</p>

<p>Liberia's contribution this year to the International Exhibition at London, though humble, yet did not fail in interest.</p>

<p>The Enlightened minds and good sense of Her Majesty's Commissioners as well as of the Jurors and the British public, did not expect a display of exquisite genius in the Liberian Court. They expected to

<pb n="Roll2-0095.jpg"/>

see raw materials. Samples of commodities that could be made highly available to the two countries by commercial interchange. I am happy to be able to say from general testimony, that they were not disappointed in their expectations, of which I am of opinion you will have no doubt, when the report of our Commissioners shall have been received.</p>

<p>I feel unwilling to close this communication to you, without expressing my gratitude to a gracious Providence for the preservation of my health; and for granting me favor while abroad, and a safe return to my country.</p>

<p>The authorities of the several European countries which I had the honor and pleasure of visiting, have placed Liberia under many courteous, respectful and friendly obligations, by reason of the attentions and high considerations accorded to the Representative of this Republic during his visits, and for the very unfeigned interest they have manifested for the general success and prosperity of Liberia.</p>

<p>With several of those powers treaties have been negotiated this year which will be presented to the Senate this session for ratification, and others are being negotiated which may arrive timely to secure ratification also at this session. You will permit me to add, that the respectful attention of the civilized powers of the earth, is now attracted towards Liberia with more scrutiny and friendly solicitude than ever before; and that our destiny is now under God to a great extent in our own hands; and that I feel sure, that the wisdom, moderation and self respect, not only of the several departments of this government, but of the loyal citizens of this Republic, will fully demonstrate in future, that the government and people of Liberia were not unworthy of the respect, confidence and good will of those great civilized christian nations.</p>

<p>It only remains for me to assure the Legislature, that I will cordially co-operate with them during their session, in every honorable measure that shall tend to demonstrate and secure this cherished object.</p>

<p>Stephen A. Benson.</p>

<p>Government House.<lb/>
Monrovia Decr. 5, 1862.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0096.jpg"/>

<p>Enclosure with Despatch No 7</p>

<p>Annual Message of President of Liberia to the Legislature</p>

<p>No 1<lb/>
Dec 31, 1862</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0097.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<note>Copy of the Original Prospectus as published in England.</note>

<head type="main">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Incorporated under the Joint Stock Companies' Act of 1856 and 1857, whereby the liability of the Shareholders is limited to the amount of their Subscriptions.</p>

<p>CAPITAL £250,000, in 25,000 SHARES of £10 Each.</p>

<p>FIRST ISSUE 12,500 SHARES.</p>

<p>£1 to be paid on application, and £1 10s. on allotment. The holders of such first Shares to have the preference, pro rata, in all further issues. No call to exceed £2 10s. per Share, nor to be made except at an interval of at least three months from any previous Call.</p>

<p>If no allotment be made, the Deposit will be returned in full.</p>

<list>
<head>Directors.</head>
<item>Thomas Bazley, Esq., M.P., Manchester.</item>
<item>Thomas Bradshaw, Esq., Temple.</item>
<item>George Braginton, Esq., Torrington, Devon.</item>
<item>Thomas Briggs, Esq., Prestwich Park, Manchester.</item>
<item>Henry Brownrigg, Esq., 33, Lime Street, E.C.</item>
<item>Thomas Clegg, Esq., Manchester.</item>
<item>Frederic Doulton, Esq., M.P., Lambeth.</item>
<item>Ambrose Emerson, Esq. (Messrs. Newby, Carson &amp; Co., Gresham House, E.C.)</item>
<item>Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, F.R.G.S., J.P., Cardiff.</item>
<item>Gerard Ralston, Esq., Consul-General for Liberia, 21, Tokenhouse Yard, E.C.</item>
<item>(with power to add.)</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Bankers.</head>
<item>The London and Westminster Bank, Lothbury, E.C.</item>
<item>Solicitors. Messrs. Cotterill &amp; Sons, 32, Throgmorton Street.</item>
<item>Brokers. Messrs. Huggins &amp; Rowsell, 1, Threadneedle Street.</item>
<item>General Manager. J. B. Langley, Esq.</item>
<item>Secretary. F. W. Stone, Esq.</item>
<item>Shipping and Insurance Agent. Charles Kitto, Esq.</item>
<item>Temporary Offices. 41, Gresham House, E.C.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Prospectus.</head>

<p>The object of the Company is–To establish Trading Stations, Factories, and Depots on the Coast of Western Africa, and by means of organized Agencies, to bring down and collect for shipment at such stations, the valuable products of the Interior; to import Goods, and introduce Machinery for cleaning and pressing Cotton, and for other purposes; and generally to enter into Commercial relations with the Native Traders, by means of barter traffic or otherwise; and thereby to open up, in exchange for British manufactures, a practically illimitable market for Cotton and other products–and to secure their transmission to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>The capabilities of Africa to meet the commercial requirements of Europe are evidenced in the variety of its productions, and the increasing extent of its trading operations; and it has long been a matter of surprise, that the encouragement of Native industry should have been left to associations of a philanthropic character, or to a few Merchants intent upon the enormous profit which exclusive dealings with the Natives incontestably afford.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0098.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Cotton.</head>

<p>The cultivation of the Cotton Plant, and the employment of African labour on its native soil, have already been sufficiently tested. There is abundance of labour seeking employment, a fertile soil well adapted for its growth, and a population actively alive to what will benefit themselves. <hi rend="italics">No expensive or uncertain experiments are required to test the ability or the will of the Natives to supply this country with cheap and good cotton.</hi> The testimony of the officers of the Niger expedition concurs with, and confirms, the evidence of Dr. Livingstone, and other African travellers, that indigenous Cotton is growing in abundance throughout vast districts, covering many thousands of miles of territory, and only waits to be gathered. Some Tribes of the Natives are largely engaged in manufacturing Cotton into clothing for their own use. It is calculated that more than 200,000 pieces of these cloths are annually exported from Africa into the Brazils. In fact, only buyers on the spot are wanted to take from the Natives what they have to offer, giving in exchange manufactured goods suitable to their requirements.</p>

<p>In a letter from Dr. Balfour Bakie, in command of the Niger Expedition, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, which Lord Russell caused to be inserted in the <hi rend="italics">London Gazette</hi> of August 29th, 1862, he emphatically urges his Lordship "to call attention, in England, to the peculiar eligibility of this portion of Central Africa (Bida Nusse), as a Cotton field." Again, speaking of Sudan, and the Yoruba country, he proceeds to say–Here Cotton is already in abundance, and cultivated by a people able and willing to work, and accustomed to its habits and rearing; nothing is required but increased demand, means of purchase, cleaning and shipment. The rest would speedily follow."</p>

<p>Another practical authority–Mr. Clegg, of Manchester, who has an establishment at Abeokuta, states–"for very many years my instructions have been to cease buying Cotton, when more than a halfpenny per pound in the Seed, and my young Africans have again and again written to say, that at that price for more was brought to them than they could buy."</p>

<p>Mr. I. Lyons McLeod, Hon. Secretary to the African Aid Society, in a Letter to the <hi rend="italics">Times</hi>, March 28th, 1861, writes–"It is a well-attested fact, that from Western Africa (shipping port Lagos), Cotton in abundance maybe purchased at 2d. per lb., and allowing for exorbitant overcharge for cleaning freight, &amp;c., it may be sold from the same locality in Liverpool at 4½d. per lb. This Cotton is equal in quality to New Orleans at 6½d. per lb., proving beyond doubt, that from Western Africa, which is nearer to our shores than the Cotton districts of America, we may obtain the same amount of Cotton for £20,000,000, for which we are paying the Slaveholders of the United States £30,000,000. In Western Africa–the Yoruba Country, and along the valley of the Niger," (the localities above referred to by Dr. Balfour Bakie)–"the Natives are ready to supply any amount of Cotton for Manchester and Glasgow Manufacturers."</p>

<p>These testimonies appear to demand the most serious attention and consideration at the present crisis.</p>

<p>The supply of Cotton from the Southern States (which till a recent date formed 80 per cent. of our consumption), cannot be fully renewed for several years; part of the crop of 1861 has been burned, and the remainder may never reach us. In 1862, it is believed, that only about one-fourth of the usual crop has been sown, and it is not likely that a larger area can be placed under Cotton Culture in 1863; so that, if the Civil War were to be ended by any means to-morrow, the full supply of American Cotton could not be resumed till September, 1864. Till that date, the price of middling and ordinary Orleans are not likely to fall below One Shilling per pound.</p>

<p>There is abundant evidence to show that India cannot for many years supply the quantity or quality required. The Egyptian supply is the only one which might be supposed likely to compete with that imported from West Africa; but the Egyptian Cotton imported into England has never hitherto reached 200,000 bales in any one year, and if doubled (which it cannot be for two or three years), it will not suffice to make up the deficiency created by the reduced supplies of ordinary Americans. Besides, the average price of <sic>Egytian</sic> Cotton has been 8d. per pound for several years. African Cotton, equal to middling Orleans, can be delivered in Liverpool, at a cost to the Importer of Fourpence Halfpenny per pound. In the seed, in Africa, it may be procured in unlimited quantities at about one Halfpenny per pound; cleaned Cotton about Threepence. Payments being made in barter, the profits on the Goods reduce the cost price of the Cotton considerably.</p>

<p>It is not the intention of the "West Africa Company" to become <hi rend="italics">Cultivators of Cotton</hi>; the Company will simply be <hi rend="italics">Purchasers of Cotton</hi>, which will be brought down to their Stations by the Native Traders, and thence Shipped to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>Several well-known Firms, having used African Cotton in their Manufactories, are able to report favourably of its quality working.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0099.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">General Trade.</head>

<p>The Company will not, however, depend on Cotton alone for realising the good dividend on the capital employed. The interchange of commodities will be widened to the largest possible extent, so as to include every other product of Africa, which will pay an enhanced value in this country. These products, which consist chiefly of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, Gold Dust, Ivory, Hides, Indigo, Copper, Ground Nuts, Pepper, Arrowroot, Gums, Dye Woods, Ostrich Feathers, Timber for Shipbuilding, and other articles of commerce, equally suitable to the requirements of our markets, will also be made the media of trade, so as to suit the industry and keen trading instincts of the various classes of Native producers. The fact that the production of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, and other valuable articles, is in excess of the local demand, can be shown by the latest and most indubitable authorities. The Rev. Samuel Crowther, writing to the Church Missionary Society lately, states, "at the Delta of the Niger alone, millions' worth, in red Oil and black Oil from the kernels of the Palm nut, rot away annually for want of inducement to collect them."* From an official document received through the Board of Trade, it appears that in 1856 upwards of 220,000 tons of these kernels, from which Oil of the value of £3,789,000 might have been extracted, were actually thrown away on the coast. The amount thus lost represents in actual value a sum of upwards of a Million Sterling more than all the tallow exported from Russia in that year; and when it is considered that the tallow was paid for in cash, and that the bulk of the trade with Africa may be carried on by barter of the manufactures of Manchester, Glasgow, Birmingham, the Potteries, and Sheffield, it is impossible to overrate the benefits which will accrue to this country by developing the resources of Western Africa.</p>

<p>As there is no currency in the Country, trade is conducted by means of barter, so that a market for English productions will be opened at every point from which the Company draws its supplies of raw materials; a profit both ways will thus be obtained by the Company, viz: Upon the goods sold in Africa, and <hi rend="italics">vice versá</hi>, upon the Cotton, Palm Oil, &amp;c., imported and sold in the English markets.</p>

<p>The "West Africa Company," will commence operations under peculiarly favorable circumstances, owing to the fact that their Agencies on the West Coast of Africa are already organized; and competent acclimatised persons, native merchants and others, at Abeokuta, Elmina, Lagos, Cape Palmas, and in the Niger river, are ready to act in behalf of the Company the moment it commences business.</p>

<p>From the foregoing statements, taken together with the fact that this Company will possess unusual facilities for successful mercantile operations, owing to its large Capital and connexions, it is confidently expected that its transactions will produce very handsome dividends. Persons having a knowledge of the Africa trade will readily <sic>undrestand</sic>that to name what would be a probable rate of interest on the Capital worked, would, to the uninitiated, bear the stamp of exaggeration. The Directors, however, feel assured that the Company will eventually assume such dimensions as to invest it with a most important character; and that the development of the resources of Africa will do more than anything else to hasten the extinction of the Foreign Slave Trade, an event not more desirable to philanthropy than to commerce.</p>

<p>* See African Aid Society's Report for 1862, page 10, and generally in confirmation of the statements herein, the Annual Reports of the Cotton Supply Association; "The Cotton Plant and Countries adapted to its Culture," pages 5-15, &amp;c.; D. J. May, Esq., R. N., (Niger Expedition), and the Reports of Mr. Consul Burton; Mr. Davis, Surgeon to the Niger Expedition; ratified as they are by Mr. Consul Campbell; the Rev. Mr. Townsend, of Abeokuta; Dr. R. Ross, Esq.; and by Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, in his recent work "European Settlements on the West Coast of Africa."</p>

<p>Application for Shares may be made in the accompanying form to the Brokers, Messrs. Huggins &amp; Roswell, 1, Threadneedle Street, London, E.C., or to the Secretary, at the Temporary Offices of the Company, 41, Gresham House, E.C.</p>

<p>[For Special Notice addressed to the Residents on the West Coast of Africa, see over.]</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0100.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Capital £250,000, in 25,000 Shares of £10 each.<lb/>
First Issue 12,500 Shares.</p>

<p>Prospectus.</p>

<p>Enclosure with Despatch No 7</p>

<p><unclear>Properties</unclear> of West African Company &amp;c &amp;c</p>

<p>No 2<lb/>
Dec 31, 1862</p>

<p>S. Straker &amp; Sons, Printers, 20, Bishopsgate Within &amp; 25, Leadenhall Street.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<p>Coast Allotment.]</p>

<p>SPECIAL NOTICE</p>

<p>To the Merchants, Capitalists, and others on the<lb/>
West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>The Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," established in England by Act of Parliament limiting the liability of each Shareholder to the amount of his Subscriptions, have <hi rend="italics">resolved to reserve 2,500 Shares for the Capitalists on the West Coast.</hi> Mr. William Grant, of Kissy Road, Sierra Leone, and Captain Davis, of Lagos, are acquainted with the Directors; and copies of the Articles of Association, under which the Company is incorporated by law, are in the hands of the former.</p>

<p>Form of Application for Shares.</p>

<p>To the Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," (in England).</p>

<p>Gentlemen,–Having remitted by Draft on &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; the Sum of &#160; &#160; &#160; sterling, I request you to allot me &#160; &#160; &#160; Shares in the Company; and I agree to accept the same or any less number that may be allotted to use me, and to comply with all the rules and regulations of the Company.</p>

<p>Name</p>

<p>Address</p>

<p>Occupation</p>

<p>Date</p>

<p>[The applicant should enclose his application with the Draft addressed to "J. B. Langley, Esq., General Manager West Africa Company, 41, Gresham House, London, England," or in lieu thereof he should forward instructions to his Agent in England <unclear>to</unclear> make application on his behalf, and to pay the deposit (£1 per Share on application, and £1 10s. on allotment). It will be <unclear>necessary</unclear> in case of remittances direct from the Coast that the whole of the deposit, £2 10s. per Share, should be seat at once.]</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>