<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.government.0008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Memorial Concerning Conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo (1904)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.government.0008</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Treaty of Peace, Friendship and Commerce between Madagascar and the United States, signed at Antananarivo, 13 May 1881</title>
<title level="m">The Consolidated Treaty Series</title>
<author>Parry, Clive</author>
<pubPlace>Dobbs Ferry, N.Y.</pubPlace>
<publisher>Oceana Publications, 1969</publisher>
<date when="1881-05-13">May 13, 1881</date>
<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">231-244</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Government Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-12" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p231"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">Treaty of Peace, Friendship and Commerce 
between Madagascar and the United States, 
signed at Antananarivo, 13 May 1881</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The English text of this Convention, which became obsolete on the 
extension of French sovereignty to Madagascar (1896), is reproduced 
from Malloy, <hi rend="italics">Treaties between the United States and other Powers,</hi> p. 1061, being printed also in <hi>United States Statutes at Large</hi>, vol. 22, p. 952, <hi rend="italics">British and Foreign State Papers</hi>, vol. LXXII, p. 566, and <hi rend="italics">Archives Diplomatiques,</hi> 1884, vol. X, p. 129, and by Bevans, <hi rend="italics">Treaties and Other International Agreements of the United States,</hi> vol. IX, p. 746, and Martens, <hi rend="italics">Nouveau Recueil Général des Traités</hi> (2nd Series), vol. XI, p. 732.</p> 

</div2>

<pb n="p232"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="main">English Text</head>

<p>Concluded May 13, 1881; ratification advised by the Senate February 27, 1883; ratified by the President March 10, 1883; ratifications exchanged March 12, 1883; proclaimed March 13, 1883.</p>

<p>Articles.</p>

<p>I. Friendship.<lb/> 
II. Rights of domicile, etc.<lb/> 
III. Personal and property rights.<lb/> 
IV. Commerce, etc.<lb/>
V. Consuls.<lb/> 
VI. Civil rights.<lb/> 
VII. Sanitary regulations, passports, etc.<lb/> 
VIII. Shipwrecks, etc.<lb/> 
IX. American goods shipped to.<lb/> 
X. Development of industries.<lb/> 
XI. Taxes.<lb/> 
XII. Ratification.</p>

<p>Whereas a treaty of friendship and commerce between the Government 
of Madagascar and the Government of the United States of 
America was concluded on the fourteenth of February, 1867, at 
Antananarivo, the capital of Madagascar, under which the most 
friendly relations between the two have existed up to the present 
time; and whereas Her Majesty Ranavalomanjaka, Queen of Madagascar, 
and his Excellency James A. Garfield, President of the

<fw type="note">This treaty became obsolete when the sovereignty of France was extended over Madagascar, and was replaced by "the whole of the conventions concluded between France and the United States."—Note of July 22, 1896, from the French ambassador to the Secretary of State.</fw>

<pb n="p233"/>

United States of America, are both desirous, for the good and welfare 
of their respective countries, to maintain the present friendly 
relations, and to expand the commerce between the two countries; 
to prevent as far as possible complications and disputes between their 
respective subjects and citizens, and to provide more definitely the 
manner of executing the obligations of the treaty and the adjustments 
of disputes that may arise in the future, the following articles 
of revision and addition to the treaty of the fourteenth of February, 
1867, have been mutually agreed to and signed by Ravoninahitriniarivo  
15th Honor, Officer of the Palace, Chief Secretary of State for 
Foreign Affairs, on the part of the Government of Madagascar; and 
W. W. Robinson, United States Consul for Madagascar, on the part 
of the Government of the United States of America, on the thirteenth 
day of May (seventeenth of Alakaosy) eighteen hundred and eighty-one.</p> 

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article I.</head>

<p>The high contracting parties solemnly declare that there shall continue 
to be a firm, inviolate peace, and a true and sincere friendship 
existing between them and their respective heirs and successors forever 
without war.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">
 
<head>Article II. </head>

<p>1. The dominions of each contracting party as well as the right of 
domicile of their inhabitants are sacred, and no forcible possession 
of territory shall ever take place in either of them by the other 
party, nor any domiciliary visits nor forcible entries be made to, or 
espionage of, the houses of either party against the will of the occupants, 
except as hereinafter provided in Article VI, sects. 4 and 23.</p>

<p>2. The right of sovereignty shall in all cases be respected in the dominions of one government by the subjects or citizens of the other.</p> 

<p>3. Citizens and protegés of the United States of America will 
respect the government of Ranavalomanjaka, and that of her heirs 
and successors, and will not interfere with the institutions of the 
country, nor meddle with affairs of Her Majesty's Government, 
unless employed by Her Majesty.</p> 

<p>4. The dominions of Her Majesty the Queen of Madagascar shall 
be understood to mean the whole extent of Madagascar; and United 
States vessels and citizens shall not aid Her Majesty's subjects in 
rebellion, nor sell munitions of war to them, nor bring them help 
in warfare or teach the art of war to them; and the some shall apply 
to rebels against the heirs and successors of Her Majesty within the 
dominions of Madagascar.</p> 

<p>5. Citizens and protegés of thoe United States of America, while in Madagascar, shall enjoy the privilege of free and unmolested exercise 
or their respective Christian religious opinions and customs; new 
places of worship, however, shall not be built by them without the 
permission of the Government of Madagascar.</p>  

<p>6. Citizens and protegés of the United States of America while in 
Madagascar shall enjoy full and complete protection and security 
for themselves and their property equally with the subjects of Madagascar.</p> 

</div2>

<pb n="p234"/>

<div2 type="section">
 
<head>Article III.</head>
 
<p>1. According to the Ia,ws of Madagascar from all time, Malngasy lands cannot be sold to foreigners, and, t.herefore-1citizens and pro.teges of the Unfted States of America are pronibited from.pur.chasing lu.nds in Mn.dngnscar; but still U1e7shall be permitted to lease or rent lands, houses, or storehouses for a term of :months or years, mutually agreed upon between the owners und United Sta.tea citizens, not exceeding twenl-y-.tive years for one term; but the lesseo-1 or owner of the loose, at the oxpil'lltion of a term, may, if he should wish to do so, and cim agree with the lessor (proprielor of the land), renew the lease by periods not exceeding twenty-five years for '"1Y one term; and the conditions agreed upon by the parties for such renewals aro to be inserLed in the lease.</p> 

However, every rc~nowu.l must fie acknowledged at the time of mak.ing it before the proper authorities, as hereinafter provided in sec. 9 of this article for executing lenses fo1· lands and ho,1ses; and the so.me fee may be exacted. 
2. United Stat.es c'itizens a.ud proteges shall be permitted to build houses and mn.gu,zines, of any m11tennl desirnd, on land lensed by them, nccording to the agreement mnde with the owner; and when the lease conta.ms o. condition pe1mitting the lessee to remo-ve the buildings and fixtures so constructed by him, the same shall be J1eritove?-within three months after the final expiration of the leasei otherwise they shall become the property of the owner of the land. 
8. This privilege of leasing lnnds n.ud building thereon by United States citizens o.nd pxoteges shnll not be construed as o, 1'.ightto build fortifications of whatever nntur~1 nor to mine on t.b:o lnnds; and should anr-m.iilerals be accidentauy fotmd on such lands, they are to be le-ft to the di~osition of Her Majesty's Government, and no 11gree.ment will be valid made between piu-ties to avoid this clause relat.ive to minerals. 
4. 
United State.<i citizens and proteges who wish to lease tracts of unapptop1iated lands in Madagascar may lease of the Mnlo.gasyGovernment, under the same ru le.s as rrov1ded above in this article, secs. 1-31 for leasing lMds of Her Mo.Jesty's subjects. 

5. 
1Jruted States citizens nnd proteges shall be allowed to hire laborers, not soldiers, nnd, if slaves, not without the permission of their masters. And if such hired laborers should desire to leave, they shnJl be at liberty to do so, and be paid up to the time of leaving on giv.ing one month's previous notice. 

6. 
This notice, howovet·, shall not be required from the Govern.ment of Madagn.qcar, when Her Majesty the Queen shall have imme.diate and unexpected need of the services of such laborers; bnt the offtcers of the Government in taking such laborei·s for govel'l)mentservice will avoid taking tlie skilled laborers-those who have beco111e hnbitunted to the special avocations in which they nre employed.and the pel'manently employed servants, wben the circumstances will admit. And the Queen calling snch laborers for soldiers or other pressing go-vernment service, sha 11 be considered as the circumstances under which they mny be take.o without U1enotice, and paid up to the time of leaving. 


2 3S 
The above restriction is intended to prevent the local n.uthorities from tnking such permanent laborers from their emploJers, but not to interfere with the right of Her Mnjesty the Queen of Mad.ago.scar to call them to government service when needed. 
7. 
Mail carriers, 11.ndbearers of dispatches, nnd bearers of frei~ht, as well as the servants and bearers of travelers employed by Uruted Stntes citizens and proteges, and provided with passports from the Malagasy Government, will not be to.ken away while en route, but must be permit,ted to finish their journeys. Novert11eless1 each per.sons if trans~rMSing the law, will not be oxcmpt from a.rrest even while on the Journey. 

8. 
$loves shall be allowed to cngnge themselves with United Stntcs citizens• and proteges for short. periods, where their masters are fn.r nwn,y,01· where it, is not known whether they are slavos or not, but ii they nro demanded by their masters they shnll be allowed to lenve, and be po.id up to the time of leaving, without giving the one month's previous notice. 

9. 
Contmcts for renting or leasing la11ds or houses, or hiring lnbor.ers1 shall bo executed by leases for lands and contracts for lo.bar in writing which sho.11 be executed before the United St.ate::i consular officer and the governor 0£ the district where such consular officer resides, or inst&id of Sllid governor such officer as he may del~nte for such duty, who, when satisfied that tho J?ru:t.ieshave the right to make the contract, shall approve it in wn.ting signed. by them, and sen.led with their official government s01tls. 

10. 
And for such se1·vice a fee not cxcooding two dollllrs ($2) mn.ybe exacted for each officio.) seal. But when the period contracted for, for labor does not ei.ceed six months, procw·ing this official approval shall be optional with the parties. 

11. 
And the Unitod St1LtesconsulM· omcor, 11s well as the governorof tho district where such oJJicer resides, or a,ny other local officer that may be designated by the governor for that purpose, shall approvethe same without delay, unless it be in the case of somo unavoidable p1·evonting circumstances, or on a day when official business is stayed by the Queen of Mo.dago.scai·. 

12. 
On fonds so leased by Amel'ican citizens and rroteges, the American Jer.5ee shall pay to Hor Majesty an o.nnua tax of two cent.s per English square a.ere upon londs for cultivatio!lt and on town Innds Ill o.rumal tax of one-fourth cent per English square 


Y°ff This tax shnll not be considered as payment in who1e or in part of ot.hor t.axes which may be levied on such Unit.ed States cit.i.zens nn~ proLeg6s, or the citizens nnd subjects of other nations resid.ing in Mndngascur and Malagasy subject.'!, not of ru1y part of the export duty upon the productions of such lands, but as a specialland tax. 
14. This tax shall be paid once ea.ch year in the month which shall ho fixed b:v tbe government for its pnyment; nnd the officer who shall be d0S1gnated to receive such, shall upon·receJ_>tionof each tax give a receipt therefor, over his signatu1·e and official seal, men.tionmg the dny, month and year on wh.ich it was received, and de.scribing the land upon which the tax is paid, nnd for what year, lt8 a proof of payment. 
236 CONSOLIDATED TREATY SERIES 
15. 
Such leases m1ty be tr11nsferred; in wllich cnses notice must be given to the government authority of Madaguscar.

16. 
Citizens o.nd proteg6s of the United tntes of America who come to Madaga n1· must pr ·ent a pa 1p rt from th i.r ~overnment, or from some consul, certifying their no.tiona.lii-y; otherwise they are linble to be prohibited from residing in Maclr.gns ar. 

17. 
But 11,ftor producing such passport, they shaU be permit.Led to follow any occupation tliey wish ; to print books or newspfl.peni o·f a moml chnrncter, 01· any books or/enocl:icnls on lilemry, commer.cial or scientific subjects provide they 1u·e not of an unlawful chnrn.cter; but sbnll not be permitted to pll.blish seditious cr1Lioi ms upon Her Matesty's Gove,:nment. 

18. 
United States citizens and proteo-~s shn.11 be permitted to pnss wif·li or without mercho.ndise, with their ben.rers, buggnge, earners, nod servnnt.'l, through all parts of Madagascar which are under the control of a governor duly appointed by Her Majesty the Qu en of Ma lugascar, with the exc ption of .A.mbohmiu.nga,Ambohmian.o.mbola, and .A.mptmlfu.ru.vato,which places foreigne11s are not po.r.mitted to entet·; and, in fact, be entitled to oJl privileges o:f com.mere or 01J1er busine.,;;.~, callin • or profession granted to the most fa.vored nation, so long ns they do not infringe I.he lttws o:f faua.gascar. 


9. The subjects of Her Majesty the Queen of Mndagascar shall enjoy the same privileges in the United States of Am ricu.. 
ARTICLE IV. 
1. 
Commerce between th people of the United States of .A.mericn, nnd Mada~scar shall be perfectly .:free, with all (,he pri vil~es under which the most iavored nations ar now, or may hereafter be t,rading. 

2. 
Citizens of the Unjted Stntes of America shall, however, pay a duty not exceeding ten per cent. on both export.'> a.nd imports in Maaagascn,r, to b r gulo.ted by a tariff to be mutually ttgreed upon. 


8. No other duties, sncli as tonnage,filotage, quarunf.u1e, or lighh.honse dues shall be imposed in ports o either country on the vessels 
o:fthe otherf to which national vessels, or vessels of the most favored nations, sha 1 not 0(1ually be liable. 
4. 
Until Her ;M:aJesty the Qu en shall decide to collect all duties in monoyt the import duty on America11 goods may be pnid in money or in kindl. on each kind of goods, at the option of the owner or con.sign e, anct according to n. tariff th11t shall be agreed upon, not ex.c ecling ten pet· cent. 

5. 
Tl,is tnrlff of customs dues shall be drnwn up by the Unite,d States consnl and an officer delegated by Hor Mnjesty's Government for the purpose, within three months alter the e ·change of the rati.fication of this treaty, o.nd shu.11 be submitted to the two govern.ments for o.pprovul; and the snme shall be published within on yeilr :from the date of the exchnnge o:f the ratifi.cation of this treaty. And this tariff may be revised in the same way, in whole or upon nny article or a1-ticles, at nny time, upon the application o:f ith r government, should it be found rated too high or t,oo low, in whole or upon any one article or articles of merchn.ndise. 


2 37 
6. 
In case any article of import or export should b inadvertently omitted :from such tal'iff, the duty levi ad on such article shaU be too per cent. ad valorem until the proper tari.fl' on the same shall l:k. agreed upon. 

7. 
United Stutes citizens and proteges nre not allowed to import murutions of war into Madagascar, except on orders from Her Mnjesty the Queen of Mndngascar. 

8. 
Li regard to nlcoholic liquors, the Malagasy Government may 1· gulnte the importation according to its pleu.sure; or proluhit the importation altogetherj or limit tlJe importation as required; mny levy ns high a duty ns it may see fit, or ma! e it n misdemeanor to sell or give such liquors to ce1-tain clilsses of its subjects. 

9. 
And should it b found at any time that any other articles of o.n inj tITious nature, tending to the inJ ury 0£ the health 01· momls 0£ Her Ma,j ty's subje ts, are being imported, Her Majesty's Government sht~ll have the right to control, restrict or prohibit the importatiou in like mallller, after giving duo notice to the United States Govern.ment. 

10. 
Prohibited from export by the laws of Madagasc1n are timber and cows. Timber, however, may be exported by Her Majesty the Queen of MadngRScar, or by her orrler. 

11. 
Ports of Madagascar_,, where there is no military station under the control of 11.governor auly nppointed by Her Ma1osty the Queen of Mn,dagasear, must not be entered by United States vesaels for pur.poses of trade; should thoy do so, they will be treated as smugglers. 

12. 
And Her Majesty's Govemment will not be responsible for dammage by robbery or, or other malfensance to United States citi.zens or proteg6s in districts where there 11.r no &"overnor~nor other offir.ers or soldiers dnly appointed by H r MaJesty!s Government,; should such Uruted tat s citizens go into such districts without special permits. 


18. Goods which have been duly entered o.nd duties po.id thereon at a r golos port of entry, may b carried to other ports in United States coitsting vessels ancl landed without further paym nt, on pres.eutation of invoices of the same, duly certified by the chief collector 0£ customs. o.t the port 0£ entry, showing tbn.t the duties have been paid. 
14. 
Vessels entering Malagasy ports which are not ports of entry for the purpose of trnde, will be sei:r,ed; the masters o.nd crews will be b.'ent d as smuggl~s, o.nd the vessel and cargo will be co:nnscnted. 

15. 
It is !1Jrther agreed be ween the high contrncti11g parties that the offering of a forged pnssport ·or one sm-rept,i.tiously obtained, fo1· enLt1' of goods' nt n.nyof Her Mn.j ty's ports, or being in any manm•r lmowin~ly conccirn d in such fr11ud11lent pnssports or invoices, either by mnkmg or buying, or selfo!i the same, or by offering to ent r goods by means of tl e same, shaJJ b consider do. fdony, and the per.son or persons found guilty 0£ such nn o:fl'ense, whether American or Mnlngnsy, shull be punished by imprisonment or µne or both accord.ing to the o.ggravntion of the offence, as hereinafter provided by .Artie! VI; nud this in addition to the _pen11lty for smuggling when goods have b>en smuggled, r a empt has b en mn.d0 to smuggle, by means of such fraudulent pa ports or in.voice. . 16. Unit~~ tat vesse~s of wnr shall be l'ermitt~d to enter :fr~ely mto the milttnry ports, l'J vei:s, and c ·eeks s1tu!1Jted 1n the dom1mons 


238 CONSOLIDATED TREATY SERIES 
of Her Mn.jesty the Q11een of Mad11gascnr, to make repairs n.nd to prov:ide themselves, at a fair and moderate price such supplies, stores rtnd provisions as t.ney mny from time to time ne d, including timber for necessary r pairs, without pn.yment of dnty. 
1'7. On account of Her Majesty the Queen of Madagascar's desire to facilitate c tIUnunicntion between the rited tates nnd Mada.gascar and thereby to advance commerce b tween the wo coun.tries, the United totes Gov rnmcnt and United tntes private steo.m.shjp comp1u1i • a,re hereby gmn d th privilege· to land o.nd deposit coal for tho use of the United tates Government and private steam.ers at Tnmatnve or Mojn.ngn, or both1 on land designuled by th gov.oruor for that purpose, a.nd to tn.ke the same a.way nguin from time to time :for tho use of such sten.mcrs, without payment of duti~ or harbor chn.rges of any kind; but a.norninul ren"t f five cents a ton shall be paid per annum as rent for the lnnd on which it may be stored. This privil ge shnll continue until cmil of Madagascar pro.duction in sufficient quantity for such steamei·s can be bought. But should any of the vessels bringing such r,.oa.l,or any of the steamers talcing the same away, bring goods to sell at such port, or take goods from the s1une, such vessel must pay the sumo duty nnd harbor charges as other m rchant vessels except on the coal. And shoold any of such conl be sold in Madagascar, duty mLtSt be paid on the quantity so sold. 
ARTICLE V. 
1. he contracting parties mny appoint consular fficcrs of any or 
o:fall g,·11,desto r-1d in the dominions of the oth r, and such on.sulnr ofJic rs hall be granted all tbe right.'3 and/rivileges g1·n.nted to fnnction~es of Wre grades of the most fnvore nation, ns witnesses of the good 1·elations existiJJg b tween the two nations, and to regu.late und protect commerce. 
2. 
The resident of the United States of America may send a d.iJ?lomatic officer of any gl'o.de to reside in Mad~ascar who shall eOJOythe rights and pt:ivileges provided by intemational law for his gi·ade. 

3. 
The Queen of Madagascar shall have the like privilege of send.ing r..diplomatic officer of any srade to lhc nil d. tnt o,: Am rice,, !Llld he shall enjoy there likew1.Seo.11the rights nnd _pl'ivileges of his gmde established by international law. 


ARTICLE VI. 
1. 
Citizens and proteges of th United tnLes of Amari n, who e11t r Madagascar, and. subjects o Her Majesty tho Queen of Mada.gascar, while sojourning in the United State..., of America, are subject to the laws of trade nnd commerce in the r pective countries. 

2. 
In regard to civil rights, whether of person or prop rty, of citi.zens 11Dd proteges of tlle United Stntes of ..America,, where disputes or djfl'erenccs shall arise between them or in cases of crimi11al offences committed upon them by each other, they shall be under the exclu.sive civil and criminal jurisdiction of their own consuls, duly in.vested with the n c snry powers. 


8. Neither shn:11 the Malng1~sy au horities inte.rfer in differences or disputes between Unjted S-tafoscitizens and proteges and the citi.zens or subjects of any third power in Madngnsoar. 
2 39 
4. But the Malagn.sy poli e may, whenever a United States citizen or :proteg6 shall be dis overed in the act of committing a crime agrunst any person1 of whatever nationality, or breach of the pence in any manner, whether by making unln.wful dist.urbane in Lhe streets nnd public places, or in any manner breaking the published faws of Madagn.scn,t·, 1nr~ such offend r without process and take him immediately before the prop r Unit d States consular officer, who will take such action in the cnso as the circumstances, the laws of the two oountri , and the stipuhitions of this trent,y 1·equire. 
6. The Malagasy Government will sup1_:>lyto each United States consuta1· Ilic r residing in Madn.,g-ascnr,within six months after the exchange of the rati.fica,tion of tlus 1!rent.--y,
one or more print:ed co~ies of all ln.ws, decre~ 1 or customs havmg the force of lnw which affect in any way, directly or indirectly, foreigners sojourning in Mad1i.gascar, in their rights and privileges, either of p 1-son or property, for the informat.ion of United States citizens sojourning m Madll..gascar. 
6. And in liJce manner, whenever nny change shall be made in such laws or de -rees, or new one.'3 be promulgated, touching the interMts of such persons, a like printed copy of the same shall be fnrnished to a 1 s1tld United tn,tes onsulnr officers, at least one m011th before such change, or new law, or decree sh1l1J take e.ffect; and when any such cbnnge, or new law, or decree, touches or changes the regulations o':f_the custom-house, or duties to be paid, or the laws ii.. regnrd to export.'3 and im:ports, the srud copies of s11ch new laws and decrees shitll be so furmshed at lellSt six months before taking effect against United States citizens. 
'l. All d:i.Bputesu. .nd differences n.rising between citizens o.nd pro.teges f the United tatcs of Ame1·icn. and subjects of adagnscar, and all criminal offences committed by such citizens and proteg6s against. said subjects of Madagascar, and n.ll criminal oil.'cnces com.mitted by the sul>jects of Madagnscar against the citiz ns and pro.teg6s of the United States of America, as well as o.11infringement of the laws of Madagascar by the United tates citizens and proteges, shall be investig1ited, tried, and adjudged by "m.i.-:ed courts,1' as follows: 
8. 
The chief United States diplomatic officer, wh n ther shall be one in Madagn.scarJ or when ther is no such oiJlcer L'esiding in the kingdorn the cruet or senior United Stat s consular oiJicer and a Mafogosy oflicei·, duly appointed by her Majesty the Q.11en ol Mada.gascar for that l?urpose, shall constitute a " mixed suverior court," which shall be a court of recot·d,' n.nd mn,y hold 11".9sittings at .Antann.narivo th apitnl of Madug cur Ol' at Tnrn1ttave, accol'uing as the circmnstn,nces of the business of. the conrt m11,yreqnfrc. 

9. 
This superior court shall have both original 11,nd appcllo.te juris.diction; that is, actions mo,y he commenced and decided in it, and it m,ay also try ca.ses aypeu.l d .from the inferior courts heroin pi:_ovided for, us follows: 

10. 
There shall be one inferior mixed court in each United States consular and ea.oil United tu.tes consular ngent>s district in Madi.gnscar. Such courts shall consist of the Unit~d States consular officer of the di<Jtrict and a Malagasy officer appointed by Her Maj.esty's Government for the purpose, for each district. 


240 C O N S O L I D AT ED T R EAT Y S E R I E S 
11. 
The inferior courts shall have original jurisdiction of civil cuses where the sum claimed does not exceed five hundred dollars ($500) or imprisonment for more thnn on year or bot,h, its will he more fully explained in the" Code of Rules" of proc edings £or tho mix d cow·ts, heroinaftm: provided for. 

12. 
Appeals from the superior mixed com·!.s may be taken to either of the two governments, a:t the option of tho party appealing, in tho manner pt· vided in said " Code of Rules." 


18. In t.ho trio.I of actions in these courts, the native judg sh1\ll !_)reside and ho.v th prevailing voice in tho decisions when United Stat citizens or protcges a.re th plaintifl's, and vice versa when they aro dofendant.s, that is, when subjects of the Queen are the plaintiffs the United tnfos (consulnr or diplomnt-ic) officer, as the case may be, shall preside ana hiwe th pt· vailing voice in U,e decisions. 
_14. But tl}e presiding j~~ge shall in every cn~e counsel with. ~nd grv~ ~lue weight to the oprrnons of th associate )ndge befor g1vwgdec1s10ns. 
15. 
It is ngr d by the high contracting pnrti t,bnt o.ny atfompt to influence the decision of tl1cse judg , or iiny one o-f them, in 1Lco.so on trial, or to be decided by them, except by arguments in open court., sbalJ be • nsidered a misdemeanor; and thnt the ffering n. brib to any one of them in money or other obj ct, of vnlu or favor for the purpose of fo(Ju ncincr his decision, shn.11 be ousidered 11 felony, and I.hat the p rson prov~ guilty oi e'itJ1 r of these offences shnll be pu11.ished by tho government to which he belongs according to tho grado of bis crime. And if it shall be proved tllat o.judge of t.heso courts, of eit.hcr nationality, shn,11 hn.ve reoeived a bribe to infh1en~ hi1:1 de ision in any case he shall be dismissed from his office of judge, nnd other:J¥i5 puni;bed according to the laws of his own nation fc r such rnal feasance. 

16. 
It is further n.gr ed that within six months after the exchange of the rntifica.Lion of Lhis treaty, tho.t tllo ohie:f diplomatic or consular· officec -of t.he -United • tates, who shn.11lrn t\t the time residing i.u Madagascar, and one or more officers to be selected b,y Her Majc,ii;y's Government, shn,11 meet n,nd together draw 11p a ccCode of Rules " of proceedings for these mixed courts, whjch code, when so drnw11 and signed by said oilicers, shall be forwarded by them to their respective governments for approval; and when approved by both government.<, shall be considered a po,1·t of this treaty, duly r:atified as such. And this treaty including said cod of ml • togeth r with international law, ttnd the laws of the Unit a States of America and of Mndagusca:r, in so far as the hitter au be made t.o hu,nnonfae, shall govern proceecliogs in these com·ts. 

17. 
IL is agreed that the said " Code of Rnles " shttll follow, in so fn.r as the laws and pt· ent status of things in Mndugascitr wUJ admit, the rules of pro • edi11gs in United S ates consuhtr coLu·ts in Mada.gascar· that all attestations in the pr ceedings sh11U be made m1der the j udjoial oath or oJlirmntion of civilized nations· and thilt the said coJ of rul shall define how actions shRll be commenced ru1d be conducted the grades of oll'ences and their punislunents, under wlutt circumstances nrr ts may be made, 1md the amount and mnnner of bull to be to.ken, the disposition to be made of fines collectc(. when, 


how, nnd to whom appeals may be taken, and all other matters necea.s~ for the intell~gent working of such courts. ~d shall also con.tam :forms :for writs and other processes and a tn,r1ff of fees. 
18. 
In all ases of arrest permitted by this treaty now, and to be provided fo • by the " Co :leof Rules," the prisoners shall be, during their deten ion, treated with all the humanity consonant with the laws of civilized nations. Her Majesty's Government will see that they are supplied with wholesom food and drink in su:iliient quan.tity, and detainecl in healthy quarters, and that they are brought to trial in the shortest time possible consonant with the convenience of the prisoner. 

19. 
1n cases of n,x·J·e.c;tof American citizens or proteges in the absence of a United States consular o.ffic r or wher no such offi er resides, I.he author.ity causing the nn·est shah immediately jnform the nearest United States consular officer of the fa t and of tl1e circum.stance of the case, n.nd also cause the vrisoner to b taken as soon us vossible before the mixed com·t of which that nearest consular officer 1s n judge. 

20. 
It shall be the duty of the court to encourage the settlement 0£ contl'Oversies of a civil character by mutual agreement, ov to submit the same to th decision of r:efe.rees'ugreed 1Jpon by the parties. .A.nd in criminal ens s, which a.i·e not of .a heinous charncter, it, shall be lawful for the parties aggrieved or concerned thel'ein, with tile assent of the ourt, to adjust the same among th mselves upon pecuniary or other considemtions. 

21. 
Her Majesty's overrunent will render all assistance in its power to United States citiz ns a.nd pr t g6s toward collecting their legal claims against Her Majesty's subjects; and United States con.sular ofl1cers will likewise render every assistance in collecting legal claims_ st Unit. cl States citizens nnd proteg6s. 

_11._gai 

22. 
Whenever it is known or there is reason to believe, that trans.gressors against the laws, fugitives from jo.stice, are on the promises of United tlttes citizens or proleges, such premises may be entered by the Malagasy police with the consent of the occupants, or against their consent in company with a United States ConsuJar officer, or with his writi',eu order. In case 0£ absence of such United States officers, or ir.. pla.c where no such officers reside, the police ma.y make su h entry by the order of the local authority, to look for the o:ll:ender or stolen property; and the offender, if found, may be al'l'ested and all stolen property seized. 

23. 
Murder ll.Ild ins11rrection or rebellion ugai.nst Lbo Government of Madagascai· ,vith intent to subvert the sOJlle, shall be capital offence, and not bailnbJ • and when a United tates citizen shall be on.victed by tills court of either of those crimes he sh11ll be b11nished the country and sent to the Unite<l tntes of America for a review of his trial and approval of his sent nee and punishment. I£ a Malagasy subjec be convicted by the court of the murder of 11United States citizen or protege he shall suffer sur.h punishment as the Mala.gasy law a,vn1·ds for such crime when Her Majesty, the Queen of Madagascar, shall hilve approved the judgment of the court. 

24. 
When 11 United States citi~en shall have been convicted of sev ral minor oil:ences, showing him to be a. turbulent and intractable person he shall, u;pon the request of the overnment of her MAjesty the Queen, be bruushed the country. 


242 CONSOLIDATED TREATY SERIES 
An'l'IOL.l!l VII. 
1. 
No United States vessel shall have communi 11,tion with the shoi-e befor re eiv:ing ~ratique from the lo al authorities of Madngascar and producing o. ' bill of health " from tho port sailed from, signed by the Malagasy consnl if there be one at thac port t i:fnone, Lhen by the person duly authorized to give such bills of heOJth. 

2. 
Malagasy subjects shall not be permitted to embark on United States vessels without a.pa~ort from Her Majesty's Government. 

3. 
In cases of mutiny on Unitl.ld St.ates merchant vessels, or in cases of desertion from United States nn.Lional or private vessels, I.he local authorities shiill1 on applfoation, render all necessary assistance as far as is possible to the United States consular offi er to bring back tho deserter or to res ore discipline on boa.rd merchan~ vessels. 

4. 
When a United States consulnr officer shall nsk the local authori.ties to a.rrest a deserter from a v l, the police shnU bo directed to do their utmost to 11rrest promptly such deserter in the district. And if the consular officer suggest any other places where the deserter mn.y hA.ve s creted himself the authorities shall give a written notice to tbe governor o:f such district pointed out, who shall in his turn do bis utmost to find nnd. llJ.Test tlie desertet. And tho re.5ult 0£ such efforts, whether successiul or otherwis , shall be promptly reported to the governor, who shall report to the consular officer. 

5. 
For the services requfred by this article for an-e!;f ng deser ers.J 


i:fsuch d erter be a,n:ested, n..fee of three dollars ($3) may be exo.cteu for on.ch deserter arrested, and five cents per i nglish 1'ilile for the distance actually tJ:o.velled by t.he police, uud oJ.sosuch necessary ex.penses ns may be incurred. for food, :ferrying, and imprisonment of the deserteP. 
6. And if discovered that such police did not do their utmost they shall be punished by the governor; nnd if such police have done theii: ntmost but without success, tbey will be none the less entitled to the e~-penses above stated, but not to the fee of three dollars ( $3) . 
.AnnOLllVIII. 
1. 
In oose 0£ a. shipw1· ck of a United States vessel on the coast of Madag-ascar, or if nny such vessel should be attacked or plundered in the waters of Maditgnscar, adfacent to any military station, the governor will do his utmost to urge the p ople to save life and to secure property and to restore it to the owno.rs 01· to the United States consul, and if I.here be no consul nor owner in such clistrict, u.n inventory of the goods r cued shall be ma.de and the goods shall b delivered to the nea:rest United States consular officer, who shall give the gove1:nor a receipt for the same. 

2. 
Tho governor of the district shall take the nu.mesof the peOJlle engaged in saving such vessel, and designate those who rescue lives and those who save goods. 

3. 
And if such vessel be an abandoned one, then one-fourth of vessel and goods may be claimed for salvnge.

4. 
An.d i:f a vessel be in distress, and the captain or crew demand help, such help shall be rewarded at the rate of tw nty-five cents a day for soldiers and laborers, o.nd one dollar a day :for officers who superintend such help. 

5. 
And if llllY vessel be wi·ecked or in distress and the captain or crew do not demand nsmstance, being in o. situo.Li n to do so, o.nd consequently the Malagasi do not save anything, the governor o.nd people will not be responsible. 

6. 
However, in case the captain or crew demand assi&tance,01· a.re in a situation where making such o. demand is impossible, and .it is known tho.t the governor did not do his ut:most to move the people to ao.ve such vessel o.nd cargo, 110 shull bo punished according to the laws of Madagascar. 

7. 
The same protection sho.ll be granted to Malagasy vessels at.tacked or plundered in the warors of the United Stat.es of America. 


2 
----------------------------43 
ARTICLE IX. 
1. 
American goods may be landed in bond to be reshl pped to other ports without payment of duties, under the following rules: 

2. 
When it muy ho desired to so lo.nd goods to be reshipped to other ports, the owner of the goods, or the consig:ne , or ma$ter of the vessel as the case may be, slmll present to the locul governor, or to _the coliect<?r of customs, 0.S the governor mttY. directJ a correct h~.vo1ce or mam:fest of the g?<>ds so l~nded, showu!g values by detail when t1rnre a.re goods of diff rent lands, or of different values, e.nd q11a1~tit:iesof ea.ch and the total value. 


a. 1'he Malugusy customs officers shall verify by inspection the goods when landed with the invoice or m.anifestb· th(m the owner, consignee, or muster of the vessel, as the ca-se may e, sho.ll execute a. bond payable to the governor or collector of customs, as may be directed by the local authority, conditioned to pay t.he established duti~ on su?h ~oods, or !>n such part of thell_l as sh~U not have been reshipped w1th1n the ]_)errnd agreed upon, which penod shall be men.tioned in the bond us th date of its maturity. Then such goods may be stored on th premises of their owner or consignee, or in magazint'fl rented by him for t,hat purpose. 
4. When he reships the goods, he will notify the party to whom this bond has been given to be present and n.gain verHy the goods with the invoice or mam.fest, wl1en, if none are lacking, he will be entitled to the return of his bond or if the goods or any part of them are lack.ing, he must pay the Juty esto.bhshed by Article IV. on such as arc not £ound and reshipped, which will equally entitle him to receive back his bond. 
ARTICLE X. 
Her Majesty's Government desires the development of t11edormant resom·ces of the kingdom, and the adv,;mc ment of all t.he useful mechunico.1 and agriculturn.J. industries therein, and thereby to pro.mote the best interests of commerce and Christian civilization bl adoption ond application of such modern improvements and appli.nnces 1\8 shall be suitable £or such purposes and best ndapted to the condition of Madagascar, and :for the oest interests of Her Majesty's people; and toward the accomplishment of these objects, should any 'trmted tutes citizens or prote~ of good character, and pos.w,sing the requisite qualifications for the special business proposed, desire to engage in such industries in Madagascar by investment of capito.l or lnbor., or in teaching the people how to apply the modern improve.ments in the prosecution of the mdustries, their applications to th~ 
244 CONS O LI DATED TREATY S ER I E S 
g'!)Vernment will be favorably received, and their propositions liber• ally entertained; and if they n.nd the government can agree upon terms, they will be l>ermitted to eniage in such avocatio11s by con.tracts, grants, col1l1Dl.SSions
or sn.lnnes. 
ARTICLE XI. 
1. 
n is agreed between the high contracting parties thnt, the 1 vy of tnx s on United States itizens as herebibefor pr vi<l d f r condi.tionally in -Article III., section 131 shall never be 1tt a hig)1et· rate than shall be levied upon Her MnJ ty's subjects for the sn,me pur.pose.s tmd upon like val~ ercept the spe ial land tax ltorcinb for provided -fot·in Article ill., section 12. 

2. 
United States citfaens and pl·oteges shall not be deprived of any privileges relinquished by this treaty unless the same ~·estrictions be placed llj?Oil the citizens and subjects of all other foreign nations residing m Madagusc1u·, but shall enjoy all the privileges that may be granted to the most :favored nations. 

3. 
And Her l:fojosty's subjects while sojourning in the United States of .America hn.11 enjoy 1.ill the pt·i vileges conceded by tho nit d h1tes Government to the. citizens or subjects of the most 


favored nation. ARTICLE XII. 
1. 
The above articles oi treaty made in good faith shall be submit.ted to both the Government of the United States of America iind Her Mlljesty, the Queen of Madagascar, for ratification; and such ratifi.cation be exchanged within one year from date of ratification at Antananarivo. 

2. 
h011ld it at any future time seem desirable in the interests of either !Jf the contn1 ting J?arties to alter or ndd to tho pres nt i.r aty, such alterations or additions shall be effected with the ons nt of both parties. 

3. 
Dupli ate origimils of this treaty, with cori·esponding text in th English and Malagasy languages, which shall be both of equal aut.hority, have b en signed and sealed at otanar·inrivo, Madagascar, on this thirteenth dn.y of May (seventeenth of Alakaosy), one thou.sand eight hundred and eighty-one. 


[SEAL.] W. W. RODINSON, 
United States Oon-S'ul for Madagascar. 
[SEAL.] RAVONINAHO'JUNIARIVO, 
15th Honor Officer of the Pal,ace, Ohi,ef Secretari.J of State for Foreign Affair~. 
In the name of Her Majesty Ranavalomanjnkn, Queen of Madagas.car und by Her Royal Command and authority, We, Her Ma.jes~y'sduly empowei·ed Ambassadors Plenipotentiary hereby mtii'y und con.firm the w:ilhin treaty and every part thereof. March twelfth, 1883. 
[SEAL.] RA VO NIN AHlTilIN l'.AIIIVO, 
15 Vtra 0. D. P. Ohief Secretary of State ff>r Fo'reign Affain1, Chief Ambassador of H. M. th~ (Jiieen of Mai/,ag(lJJca:r. 
RAMANIRKA, 
14 Vtra 0. D. P. Member of tlte Privy 0011.ncil, Ambassador of 
H. M. the Queen of M adagaJJca:r. 



</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>