<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0307">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Secretary of State, November 23, 1907</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, encoding, and translation</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0307</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Secretary of State</title>
<date when="1907-11-23">November 23, 1907</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 239, Liasse 205</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Detry</term>
<term>Dodds</term>
<term>Everaert</term>
<term>Hutereau</term>
<term>Smith</term>
<term>Speck</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bangala</term>
<term>Bayenge</term>
<term>Dobo</term>
<term>Gali</term>
<term>Lisala</term>
<term>Mongala</term>
<term>New Antwerp</term>
<term>Saint Germain</term>
<term>Stanleyville</term>
<term>Upoto</term>
<term>Yambata</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Vice Governor General</roleName>
<placeName>Boma</placeName>
<date when="1907-11-23"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-12" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2018" who="pr">Translated and encoded header information.</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.001.jpg"/>

<p>Etat Independant
Du 
Congo<lb/>
Gouvernement Local<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 2267<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse la date et le numéro<lb/>
1 Annexe<lb/>
OBJET:
Voyage Consul Général des
Etats-Unis d'Amérique.</p>
    
<p>Boma, le 23 Novembre 1907.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Secrétaire d'Etat,</p>
    
<p>Comme suite à ma dépêche no 2132, du 4 courant,
j'ai l'honneur de vous faire parvenir, sous
ce pli, en copie, la lettre no 14/f, du 8 de ce
mois, que le Commissaire de district des Bangala
m'a adressée, en réponse à un télégramme que
je lui avais envoyé et dans lequel je le priais
de me faire parvenir d'urgence tous renseignements
au sujet du voyage du Consul Général
des Etats-Unis d'Amérique.</p>
    
<p>Cette lettre est à mettre en rapport, pour
certains points, avec une autre correspondance
de ce courrier sous la rubrique "Situation dans
la Mongala, Voyage du Consul Général des Etats-
Unis d'Amérique."</p>
    
<p>Le Vice Gouverner Général,<lb/> 
<unclear extent="signature"/></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.002.jpg"/>

<p>No 14/f.</p>

<p>Nouvelle-Anvers, le 8 novembre 1907.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Gouverneur Général,</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous confirmer mon télégramme de
ce jour ainsi conçu:</p>
    
<p>"Réponse à no 739/f, du 14 octobre. No 12/f, Consul
Général Etats-Unis être passé à Nouvelle-Anvers le II
septembre montant vers Stanleyville rien de particulier
à signaler pour passage Nouvelle-Anvers. Arrive après-
midi parti lendemain matin Je apprendre après Consul
Général Etats-Unis être resté à Upoto et environs détails 
par lettre confidentielle."</p>
    
<p>Comme suite à ce télégramme, j'ai l'honneur, Monsieur
le Gouverneur Général, de vous communiquer ce qui suit:
M. le Consul Général des Etats-Unis, Smith, est arrivé à Nouvelle-
Anvers par vapeur "Harry Read" vers 2 1/2 heures de
l'après midi, le 11 septembre. Il a quitté le lendemain matin
à la première heure. L'après midi du passage de M. le
Consul Général a été consacré à une promenade dans les
cultures (Funtumia et Hevea) et à une visite du lazaret
ainsi que de la station. J'ai personnellement piloté M. le
Consul Général pendant cette visite et le soir au diner
que je lui ai offert, il s'est déclaré fort enchanté de sa 
visite et de ce qu'il avait vu à Nouvelle-Anvers.</p>

<p>M. le Consul Général Smith, en quittant Nouvelle-Anvers,
me disait qu'il avait l'intention d'aller jusque
Stanleyville.</p>
    
<p>Il n'en fut pas ainsi, car en effet, il s'est arrêté
à Upoto. Chose que je n'ai connue qu'après son passage ici,
à la descente le 10 octobre.</p>
    
<p>D'après les renseignements qui m'ont été donnés par
M. le Substitut Detry, à sa rentrée à Nouvelle-Anvers, le
2 novembre dernier, M. le Consul Général Smith serait arrivé
à Upoto et de là à Lisala où il aurait été invité à
diner le 18 septembre. Assistaient au diner M. le Procureur
d'Etat Gréban de Saint Germain, M. Hutereau, Commandant du
Camp. le Substitut Detry et le Révérend Dodds, de la B.M.S.

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.003.jpg"/>
    
Le lendemain, M. le Consul Général Smith est parti pour
Gali, accompagné du Révérend Dodds.</p>

<p>Pour ce voyage je n'ai obtenu aucun renseignement.</p>
    
<p>De Gali, ils sont allés à Bayenge où ils sont restés
plusieurs jours (du 22 au 28). Le 27, M. le Substitut
Detry est arrivé et M. le Consul Général Smith a annoncé
son départ pour le lendemain. Pendant son séjour à Bayenge,
M. le Consul Général Smith à voulu procéder à une 
expérience de récolte de caoutchouc. </p> 
    
<p>Conduits par M. Everaert, ils se sont rendus en forêt
accompagnés d'un certain nombre de récolteurs. Ils ont
procédé à la récolte du latex et d'après les renseignements
qui me sont fournis par M. Detry, le résultat est
qu'un homme peut produire, déplacement compris, 3 kilos de
caoutchouc pour <unclear>42</unclear> heures de travail.</p>
    
<p>Le 27, au soir donc, le diner fut présidé par M. le
Substitut Detry. Au cours de la conversation, M. le Consul
Général Smith aurait émis cette opinion: "Je me rends maintenant
compte des difficultés que l'on a eues ici et du
travail qui a été fait".</p>
    
<p>Le 28, au matin, M. Smith, toujours accompagné de M.
Dodds, est parti pour Yambata où il est arrivé le même
jour. Pendant le séjour à Yambata, M. Speck, le Chef de secteur,
les a accompagnés tout le temps. Je ne connais rien
de particulier à signaler.</p>
 
<p>De Yambata, les voyageurs sont partis pour Dobo où
ils sont arrivés le 4 octobre, y ont diné avec M. le Procureur
d'Etat Gréban de Saint Germain et de là, sont partis
le 5 octobre pour descendre.</p>
    
<p>Le 10 octobre, M. le Consul Général des Etats-Unis
est passé à Nouvelle-Anvers vers le milieu de la matinée.
Il a continué immédiatement.</p>
    
<p>Tels sont, Monsieur le Gouverneur Général, les renseignements
que j'ai pu obtenir jusqu'à ce jour.</p>
    
<p>Le Commissaire de district,<lb/>
(s) Gehot.</p>

</div1>


<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.001.jpg"/>

<p>Independent State
of the
Congo<lb/>
Local Government<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 2267<lb/>
Recall in the response the date and the number<lb/>
1 Annex<lb/>
Subject:
Voyage of the General Consul of the
United States of America.</p>
    
<p>Boma, November 23rd 1907.</p>

<p>Mr. Secretary of State,</p>
    
<p>Following my dispatch no 2132, from the 4th of this month,
I have the honor to send to you, under
this letter, in copy, the letter no 14/f, from the 8th of this
month, that the Commissioner of the district of the Bangala
addressed to me, in response to a telegram that
I had sent to him and in which I prayed him to
send to me with urgency all information
on the subject of the voyage of the General Consul
of the United States of America.</p>
    
<p>This letter is to get on, for
certain points, another correspondence
of this messenger under the rubric "Situation in
the Mongala, Voyage of the General Consul of the United
States of America."</p>
    
<p>The Vice General Governor,<lb/> 
<unclear extent="signature"/></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.002.jpg"/>

<p>No 14/f.</p>

<p>New-Antwerp, November 8, 1907.</p>
 
<p>Mr. Governor General,</p>
    
<p>I have the honor to confirm my telegram to you from 
this day as follows:</p>
    
<p>"Response to no. 739/f, from October 14. No 12/f, Consul
General of the United States to be moved to New-Antwerp September 
II  to Stanleyville nothing specific 
to inform of for passage to New-Antwerp. Arrive in the afternoon 
leave the next morning I learned after the Consul
General of the United States to be left at Upoto and around details 
by confidential letter."</p>
    
<p>As follows by this telegram, I have the honor, 
Mr. Governor General, to communicate to you the following: 
Mr. Consul General of the United States, Smith, arrived at New- 
Antwerp by steamboat "Harry Read" around 2 1/2 hours from
the afternoon, September 11. He quit the next morning 
by the first hour. The afternoon of the passage by Mr.
Consul General had been consecrated by a walk in the 
cultures (Funtumia et Hevea) and at a visit to the lazaretto
just as in the station. I have personally driven Mr.
Consul General during this visit and the night of the dinner  
that I offered him, he announced strongly enchanted with his 
visit and of what he had seen in New-Antwerp.</p>

<p>Mr. Consul General Smith, while leaving New-Antwerp, 
told me that he had the intention of going as far as
Stanleyville.</p>
    
<p>It was not so, for in fact, he stopped 
in Upoto. Something that I didn't know after his visit here,
on the way down October 10.</p>
    
<p>After the details that were given to me by 
Mr. Substitute Detry, by his return to New-Antwerp, 
las November 2, Mr. Consul General Smith would have arrived
in Upoto and from there in Lisala where he would have been invited to 
dine September 18. Assisted to dinner Mr. Prosecutor 
of State Gréban de Saint Germain, Mr. Hutereau, Commander of the
Camp, the Substitute Detry and Reverend Dodds, B.M.S.

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0307.003.jpg"/>

The next day, Mr. Consul General Smith left for 
Gali, accompanied by Reverand Dodds.</p>

<p>For this trip I did not obtain any details.</p>
    
<p>From Gali, they went to Bayenge where they remained 
several days (from the 22nd-28th). The 27th, Mr. Substitue
Detry arrived and Mr. Consul General Smith announced 
his departure for the next morning. During his stay in Bayenge,
Mr. Consul General Smith wanted to proceed to  
experience the rubber harvest.</p> 
    
<p>Driven by Mr. Everaert, they were taken to the forest 
accompanied by a certain number of workers. They 
proceeded to the harvest and after the information 
that supplied me by Mr. Detry, the result est 
that a man can produce, complete transfer, 3 kilos of
rubber for two hours or work.</p>
    
<p>The 27th, in the evening, the dinner was presided by Mr.  
Substitute Detry. In the course of the conversation, Mr. Consul
General Smith had volunteered this opinion: "I now realize 
the difficulties that they have here and from
work that was made".</p>
    
<p>The 28th, in the morning, Mr. Smith, always accompanied by Mr. 
Dodds, left for Yambata where he arrived the same
day. During the stay in Yambata, Mr. Speck, the Chief of the area, 
accompanied them the entire time. I know nothing 
specific to highlight.</p>
 
<p>From Yambata, the travelers left for Dobo where
they arrived October 4, dinned there with Mr. Prosecutor
of State Gréban de Saint Germian and from there, left 
October 5 to move.</p>
    
<p>October 10th, Mr. Consul General of the United States
passed in New-Antwerp around the middle of the morning.
He continued immediately.</p>
    
<p>Such are, Mr. Governor General, the information
that I could obtain up to this day.</p>
    
<p>The Commissioner of the district,<lb/>
(s) Gehot.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
