<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

John A Parson
To Department of State

Subject
Mutiny

Abstract of Contents
Informing the Department of the insubordination of the crese of the American Brig "Ann Elizabeth" of Boston, and the sending two of the crese in the American Barque "Liberia" of New York, <unclear/>.

Enclossures 6 Statement of Capt, mate, and four of the crese. 

No 10

United States Consulate at 
Sierra Leone Africa May 5th 1879

To
<unclear/> F.W. Seward
Asssistant Secretary of State
Washington D.C. 

Sir,
I have the honor to report to the Department, that on the 29th of April ;ast, Captain T.G. Burgess, mastering the American Brig "Ann Elizabeth of Boston Mass. then in the port; applied to this Consulate for protection; stating that a portion of his crew were in a state any more work, that the mate had been severely out and multilative, he himself had been struck twice with the windas normon, and the men had <unclear/> to kill the mate if he returned on board of the vessel, and that things were in such a state, they did not feel safe to have these men on board. Immediately went on board of ... said Brig and found matters just as the local authorities for aid: The men were arrested and imprisoned.

I subsequently ordered the men to this Consulate for investigation, and received each man's statement upon oath, a coppy of which I herewith inclose. From what I could gather, it seems that the man Bennis was under the influence of liquor, and the 1st Officer had been on a spree over night, hence they were not in a state to care mcuh. The row began between these two while the Capt was in the cabin, and the rest of the crew below, consequently those who came on deck were <unclear/> to take their own view of the matter as it appeared to them. the Capt seemed to be parting the two, when the news had been passed below that time bound for New York, I thought it best to send them by her.

I accordingly sent the two men James Carleslile and Joseph Dolan by the said Barque Liberia on the 2nd of May, J.B. Williams master, bound for New York: giving the Capt a certificate n the Treasury Department for sixty Dollars for their passage.

I have to state that I did not send them in irons, as the Capt of the Barque said he did not require it, and the men seemed perfectly willing to be sent home from trial. 

The other two men Bennis and Relly were sent back on board of the Brig "Ann Elizabeth" as they showed less signs of hostility, and seemed willing to return to duty...

The 'Brig "Ann Elizabeth" will probably leave this port for Boston in a fort tonight from this date.

I have the honor to be
Sir
Your
Your Obedient Servant 
John A Parson
U.S. Consul 

Enclosures C Statement of Capt mate; and four of the crew. 


