<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0244">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from Charles Hall Adams to John Hay, October 17, 1898</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0244</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from Charles Hall Adams to John Hay, October 17, 1898</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1898-10-17">October 17, 1898</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Encounters with Africans</term>
<term>Slavery and Slave Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Ayres, Eli</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/72318871">Carroll, Charles, 1737-1832</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32012452">Clay, Henry, 1777-1852</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/30330745">Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908</term>
<term>Coleman, William D.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/20436089">Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901</term>
<term>Gibson, Garretson W.</term>
<term>Hoppin, W. J.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/63008966">Latrobe, John H. B. (John Hazlehurst Boneval), 1803-1891</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/59096754">Madison, James, 1751-1836</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/15553452">Potter, Henry Codman, 1834-1908</term>
<term>Pauncefote, Julian</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61981404">Puttkamer, Jesko von, 1855-1917</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3322134">Sherman, John, 1823-1900</term>
<term>Stockton</term>
<term>Warner, D. B.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32431122">Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cameroons</term>
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Cavalla River</term>
<term>Kong Mountains</term>
<term>Mano River</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>San Pedro River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Upper Niger River</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Kroo</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Adams, Charles Hall</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General of Liberia</roleName>
<placeName>Boston, Massachusetts</placeName>
<date when="1898-10-17"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76456718">Hay, John, 1838-1905</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02-10" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw">encoded</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="20170616_150748"/>

<p>Liberian Consulate General<lb/>
(23 Court Street)</p>

<p>Boston, Mass., October 17, 1898.</p>

<ab>Sir:-</ab>

<p>I have the honor to submit for your consideration 
the following facts concerning the Republic 
of Liberia, the only Christian Negro State in Africa,
situated between the parallels of 4&#176; and 7&#176; of North 
latitude, reaching from Monnoh River, on the
North,&#8212; now the conterminious boundary between
Sierra Leone and Liberia,&#8212; to the Cavalla River on the
South, embracing a coast line of about 400 miles on 
the Atlantic Ocean, and extending to the Kong Mountains 
in the interior, a distance of between 250 and 300 miles, 
comprising some of the finest land on the 
West coast of Africa.</p>

<p>Liberia owes its origin to the American 
Colonization Society, a society which was founded in the
city of Washington, on December 21, 1816, by men from
all parts of the United States prominent in politics, 
business and learning, and is still actively 
continuing its work after 80 years of existence. The
character of the Society is apparent from the list
<catchwords>of</catchwords>

<fw type="address">To/ Hon. John Hay,<lb/>
Secretary of State &amp;c.,<lb/>
Washington.</fw>

<pb facs="20170616_150753"/>

of its presidents, the office having been filled by 
the following named gentlemen; Hon. Bushrod Washington,
Hon. Charles Carroll of Carrollton, Ex-President 
James Madison, Hon. Henry Clay, Hon. J.H.B. Latrobe
and Right Rev. Henry C. Potter, D.D. The Society 
has strictly confined its labors from the outset
to the "Colonizing, with their own consent, 
the people of color residing in America, in Africa."
The ship "Elizabeth," the "Mayflower" of Liberia, 
chartered by the United States, sailed from New York,
February 6, 1820, with eighty-six emigrants.
A treaty with the aboriginal owners <sic>if</sic> the land was 
signed at Mesurado (now the city of Monrovia) by
Capt. Stockton of the United States steamship
"Alligator" and Dr. Eli Ayres, Secretary of the Society,
on December 15, 1821, by which a large tract of 
territory was acquired for the colonists, and on which 
they were located on April 25, 1825, and the United 
States' flag was unfurled over the territory.
From that time on there has been an emigration of 
negroes from the United States to Liberia under the 
auspices of the Society and its auxilliaries.
The Liberians take great satisfaction in the 
knowledge that every foot of the territory was acquired 
by honorable and open purchase from the rightful 
owners.</p>

<p>In 1839 the several colonies founded by the 
Society were, with one exception, united in the 
Commonwealth of Liberia, the country remaining as
a colony under the fostering care of the American 
<catchwords>Colonization</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150758"/>

Colonization Society till July 26, 1847, when,
owing to foreign complications arising out of the
enforcement of revenue laws and port regulations, the 
people of the country met in convention, adopted a 
constitution, and declared themselves "a free,
sovereign and independent state by the name and 
title of the Republic of Liberia."</p>

<p>A stable government, republican in form,
closely modelled after that of the United States, was
immediately established, has been successfully carried
on for upwards of fifty-two years, and has received 
recognition from and entered into treaty relations 
with all the leading powers. During 
its existence as an independent state, it has 
sustained its dignity and self respect, and during the 
entire period has not been disturbed by any revolution 
or insurrection in which its citizens have engaged. It
now has a population of about 1,250,000,
of which number some 25,000 are emigrants from the 
United States and their descendents, the remainder 
being aboriginees, some having become more or less
civilized. Of the aboriginees of Liberia, the 
Kroo people, some 50,000 in number, deserve special
mention as they are hardy and industrious and have 
made considerable progress in the ways of 
civilization. They are the sailors and pilots of the coast 
and are highly esteemed for their services as laborers,
carriers and watermen.</p>

<p>In referring to the American Colonization 
Society and to Liberia Hon. D.B. Warner, ex-President
<catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150803"/>

of the Republic says;&#8212; "Perhaps the pages of 
modern history contain a record of no beginnings so 
small, instruments so weak, and weilded by a power 
so feeble that have, in the same time, accomplished 
more than the Society has through its African 
Colonization scheme."</p>

<p>For upwards of three centuries prior to the 
establishing of the colonies on the Liberian coast 
the African slave trade had been carried on, and 
slaves were brought from Africa to America almost 
from the earliest Caucassian settlement of the latter
country. Annually thousands of Africans were
deported, and many expired on the middle passage in
crossing the Atlantic. For years this wicked, unjust
and unholy traffic continued. True, the United States 
as a nation, retired from the traffic, declaring 
it piracy, and those engaged in it worthy of 
death, but it prospered. The United States sent 
out its agents to assist in making the original 
purchase of Liberian Territory from the natives, as an 
asylum for nearly 6,000 recaptured Africans, taken 
by American<del>s</del> War vessels in carrying out the law of 
1819 for the suppression of the slave trade. From 
that time to the present the United States government 
has assumed to have a friendly interest in Liberia, 
and the Liberian people have done much toward driving 
the slave traders from the West coast of Africa, and 
have rendered all aid in their power to the United 
States and Great Britain in suppressing the traffic.</p>

<p>It is deeply to be regretted that some of 
<catchwords>the </catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150807"/>

the European powers, who are so greedily and
rapidly appropriating to their own use the continent of 
Africa, manifest a disposition not only to 
circumscribe the boundaries of Liberia which have not been
questioned for more than half a century, but also
to lay claim to the extensive and most valuable territories
clearly within these boundaries. A very 
noticeable instance of this disposition was furnished 
in the efforts made by France to get possession 
of the valuable territory lying between the Cavalla
and San Pedro Rivers, having a sea coast of some 
seventy miles on the Southeastern border of what has 
been known heretofore as Liberia.</p>

<p>The Cavalla River and some of the tributaries
of the Upper Niger, have neighboring sources in
the highlands, and the Cavalla which is navigable 
for a hundred and twenty miles furnishes an excellent 
highway from the Atlantic Ocean towards the region
about the Upper Niger. Hence France desired to 
control the Cavalla River, as it gives a greatly 
desired outlet to the Atlantic Ocean for her Niger 
possessions. She therefore brought forward claims
to several isolated points distributed along the
coast of Liberia. Those claims for the most part 
had their origin in a distant past, antedating the 
founding of Liberia, and although France formally 
recognized the Republic of Liberia when it became an 
independent State, and subsequently concluded a treaty
with it to establish friendly relations, and an 
understanding between the two countries, yet on neither 
<catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150813"/>

of these occasions did she prefer these claims. The
Liberian Government, unfortunately, through fear 
of the French Republic, negotiated a treaty with 
that country which was signed at Paris on December 8,
1892, by the terms of which Liberia ceded to France 
all that part of her territory between the Cavalla 
and San Pedro Rivers, receiving in consideration
therefor certain remote hinterlands of no considerable
importance, and an indemnity of 25,000 francs as 
reimbursement for certain expenditures for establishment
incurred on that part of the coast which 
is on the East side of the Cavalla. Then it was 
that the executive committee of the American 
Colonization Society addressed an earnest memorial to the 
United States asking the interposition of the United 
States Government, not only to prevent the unjust 
spoliation of Liberia, but also to protect the rights 
of citizens of the United States and of the Society, 
which had originally purchased the territory in 
question, and in ceding it to Liberia and reserved 
certain portions of it for their own use and colonization.
The Government of the United States firmly
remonstrated against the cession of this territory 
to France. Article 5 of the treaty is very suggestive,
it reads, "In recognizing the boundaries 
now fixed the Government of the French Republic 
declares that it binds itself only to the free and
independent Republic of Liberia, and makes all 
negotiations in case of that independence being impaired
or in case of the Republic of Liberia alienating any 
<catchwords>por-</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150819"/>

portion of the territories recognized as here by the 
present convention."</p>

<p>At the present time there is much rivalry 
between Paris and Berlin to obtain ascendency in 
Liberia. Early in the present year a German subject 
at Cape Palmas had a dispute with natives who
destroyed a part of his coffee plantation. A German 
gunboat happened to be at Monrovia at the time with 
the Hon. Von Puttkammer, the Imperial Governor of
the Cameroons, and 300 natives marines on board. The 
Governor demanded a monied indemnity for the German subject 
and punishment of the offenders within 
forty-eight hours, threatening that if reparation 
was not made, to land his marines for the purpose 
of compelling compliance with his demand.</p>

<p>President Coleman succeeded in convincing the 
Governor that the affair could be adjusted in the 
Liberian Courts. The matter is now the subject 
of negotiation with the Government at Berlin, but 
the special interest in the affair attaches to the 
fact that, concurrently with the ultimatum the
German Governor submitted a carefully drafted treaty 
providing for the establishment of a German 
protectorate over Liberia, offering, if the treaty was
approved, to withdraw all demands for indemnity.</p>

<p>The moral right and duty of the United 
States to assist Liberia in preserving its 
integrity, is thus forcibly presented in one of the 
Annual Messages of President Cleveland;- "The 
weakness of Liberia and the difficulty of maintaining 
<catchwords>ef-</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150833"/>

effective sovereignty over its outlying districts 
have exposed that Republic to encroachment. It can 
not be forgotten that this <sic>distand</sic> community is an
offshoot of our own system, owing its origin to the 
associated benevolence of American citizens, whose
<sic>praisworthy</sic> efforts to create a <sic>necleus</sic> of civilization 
in the dark Continent have commanded respect
and sympathy everywhere, especially in this country. 
Although a formal protectorate over Liberia is contrary
to our traditional policy, the moral right and 
duty of the United States to assist in all proper 
ways in the maintenance of its integrity is obvious,
and has been consistently announced during nearly 
half a century."</p>

<p>On many occasions the United States Government 
has without hesitation taken a firm stand on behalf
of Liberia and Mr. Evarts, while Secretary of 
State wrote Mr. Hoppin under date of April 21, 1880:
"The United States are not adverse to having the 
great powers know that they publicly recognize the 
peculiar relations between them and Liberia, and that 
they are prepared to take every proper step to 
maintain them".</p>

<p>Since Liberia declared her independence in 
1847, Her Majesty's Government has frequently shown
its good will towards the Republic by rendering 
assistance and moral support in one form or another, 
and it was that Government that first entered into 
treaty relations with the Republic.</p>

<p>In view of the youth and consequent weakness 
of Liberia, and its exposure to encroachment on 
<catchwords>its</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150838"/>

its territory and rights by European powers, which 
circumstances engender a feeling of insecurity and 
apprehension on the part of the Government and 
people, that tends to check enterprise and to paralyze 
the energies of the country, and in view of the 
friendly interest and deep concern recently 
expressed by the Government of Her Britanic Majesty and 
that of the United States in the welfare and perpetuity 
of Liberia, the Government of that Republic
deems the present an opportune time to ask for 
closer relations with these countries hoping a 
convention may be entered into whereby Great Britain 
and the United States will jointly guarantee the
independence of Liberia and the integrity of its
territory, and Liberia concede in return, special 
privileges of trade and residence to the citizens of 
these Governments. It is hoped your Government 
will perceive the great advantage that will accrue 
from such a treaty as it will save Liberia from 
absorption by foreign powers and allow her to go on 
in the dissemination of the principles of Christianity 
and Republican institutions on the Dark Continent,
and aid the United States in solving the
perplexing "Negro Problem." Not, only this, such 
action would tend to give the United States an
influence in Central and Western Africa far beyond 
that of any of the European Continental powers.</p>

<p>The Republic with its rich and varied soil,
has great possibilities of trade and commerce, and 
there is an encouraging opening for the people, who
<catchwords>see</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150844"/>

see and seize the opportunity. It is a matter of 
regret that the commercial relations between the
United States and Liberia have not been more extended, 
and of more material advantage to both countries
in the past and it is hoped that such relations 
will be greatly extended in the future. 
Naturally the desire of the Liberians is that the 
benefits of their trade shall go to the people of 
the United States and Great Britain, who speak the 
same language and have the same religion, and with 
whom they have so many interests in common, and whom 
they have always looked upon in the past as their 
best friends.</p>

<p>I had the honor of an interview about a year
ago with Mr. Sherman, then Secretary of State, concerning 
the desires of my Government relative to 
the guaranteeing of its independence and the integrity 
of its territory by the Governments of the United
States and Great Britain, and soon after that 
interview I had the further honor of forwarding to 
Mr. Sherman a despatch on the same subject from 
Mr. Gibson, the Liberian Secretary of State. Mr. Sherman 
expressed himself as favorable to a convention with 
Great Britain for the purpose mentioned and there 
the matter rested while the Foreign office of Her 
Majesty's Government was approached. The representatives 
of Liberia visited the London Foreign office 
regarding the proposed convention and have stated 
the desires of Liberia, and Her Majesty's Government
has expressed its deep interest along the lines 
<catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170616_150849"/>

of the Pro-Memoria submitted by His Excellency, Sir
Julian Paunceforte, the British Ambassador, at Washington
on March 8, 1897, to the Honorable, the Secretary 
of State of the United States. It is hoped 
and believed that Her Majesty's Government will
consent to becoming a party to such a convention, but, 
it is thought, will not wish to take the initiative.</p>

<p>I now ask, at the request of my Government, 
that the United States Government take the initiative 
in inviting Her Majesty's Government to join in 
a treaty guaranteeing the independence of Liberia and 
the integrity of its territory, the Republic of Liberia 
on its part making certain concessions to 
Great Britain and the United States.</p>

<p>Hoping that your Government will be pleased
to favorably consider the request,</p>

<closer><salute>I have the honor to be,<lb/> 
Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,</salute> 
<signed>Chas Hall Adams.</signed></closer>
   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
