<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1350">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to John Hay, October 15, 1880</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1350</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to John Hay</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1880-10-15">October 15, 1880</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/28716749">Noyes, Edward F. (Edward Follansbee), 1832-1890</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</term>
<term>Thomas, William H.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Accra (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Bonny (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Lagos (Nigeria)</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>Whydah (Dahomey)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1880-10-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76456718">Hay, John, 1838-1905</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1880-12-02"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-02" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2323.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Dec 2 1880</note>

<p>No. 58.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, La, Oct. 15, 1880.</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to the Ass't Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Consulate of the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>Synopsis:</p>

<p>The importance of the direct exercise of a supervision over them.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2324.jpg"/>

<p>No. 58.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, La, Oct. 15, 1880.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to respectfully refer you to my No. 43, consular series, Dec. 12, 1879, in which dispatch I took occasion to call attention to the exercise of a supervision over our consulates on the West Coast. Allow me to recur briefly to the same subject.</p>

<p>Although the consulates on this coast are not, at present, of sufficient importance to guarantee the appointment of Americans to fill <catchwords>them</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. John Hay,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2325.jpg"/>

them of large ability, for the reason that they are feed rather than salaried offices; yet the necessity for their continued <sic>continued</sic> existence, will hardly be questioned, when it is remembered that African commerce, at this time, is but the commerce of the fringe, or outer edge of this richly fertile continent.</p>

<p>As explorations go on, and the interior trade shall be directed, and shall tend coastwise, our relation to the commerce maybe guaranteed.</p>

<p>Accra, Wydah, Lagos, Bonny, Gaboon and St. Paul de Loanda, are, as far as I am aware, without consular representatives. The last <catchwords>named</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2326.jpg"/>

named place, up to 2nd Aug. last, had not been visited by Mr. Thomas, the appointee.</p>

<p>While there is little difficulty in securing persons to hold consular positions, it is highly important that we have officials who are interested in the introduction of American productions and manufactured articles.</p>

<p>Europeans, have European interests to serve to the exclusion of American interests.</p>

<p>The native people, where they come in contact with Americans, like them, and prefer to do business with them, hence where the native African <catchwords>is</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2327.jpg"/>

is found to be competent to act as a consular officer, in the absence of an American resident, a wise discretion would dictate the selection of the native rather than the European who is not known to be interested in the advancement of American commerce in Africa.</p>

<p>The duty, is an important one, of visiting these places already mentioned; and others to which our vessels go, and to become familiar with the people, and commercial advantages of the coast.</p>

<p>The distance from the United States to West Africa, should be considered with relation to these consulates and prospective ones.</p> 

<p><catchwords>In</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2328.jpg"/>

In the language of the late Assistant Secretary, Hon. F. W. Seward, 'we need new markets, where the quality and price of our wares will insure ready sale or profitable barter'. Mr. Seward to Mr. Noyes, Foreign Relations, 1879, p'g. 343.</p>

<p>I would respectfully suggest that Africa affords the 'markets', and our consulates should constitute the gateways to them.</p>

<p>The supervision of the coast should be intrusted where the ability to perform the trust, in the interest of our commerce, resides.</p>

<p>With sentiments of highest consideration, I have the honor <catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2329.jpg"/>

to be, Sir,<lb/>
Your obd't serv't,<lb/>
Jno. H. Smyth, U.S.<lb/>
Consul Gen'l</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>