<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<pb facs="p0"/>
THIS BOOK IS DEDICATED 
TO
MANUEL GONZALES,
MY COMPANION AND PHOTOGRAPHER
UPON MY CONGO EXPEDITION 
AND TO 
OUR BLACK BOYS, MANOELI AND TUMBA

<pb facs="vii"/>
<pWhen I returned to America, I had decided 
to express no opinion upon the public and 
political questions of the Congo Free
State. Having found conditions there quite different 
form what I had expected, it was impossible for me 
to state my actual impressions without danger of 
anatagonizing or offending some whom I valued as 
friends. Hence, on landing at New York, I refused 
to say anything upon those matters to several report-
ers who interviewed me. A little later, the Chi-
cago Tribune asked me to write upon these subjects,
urging the importance of the whole matter to our 
nation, and leaving me entire freedom in viewpoint 
and mode of treatment. In response to its request, 
I prepared a series of articles, which appeared in suc-
cessive issues from January 20 to February 3, 1907.></pWhen>
    <pThe articles were received with general interest
only, and as I have much other Congo matter for 
books and pamphlets-- more directly in the line of 
my professional work-- I was inclined not to reprint 
them. But I soon found myself the subject of bitter 
attack. Malicious and untrue statements were 
made regarding me and my motives. I have con-

<pb facs="viii"/>
cluded, therefore, that it is best that my articles 
should be accessible to all who are interested. What 
I wrote, I am ready to defend. I am not ready to be 
judged from misquotations, or condemned for what 
I never wrote. Hence this book./>
    <p> I am not personally responsible for the title--
The Truth about the Congo. Alhough I believe all 
my statements are true, I should not have selected 
that title for my articles. No man can say all that 
is true on any subject, and I do not arrogate to my-
self a monopoly in truth-telling, either about the 
Congo or any other topuc. But after my announc-
ment under that heading, I decided to let it stand.
I preferred some less assertive title, but I am content.
So I use the same title for this book. The headlines 
of the articles, however, I have suppressed. They 
were not of my preparation and did not adequately
suggest the matter or the treatment. The articles 
are reprinted with no changes except corrections in 
spelling, punctuation, or mistaken words.</p>

    <p>No man more desires the happiness and progress 
of the Congo natives than do I. I know them 
pretty well. I am their friend; they are my friends. 
I shall be glad if what I here present makes them and 
their cause better known to thoughtful and sympa-
thetic men and women. Mere emotion, however vio-
lent, will not help them. Stubborm refusal to recognize 
and encourage reforms, which have been seriosuly 
undertaken for their betterment, will only harm them.</p>

<pb facs="1"
THE TRUTHABOUT THE CONGO
I.
January 20, 1907.

<p>My own interest in the Congo Free State began at 
the St. Louis exposition. As is well known,
that exposition made a special feature of groups
of representatives of tribes from various parts of the world.
These natives dressed in native dress, lived in native 
houses, and so far as possible reproduced an accurate pic-
ture of the daily life to which they were accustomed in 
their homes</p>

<p>Among the groups there brought together was one of 
Congo natives. This group was commonly known as the 
pygmy group, though but four out of the nine members 
composing it made claims to be such. The group was
brought by mr. S.P.Verner, at one time missionary to the
Congo, who was engaged by the exposition to make a 
special journey into central Africa to procure it. Four 
members of the group were Batua, the others were large 
blacks represneting the Bakuba and Baluba.</p>

<p>The idea of visiting Africa was one which I had never 
seriosuly entertained, but in the study of these Congolese 
it seemed to me that there were interesting questions the 
solution of which would well repay a visit. The conse-
quence was, that I determined to visit the Congo Free 
State-- and specifically that part of the state from which
these natives had been brought</p>

<pb facs="2"
    <p>About this time I received considerable literature from
the Congo Reform Association at Boston, the reading of
which had its influence in deciding me to undertake the 
expeidtion.</p>

    <p>After reading this literature I started for the Congo,
fully prepaed to see all kinds of horrors. I supposed that
mutilations, cruelties, and atrocities of the most firghtful 
kinds would everywhere present themselves. I expected
to find a people everywhere suffering, mourning, and in 
unhappiness.</p>

    <p>My errand, however, was not that of a searcher after
all these dreadful things, but purely that of a student of 
human races, with definite questions for investigation.
    I may say that my opportunities for forming an opinion
of conditions in the Congo have been exeptional. Mine 
was no hasty journey, but a tarry in the country extending 
over more than one year.</p>

    <p>While my original plan was to spend the greater portion
of my time in the district ruled by the Bakuba chief,
Ndombe, with but a short period in other parts of the 
state, I had decided before reaching the mouth of the 
Congo to more evenly distribute my time, and to see far
more of the Congo proper than I at first intended. As a 
consequence, I went first into the Kasai district, where I
spent four months, after which, returning to Leopoldville,
I went up the main river to the head of navigation, and 
even beyond, to Ponthierville, the terminus of the newly
built line of railroad. We also went up the Aruwimi, to
the famous Yambuya camp, where the navigation of that 
river is interrupted by cataracts.</p>

<ab>I have, therefore, seen not only the lower Congo, which</ab>

<pb facs="3"
<p>has been so frequently visited in recent years, but traveled
thousands of miles upon the great river and two of its most
important tributaries.</p>

<p>In this extended journey I came into constant contact
with representatives of the three groups of white men who 
live in the Congo Free State-- state officials, missionaries,
and traders. I had repeated conversations with them all,
and have heard opinions upon the Congo State from these
diverse points of view.</p>

<p>My position with reference to Congo matters is peculiar,
doubly so. I may even say it is unique. My journey was 
made at my own expense; I was not the representative of 
any institution, society, or body. I was without instruc-
tions, and my observations were untrammeled by any 
demands or conditions from outside.</p>

<p>While I am under many and weighty obligations to 
scores of state officials, missionaries, and traders, I am not 
prevented from speaking my mind in regard to any and 
every matter. Both to the missionaries, state officials,
and traders I paid board and lodging at every stopping
point-- with the single exception of one American mission 
station-- a fact which leaves me freedom. While the 
state faciliated my visit and my work in many ways, I was 
not, at any time, in relations with it of such a kind as to 
interefere with free observations or free expresion. I
made this entirely clear on my first visit to the state author-
ities at Brussels, and it was understood by them that I 
should speak freely and frankly of everything which I 
should see. On their part, the state authorities expressed 
the liveliest satisfaction that an idependent American
traveler should visit the Congo Free State, and said that</p>

<pb facs="4"
<ab>they did not wish anything concealed or attenuated, as 
they felt sure that such a visit as mine could only do them 
good.</ab>

<p>I have said that my position was doubly peculiar. I 
was not only independent and untrammeled in observation
and expression, but my personal attitude to the whole ques-
tion of colonizaion and administration by a foreign power,
of natives, is radical. Personally I dislike the effort to
elevate, civilize, remake a people. I should prefer to leave
the African was he was before white contact. It is my belief
that there is no people so weak or so degraded as to be 
incapable of self-government. I believe that every people 
is happier and better with self-government, no matter how 
unlike our own form that government may be. I feel that 
no nation is good enough, or wise enough, or sufficiently
advanced to undertake the elevation and civilization of a 
"lower" people. Still less do I approve the exploitation 
of a native population by outsiders for their own benefit.
Nor do I feel that even the development of British trade
warrants intereference with native life, customs, laws, and 
lands. I know, however, that these views are unpopular
and hertical.</p>

<p>In the series of articles, then, I have been asked 
to prepare, I shall try to take the standpoint of the practical
man, the business man, th man of affairs, the philanthro-
pist, the missionary. All these agree that civilized folk 
have a perfect right to interfere with any native tribe too
weak to resist their encroachment. They agree that it is 
perfectly right to trample under foot native customs, insti-
tutions, ideas-- to change and modify, to introduce inno-
vations, either to develop trade, to exploit a country, to</p>

<pb facs="5"
<ab>elevate a race, or to save souls. I am forced, then, to 
look at Congo matters from the point of view of these
eminently practical men.</ab>
    
<p>Of course, I saw much to criticise. It is true that there 
are floggings, and chain-gangs, 
and prisons in the United States. Mutilations are so rarw
that one must seek for them; abd I had too much else to 
do. There is taxiation-- yes, heavy taxiation-- a matter
which I shall discuss quite fully further on. And in con-
nection with taxiation there is forced labor, a matter which,
of course, I disapprove, but it appears as just to all the 
groups of eminently practical men to whom I have re-
ferred. There are, no doubt, hostages in numberS, but I saw
less than a dozen. And the whole matter of hostages is one
which merits careful and candid discussion. And I know
that in many a large district the population is much smaller
than in former times. The causes of this diminution in 
numbers are many and various, and to them I shall return.</p>
    
<p>Flogging, chain-gang, prison, mutilation, heavy taxa-
tion, hostages, depopulation--all these I saw, but at no
time and at no place were they so flagrant as to force them-
selves upon attention. And of frightful outrages, such as
I had expected to meet everywhere, I may almost say there
was nothing. It is, of course, but fair to state that I was 
not in the district of the A.B.I.R. I cannot believe, how-
ever, that conditions in that district are so appalling as the 
newspaper reports would indicate.</p>
    
<p>On the contrary, I found at many places a condition
of the negro population far happier than I had dreamed
it possible. The negro of the Congo--or Bantu, if you</p>
    
<pb facs="6"
<p>please-- is a born trader. He is imitative to a degree.
He is acquisitive, and charmed with novelties. He is 
bright and quick, remarkably intelligent. He readily
acquires new languages, and it is no uncommon thing to 
find a Congo Bantu who can speak six or seven languages
besides his own. In disposition variable and emotional,
he quickly forgets his sorrow. I saw hundreds of natives
who were working happily, living in good houses, dressing 
in good clothes of European stuff and pattern, and saving 
property. That this number will rapidly increase I have 
no doubt.</p>
    
<p>And now, on my return, after having many of my pre-
conceived ideas completely shattered, and feeling on the 
whole that things in Congoland are not so bad, and that 
improvement is the order of the day, I am startled to find 
the greatest excitement. Pages od newspapers are filled 
with stories of atorcities, many of which never happened, s
some of which are ancient, and a part of which, recent in
date, are true.</p>
    
<p>I find a fierce excitement about the Belgium lobby,
vigorous resolutions presented in the senate, and the Presi-
dent of the United States outrunning his most urgent
supporters and advisers, ready to take some drastic action 
to ameliorate the conditions of the suffering millions in the 
Congo Free State. The suprise is so much the greater,
as my latest information regarding the American official
attitude had been gained from the letter written by Secre-
tary Root some months ago.</p>

<ab>What can be the reason of such prodigious and sudden 
change?
What has happened in the Congo since April to produce</ab>
    
<pb facs="7"
<p>the present state of mind? What is the motive under-
lying the bitter attacks upon Leopold and the Free State
which he established? Is it truly humanitarian? Or
are the laudable impulses and praiseworthy sympathies
of two great people being used for hidden and sinister ends
of politics?</p>
    
<p>I do not claim infallibility. I do claim that my having
spent a year in the Congo Free State, independently, should
qualify me to express opinions on the conditions. I have
heard both sides. I have traveled thousands of miles in 
Congo territory. I have visited natives of twenty-eight
different tribes. No interference has been placed in my 
way. I have gone where I pleased, and when and how 
I pleased. No preparations have been made with refer-
ence to my visits. I believe no changes in practice have 
been produced by my presence.</p>
    
<p>In the series of articles before us it is my intention to 
present in detail what I have seen, and much of what I 
have heard, in the Congo Independent State. I may make 
errors, but I shall tell no intentional falsehoods. I shall
criticise what deserves criticism. I shall praise what is 
praiseworthy. I trust that those who are interested in 
forming a true idea of Congo conditions may find some-
thing useful in my observations.</p>
    
<p>At this point it is necessary for us to know something 
of the Congo native himself. In Dark Africa-- for north-
ern Africa is and always has been a white man's country--
there are three negro or negroid masses. There is little 
doubt that the original inhabitants of the continent were
dwarf people, ancestors of the pygmies of the high Ituri
forest, and the Batua of the upper Kasai.</p>
    
<pb facs="8"
<p>To-day the pygmies are mere fragments, scattered and 
separated, but retaining with tenacity their ancient life.
They are the same to-day as they were 5,000 years ago,
when they were objects of interest to the old Egyptians.
Little in stature, scrawny in form, with a face shrewd, cun-
ning, and sly, the pygmy is a hunter. With his bows and
poisoned arrows he kills the game of the forests and makes 
no pretense of doing aught in agriculture. He is univer-
sally feared by the large blacks in the neighborhood of
whose towns he settles. He trades his game for agricul-
tural products with his large neighbors.</p>
    
<p>In the Soudan and neighboring parts of western Africa
live the true negroes, notable for their thick lips, project-
ing lower faces, and dark skin.</p>
    
<p>Throughout southern Africa we find a group of popu-
lations much lighter in color, and on the whole more at-
tractive in appearance, than the true negro. These tribes,
plainly related in language, are no doubt of one blood, and 
are called Bantu. The name is unfortuante, as the word
bantu simply means "men" in that group of languages.
Practically the while of Congo population are Bantu
--there being almost no true negroes and but few pyg-
mies in the area.</p>
    
<p>It would seem as if the Congo native should be so well
known by this time that the current description of him in 
the text-books would be accurate; yet at least in two
respects, these stereotyped accounts are wrong. The 
Congo Bantu are not long-headed, and it is not true that 
they differ from the real negro in the absence of a charac-
terestic and disagreeable odor. There are scores of Bantu
tribes, each with its own language and minor peculiarities</p>
    
<pb facs="9"
<ab>in appearance and life. It would be untrue to say that all 
smell badly, but I have often wished the writers of the 
books could be shut up a while in the same room with, for 
example, a group of Bobangi. It is cetain that no type of 
African smells worse.</ab>
    
<p>It would be, however, a mistake to think that the Bantu
are dirty. Far from it. I have repeatedly observed my 
carriers, when we came to some brook in the forest, set their 
loads aside, strip themselves when necessary, and bathe 
in the fresh cool water. They are scrupulous in attention
to their teeth, and use, often several times a day, a little
stick of wood, somewhat larger than a lead-pencil, shred-
ded at one end, to clean their teeth. The instrument, by 
the way, serves its purpose far better than our own tooth-
brushes.</p>
    
<p>According to his tribe, the Bantu may be short, medium, 
or tall. King Ndombe of the Baakuba measures six feet
three in stature, and is well built, though not heavy.
Among the Bakuba, Baluba, Batetela, and Bakete, tall
statures are common. It is rare, however, that the Bantu 
present what we would call finely developed forms; their
chest is often flat and sunken; their shoulders not well
thrown backward; and the musculature of their back,
their chest, arms, and legs, is poor. Of course, there are
exceptions, and one sometimes sees magnificently devel-
oped specimens. In the lower Congo, where on the whole 
the men are shorter, they make excellent carriers. In the 
old caravan days the standard burden was sixty or seventy
pounds, and a man would carry it without diffculty all the 
working day. The Kasai tribes are poor carriers and 
indifferent workers. The chopbox of sixty pounds weight,</p>

<pb facs="10"
<ab>which the lower Congo man shoulders easily and carries
without complaint, will be slung to a pole to be borne by 
two carries among the Baluba.</ab>
   
<p>In life the Bantu populations, so far as the Congo is con-
cerned, present notable general uniformity. The general 
pattern is the same everywhere, though there are local
and tribal differences of minor sort. Thus, almost every
tribe has its own tribal marks cut into the flesh of face or 
body.</p>
    
<p>Simiarly, the members of one tribe may be distin-
guished by their mode of dressing the hair. To a less
degree, the form to which the teeth are chipped and broken
mark tribal differences. It may almost be said that no 
two tribes in all the Congo build houses that are just alike,
and almost every tribe has irs characteristic mode of ar-
ranging the houses in a group. Thus, in one tribe the 
houses will be arranged in continous lines, one on each 
side of a straight road; in another the houses may be 
grouped around the three sides of a square, the group
belonging to a single chieftain and being succeeded in the 
village by other similar groups of buldings; in another 
the houses will be arranged in two curved lines, leaving the 
open space in the center of the village oval or elliptical.
The chairs or stools of one tribe will differ in form and 
decoration from those of another; so will the wooden 
spoons, the stirring-sticks, the combs, the dress and orna-
ments.</p>
    
<p>The Congo natives for the most part still lead a tribal
life. A chief is the head of a little community clustered
about him. He may not be the chief of a whole village;
for example, at Bomanih, on the Aruwimi, there are three</p>
    
<pb facs="11"
<ab>chiefs. Each one has his own cluster of houses, and though
the three clusters are arranged continuously in two, parallel, 
straight lines, every native of the village knows precisely
where the domain of the individual chiefs ends or begins.</ab>
    
<p>The power and authority of the chief has been greatly
weakened by contact with the whites, but he still retains
great influence. At least over the members of his own
household, including, of course, his slaves, he had the 
power of life and death. In large affairs, interesting a 
considerable number of people, he usually acted on the 
advice and opinion of his fellows as expressed in a village
or tribal palaver. The chief was, and still is, distinguished 
from the common people by his dress and ornaments.
He is usually a man of wealth, and has a considerable 
number of people actually dpeendent upon him, subject 
to his orders, and a force upon which he can depend in
case of war or trouble.</p>
   
<p>When I first entered the Congo my heart sank, for it 
seemed as if the native life was gone. In fact, in letters 
written from Matadi I doubted whether I had not come 
too late for aught of interest.  My spirits began to 
revive, however, with the railroad journey from Matadi
to Leopoldville. Groups of natives, with scanty dress and 
barbaric ornaments, replaced those who at Matadi and its 
neighborhood gathered at the station to see the train pass.</p>
    
<ab>In my first walk from the mission house where I lodged
at Leo, within three minutes' walk of the mission I found 
a little cluster of Bateke houses which, with its inhabi-
tants, much delighted me.</ab>
    
<p>Almost naked women, the abundance of beads and 
teeth hung at their necks as ornaments, with hair elabo-</p>
    
<pb facs="12"
<ab>rately dressed and bodies smeared with red camwood
powder, squatted on the ground, were making native 
pottery in graceful forms</ab>
 
<p>In the shade in front of the door of one of the houses
was a true barbarian, lord of the place. By rare good 
luck he spoke a little English, so that we were able to carry 
on a conversation. When I asked him who the women
were, he replied that they were his wives. I think there 
were three of them, and it was my first introduction to 
African polygamy. Each of these  women occupied a 
separate house. Each of them had a garden patch in 
which she worked. All of them contributed to the im-
portance and support of their husband.</p>
    
<p>Polygamy, of course, prevails throughout Dark
Africa. But do not misunderstand me. I do not use 
the word "dark" to characterize polygamy. It is a 
settled insitution which seems to work quite well. Later
on I saw the wives of Ndombe, thiry-four in number.
Ndombe is a really important chief, but compared with 
some whom we met or of whom heard in the Upper 
Congo, he was but scantily equipped. Sixty, seventy, a 
hundred, or hundred of wives and female slaves, which
count for much the same, are in possession of great chief-
tains. There is, of course, always one favorite or principal
wife. When Ndombe used to come, as he frequently did,
to my house to see the stereoscopic pictures, he frequently
brought his favorite wife with him. She was a pretty
creature--young and plump, graceful and modest.
She wore good cloth and any quantity of beads and brass
arm and leg rings.</p>

<ab>In every case the women of a chief or rich man live in</ab>
    
<pb facs="13"
<p>separate houses, each having her own. Until a man is 
married he is but little thought of. The greater the num-
ber of wives, the more important he becomes. As 
each one cultivates a field and does other productive 
labor, it will be seen that the man with the most wives
is the richest man.</p>
    
<p>The man has his own house, but visits and lives in the 
houses of his wives in turn. The child in Africa is rarely 
weaned before it is two or three years old, and during the 
period of time when a child is unweaned the father has no 
marital relations with the woman. On the whole, there is 
less quarreling among the wives of a polygamic husband
than one would expect. Bantu women, however, are often
termagants, as women elsewhere, and at times the chief's
house group is lively.</p>
    
<p>Domestic slavery still flourishes. The state, of course,
has done much to end the actual slave trade for supplying
white men and Arabs. It is, however, diffcult to deal 
wot the matter of domestic slavery, and in fact is scarecely
worth the candle</p>

<p>Every chief or man of any consequences has slaves.
Calamba, my interpreter, at Ndombe, though a young
fellow, probably not more than 25, had two. It is rare
that the lot of the domestic slave is unhappy. It is usually
women or children who are brough, and they are treated
in all respects as if members of the family. Little is re-
quired of them in the way of work and service, and they 
must absoultely be provided for by the master, who is 
also frequently responsible before the public for their
misdeeds. Formerly, of course, there was the possibility
of being killed upon a festal occasion, the accesion of the</p>

<pb facs="14"
<ab>chief to increased power, or to grace his funeral. Within
those districts where the state has a firm hold and strong
influence this possibility is done away with, and the most 
seripus diadvantage in being a slave is thus removed.
Slves may become rich men, and no infrequently them-
selves hold slaves.</ab>

<p>Perhaps the most striking characteristic of the Bantu,
as of the true negro, is his emotionality-- one instant
joyous, the next in tears. Vowing vegeance for an in-
jury to-day, he is on the happiest terms with his injurer
to-morrow. He laughs, sings, dances. Of all the in-
troductions of the white man, perhaps the accordion is the 
favorite. Men use it, but women play it constantly.
Most of them play one song piece only, and one may 
hear it from one end of the state to the other at every 
hour of the day and night. Of course, there are native 
instruments in plenty, drums of every size and form, from 
the small hand drum, made by stretching a skin across an 
earthern pot three or four inches in diameter, up to the 
great cylindrical, horizontal drum made by hollowing
logs a yard in diameter and ten feet long. There are horns,
fifes, pipes, and whistles, and a great series of stringed
instruments, ranging from the musical bow with but one
cord to lutes with ten or twelve. Of course, the instru-
mental music goes with the dancing.</p>

<p>The native is born to dance. Babies, two or three
years old, dance with their elders. Men dance together;
women have their special forms; but in the majority of 
cases the two sexes dance together. There is, however,
nothing like our waltzes or round dancing, individuals 
keeping themselves separate. The dances are most fre-</p>

<pb facs="15"
<ab>quent and lively when the moon is growing. On moon-
light nights hundreds of people-- men, women, and chil-
dren-- gather at dusk, and to the noise of drums dance 
wildly, often till morning. It is no uncommon thing for
people working on plantations to work all day and dance
almost all night, and this day after day. While some of 
the dances are extremely graceful, most of them are ob-
scene and are followed often by frightful orgies.</ab>

<p>One thing greatly interested me. Had I been asked 
before my trip to Africa about the cake-walk-- a form of 
amusement which I love to see--I should have said that 
it originated in America among the black folk of our 
southern states. But no, the cake-walk is no American 
invention. In every part of the Congo one may see it--
even in regions where white influence has seldom pene-
trated. The American cake-walk is an immigrant.</p>

<p>The Bantu child is wonderfully preocious. This 
precocity displays itself in everything. The children run 
about with perfect freedom, instead of tottering along, one 
unsteady step after another, as our children of the same
age. They speak astonishingly soon. A babe in arms
eats solid food-- notwithstanding the fact that it is not 
weaned until two or three years of age-- shockingly early.
The little child imitates the every action of its older
friends. Children of four or five, in shrewdness, com-
prehension and intelligence, are like our ten-year-olds.
This precocity suggests the fact of early ripening. As a
fact, boys of sixteen and girls of thirteen are frequently 
ready for marriage. A man of twenty-five is in the prime 
of life, a man of thirty aged, and on the whole the term
of life closes at thirty-five.</p>

<pb facs="16"
<p>Life is easy in the tropics. Wants are few. A 
house to live in can be built in a few hours. Food
can be gathered or produced with little labor.
Dress is needless. Where life is easy there is little im-
pulse to labor.</p>

<p>The chief incentive to the Bantu to work is secure
the wherewithal to buy a wife. The boy, who, through a 
careless, happy childhood, has done naught but play,
begins to think of settling down. But to have a wife he 
must have money or its equivalent. So he goes to work.
It may require a year or more before he has the pieces of 
cloth which are necessary for the purchase of his desired
loved one. The same stimulus which impelled him to 
labor for one wife may prod him to efforts for others. But
with the establishment of a home, and the purchase of two 
or three wives to care for him and produce him wealth, his 
work is done. From fourteen years to twenty-fivr is his 
working period. Before that time a child, after that time 
he is a man of means. What wealth comes later comes
through the women and their labor, and through trade.</p>

<p>We have already stated that the Bantu is notably
acquisitive. Wealth, apart from women and slaves, is 
counted mostly in cloth. One of the chief aims in life is 
to accumulate cloth, not for use as clothing, but as evidence
of wealth and for the final display when the man dies and 
is buried. Among the Lower Congo tribes the dead body 
is wrapped in piece after piece of cloth, until the body 
disappears in a mass of wrappings made of scores of pieces,
each piece consisting of eight or sixteen yards, as the case</p>

<pb facs="17"
<ab>may be. Young men have cloth, and it is most interesting 
to look through the boxes of the "boys." At Basoko we 
were robbed, and the authorities instituted a search. I
was asked to inspect the boxes of all the workmen on the 
place. Without warning, every man and boy had to open 
his trunk, chest, tin box, or other store. I saw young fel-
lows of no more than sixteen or seventeen years who had a
dpzen pieces of good cloth carefully folded away, watches, 
jewelry, ornaments, knives, dishes-- every kind of white 
man's tradestuff that could be imagined. When they are
thirty those "boys" will be rich men, with womn, slaves, 
and piles of stuff.</ab>

<p>The government of the Free State has issued coins for 
native use. There are large coppers of the value of one,
two, five, and ten centimes. There are silver coins of half-
franc, franc, two franc, and five franc value. But these
coins have no circulation beyond Leopoldville. In the 
Kasai district and the Upper Congo every commercial
transaction is done by barter.</p>

<p>Certain things are so constantly in use as to have fixd 
values. For articles of trifiling value nothing is so good as
salt. A standard which varies from plave to place is the 
brass rod, or mitaku. This is simply a piece of brass wire
of certain length. The mitaku in the Lower Congo are
short, those in the Upper Congo much longer. Beads
have ever been used in trade, but the wise traveler avoids 
them, as their value has dwindled, and the taste not only
varies from place to place, but from time to time. The 
bead which one traveler found useful in a given district
may have lost its attractiveness before the next traveler,
loaded with a large supply, comes that way.</p>

<pb facs="18"
<P>At Ndombe the brass rod has no vogue. There the 
cowries (sea shells) are the standard in small transaction.
Cowries were once used in many parts of Africa, but in 
most places have ceased to have value. Ndombe, how-
ever, arrogates to himself and family the sole right of wear-
ing brass arm and leg rings. Hence mitaku are not used,
and the old-fashioned cowry remains. But the chief
tradestuff, of course, is cloth. With it you may buy
chickens or goats, pigs or wives. In the Upper Kasai a 
piece of cloth means eight yards-- "four fathoms." In
the Upper Congo a piece of cloth is sixteen yards, or eight
fathoms. Formerly at Ndombe eight or ten chickens
were given for a piece of cloth, value five francs, or one 
dollar in our currency. To-day one must pay a fathom
for each fowl.</P>

<p>The attempt to introduce the use of coin among the 
natives was unsatisfactory alike to the people and the 
trader. It hasm however, taken hold strongly in the Lower
Congo, and in time the use of true money must push its 
way up the river. Curious is the contempt of all for cop-
pers. Ten centimes in Belgim would give delight to many
a boy of twelve or fifteen years. The Congo mative fre-
quently throws it away or returns it to the person who 
gave it to him. Nothing less than a half-franc piece--
ten cents--is valued.</p>

<p>I have seeb this illustrated many, many times, the first
time in my own case. We were visiting a miserable fish-
ing village of poor Bakongo. As I entered the village a 
naked child, no more than two or three years old, met me.
I smiled at hime and he at me. I extended my hand, which 
he clasped and accompanied me for half an hour as I</p>

<pb facs="19"
<ab>wandered from house to house, never once relaxing his 
hold upon my fingers. It casued great amusement to the 
adult portion of the village, as apparently the little one
rarely made such friendships. When I was about to leave 
I took a ten centime piece from my pocket and gave it to
him. Such a look of disgust came over his face would 
not be expected in any one short of adult years. It was
the last time that I gave a copper to a native.</ab>

<p>Unquestionably one of the most striking characteristics
of the Congo people is loquacity. Their tongues hang 
loosely, and wag incessantly. Anything will do to talk
about. tart one and he will talk until you stop him.
Quarrels, troubles, friendships, joys, plans, and achieve-
ments, all are retailed at any hour of the day or night.
When excited, several will talk together with great vivacity,
though it is plain that no one knows what any other is 
saying.</p>

<p>One of the chief occupations of the man is the palaver.
The Portuguese tern applies to any serious consultation
on any subject, pleseant or otherwise. A palaver may be 
confined to chiefs or it may include practically all the men
of one or more villages. In many towns there is a place
for gathering for palavers under a tree known as the pa-
laver tree. Those who participate in a palaver bring their
chairs or stools or a roll of skin, which they place upon the 
ground to sit upon. At the beginning there is more or less
formality, and each one presents his view decently and in 
order; sometimes, however, hubbub ensues, disturbance
arises, and the palaver breaks up in disorder. In these 
palavers frequently speeches of great length and finished
oratory are delivered. not only are the emotions played</p>

<pb facs="20"
<ab>upon by the speaker, but keen argument is employed, and 
the appeal is made to the intelligence.</ab>

<p>All matters of consequence-- tribal, intertribal, and
dealings with the white man--are settled in palavers. The 
white man who knows the natives is wise to conform to
native customs. If he has some diffculty to settle, some 
favor to ask, some business to arrange, he will do well to 
have a formal palaver called in which he himself partici-
pates.</p>

<p>On the occasion of my second visit to Ndombe I found 
the town in great excitement. Going to the chief's head-
quarters, we found a great palaver in progress. Our com-
ing was looked upon as a favorable omen, and with much 
formality chairs were brought and placed for us in the
midst of the gathering. The remarks were translated to 
me as they were made.</p>

<p>Ndombe's town is really an aggregation of vilages.
Not one but four different tribes are represented in the
population. The central town, walled and of Bakuba
style, was Ndombe's own. Three or four Bakete towns
were clustered near it. In another direction were several
Baluba towns, and close by them small villages of Batua.
These four populations, though living by themselves, were
all subject to Ndombe, and the group of villages taken
together made a town of some pretension.</p>

<p>The day before our visit, there had been a battle with 
the Bakete in which several men had been wounded,
though none were killed. The trouble was taxes. The
state demanded increased payments. The proud Bakuba
decided that the Bakete should pay the new tax, and so 
informed them. Against this there had been a feeling of</p>

<pb facs="21"
<ab>rebellion, and the Bakete refused to pay the tax. Hence
the battle. All were greatly excited. The speeches were 
full of fire. The men--Bakuba--challenged each 
other to show mighty deeds of valor; they belittled and 
derided the unfortuante Bakete; they drew unpleasant
contrasts between themselves and their vassals.</ab>

<p>Many of the speeches were fine efforts, and the words
were empahsized by the most graceful and vigorous gestic-
ulation. Finally an old woman crowded in from one side 
where she had been listening to the speeches. In impas-
sioned language she described the heavy labors which the 
women of the tribe already endured. They could stand 
no more. If the Bakuba were men let them prove it now 
or forever after remain silent. Force the Bakete to work.
Put no more heavy tasks upon your mothers, wives, and 
Sisters. The old woman's speech stirred the audience, and 
the meeting broke up, the men hurrying to prepare them-
selves for a new battle.</p>

<p>The market was among the most important institutions
of the Congo native. It retains importance to the present
day. In the Lower Congo a week consisted of four days,
and market was held at each market-place once a week.
The markets were named from the day of the week on 
which they were held. Thus, a Nsona market was a 
market held on the day of that name.</p>

<p>To these markets people came in numbers from all the 
country round and it was no uncommon thing to see
thousands thus gathered. There were special places for 
certain products. Thus, women who brought pottery for 
sale occuplied a set place; those who brought bananas
would be grouped together in their section; sellers of cam-</p>

<pb facs="22"
<ab>wood, sweet potatoes, kwanga (native cassava bread),
palm wine, oil, salt, fowls, pigs, goats--all occupied
places well known to the frequenters of the market. In
the olden times, of course, there was a section devoted to 
the sale of slaves.</ab>

<p>Such a market presented a scene of active life and 
movement. Yet order was preserved. No crime was 
considered more serious than the disturbance of a mar-
ket. Such an act deserved severst punishment, and 
those in whose hands the maintenance of order lay never
hesitated to kill the offender at once, and to make a public
display of his punishment as a warning to all.</p>

<p>There is no question that the Congo native is cruel, and
this cruelty shows itself in many ways. The killing of 
slaves was extremely common. It is true that it was never 
carried to the extreme in Congoland that it reached in
some true negro kingdoms, as Dahomey and Benin. It 
was, however, customary to kill slaves on the occasion of 
the death of a man of any consequence. The body of one 
of the slaves thus killed was placed first in the grave to 
serve as a pillow for the dead man. It was a common 
practice to preserve the skulls of victims sacrificed on 
such occasions as memorials.</p>

<p>Not only were slaves sacrificed to grace the funeral 
ceremony of chiefs, but often one or more were killed upon
occasions of festivity and joy. King Ndombe once pre-
sented me a skull. It was that of a Batua slave who had 
been killed upon the occasion of the chief's coming into
power. In this case, apparently, judging by the condi-
tion of the skull, the victim had been killed by simply
knocking in his head.</p>

<pb facs="23"
<p>Until lately all through the Congo public executions 
were of a more formal character than this. At Lake 
Mantumba we were shown the exact mode of procedure.
A sort of stool or seat was set upon the ground and sticks
were tightly driven in around it, in such a way as to limit
the motions of th vicitm after he was seated; in fact, to 
almost prevent all movement. A sapling was then thrust
in the ground. A sort of cage or framework made of pliant
branches was fixed about the head of the victim. The
sapling was then bent over in an arch and firmly fastened
to the cage, thus holding the head firmly and stretching
the neck tense and hard. The hands were tied together,
as were the feet. When all was ready the executioner
with his great knife at a single blow struck off the head.</p>

<p>Enemies killed in battle were often mutilated, and 
fingers, nails, bones, or the skulls were treasured as tro-
phies. When the white men first visited the villages of 
the Upper Congo there was scarce a house without its
ghastly trophy, and the houses of greats chiefs displayed
baskets filled with skulls.</p>
   
<p>It is doubtful whether the Congo native has as keen
a sense of physical suffering as ourselves. In almost every
tribe men and sometimes women, are marked with tribal
marks upon the face or body; thus, among the Bangala
each member of the tribe bears a projection like a cock's
comb running vertically across the forehead from the nose 
root to the hair line. This excrescence is frequently
three-quarters of an inch in breadth and of the same eleva-
tion. Its development begins in childhood, when a series
of short but deep horizontal lines are cut in the child's
forehead; these are irritated to produce swelling; later</p>
    
<pb facs="24"
<ab>on they are cut again, and again, and again, until the 
full development is produced. We should certainly find 
such an operation painful in the extreme. I have seen 
women whose entire bodies were masses of raised pat-
terns, produced by cutting and irritating.</ab>
    
<p>When being operated upon the subject usually squats 
or lies in front of the operator, who sits cross-legged on
the ground. The head or other portion od the body which 
is being cut rests upon the lap or knees of the cutter. No
particular pain is shown by the  subject, though the cuts
are often deep and blood flows copiously. A few minutes
after the operation, smeared with fresh oil on the wounds,
the scarred person walks about as if nothing had happened.</p>
    
<p>The first subject that I saw treated for rheumatism was
a youbg woman. She was standing before her house 
door, while the old woman who was treating her was
squatted on the ground before her. In her hand the old
woman had a sharp, native razor, and with it she cut lines
several inches long and to good depth in the fleshy part of
the leg of her standing patient. Not once nor twice, but 
a dozen times the old woman cut, and rubbed in medicine
in the open wounds. The patient gave but little signs of
pain. Once or twice she winced as the knife went a little 
deeper than usual; she held a long staff in her hand, and 
in te most serious moments of the cutting she clutched
it a little the tighter. But there were no groans, no cries,
nor tears. I have never seen a white person who could
have stood the operation with so little evidence of suf-
fering.</p>
    
<p>Part of the time that we were in Ndombe's district we
had charge of an establishment employing 140 natives,</p>
    
<pb facs="25"
<ab>more or less. Among these natives wa sone Casati. I 
think he was a Zappo Zap. Originally a man of quick-
ness and intelligence, he had become a complete physical
wreck through drink and other forms of dissipation. He
boarded with a girl named Tumba. One afternoon
they presented themselves before me with a palaver. It
was some question in regard to payment and service.
Like most Bantu difficulties, its beginning seemed to 
extend backwards to the world's creation.</ab>
    
<p>I knew Tumba to be a worthy and industrious girl;
Casati was a miserable and worthless wretch. I therefore
refused to decide the difficulty, stating that the parties
interested must wait until the return of the true owner of 
the establishment, who would decide their question.
This was not at all to the satisfaction of Casati, who,
merely to show his dissatisfaction, took a sharp knife and 
cut three big gashes in his own shoulder. It seems plain
to me, from this apparent lack of pain under scarring,
medical treatment, and self-infliction, that there is a nota-
ble difference between the Bantu and ourselves.</p>