<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1128">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Ezekiel E. Smith to Alvey A. Adee, January 3, 1890</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1128</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Ezekiel E. Smith to Alvey A. Adee, January 3, 1890</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 5</biblScope>
<date when="1890-01-03">January 3, 1890</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Fuller, Alice</term>
<term>Yates, Sarah C.</term>
<term>Cooper, Emma A.</term>
<term>Davis, William M.</term>
<term>Howard, Thomas W.</term>
<term>Leone, Louis R.</term>
<term>Leone, Louisa</term>
<term>Fuller, Anna W.</term>
<term>Rowell, Maria Z.</term>
<term>Daylas, John B.</term>
<term>Cand, Robert</term>
<term>Daylas, Mary</term>
<term>Gibson, Joseph M.</term>
<term>Perkins, N. L.</term>
<term>Porter</term>
<term>Braxton</term>
<term>Nimms</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Charleston, South Carolina</term>
<term>New York</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Ezekiel E.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consular General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1890-01-03"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Adee, Alvey A.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Second Assistant Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1890-02-08"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-09-21" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll5-2109.jpg"/>

<p>No. 49</p>

<p>DEPARTMENT OF STATE
FEB 8 1890
RECEIVED.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,
Monrovia, Liberia, January 3rd, 1890</p>

<p>Mer. Ezekiel E. Smith
To the Deartment of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Last WIll and Testament of Mers.
Alice Fuller</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2108.jpg"/>

<p>No 49</p>

<p>Consulate General of the  United States,
Monrovia, Liberia, January 3rd, 1890</p>

<p>Honorable Alvey A. Adee,
Second Assistant Secretary,
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:
I have the honor respectfully to
acknowledge the receipt of your No. 9.
Despatch of November 16th 1889, instructing
me to procure a copy of the "Last
Will and Testament" of Alice Fuller,
who died in this city in the month
of June 1888.</p>

<p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>

<p>Ezekiel E. Smith
U.S. Consul General</p>

<p>Enclosures One.
Copy of the Last Will
and Testament of Mers Fuller.</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2111.jpg"/>

<p>In the name of God Amen I Alice Fuller of the City
of Monrovia County of Mentserrad, and the Republic
of Liberia being of Sound disposing mind but
feeble in body do make public and declare
this to be my Last Will and Testament in Mannes
fallowing.</p>

<p>1st After all my just debts and funneral expenses are
paid, I give and leave my half lot on Broad
Street in the city of Monrovia to Clara Fuller
Weaver wife of Kincoln Napolion Weaver. to her and
her heirs forever, free from all control or disposal
of her husband. to have and to hold the same to
her and her heirs forever.</p>

<p>2nd I give and devise to Mrs Sarah J Woods wife
of Tyson Woods of Cape Palmas, one of my Town
Lots located if one collection <unclear></unclear> in the town
of Greenville Senoe County to have and to hold
to her and her heirs forever ____ and
I give an devise the other two lots located
in said Greenville, one to my dear friend Emma
A. Cooper and the other to my dear friend
Sarah C. Yates to have and to hold the said
prperty to each in Severalty to them and their heris</p>

<p>3rd I give and bequeath to Benjamin V. R. Melville, all
my <unclear></unclear> and Tethle to the house in Front Street
in Monrovia that yours now having built and I also
give and bequeath to him two hundred dollars
in order to help him to finish siad house--
(over).</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2112.jpg"/>

<p>4th I have Several orders coming out from America
and England and when they come and are
disposed of I give and bequeath an
equal share of the proceeds to the Saia B. V. R. Melville
Arna U. Fuller his mother, my friend Sarah C.
Yates, and my friend Marla Q Pervell's and
a <unclear>Ration</unclear>of said proceeds I wish to go to my
friend Mrs Braxton Bath fifty six dollars
of the money in these orders belong to Anna
W. Fuller and the above devision of proceeds
cannot be made until after her said money
are deducted out of the proceeds.</p>

<p>5th I give and bequeath all my new goods now
in the house where I am living to my friends
Anna W. Fuller, B. R. Melville, <unclear>Mara Q Povell</unclear>
Sarah C. Yates and Mrs Braxton to be divided
in equal shares to all except Mrs Braxton
who is to have a lesser share than the others.</p>

<p>6th I give and bequeath to my dear friend Emma
A Cooper my <unclear>Large Shin case</unclear>now in her
posession, and anything else of mine that
she may want; and also my Seales.</p>

<p>7th I give and bequeath to my friend Y. C. Dickens
my small seales now in his possession</p>

<p>8th I have (eighteen hundred dollars) $1800
now in the East Brooklyn Saving Bank
which I wish the <unclear>moneis</unclear> there on interest
for two years after my death, at which time
I want it divided and I give and bequeath
(over)</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2113.jpg"/>

<p>out of said money (Five hundred dollars) to my
afflicted Sister Mary Daylan residing in
Charleston South Carolina, and I request
Messers Yates and Porter feild of 59 South SA New York
who now have my <unclear>Deposet</unclear> Book in their
presence to find out my said sister and pay
over said money to her in person or to her
<unclear></unclear> representation, and to my nephews
Robert Cand, John B. Daylan of the City of Washington
D.C. M.S. A. I give and bequeath two
hundred dollars ash out of said money
to be paid to them by Messers Yates &amp; Porter field,
and I give an bequeath to Mary M. Denglass
wife of Robert I. Darylass my brother one hundred
dollars $100 out of said money, and mt of the
remainder of said money I give and bequeath
to my friend Maria Z Rowell one hundred dollars
and to my friend Sarah C. Yates one hundred dollars
and to my friend Emma A Cooper One hundred dollars
and to my friend Anna W Fuller one hundred dollars
and alos one hundred dollars to my friend B. R. Mehills
also fifty dollars to my dear friend Mrs Ninmms-
also I give to Joseph M. Gibson Fifty Dollars
also to Mary Euphemia daughters of W M &amp; E. S. Davis
Fifty dollars to Mary McIntosh daughter of
Anna V. Houston I give Fifty dollars and to
Louisa Leone daughter of the lat Louis R Leone
I give Fifty dollars also I give fifty dollars
to my friend Thomas W Howard
(over)</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2114.jpg"/>

<p>I give and bequeath the above Several Sums
of money to the Several persons above named
in the order named the above erasure and
after <unclear>Alive over</unclear> made before this was signed
Y name Wm M. Davis and Bey V. R. Mellville
to be Executives of this my last will and Testament.</p>

<p>Monrovia June 14th 1888 (Signed) Alice Fuller</p>

<p>Signed Sealed and delivered in presence of us
and declared by the said Alice Fuller to be
her last will and Testament in presence of us
who at our names as witnesses</p>

<p>Emma A Cooper
Sarah C. Yates</p>

<p><unclear></unclear> copy from the original the
2nd day of Jany 1890
N. L. Perkins
<unclear></unclear></p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>