<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0002">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Henry M. Turner, "Letters of Bishop Henry M. Turner" (1892)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0002</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Letters of Bishop Henry M. Turner</title>
<author n="Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915">Henry M. Turner</author>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
<date when="1892-04">April 1892</date>
<biblScope unit="page">446-498</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionary Activity</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Amos, W. H.</term>
<term>Arnett, Benjamin William, 1838-1906</term>
<term>Barboza, Mary Garnett</term>
<term>Barclay, E. J.</term>
<term>Baumgarten, P. M.</term>
<term>Bergstrester, Edwin</term>
<term>Bibbs, M. L.</term>
<term>Blarbubber</term>
<term>Blyden, Edward W.</term>
<term>Bolden</term>
<term>Bonnefoy</term>
<term>Bowser, Bolding</term>
<term>Bowser, G. E.</term>
<term>Bransoulie</term>
<term>Brown, H.</term>
<term>Bruce, B. K.</term>
<term>Campbell, Jabez Pitt</term>
<term>Campbell, S. J.</term>
<term>Cartright</term>
<term>Cheeseman, J. J.</term>
<term>Clark, Alexander</term>
<term>Clark, Payne</term>
<term>Clark, Robert J.</term>
<term>Clarke, Alexander</term>
<term>Coker, Daniel</term>
<term>Coker, Henry</term>
<term>Coker, Hillery T.</term>
<term>Coker, Isaiah</term>
<term>Coker, Jane</term>
<term>Coker, Susan</term>
<term>Cold, I. H.</term>
<term>Coleman, W. D.</term>
<term>Columbus, Christopher</term>
<term>Cooper, Henry</term>
<term>Cooper, J. R.</term>
<term>Coppin, Levi Jenkins, 1848-1924</term>
<term>Corzan, Phoebe</term><!-- formerly: Deputie, Phoebe Brown -->
<term>Crowther, Samuel</term>
<term>Daniels, G. S.</term>
<term>Davis, W. M.</term>
<term>Decker, George D.</term>
<term>Dennis, J. B.</term>
<term>Derrick</term>
<term>Dickinson, J. C.</term>
<term>Dixon</term>
<term>Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895</term>
<term>Deputie, James H.</term>
<term>Eljen, Kobbena</term>
<term>Elliott, Scott</term>
<term>Ficklin, Samuel</term>
<term>Ficklin, Stephen</term>
<term>Finch, William</term>
<term>Frederick, John R.</term>
<term>Gaines, John W. (John Wesley), 1860-1926</term>
<term>Garnett, Henry Highland</term>
<term>Geda, T. R.</term>
<term>Gibson, Garrison W.</term>
<term>Gould, Theodore</term>
<term>Greer, Hannah</term>
<term>Grimes, H. W.</term>
<term>Hamilton, Alexander</term>
<term>Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901</term>
<term>Hay, David</term>
<term>Hay, James H.</term>
<term>Hopkins, M. A.</term>
<term>Irons, Clemmons</term>
<term>Jackson, Elizabeth</term>
<term>Johnson, I. M.</term>
<term>Johnson, H. R. W.</term>
<term>Kenny, A. H.</term>
<term>Kimball, H. J.</term>
<term>King, C. T. O.</term>
<term>Lamadon</term>
<term>Lamprey, J. J.</term>
<term>Lincoln</term>
<term>Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865</term>
<term>Melin, Emanuel</term>
<term>Moore, H. J.</term>
<term>Moore, June</term>
<term>Newland, Matthew</term>
<term>Parsons, C. L.</term>
<term>Patterson, James D.</term>
<term>Patterson, William</term>
<term>Payne, Daniel A.</term>
<term>Perry, F. B.</term>
<term>Pierson, A. T.</term>
<term>Randolph, J. W.</term>
<term>Richmond, Herbert H.</term>
<term>Roach, David B.</term>
<term>Roberts, William</term>
<term>Robertson, Scipio H.</term>
<term>San u Si, Alpha Mahomed</term>
<term>Sedgewick, John Edmond</term>
<term>Sharp, Jennie</term><!-- maiden name: Davis -->
<term>Sharp, Jesse</term>
<term>Sherman, R. A.</term>
<term>Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891</term>
<term>Slack, J. Bradford</term>
<term>Slocum, James</term>
<term>Smart, William G.</term>
<term>Stanford, A. L.</term>
<term>Stanford, Willie Francis</term>
<term>Steady, H. M.</term>
<term>Stephens, M. S.</term>
<term>Stephenson</term>
<term>Stewart, A. L.</term>
<term>Stewart, T. McCants</term>
<term>Tanner, Benj. T. (Benjamin Tucker), 1835-1923</term>
<term>Taylor, William</term>
<term>Thomas, Matthew</term>
<term>Travis, H. W.</term>
<term>Turner, David M.</term>
<term>Turner, Eliza Ann</term>
<term>Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915</term>
<term>Tyler, Abram</term>
<term>Ware, D.</term>
<term>Whittingham, William Henry</term>
<term>Williams, H. A.</term>
<term>Winchell, Alexander</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abilene (Kan.)‏</term>
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Alabama</term>
<term>Alabama River</term>
<term>Arthington (Liberia)</term>
<term>Ashland (Liberia)</term>
<term>Atlanta (Ga.)</term>
<term>Barbados</term>
<term>Barnsville (S.C.)</term>
<term>Baton Rouge (La.)</term>
<term>Bay of Biscay</term>
<term>Boporo (Liberia)</term>
<term>Brewersville (Liberia)</term>
<term>Caldwell (Liberia)</term>
<term>Carrysburg (Liberia)</term>
<term>Charleston (S.C.)</term>
<term>Chattahoochee River</term>
<term>Chicago (Ill.)</term>
<term>Cincinnati (Ohio)</term>
<term>Clay (Liberia)</term>
<term>Columbia (S.C.)</term>
<term>Cork (Ireland)</term>
<term>Delaware River</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Freetown (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Funchal (Madeira Islands)</term>
<term>Georgia</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Gold Coast</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Canary (Canary Islands)</term>
<term>Gunpowder River</term>
<term>Harrisburg (Liberia)</term>
<term>Helena (Ark.)</term>
<term>Hudson River</term>
<term>Illinois</term>
<term>Indiana</term>
<term>Iowa</term>
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Jacksonville (Ill.)</term>
<term>Kansas</term>
<term>Lagos State (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Las Palmas (Canary Islands)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>London (England)</term>
<term>Los Islands (Guinea)‏</term>
<term>Louisiana (Liberia)</term>
<term>Louisville (Ky.)</term>
<term>Madeira Islands</term>
<term>Marseille (France)</term>
<term>Memphis (Tenn.)</term>
<term>Mesurado River</term>
<term>Millsburg (Liberia)</term>
<term>Minnesota</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Morrilton (Ark.)</term>
<term>Mount Mesurado</term>
<term>Muhlenberg (Liberia)</term>
<term>Nebraska</term>
<term>New Georgia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Newfoundland (Canada)</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>New York (Liberia)</term>
<term>New York (N.Y.)</term>
<term>Niger</term>
<term>North Carolina</term>
<term>Ohio</term>
<term>Ohio River</term>
<term>Pan Pedro River</term>
<term>Paris (France)</term>
<term>Philadelphia (Penn.)</term>
<term>Pine Bluff (Ark.)</term>
<term>Porto Santo Island (Madeira Islands)‏</term>
<term>Queenstown (Ireland)</term>
<term>Richmond (Va.)</term>
<term>Rokel River</term>
<term>Savannah (Ga.)</term>
<term>Savannah River</term>
<term>Sherbro River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Skipton (England)</term>
<term>South Carolina</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>St. Paul (Minn.)</term>
<term>St. Paul River</term>
<term>Stockton Creek</term>
<term>Tenerife (Canary Islands)</term>
<term>Tennesee</term>
<term>Tennessee River</term>
<term>Texas</term>
<term>United States</term>
<term>Upper Caldwell (Liberia)</term>
<term>Vicksburg (Miss.)‏</term>
<term>Virginia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
<term>Webster Grove (Mo.)</term>
<term>White Plains (Liberia)</term>
<term>Wisconsin</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Akoo</term>
<term>Ashantee</term>
<term>Cosso</term>
<term>Ebo</term>
<term>Fullah</term>
<term>Gullah</term>
<term>Kromantie</term>
<term>Kroo</term>
<term>Limba</term>
<term>Mandingo</term>
<term>Mendi</term>
<term>Pessa</term>
<term>Portuguese</term>
<term>Sherbo</term>
<term>Timnee</term>
<term>Vey</term>
<term>West Indian</term>
<term>Yennie</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>African Methodist Episcopal</term>
<term>Anglican</term>
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Free Methodist</term>
<term>Islam</term>
<term>Lutheran</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
<term>Roman Catholic</term>
<term>Wesleyan Methodist</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>Akoo</term>
<term>Arabic</term>
<term>English</term>
<term>French</term>
<term>Fullah</term>
<term>German</term>
<term>Greggree Bush</term>
<term>Italian</term>
<term>Kroo</term>
<term>Mandingo</term>
<term>Portuguese</term>
<term>Spanish</term>
<term>Su Su</term>
<term>Timnee</term>
<term>Wahoma</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-22" who="kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p445" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Letters of Bishop Henry M. Turner.</p>

<p>Written During His Visit to Africa.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Steamship "City of Paris," October 15, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I am out on the ocean sailing—or rather steaming to all
human appearances—to the unknown—where?</p>

<p>I left the great city, New York, yesterday about two o'clock,
with peculiar sensations.</p>

<p>I had long contemplated a trip to Africa, the world's future
paradise, but had never realized what it was to start. I never
dreamed that it would take the starch out of a fellow as it did
me.</p>

<p>The hurly-burly of preparation and the desire to leave absorbed 
every faculty of my soul, but when I mounted this
mighty sea craft and looked down upon the faces of Rev. Theodore 
Gould, Dr. Derrick, the presiding elders Morgan and Israel
Derricks, and several other ministers who stood with upturned
faces; also Mrs. Dr. Derrick, Mrs. Bolden and a number of
ladies, all of whom waved handkerchiefs at me as the ship
steamed out, I began to realize that this was more than an ordinary 
trip to some portion of our common territory.</p>

<p>Mrs. Dr. Derrick touched me when she threw her handkerchief 
to her eyes; but the thought rushed to me—that is
womanish, and I tried to dismiss it, but in a moment my eyes fell
upon my son, David M. Turner, who had come from Washington 
city to see me off—despite the fact that I had told both sons
to attend to their business, and not spend money to bother after
me. David, however, ignored my order and came any how, and
as I espied him looking up wistfully and then dropping his head,
my emotions reached their culmination, all my manhood succumbed 
and tears suffused my face; I loved David as I never
dreamed of before. The other children appeared before me in
detail, and the thought rushed upon me, "Mother is gone, wife
is gone, and now possibly children are gone." My mind flashed
through the Church, and an inkling of dislike here and there, I
had indulged, owing possibly to misunderstanding in most instances, 
all fled, and I found myself loving everybody I had left
behind. I never loved in all my life as I did then, and do now,
and expect to while I live.</p>


<pb xml:id="p446" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.002.jpg"/>



<pb xml:id="p447" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.003.jpg"/>



<p>Some four hours after we left New York, one of the ship's
officers appeared in my state-room and told me to follow him,
and he led me to a saloon state-room, which he told me was to
be mine, single and alone. It possessed every comfort the mind
of man could conceive.</p>

<p>Its furniture and conveniences looked to me to be too superb
to be risked upon the water, but the thought struck me, it's no
more valuable than the thousand or more persons on board—not
the one millionth part so valuable.</p>

<p>The ship rocked and rolled a little last night, but not from the
effects of any wind that blew; the sea-swells were the result of a
gale, which soon subsided. Many persons, however, cascaded a
little, but it only sharpened my appetite.</p>

<p>This morning at the breakfast table, a gentleman in my front
called my name in a clear voice and said, "Good morning!" I
looked up and it was H. J. Kimball, the man who built the great
Kimball House, of Atlanta, Ga. Mutual congratulations were
passed at meeting at the same table at sea, if not on land. Much
of the day has been spent in conversation with this great financier. 
He paid many compliments to Bishop Gaines, Alexander
Hamilton, the famous house-builder, William Finch, tailor, and a
host of colored men of Atlanta.</p>

<p>About two o'clock to-day our ship overtook the steamship
"Germanic," which left New York four hours ahead of us yesterday. 
We ran side-by-side for some time, but the "Germanic"
had to yield to the great speed of this large ocean greyhound.</p>

<p>Elder Geda, who is with me, and is in another cabin not quite
so well furnished, has made more acquaintances than I could
make in a week. He disregards introductions, knows everybody 
because they are human, and everybody knows him.</p>

<p>The ocean, which has behaved so well ever since we left the
city, is being lashed into fury by a rising wind, but the ship runs
steadily, and before the big waves come I will go to bed.</p>

<p>October 16.</p>

<p>The breeze calmed down last night, and I slept like a log. This
morning the sun is shining in his splendor, and while the ocean
surface was throbbing with the pulsations of life, the mammoth
ship strode its way like a thing of life also. Two steamers
bound for New York appeared in the distance, one in the
forenoon and the other in the afternoon.</p>

<p>Yesterday, up to twelve o'clock, we had come 312 miles, and
to-day up to the same hour, 427 miles. Some of the officers are
mad because we did not make 500 miles.</p>

<p>I had a long talk with Col. Jas. D. Patterson, of Richmond,
Va., to-day. He is a rich tobacco merchant. He paid Dr. Derrick 
a marvelous compliment, and poohed at the idea of any one
attempting to criticise him while at Richmond, Va.</p>

<p>About one o'clock a school of porpoises or cetaceous sea-hogs


<pb xml:id="p448" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.004.jpg"/>



appeared near the ship, and leaped and frollicked for an hour.
All eyes were fastened upon them till they disappeared in the
distance. Shortly after a flock of what is called Mother Carey's
chickens, flew along just above the water surface, and many predicted 
a storm, but no storm has arrived up to ten o'clock to-night.</p>

<p>A gentleman from New York, said to be worth one hundred
and fifty thousand dollars, is a steerage passenger, and has
dressed himself quite coarsely to keep from attracting attention;
but some of the saloon passengers know him and such a cursing
as he gets is non-repeatable. A gentlemen said, he loved money
too, and was almost a miser, but such miserliness as that was a
shame to humanity.</p>

<p>It has been very warm, but it grows chilly as we approach the
Newfoundland coast.</p>

<p>October 17.</p>

<p>This morning was chilly and misty, and the sea a little
rolling, but everything is pleasant and inspiring. Congratulations
upon such a fine trip so far are abundant. The ship is so long
and reaches over so many of these short waves that no one
realizes that the sea is not smooth when inside.</p>

<p>A whale was seen in the distance this morning, rising up and
spouting water, but soon disappeared.</p>

<p>At twelve o'clock to-day we had come 437 miles since yesterday 
at the same hour.</p>

<p>A little before midday four small boats were passed, floating
around in ocean, said to be fishing crafts, yet hundreds of miles
from the banks of Newfoundland. I would be afraid of those
little boats on the Potomac River, much less on the great ocean.
Rev. T. R. Geda has made an ocean of acquaintances, and an
Englishman offers him a position in the salvation army in London;
he leaves it with me as to whether he shall accept it or not.
I told him I would not release him from accompanying me to
Africa, unless they wanted him to beat the drum for the army.
We have had a delightful trip up to the present, but the wind
is rising and to-morrow is predicted a bad day.</p>

<p>October 18.</p>

<p>The wind is blowing stiffly and the ship rocks lively. The
white-capped waves chase each other grandly. Divine service
was called at 10.30 o'clock, but nothing was done or said, save
the captain reading the English prayer service; as the writer did
not think he could stand to speak intelligently while the ship
was rocking; the other ministers thought the same. "O, ye of
little faith!" At 12 o'clock we had come 436 miles.</p>

<p>October 19.</p>

<p>The wind increased yesterday afternoon and last night. A
mighty wave dashed over the lower pass-way of the ship at 3
o'clock in the afternoon, and knocked down a dozen men and five
ladies, and drenched them from head to foot.
Some time after,




<pb xml:id="p449" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.005.jpg"/>





I went strolling back to the upper deck of the second cabin, 
to view the sea from the rear of the ship, when a giant wave swept
over with a vengeance and I escaped by jumping behind the
kitchen house. Some of the officers of the ship made me hustle
back to the saloon; as I came within ah inch of being washed over
in mid-ocean. A terrific sea struck the ship about 7 o'clock and
she rocked as though every moment would be the last. I leaped
to my feet frightened. The passengers laughed by the scores
and tried to comfort me by telling what sights they had seen and
passed through safely. I tried to make out like I was not
frightened much, but I believe I was. I sat about with my heart
in my mouth, and finally went to my state-room and committed
my all to God. I told the Lord if my trip to Africa was in
keeping with his will, to remove this fear and put me to sleep.
I had hardly arisen from my knees when all fear was gone, and,
notwithstanding the gale that blew and the screeching of the
ship's timbers, I was scarcely in bed before I was asleep.</p>

<p>This morning, when I arose at 9 o'clock, I knew the ocean
was rough, for the ship seemed to be laboring for life. I dressed
and went out, and, oh, heavens, what a sight! As far as the eye
could scan, mountain waves were rolling in matchless grandeur,
between which great valleys lay, more or less undulating, till
another surging billow rolled across the plain and sent its spray
skyward. Old "Neptune," the ocean's god, had been using
wind withes to lash the blue waters, and they were churning out
foam jewels as ornaments to his brow, and throwing misty vessicles 
to weave rainbows to crown it; for they were abundant in
the northeast. But the scale turns to-day. Yesterday, when
I got frightened, several passengers laughed, but nearly every
one of them is scared or sick. I am neither, thank God. Some
are saying the ship can't stand it; others say nothing, but are
fearfully alarmed. I feel to be in God's hands and am cool,
cheerful and happy. Indeed, there is no time to be frightened
when such superb grandeur meets the eye in all directions. Up
to 12 o'clock to-day we had come 421 miles—marvelous running
for such a gale; fortunately, however, the wind and mighty waves
were mostly in our rear. But this mighty ship being 580 feet
long, 62$ feet wide, 2,000 horse-power, 10,500 tons burden, has
on board 1,225 persons. A ship passes on the left, going to New
York, but she is small, light, and rides the mountainous billows
like a duck. The captain of our ship comes into the smoking
saloon and sits down; a number gather around him and inquire
about possibilities of the storm allaying: he tells them it will 
increase for some hours yet, but he laughs at any one apprehending
danger. He says this little shake-up is mere child's play, that
the ship is built with twelve compartments and any one or even
two might fill up and the ship could not sink. The ladies of the
saloon cabin go to their state-rooms, the ladies of the second
cabin sing, the ladies of the steerage sing; the men of the steer-



<pb xml:id="p450" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.006.jpg"/>



age play cards and sing some of the sweetest hymns I ever heard.
I never knew before that men could gamble and sing so solemnly.

Everybody nearly is inclined, more or less, to some kind
of game on ship.</p>

<p>October 20.</p>

<p>Last night, as the captain said, the wind got worse and worse,
till about n o'clock, when it blew terrifically. I think it must
have blown 70 miles an hour. I looked out upon the fearful face
of the great deep, and the scene beggared description, but our
herculean vessel was riding like a master. Some said they had
crossed the ocean dozens of times, but had never seen anything
like this. Elder Geda, who had been to Spain and had seen such
mighty seas, had to give it up. A gentleman who had gone with
General Grant around the world, had never seen the sea worse.
But the more it blew and raged the more contented I felt. I
tried to get up a scare once to make me pray more earnestly, but
could not for my life. I went to bed quietly, slept like a log,
awoke this morning, the sun was shining, the winds had stopped,
the ocean was calming down and the fuss all over. Everybody
was out for breakfast and congratulations upon our safety were
mutual.</p>

<p>I have had no sea-sickness whatever, have always been ready
to eat, yet many have cascaded fearfully.</p>

<p>The Negro question has been discussed in all forms since we
left New York. The mark of Cain, the curse of Noah, the color
of the devil, the Negro in history, his place in science and 
philosophy, the unity of the human race, his future in the South, 
his status in the nation, and all such subjects have been dissected
God has helped me to make some of our learned American wise-
acres laughing-stocks in the eyes of Englishmen. It is astonishing 
to see how little some of our would-be great and wise white
men know about the Negro, his ability, his progress, his books,
newspapers, churches, home tastes, etc. Mr. Kimball makes the
Negro of the South a mighty man. He puts it on thicker than
I can; when he starts, I hold up: he needs no help.</p>

<p>We are fast approaching Queenstown, where I may mail this
letter. Old ocean is as quiet as a lamb. All the decks and
walks on the ship are crowded with gentlemen and ladies, pacing
backward and forward, resembling a picnic festival. Bishop
Tanner and the late Bishop Campbell are the most frequently
inquired for.</p>

<p>The rise and progress of the A. M. E. Church, as given by the
writer from time to time, is an item for much comment and high
congratulations. Our bishops, general officers and ministers
would be gratified to hear what is said complimentary to our
ecclesiastical independency, even by members of the M. E.
church.</p>

<p>Bishop Arnett's great speech at Washington was the subject
of many compliments, also.</p>




<pb xml:id="p451" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.007.jpg"/>




<p>Second Letter.</p>

<p>Steamship "City of Paris," October 21, 1891.</p>

<p>Last night, after closing my other letter, a Chicago gentleman,
who had watched the meteorological changes with cautious
interest, came and sat down by my side and said, "We are all to
go down to night." I asked him—go down where? He said to
the bottom of the ocean; that he had just looked at the barometer 
and it was very low. He was terribly excited and tried to
excite everybody else, but the passengers laughed at him and
called him a crank. Supper being over, the saloon was cleared
for a concert, and was soon packed to witness the display of
talent. The actors were improvised, however, for the occasion,
yet several were professional singers, readers, speakers, etc. The
programme ran as follows: 1st, piano duet; 2d, recitation, by
Dr. J. Bradford Slack, B.A.; 3d, violin solo, by Miss Dixon; 4th,
song, by Payne Clark; 5th, recitation, by Mrs. A. L. Stewart;
6th, "Emperor William's Visit to the Vatican," by Very Rev. P.
M. Baumgarten, LL.D.; 7th, song, by Miss Lincoln; 8th, reading 
from "A Dream," by Rev. A. T. Pierson, D.D.; 9th, "My
country, 'tis of thee," by Miss Lincoln; 10th, "God, save the
Queen," by Mr. Clark. The whole affair was of a very high
order. As for Mrs. Stewart's recitation, which was novel, from
the fact it was historical, one cannot tell half of its superbness.
She simply beat anything I ever heard. When she began, I said,
"O, you go along, Hallie Q. can beat that;" but, as she waxed
warm with her subject, I had to say, "Well, Hallie, I fear she
has got you."</p>

<p>But about 9 o'clock, as our Chicago weathercock had predicted, 
a gale struck the ship, blowing seventy-five miles an hour.
She careened from side to side for awhile. Several looked unusually 
white, but they sat still. One of the gentlemen cried out,
"All's right, we have one of the best ships on the ocean and one
of the best captains to manage her." I soon left, however, went
in my state-room and held a private interview with Captain God.
The wind howled for a short time, then subsided. I went to
sleep and was awakened this morning to look at Queenstown,
Ireland. We were safely in the harbor and nothing hurt. Our
Chicago man, however, left the ship, and said he would take the
cars through Ireland for Liverpool, as he knew another gale
would strike us while running down the Irish Sea. He was mistaken, 
however, as we found the Irish Sea as calm as a lamb.
The passengers were all glad when the Chicago man left, and
thought if they had thrown him overboard in mid-ocean we
would have had a finer trip.</p>

<p>With my large marine glasses I had a fine view of Queenstown,
and, during the day, of over two hundred miles of the Irish
coast. Queenstown did not nearly meet my expectations in size
and grandeur. Standing upon a declivitous elevation not over a
mile in length, with one large Cathedral, some smaller churches,




<pb xml:id="p452" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.008.jpg"/>




school-houses and several blocks of antiquely built houses,
covered with tiles, etc. But the Irish coast, minus trees, presented 
a most magnificent spectacle. My glasses brought distant
fields and far-off houses and sceneries to view so vividly that it
was a charm for me, and I did not wonder that no snake could
live there, yet some few snaky Irish have come to America I am
compelled to admit.</p>

<p>Our ship has reached the Liverpool bar, but must wait here till
12 o'clock to-night before she can enter, as the tide is too low to
cross. The passengers are sitting out, talking, singing, looking
at the lights, viewing tug-boats pass and congratulating each
other upon our safe arrival. I am bored with invitations to visit
gentlemen and ladies in London, Yorkshire, Cork, Paris and
other points. It turns out now, as we are across the ocean, that
we had some mighty men on board, but they kept so quiet that
no one but the clerk knew it, and he was ordered not to tell. I
must go to bed; sleepy.</p>

<p>October 22.</p>

<p>The ship was in the docks of Liverpool when I awoke this
morning. The gong rings, and we are all glad that breakfast will
be tendered; we feared that we would get none. We eat like
hungry wolves and are arranging to leave the ship. Mr. Kimball
passes me and says, "See here, Bishop, you cannot afford to be
small over here; you must give your state-room steward ten
shillings, your dining-room steward ten shillings and the porter
ten shillings. I asked him how much ten shillings were. He
said two dollars and a half. I frowned, but he said, "No use to
frown: it counts up, but you must stand it or be set down as
small." I came to time.</p>

<p>Disembarkation soon followed, and we were ushered into the
custom-house, where the examination of our trunks took place,
and such a scene beggars description. Some laughable things
transpired. My trunks were passed by. One man started to
investigate them, but another said, "Let him alone; didn't he tell
you he was going to Africa? Let him take anything to Africa
he wants; they need it there."</p>

<p>Elder Geda and myself took a carriage for the Session Hotel,
right in the heart of Liverpool. In front stood the towering
monument of Wellington, a little further the great building
known as St. George's Hall, just to the right the mighty art
building, and to the left the Technological building, etc. A
surging mass of humanity was moving in every direction. The
tunic-uniformed and helmet-headed police were plentiful, it is
true, but unlike our American police, not one had a club or a
billy or a pistol about him. All the use they had for hands
were to put them in their pockets. They say the American
police are a set of brutes, and I about agree with them.</p>

<p>An English lady, at the dinner-table, became greatly smitten
with my hair to-day, stroked it back and said she almost be-





<pb xml:id="p453" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.009.jpg"/>




grudged it to me. I told her thousands of our people in America
called my hair bad. She said, tell them they are foolish.</p>

<p>They have the largest horses in Liverpool my eyes ever beheld;
they can pull the heaviest burdens I ever saw. Some of their
feet look like bushel tubs.</p>

<p>The general intelligence of the people is far ahead of our
people, and no wonder; every night there are lectures upon
every subject the mind of man can contemplate—astronomy,
geology, botany, natural history, conchology, water, smoke, 
continents, mountains, valleys, clouds, anatomy, physiology, lice,
spiders, whiskey, eatables, shipping, trees and everything. Elder
Geda and I heard a Roman Catholic Priest lecture on botany
with masterly ability this evening, yet not a cent was charged at
the door; all these lectures are free to the public. I have told
our young ministers for years, to learn to lecture; that our race
will never be anything till they do so. I am now satisfied, as
never before, that I was right. These lectures are attended, too,
not by the finely attired only, but by the laboring people. But,
to cap the climax; after the lectures, theaters and churches close,
the people by thousands upon thousands gather in all the large
city squares, and, unless too cold or rainy, sing some of the
sweetest hymns ever heard on earth. Men, women, children,
strangers, all join in, till the melody of the song literally 
reverberates through the city! They bring organs into the streets 
and somebody plays while the people sing for about an hour, then
all go home to bed. I never dreamed that such procedure
existed this side of heaven. I have been preaching for years
that the mission of the Gospel is the heavenization of earth, and
now I am sure my position is correct, if I ever had any doubt
before.</p>

<p>Elder Geda and myself went down this afternoon and looked
at an African ship which will leave Saturday, 24th inst., for the
places of our destination. The ship is called the "Roquelle."
We met several native Africans from Sierre Leone, of the Crew
or Kroo tribe, who know Brother Frederick, and when they
were told by Elder Geda that I was going there, they laughed
and shook my hand for joy. They said, "We been look for ze
long time." The Crew tribe seems to be a superior class of men.
Their heads are round, symmetrical and frontly high; only one
cephalic cranium of the six, and not a receder in the number.
The ship "Roquelle" is rather small, but they say she rides old
ocean like a duck. At all events we shall try her Saturday
morning at ten o'clock. Several white African merchants are
here, and I find them a little tainted with color-phobia, as Bishop
Tanner calls it These Africans say: "He not act so in our
country."</p>

<p>I am urged to remain over and speak on Sabbath, and to visit
London and other points of interest, but I prefer to proceed to
Africa.</p>


<pb xml:id="p454" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.010.jpg"/>


<p>October 23.</p>

<p>Last night several gentlemen called into the hotel parlors, and
we talked till 12 o'clock. We discussed the McKinley bill at
great length. They told me how it affected England, and how
many manufacturing places it had closed. I gave them to
understand that somebody had to be affected, and that free tariff
or no tariff would close up our manufactories by the scores, and
Great Britain could endure it as well as we. I never let on to
them that I did not care three cents about it, one way or the
other, but I do not; as it is all white man any way, yet as they
thought I was a big factor in the matter, I let it go so.</p>

<p>I have traveled through the city to-day considerably, but to
attempt a detailed account of my observations would be an effort
of folly; I might as well try to describe creation as to describe
my observations to-day, on the docks, the ships, historic halls,
monuments, art scenes, relics, books, manuscripts, mementoes,
furniture, paintings, vehicles, etc.</p>

<p>I looked and reasoned about my race, noted how far we are
behind, and the possibilities of continuing there, and got sick,
went to my hotel and fell over in bed and dreamed of earthquakes, 
till my dead wife appeared and said, "Wait, God will
wake our people up from their slumbers by-and-by."</p>

<p>A gentleman from Ireland wishes Elder Geda and myself to
visit him. He said, "We have some colored Negroes over
there, who are very nice people." Geda laughed, I winked at
him to stop; the man meant all right I never thought of the
term, "colored Negroes," before, but it fits in correctly in many
instances, I confess.</p>

<p>Before closing this letter—as we shall leave for Africa in the
morning, for I had rather see Africa than London and Paris put
together. I wish to express my gratitude to Mr. William Henry
Whittingham and his cultured wife, of Skipton, Yorkshire, England, 
for kind attention and valuable information since we have
been in the Session Hotel. They are stopping here only, true,
but they know all about the country.</p>

<p>Third Letter.</p>

<p>Steamship "Roquelle," October 24, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>When I last night wrote to you, I was in the Session Hotel in
Liverpool; now I am crossing the Irish Sea, inclining southward,
bent upon Africa as my point of destination.</p>

<p>The ocean is quite calm and the hope is we may have a quiet
sail, notwithstanding the rage which ships have encountered for
the last three weeks. One African ship which left Liverpool
some days ago, had to return, owing to the unusual winds and
heavy billows.</p>

<p>I had some long interviews with the leading merchants of
Liverpool, and with men who manage iron ships by the scores,



<pb xml:id="p455" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.011.jpg"/>



and the Lord Bishop, as the writer was called, was heard with
great eagerness. What may follow I dare not indicate at present, 
but the writer is offered more than he would think of accepting.
I am cabined with a regular African, and without doubt he is
one of the most learned men I ever met. His name is Matthew
Thomas, of Lagas, West Coast; black as ink, reads and talks
English, French, German, Italian and Spanish; reads Greek,
Latin, Hebrew, Syriac and Arabic, and virtually talks Latin. He
took up the New Testament this afternoon, and found out I had
been reading some Latin, and he read it awhile and quoted so
much Scripture in Latin and Greek that I had to go to nodding
to get him to stop. Talk about the African being ignorant; here
is one who has no superior for book learning in our country, yet
he is only 37 years of age. Everything involving book learning
he seems to be the master of. If it was not for my knowledge
of science and transcendentalisms, I would be afraid of him, but
while he runs away from me in books, I can hold him a little in
theories. But for the fact he takes his toddy when he feels like
it, I should urge that he be invited to a chair of languages
in some of our colleges. He however holds a commission in
his pocket which might prevent him from accepting.</p>

<p>I am surprised at the number of African ships running out of
Liverpool, yet they cannot accommodate the trade and passengers.
 This ship is crowded to density with passengers.</p>

<p>They are building a number of other larger ships for the trade.
The African Steamship Navigation Company, of which the Roquelle, 
(this ship) is one, has fifty-three steamships in the African
trade, besides what Germany, France, etc., have running there.</p>

<p>Europe has about eighty steamships hugging the African
coast the year round, yet our country cannot find employment
for one. But English merchants soon will if contemplated
measures are not foiled.</p>

<p>October 25.</p>

<p>This is Sabbath again and I am out on the deep blue waters.
Divine service was held to-day at 10.30 o'clock. Elder Geda
and myself took part. The sun shines with splendor and the
ocean is quiet. We are verging the Bay of Biscay; some fears
are entertained of a little rough weather, but the captain says
not. Elder Geda sang a number of old-time hymns this evening to 
the pleasure of all who heard them. Rev. John Edmond
Sedgewick, D.D., of the English Church, is "a passenger to one
of the islands; he is a man of rare learning in theology, yet he
is high church to kill. Edwin Bergstrester, M. D., of Abilene,
Kan., United States, is also a passenger on the ship and is en
route for the Madeira Islands.</p>

<p>October 26.</p>

<p>The wind rose last night and the sea was quite ugly this morning
We were almost to the Bay of Biscay and considerable uneasiness




<pb xml:id="p456" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.012.jpg"/>




existed as to the possibilities of encountering a gale while 
crossing that rough arm of the ocean, for the Bay of Biscay is 
always disorderly at best. About 12 o'clock we entered the bay. 
Elder Geda suggested that we go and pray for God to quiet the 
winds. We went. Shortly the wind quieted down. Whether God
heard his or my prayer I cannot tell. The captain said that
after 12 o'clock the winds would calm any way. The ocean is
somewhat undulating, but this is said to be indigenous to the
bay.</p>

<p>Dr. Sedgewick, after scanning cursorily "Methodist Polity,"
thinks the A. M. E. Church has the best machinery for the
African mission work of any church in Christendom. He is
amazed at such a church among the people of African descent.
He is also surprised that the author of the work on the "Relation 
of Baptized Children to the Church," by Dr. L. J. Coppin,
should be a black man.</p>

<p>I am becoming accustomed to ocean life. At first the rocking
of the ship was rather annoying, but it is now pleasant; one can
sleep so comfortably in the rolling cradle of the sea. They all
say I am a fine sailor, but had they known my fright for two or
three times at first, they might not have been so complimentary.
I was quiet, but looking heavenward in earnest.</p>

<p>October 27.</p>

<p>We had a grand time last night. Right in the Bay of Biscay
everything was as calm as any one could wish; all day we have
had the same. There was a considerable sensation about 3
o'clock, when the engine stopped and smoke was seen rushing
out of the engine room. But it turned out to be a hot shaft
only, which was soon cooled off.</p>

<p>A small boat passed us to-day with two little sails, skipping
nicely over the water a thousand miles from land. Several birds
came last night and took up their abode upon the ship and have
remained with us all day, flying off and on again. A pet goat
is on the ship, which is the playmate of every one; his instinct
about gales and storms is better than the captain's barometer.
Dr. Stephenson ought to be here to direct his morals. When I
reached Liverpool I found that Philadelphia time was five hours
behind; as I move southwestward I see another change is
taking place.</p>

<p>October 28.</p>

<p>The ocean is smooth as glass. Our ship glides along like a
creature of life. The passengers sit on deck, read, sing, play the
piano and organ, talk, walk and sleep.</p>

<p>We are gradually approaching the Madeira Islands, which is
a great health resort; there are people on the ship from various
parts of the world, bound for these islands, for the benefit of
their health. As we approach the south the sun becomes more
vertical in the heavens, and new stars appear which I never saw




<pb xml:id="p457" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.013.jpg"/>





before. I have not seen the Southern Cross yet, a sight I have
desired to see for many years; it cannot be seen from the United
States.</p>

<p>To-day at 12 o'clock we were in latitude 39 degrees, 44
seconds north, and in longitude 13 degrees west; so you see we
are a long way from home.</p>

<p>I have not had the least sea-sickness yet; they say my
stomach is iron-clad.</p>

<p>I had a hearty laugh at an African to-day, who bought a new
pair of pants and tried to put them on while lying down.</p>

<p>Elder Geda has opened a school for the seven illiterate Africans 
on the ship.</p>

<p>October 29.</p>

<p>The ocean is still quiet; scarcely a ripple can be seen upon
the great expanse of the deep waters, except what is made by
our ship as she curls the waters behind her.</p>

<p>About 10 o'clock to-day an American steamship from New
York passed us, going to somewhere, but no one knows where.
I was glad to see our flag, while I knew that there was not a star
in the galaxy that recognized the manhood of her black inhabitants.</p>

<p>I overheard a conversation to-day going on between a number
of whites, English, Welsh, Portuguese, etc., and they all decided
that Africa was forever doomed; that white men could not well
live there and the black man, whether in Africa or elsewhere, was
a failure. They could not understand why God should give the
Negro the richest spot on earth, and that her people should be
the poorest specimens of humanity in the world. They reasoned
the Negro out as fit for nothing but to play, idle, drink whiskey
and steal from the white race. After they had concluded I
stepped out and met every argument advanced, and told them
what I had seen black men do, and while they might steal from
white men, they did not steal from each other in Africa, as the
whites who lived among them in Africa had to admit.</p>

<p>Mr. Matthew Thomas holds that all races started black, and
presents a powerful argument in the maintenance of his position.
I told him that the learned Professor Winchell had been dismissed 
from Vanderbilt University, Tenn., for advancing that
doctrine. Mr. Thomas sprang to his feet, and with many gesticulations 
and, indeed, with some genuflection, exclaimed,
"Winchell is right; right, I say; yes, he is a scientist and a 
philosopher of the first type." Mr. Thomas reasons so masterly
upon this ethnological postulate that I am almost a convert.</p>

<p>One of the native Africans employed on the ship and the
chief cook (white) had a big row to-day; the cook struck at the
African twice, but the African did not dodge worth a cent, stood
cool and awaited the blow of his assailant, which was not given.
The African said, "Tu lu shu sa moot boo." I asked one who
could speak English what he had said; he replied, he said "If
that man struck him he would throw him in the ocean."</p>



<pb xml:id="p458" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.014.jpg"/>


<p>The days and nights are almost equal in length here; one or
two more days' sail and they will be equal. We are overtaking
the sun, it seems.</p>

<p> We are now one hundred miles from the Island of Madeira,
where I shall mail this letter, so I close, and will let you know
about the island in my next.</p>

<p>Fourth Letter.</p>

<p>Funchal, Madeira Island, October 30, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I closed my third letter last night when within a hundred
miles of the Madeira Island, where I mailed it this morning.</p>

<p>Early this morning Elder Geda called me and said, "Get up
and see a sight." I feared it was something of a distressing nature,
as the tail end of a heavy squall had struck the ship at four
o'clock, but reposing in the consciousness that I was in God's
hands, I had fallen asleep again. I got up, however, and walked
out upon the deck; and such a scene as met my eye no pen can
picture! Thirty miles in front stood the Island of Madeira, with
its sunlit brow reaching 6,000 feet into the heavens; all around
the ship was still dark, the god of day had not thrown his fiery
beams upon the waters about us, but had passed over our heads
and was penciling the summits of Madeira with hues of liquid
gold. The peaks and splits on the top, and the clouds which
floated around the caps of the lofty elevations, all gilded with the
varied tints of the sun, imparted a novelization to the sight in mid-
ocean, that ecstasized every fiber of my being.</p>

<p>Several days had passed since anything had saluted our eyes,
but other vessels bound for the ports of their own choice; but
here is terra firma again. But it looks like the harbor of heaven
itself.</p>

<p>This island, 38 miles long and 15 miles broad, with a population 
of 140,000 inhabitants, belongs to Portugal.</p>

<p>As I drew near to this odd projection, towering out of mid-
ocean, dotted with houses on its craggy sides, with vineyards and
trees all a-bloom with beautiful and fragrant flowers, I naturally
asked the infinite past how long or under what circumstances?
this babe of nature had been born.
I involuntarily exclaimed,</p>

<p>Great granite monster, whence thy birth;<lb/>
What power upheaved thy giant form,<lb/>
Why has the rent and laboring earth<lb/>
Disgorged thee bare to sun and storm?</p>

<p>However, while it presented the appearance of gray granite at
a distance, a closer inspection revealed the fact that it was a dark
basaltic stone with several precipitous elevations resembling the
palisades on the Hudson River. I do not remember of ever seeing 
anything answering to it, except between Sherman and Ogden 
on the Northern Pacific Railroad. As I realized that it was
a product of volcanic action, I asked Dr. Sedgewick, how old he




<pb xml:id="p459" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.015.jpg"/>



supposed it was? He said twenty million years. I told him I
was about to hypothecate five million. He thought that would
call for aqueous deposits, which did not exist there. But learned
as this English prelate is, I think his reasoning faulty. But as
your readers may be more concerned about the other phases of
the island than its scientific side, let us proceed.</p>

<p>About a mile before we reached Funchal, the principal city,
where the ships stop to discharge their cargo, several small
boats met us with two boys in each; one with a shirt off and
the other doing the rowing, and such a jabber in Portuguese
you never heard, begging the passengers to throw money over
into the ocean, where the water is five hundred feet deep. Several 
did so, and they would leap out of their boats and under
the water they would go. But in a few moments they would
come up with the money in hand. Dozens of persons threw
money in the ocean, but the boys caught it all, and such a
babble when they would rise with it. When the ship anchored,
for there are no wharfs, then came another bedlam—custom-
house officers, quarantine doctors and boat-rowers to carry you
ashore for a shilling. The captain said, the ship would remain
here twenty-four hours.</p>

<p>A missionary stationed here from England, Rev. William G.
Smart, came aboard and took Dr. Sedgewick and wife, Elder
Geda and myself ashore, and treated us with marked consideration. 
He showed us his mission buildings, gave us a fine dinner,
had his school to sing for us, etc.</p>

<p>The knives here are sharp on both sides, and as keen as a razor.
I cut my mouth with them twice, and for once had to eat with a
fork. Fruits of all kind were upon the table, but the passion fruit
beat anything I ever saw.</p>

<p>The Roman Catholics have the island in their clutches. They
have here one Bishop and 155 priests. They call a Methodist,
Baptist, Presbyterian,—or any other Protestant,—" the imps of
hell." Priests walk the streets in their robes in all directions, and
everybody pays them homage.</p>

<p>You see nothing on wheels; everything is on sleighs pulled
by oxen—not horses, mules or asses—yet these oxen, unlike ours, 
move as fast as our horses. The sleighs glide over the smooth
stones as easily as over ice. I saw only one horse on the island,
and he was being rode. It is a mark of distinction to have a
horse.</p>

<p>Rev. Emanuel Melin, formerly of Jacksonville, Ill., near Springfield, 
called upon me, and when I told him I had visited Jacksonville 
in July, he almost went frantic with delight.</p>

<p>The representative of our government, whom President Harrison 
has sent here, is an ass, and ought to be moved from here at
once. He has not the respect of the rabble, much less the better
class. He is an Irish Catholic bigot of the baser sort, and a regular 
rough besides.</p>



<pb xml:id="p460" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.016.jpg"/>


<p>Here is where the celebrated Madeira wines are made, and I
find all nations are grabbing for them.</p>

<p>I did not see a colored man on the island; but the Portuguese 
themselves are yellow people; some have hair quite curly.</p>

<p>Another island juts up out of the ocean some 23 miles north-
east of Madeira, and is called the Porto Sante Island. Here
is where Columbus studied out the route to America. It is
now inhabited by only 1,850 persons; the highest point reaches
1,666 feet toward heaven. It, too, is the result of volcanic
action. About 11 miles southeast, Desertas Island also lifts a
rugged head above the waters 1,610 feet. It is six miles long
and one mile broad. The only inhabitants living upon it are
goats and rabbits. The eagles repair there at times to build their
nests. There are no snakes upon any of these islands. A legend
relates that a man once upon a time started there with some
snakes, but a storm sunk the ship and all on board were lost, and
no one has tried the experiment since. How the goats and rabbits 
got upon the barren island no one can surmise. They were
said to have been there when first discovered at least 2,700
years ago.</p>

<p>The Madeira Island has a variety of mineral, springs, which
draw health-seekers from England, France, America, Spain,
Italy, etc. But enough for this island, as the half could not be
told of its grandeur, beauty, fertility, etc.</p>

<p>October 31.</p>

<p>After resting at anchor all night and discharging the remaining 
cargo this morning, our ship steamed away for the island of
Teneriffe this forenoon at 10 o'clock. The wind was a bit brisk
and the sea a little undulating; but in a short time all was still
and the ocean seemed to get too lazy to move. The day was
rather monotonous as some of our passengers had left us at Madeira.</p>

<p>We have 255 miles to go before we reach Teneriffe.</p>

<p>November 1.</p>

<p>Early this morning I arose, dressed and came out to take 
observations.</p>

<p>The sun while not up, was throwing his illuminated plumes
upon the upper atmosphere and floating sheet clouds were
fulgent with the glory of his radiant beams, and grey dawn was
succumbing to the majesty of his revolving approach, and all the
east seemed to be aglow with the imperious hippodrome of concentrated 
splendor. A short while passed and a crescent oriole
oscillated above the ocean's pulsation, a fiery wheel rises from the
depths, and the scene becomes a halo of indescribable grandeur.
And then, as if conscious of his matchless majesty, he seemed to
look down upon the face of the sleeping ocean, and threw his
vermilion tinge with such force that the blue waters themselves
vesicated, and to my eye were check colored for several minutes.
But this did not obscure the surface of the seemingly sluggish


<pb xml:id="p461" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.017.jpg"/>



waters, which were as still as death, for they reflected the prismoid 
tints of old Sol, till the ocean appeared to be aflame itself.
As far as the eye could skirt the blue waters, they appeared to be
on fire. I said to Elder Geda," Great heavens, the ocean is burning!" 
He laughed and I resumed my balance. I never saw such
earthly splendor in my life. I can never see a sight more soul-ravishing, 
if I live a thousand years, yet, they tell me sun-rising
in Africa can beat that; but I cannot believe it, as in fact we are
now within seventy-five miles of Morocco, Africa; while it will
take us some days yet to reach Sierra Leone.</p>

<p>When I had gotten through with sun-rising and its supernalness, 
Mrs. Dr. Sedgewick called my attention to the other side of
the ship, as she had been watching for the peak of the Island of
Teneriffe. There another scene of huge and rugged majesty met
my eye. Teneriffe is' about 6,000 feet above the ocean surface,
with a massive circular cone extending heavenward 14,000 feet,
from the summit of which steam and smoke issue. I had never
seen a live volcano before, and as you may judge, it was a novel
sight. Geda and I looked on with amazement. As we neared
the island you could see sheet clouds mantling it about midway.
But, oh, such a sight! It was worth all the travel itself. Teneriffe
Island is 61 miles long and 37 miles wide with a population of
106,000 persons. It is principally composed of volcanic Scoria
and slag petrescence, with a large number of small cones, slits,
gulches and gorges and the mighty peak which can be seen two
hundred miles at sea. The early Spanish settlers, for Teneriffe
belongs to Spain, called this peak the "mouth of hell." The
ancients, you remember, called it the "abode of Hesperides" and
14,000 years before Christ the peak was called "the throne of
Jupiter." If I was at my library in Atlanta, I could give you the
history of the island, but I have no books here on the subject.
I think that Hercules had something to do with this place. But
I am afraid to quote doubtful history. But I am sure that it was
called " the island of the blessed " while it contained the mouth
of hell. And it is a grand spot. This being Sabbath, and the
ship having to remain twenty-four hours or more here, I said
to Elder Geda, "Let us go ashore and visit some church." We
did so and fell into a Roman Catholic Cathedral. We witnessed 
a baptism, a funeral, and heard and saw much and
understood nothing we heard, for it was all in Spanish. But
the dress, looks of the people, beautiful streets, horses, carriages,
fine houses, and all told us we were in the midst of an excellent
people.</p>

<p>This Spanish island has a superior class of people upon it to
those in Madeira. I have not seen a black face upon either island, 
however. The weather is similar to our June here at present.
It is quite warm. This morning another fight was on the
ship. Three white sailors got in a fight with an African deck
hand. They fought till I went after the captain to stop them.


<pb xml:id="p462" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.018.jpg"/>


The African faced the three as bravely as a lion, and every time
he struck either of them the blood flowed like water. But the
three white sailors never drew a drop of blood from him. The
captain parted them and took sides with the African. The African 
said: "Has sa kee foo buer se de hoo," which means, "I
can whip a dozen of such dogs."</p>

<p>I must close this letter without beginning to describe the many
things of interest about Teneriffe. As in fact we are at the island
of the blessed. Outside of that smoking mountain I have never
seen any place that looks more inviting. Yet the mountain has
not erupted in ioo years. We will leave here some time to-morrow 
for the grand Canary Islands—sixty-five miles southeast. I
shall mail this letter there.</p>

<p>November 2.</p>

<p>To-day at one o'clock our ship weighed anchor and we started
for the grand Canary Island.</p>

<p>The ocean looked like a great basin of oil or molasses; not a
ripple upon the surface. No wonder the people are said to be
lazy in this region of the world, for the waters of the sea are too
lazy to move; they scarcely want to move when the ship passes
through them. The ocean seems to be a huge pond with no life
in it. They say it takes a regular tornado to move it. As we
steamed out from Teneriffe, and looked back, the volcanic cone
lifted its cloudless brow skyward in awful majesty. All eyes
were riveted upon the mighty peak, but no steam issued from its
summit as we saw yesterday morning.</p>

<p>In front stood the grand Canary, with peaks 7,000 feet high,
apparently ten miles off instead of sixty miles, and a placid ocean
to pass us safely on.</p>

<p>A gentleman tried to show me a portion of the Saharian Desert
in Africa, but I could not see it, nor do I believe he did, though
we are on the African coast. They tell me I will see the canary
birds flying around wild, for here is the place of their origin.</p>

<p>These islands look grand beyond estimate, and while our ship
wastes a sight of time at them, passengers have an opportunity to
go ashore and take in marvelous sights.</p>

<p>The days are two hours longer here than they are at Liverpool,
and the weather is quite warm. Nature is all in bloom
and flowers are fragrant and sweet</p>

<p>We reached grand Canary at 6.30 o'clock this evening, and
will remain here at least 24 hours.</p>

<p>Geda and I will go out sight-seeing in the morning. Geda
says it is the garden of Eden or paradise won.</p>

<p>Fifth Letter.</p>

<p>Las Palmas, Grand Canary, November 3, 1891.</p>

<p>After spending 26 hours at this magnificent island the ship
raised anchor at 7 p.m., and we are just starting again for the



<pb xml:id="p463" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.019.jpg"/>



remainder of our trip. Early this morning I arose, and, after eating 
breakfast, Elder Geda and myself went ashore and rode
around a crescent-shaped peninsula which joins the larger and
smaller islands together, and began to take observations. I soon
discovered that the Grand Canary Island was by far the most
thrifty place we had visited. There were more ships in the harbor, 
more evidences of business, and a higher taste for the beautiful 
and ornamental, but an attempt to describe the museum,
concrete pavements, squares of flowers and many other things
would be useless.</p>

<p>Extinct volcano craters took up a large share of my attention.
With their slag twisted into a thousand singular and unique
forms, stalactic in appearance, quite often, and frequently univalvular 
in shape.</p>

<p>But the most imposing sight, so far as human art extends,
was the great Roman Catholic cathedral, a giant building itself,
and possessing valuables incalculable. Hearing so much on the
way about it, we resolved to see it. About ten o'clock a boy
became our conductor, and proffered to show us in and outside
of the object of our desire. He led and we followed; as we
stepped into the great auditorium the sweetest music conceivable 
saluted our ears. We sauntered around for awhile and
stepped into a small room where there was an open door, and
where, the boy told us, we could go without violating any rule.
In a few moments a priest came in and seized the boy by the
ears and knocked him about fearfully, for being in that sacred
place. But he said to us, "You are all right; look on, look on."
We were too glad to escape like punishment. The priest then
became our conductor, and in broken English began to explain
the wonders in view. He had at least a dozen keys, and after
showing us the silver altar, which cost thirty thousand dollars
alone, and other golden utensils, diamonds and gems, which must
have cost enormous sums, he showed us several old books written 
upon parchment long before the art of printing was discovered. 
He showed us a religious work in Latin, written in the
year of our Lord 261, making the book 1630 years old. The
backs of the books were made of boards, an inch thick, and they
were bound with rawhide. Other books were 1300, 1200 and
900 years old, yet the letters were large, well made and displayed 
a care, a neatness, a patience, a particularity that did
credit to the scribes of the olden times. Some of these old
books were about a yard long, and 20 inches wide, and from 6
to 8 inches thick. I could scarcely lift one of them.</p>

<p>The sight of these old volumes, and the struggles and
revolutions which they had witnessed, and the nations they
had existed through the rise and fall of, the men they had
seen (metaphorically) born and disappear as vapors before
the gale, gave me such a respect and admiration for them,
that I went before the altar of the
Cathedral, fell upon my



<pb xml:id="p464" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.020.jpg"/>



knees and thanked God for the honor of touching these
old religious volumes, much less seeing them. One of these
volumes contains the Gospel by St. John, alone, in Latin,
and another the Acts of the Apostles. It is thought that during
the wars and revolutions in Europe and Africa, hundreds of
years ago, that these old manuscripts were sent over to these
islands in the ocean, to be protected by these sea-girt asylums.
Who knows but what God had the sibilant and irritating fires
coursing through subterraneous vaults millions of years ago to
hurl these islands up to preserve certain records from the ruthless 
hands of wicked men? Records, too, that would have made
his Church a virtual nonentity if they were wanting. For, while
the Grand Canary, and indeed all these islands, are upon the
African coast, they are nevertheless in accessible proximity to
Europe. So there is more to be seen here than scoria, slag, 
cinderated basalt and igneously constructed valves. Let us return,
however, to our priest conductor.</p>

<p>After concluding our observations here, he led us into the
rear and down-stairs rooms of the Cathedral; each door he
would come to had to be unlocked and then locked again behind us. 
As we descended into the basement compartments,
with massive iron doors and heavy stone walls, Elder Geda, for
once turned white, for he knew no cry of alarm would ever be
heard from those cryptic cells. I felt a bit weak in the knees,
but neither of us let on. The priest showed us strange sights,
but we were too scared to remember much. We were anxious
to get out; we did not like those doors being locked behind
us.</p>

<p>In process of time, however, he retraced his route, and door
after door was unlocked and relocked, till we were in the main
auditorium. O, what a relief it was! I gave him eight shillings,
or two dollars. Elder Geda gave him one shilling, and the
priest bowed good day. He was the most obliging priest I ever
met.</p>

<p>A novel feet about Grand Canary Island, which is thirty-eight
miles long, thirty-six miles wide and some four or six thousand
feet high, is the fact that at a certain point, covering several acres,
a mysterious quantity of sand is accumulating and thickening
all the time. It has killed out or submerged all the vegetation
which grew there, and the surface is being raised and arid, but
where it comes from no one can tell. They say it does not rise
out of the ocean, nor could it be conveyed from any other portion 
of the island. The conclusion, therefore, is, that it is blown
from the Saharian Desert in Africa, some sixty miles away. Yet
no one can assert that as a fact Its increase, however, is creating 
some concern. Strange to say, no one thinks about Elder
Gedi and I being colored men on any of the islands. I mean at
Madeira, Teneriffe or here at Grand Canary. Anybody not
purely black is no African with them. I told some I was a Ne-




<pb xml:id="p465" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.021.jpg"/>





gro; they said "No, no!" Yet they do not care about color, for
there is no prejudice. Messrs. Thomas and Sams, both dark as
men can be, meet no repulsiveness. I have looked in vain for a
sight to establish an A. M. E. Church Mission on any of these
islands. I would like to see a church of ours upon one or more.
But these people, I fear, would not join, owing to Catholicism.
The Peak at Teneriffe is so plain here that it scarcely looks ten
miles off. We will now stop with the islands; the ship has
started for Sierra Leone again.</p>

<p>November 4.</p>

<p>We had a pleasant sail last night and to-day. The ocean is
quite calm and respectful. All the ladies left the ship at Grand
Canary, and our companions are now men, bulls, and cows,
sheep, goats, chickens, ducks, geese, cats, dogs and a few rats;
all except the rats, run around on the ship at liberty. The sand mounds 
of Sahara, on the African coast, can be seen occasionally. 
Flying-fish every once and awhile spring up and fly for
a hundred or two yards and plunge under water. The constellations, 
Orion, Andromeda, Hercules and the Dipper, seem
located in the heavens a little differently from the way 
they appear in America.</p>

<p>November 5 and 6.</p>

<p>We have reached the trade-wind region, but they, too, are
quiet. So everything is dull and calm. The men sing and walk
around, play games of various kinds nod and read and talk
about everything in creation. I went after the captain to run the
ship faster; ten miles an hour being too slow, when he could
make several more. He said, "The colored people of the United
States throw enough money away, yearly, for whiskey, to build
fifty ships that could run twenty miles an hour, and I had better
get them to save their money and build a faster ship." "Englishmen,"
he said, "were slow but sure." He also said, "The
United States had no African steamers at all—neither fast or
slow." I had no more to say.</p>

<p>Mr. Matthew Thomas, the great scholar, read the prize essay
of Miss Elizabeth Jackson, of Wilberforce, on Africa, to-day,
and became so infatuated with her, that he said, "She must be
my wife." He asked me what I would charge to court her for
him. I told him a thousand dollars, as she was worth a hundred
thousand.</p>

<p>Mr. William Roberts, the second officer of the ship, at my
request, measured with his instruments to-day the distance from
New York to Liberia, Africa. The distance is 3,720 miles.
From New York to Liverpool is 3,115 miles, and from Liverpool 
to Liberia, Africa, is 3,250 miles; so coming to Liberia,
Africa, by way of Liverpool, makes the distance 6,365 miles.
Had we a steamer from New York to Africa we could save 2,645
miles travel, and save 300 more from Charleston or Savannah.


<pb xml:id="p466" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.022.jpg"/>


This ship skirts the coast of Africa about 3,000 miles and
returns.</p>

<p>The captain took his map and showed me, a few moments
ago, 39 mission points where, to his knowledge, a missionary
is now needed, and 15a other points where he is almost certain
missionaries would be permitted to live. Gracious! the work
here is so enormous that its ponderosity frightens me. Bishop
Taylor's self-supporting scheme is severely criticised by all the
shipmen, traders and merchants now on the ship.</p>

<p>November 7.</p>

<p>We passed a vast African promontory to-day, and the forest
upon land, as revealed through my large eye-glasses, was simply
massive.</p>

<p>The ship put on a new dress yesterday; vast stores of everything 
that can be thought of were opened and arranged for the
natives to purchase when they began to land along the coast
where the people are most numerous. Not less than six magnificent 
stores are now in full blast; all kinds of dry goods, musical 
instruments, trinkets, and everything except books and
papers; yes, and a few Bibles and hymn-books. They sell these
goods to the natives for three, four, and five times their value in
Liverpool; but, after all, it is doing good, for several natives are
now going to Liverpool and London and learning to speculate
themselves. Mr. Thomas says, "If our brethren will not come
from America and make themselves immensely rich by traffic, as
they might do in a few years, we natives will do it ourselves;
white men shall not always be getting rich off us."</p>

<p>November 8.</p>

<p>We are anchored in front of Iles De Los, sixty miles from
Sierra Leone; but I have seen the high mountains of Sierra
Leone through my large glasses, which appear awfully sublime.
I had no idea that such a mighty range of mountains ran along
the coast here as I see lifting their mighty summits skyward. I
have been ashore and trod the African soil at last, and nature
here is lavish with her stores. True, the weather is quite warm,
the thermometer at seventy-six degrees, but I have felt it twenty
odd degrees warmer in America. The ocean has been marvelously 
quiet ever since we left the Bay of Biscay; but they tell
me they never have storms here to last over two hours. The
ocean is nearly always calm, and fish sporting in the waters.
I had heard so much since I left Liverpool about the laziness,
stupidness and worthlessness of the native African, that I had
almost become disheartened, and was about to think my expectations 
would be a myth; so to-day as we steamed up here to
this French port (as it belongs to France). I saw two pilot-boats
pulling to meet us, with -dressed men in the rear, and four seemingly 
naked Africans bending to the oars. One had a black


<pb xml:id="p467" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.023.jpg"/>


pilot, the other a white one. The black pilot beat, and took our
ship in charge. He was dressed, but barefooted ; the white pilot
had on shoes; the rowers, or oarsmen, were all naked, except
about the waist. I said to Geda, "Things are gloomy here."
Geda shook his head and dropped it. Finally the cannon was
fired, the anchor let down, and the ship stopped.</p>

<p>Then from the shore came the oar-boats in large numbers, for
all the freight had to be boated from the ship to the shore, there
being no wharves here. But the scene changed. Here came
native Africans by the score, nearly all decently dressed, some
finely attired, others with only shirts on, some with only pants,
only a few with waist napkin. They literally thronged the
ship from end to end, and began to unload the ship and carry
the freight ashore as actively, as aptly and as intelligently as I
had seen anywhere since I left New York. Their head men understood 
running the steam machines, gave intelligent orders,
and beat the Portuguese at Madeira all hollow in managing
affairs. These Africans are men, naked or clothed. Some are
members of Frederick's Church, at Sierra Leone, and were enraptured 
when told we were Parson Frederick's missionaries.
Some said, "Daddy Frederick been look for ye long time; you
be welcome, welcome a heap."</p>

<p>I was amused to see a half nude African and the ship-clerk
get into a dispute in running up some figures about the freight
he took in his boat. The African told him, "You no understand
arithmetic." The clerk insisted he was right. The African
snatched the clerk's book from his hand, ran over the figures,
pointed out the mistake and told him to go to school again.
Several African ladies are on the ship, and I never saw hair fixed
up as finely as two of theirs was. It is rolled like watch-chains.
But as I am so near Sierra Leone, I will close this letter. Geda
is pleased all over with the African, and I am crazy with delight
so far. I do not know what is ahead yet.</p>

<p>Sixth Letter.</p>

<p>Freetown, Sierra Leone, Africa, November 12,1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I arrived here a few days ago, after a rather tedious jaunt from
Liverpool. The ship could run fast enough, but the captain would
not let it.</p>

<p>My reception here was indescribable. The ship came into port
late at night, but I awoke early in the morning and looked out
upon the city and saw a place much resembling Vicksburg,
Miss., except that the mountains rose in the rear of the city much
higher than the lofty bluffs of Vicksburg; upon the inclinations
or declivities of the receding elevations a city of 30,000 population
stood in surprising majesty—surprising by reason of the wide
streets and stately two-, three- and four-story buildings which
stretched along the streets for a mile or two. I had looked for



<pb xml:id="p468" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.024.jpg"/>



no such place. I thought it was a low, swampy, lagoony town.
with narrow, muddy streets, as filthy as a cess-pool; but cleanliness, 
pavements, sidewalks, rock-sewers and decency everywhere
met my eye. But when I pointed this and that fine building out,
and was told that they all belonged to black men, I was surprised
more than ever. Again, when I inquired about the great cathedral, 
with tower and clock, and other large churches, with spires,
domes and steeples, and was told they were all black people's
churches, I had to say, thank God for this sight!</p>

<p>Shortly boats came to the ship in scores, and the ship was
crowded with black men. All had clothes on and some were
finely clad. Every officer was black, and some were haughty and
dictatorial as lords; a few a little too much so, I thought; but
when I discovered the downright villainy of some of these
English officers, I saw the point.</p>

<p>However, while standing upon the ship, noting things as they
transpired, a gentleman from the wharf walked up and said, "Are
you the Bishop of Mr. Frederick?" I replied, "I am Bishop Turner." 
He said, "Give me your card for him, as he has been
looking for you several days." I gave him my card and he disappeared. 
In a short time Elder Frederick and Mr. Bowser, the
representative of the United States Government, a noble-looking,
brown-skinned gentleman, formerly from Ohio, came on board,
accompanied by some more prominent gentlemen. The salutations were 
cordial; Frederick and Geda hugged each other, etc.</p>

<p>In a few moments more we were en route for the wharf, where
I expected to kiss the ground of my first proper disembarkation;
but as I set my foot on shore, a waiting multitude of men and
women rushed upon me and shook my hands and exclaimed,
"Glory to God, hallelujah!" etc., till I was melted with tears. I
never witnessed such emotions of thankfulness in all my life; but
the scene beggars description.</p>

<p>Elder Geda, myself and trunks were conducted to the Custom
House. Every Custom House official was black; the collector-
in-chief was intensely black. All trunks were examined except
mine and Geda's. The collector told his officers not to touch
our trunks, but he asked me a few questions as to their contents,
and ordered them passed through the Custom House. Frederick
thanked him and marched them off to the Lady Huntington A.
M. E. Church.</p>

<p>As we filed along the street for some four squares great crowds
stood out and looked on with much eagerness.</p>

<p>The church was ultimately reached—an edifice, corresponding
to our church in Richmond, Va., except that it has only one aisle,
in the centre. As we entered, the packed house, up and down
stairs, arose and sang, "Praise God, from whom all blessings
flow," in a most solemn and pathetic manner. Geda and I were
conducted to the altar, and Elder Frederick gave out page 252,
"We bid thee welcome in the Name," which was forcibly sung,




<pb xml:id="p469" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.025.jpg"/>




and prayer offered to heaven for us. I was then presented to the
people in an able speech by Elder Frederick, but I could not
speak, I was completely broken down. When I saw the emotions
of gratitude, not to me, but to the Church I represented, I cried
like a child; I would have given my life could all the Bishops
have been present. While it is impossible to picture the scenes
in words, let me say, the joy of those people—I mean our people
—at the presence of a Bishop was simply overwhelming. They
had been told so often that no Bishop would ever come from our
Church, that the American colored Bishops did not care if they
all were lost, etc.; and, strange to say, too, they were told this by
white missionaries, so that when one did come their joy knew no
bounds. Gracious alive! how white people have misrepresented
the A. M. E. Church and her Bishops in Africa. I hate to say
some of them were white Bishops, too, but it will have to be said
ultimately.</p>

<p>This morning at 10 o'clock we opened the First Annual Conference 
of the A. M. E. Church in Africa, in the Zion A. M. E.
Church, formerly known as the Lady Huntington Church.</p>

<p>As Elder Geda is so well pleased with the possibilities of
Africa that he is going to remain here, I have transferred him
from New England to the Sierra Leone Annual Conference, which
gives us at present five members of our Annual Conference, but
as two learned Wesleyan preachers may join the Church to-night,
it is likely we will soon have seven members. Our session to-day
was watched with much interest; the term "African" to our
Church is a magic word.</p>

<p>There is no Church on earth can grow like ours if we will half
work. The heathen kings will drive out other denominations, so
I am told, and declare our Church the Church of their kingdom.</p>

<p>But as I must close this letter, as the mail will soon leave—in
one hour from now—I beg to say, the three days I have spent
here have been fine. I am no more alarmed about sickness than
I would be anywhere else. I may get sick and die, but I feel fine
now. Geda says he is not scared worth a cent.</p>

<p>Sierra Leone is about like Memphis, Tenn.; Helena, Ark.;
Vicksburg, Miss., or Baton Rouge, La.</p>

<p>I saw a white girl who came here from Ohio three weeks ago
to marry a fellow; she is fourteen years old. She looks well
enough.</p>

<p>I believe much of these European and American white
people's deaths here at Sierra Leone is due to their liquor drinking; 
most of them who come here are whiskey sots.</p>

<p>I may be sick here, but I shall not believe it till I feel it.
Geda declares he feels better, yet from nine till one it is quite
hot; but I have felt it much hotter in America.</p>

<p>I will write much more in my next letter.</p>



<pb xml:id="p470" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.026.jpg"/>



<p>Seventh Letter.</p>

<p>Freetown, Sierra Leone, Africa, November 16, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>In my last letter I stated the impressions and circumstances
of my arrival at Sierra Leone. Before proceeding further
on that line, permit me to state a fact that some of our learned
men may philosophize upon in some of their leisure moments: 
I find that the waters of the ocean here are more salty,
dense and heavy, than the waters of the same ocean about New
York and Liverpool and in the Northern Hemisphere. They are
harder to raise into waves and billows and hence are far more
pacific than our section of the same ocean. The quantity of
water that will weigh two pounds at Liverpool or New York will
weigh two pounds and a quarter here, and sometimes a half ounce
more. I confess it is a puzzle to me; and all I have asked—sea-
captains, doctors, engineers and mineralogists—have failed to explain 
this secret of nature. Will some of our learned professors
at Wilberforce, Paul Quinn, Allen, Morris Brown, Kittrell or
some of our other centers of learning tell us the reason?</p>

<p>But let us return to Sierra Leone. I find the mountains, which
rise up in the rear of this city, are all of volcanic origin, a blue
granite, which is the youngest of the granite series, if the learned
theories are correct, form the substratum and glide into the ocean,
but over that is a thick layer of porous rock (we will call them),
tinged heavily with iron, which is compounded with a basaltic
feldspar; the old geologists would call it "Titanic iron base."
This condition runs, subject to undulations and horizontals, from
the ocean beach to the top of those 3,700 feet mountains. The
English government has a fort that overlooks the city, and a hospital 
upon the mountain-top, only for soldiers, however. All the
troops here are colored—West Indians—except the officers, who
are all white.</p>

<p>Freetown is at the mouth of the Roquelle River, which higher
up appears to be the recipient of two or three others; this makes
the city of Freetown quite accessible to large regions of the interior 
by the agency of small boats and canoes.</p>

<p>But why waste time and space with the topography of the
country? Your readers will be more concerned about the people,
their habits, customs, manners, etc. I find about everything here
common to other cities. House builders, rock blasters, lime
burners, stone chiselers and polishers, blacksmiths, wheelwrights,
painters, whitewashers, tailors, watchmakers, jewelers, finest kind
of bootmakers, dressmakers, glass polishers, boat caulkers, en-
gineers, grand storekeepers, doctors, lawyers, judges, druggists,
postmasters, custom house officers, schools, seminaries, colleges,
cathedrals, publishers, editors, bookbinders, medicine makers,
chemists, scholars and everything except horses and mules. Yes,
I hear there are a few jackasses about—four-legged I mean. We
can find two-legged asses anywhere. But what is grander to me


<pb xml:id="p471" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.027.jpg"/>



than anything else, is the fact that all these are black men and
women. Mixed bloods are not excluded, however. They have
a share in everything. Several white men from England and
some from France, Germany, Italy and America have come here
and married black women and raised up families of mixed blood.
Some have lived with colored wives awhile and left them several
children to look after, and disappeared, so mulattoes are not
absent at all, but other white men have lived with their colored
wives right along and died with them. A few black men have
also gone to England and elsewhere, and married white ladies,
and they have children, etc.</p>

<p>All the ministers here, except the Baptists, wear robes. The
Catholics, Mahomedans, English Church, Wesleyan Methodists,
Free Methodists, Presbyterians, Lutherans and African Methodist 
Episcopal. Elder Geda looks grandly in a robe, and the
people here thought he was used to it. I smiled but said nothing.
Of course, I was at home in my robe. The Catholic and Mahomedan 
priests wear robes all over the city.</p>

<p>The dress of the people is not uniform at all. Some are
dressed in fine broadcloth, some in silks, bonnets, jewelry, and in
the fashions; others in cheaper style; others in shirts, gowns,
wraps; others almost as God made them. The old settlers are
the bloods or dignitaries, then comes in the tribal part, according
to grade. Tribal prejudice runs high in many cases. The bush
crowd are the servants and domestics.</p>

<p>The bush or native heathen Africans do all the drudgery work,
such as "pulling and pushing the carts, wheel chairs, sedan chairs,
hammocks, hearses; carry all boxes, barrels, stones, mortar,
bricks; oar all the boats on the river, etc. The people are peaceable; 
I see or hear of no fighting; shooting is never heard of.
Sometimes an African king may come from the bush, or country,
and kill some runaway wife, then he is arrested and banished to
some island, if caught, and made to work the balance of his life;
but if a king comes to the city and kills a decent wife, he will
likely kill himself before he will be arrested.</p>

<p>Elder J. R. Frederick is a great and good man; he has done
a noble work here. While I have found fault with Bishop
Payne for ignoring the missionary channels and sending his
missionary money directly to Brother Frederick, I am prepared
now to say, Bishop Payne deserves the gratitude of our Church;
the reasons why I hope to give in the future. The ladies of the
Mite Missionary Society also have done more good than they
have any idea of. God bless every one of them!</p>

<p>I have received two able ministers from the Wesleyan Church
and have entered them into our itinerant work; one is very
learned. I have preached or exhorted every night since I have
been here, and most of the time presided over the Sierra Leone
Annual Conference of the A. M. E. Church, four hours each day,
and feel as well as ever I felt. Sierra Leone is far healthier than



<pb xml:id="p472" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.028.jpg"/>



Memphis, Tenn., Pine Bluff, or Helena, Ark.; no one coming from
Memphis would ever notice anything but a favorable change.</p>

<p>We will have two or three churches here soon—possibly before
I leave—besides what we have up the rivers. The A. M. E.
Church can be the Continental Church of Africa if it will hear
me when I reach home.</p>

<p>I learn that Bishop Crowther, of the Niger, has not been
treated right somehow by the Church of England, and he and
his ministers are about to set up an independent Apostolic denomination. 
I am urged to go and confer with him, but the
object might be misconstrued, therefore I shall not go. I do
not blame the Bishop for kicking, if what some of his ministers
tell me be true.</p>

<p>White men and their wives are coming here from New York
State, Ohio, Indiana and Iowa and going one hundred miles in the
country and settling among the heathen, preaching, teaching
school and training the black children.</p>

<p>Rev. I. M. Johnson, of Iowa, came in this morning from over
a hundred miles and related his labors, and his wife's labors, and
told me of others out there, etc., while we are evading Africa as
a deadly viper.</p>

<p>These whites say the interior is cooler than Texas and far
healthier than Houston, while iron ore stands in mountain heaps
and the finest wood on earth is boundless.</p>

<p>A singular fact is, that anybody, white or colored, from America 
is welcomed out here in Africa, either on the coast or back
in the interior. While Englishmen, French and Germans are
mostly hated. The kings hate them, especially about robbing
them of their lands. The French are hated as the devil. Americans 
are looked upon as the guardians of Liberia and the friends of
her blacks, and it modifies the prejudice somehow. I do not
understand it yet. France is more intolerant in her claimed possessions 
than England it seems, and far less compromising,
while the Mohamedans abominate Germany about the shiploads of
rot-gut whiskey they land along the coast to ruin the more
heathen African. The English ships despise the German ships
about the same; nearly every time they see a German ship at
sea the entire crew will curse it about shipping poisoned liquor to
Africa. The English ships carry a good deal, too, but they ease
their conscience by saying, "Our whiskey is all first-class. It is
inspected before we leave Liverpool and London."</p>

<p>The "Galaxy," containing the bishops and their wives, is a great
treat to our members here and the people in general. I wish I
had 10,000 of them instead of 40 copies. The preachers and
people want them for the interior by thousands, for kings and
their judges and big men.</p>

<p>The African ladies who come in the city from the bush, for
hundreds of miles, have to buy white doll-babies for their children. 
They want black, brown and yellow dolls. If some of



<pb xml:id="p473" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.029.jpg"/>



our people will engage in their manufacture they can sell millions
of colored dolls. England, France, etc., only send out white dolls.
The black merchants out here (and they are plentiful) are crazy for
a line of steamships to America, like England, France and Germany 
have, so they can deal in American goods, medicines, etc.,
so the merchants can come over in ten or fifteen days and return
in haste—the sail vessels are too slow.</p>

<p>I find people here 75, 80, 90, 100 and a few 112 and 117 years
old, about as old as some of the people who are afraid to
visit Africa. I do not think Rev. J. W. Randolph, D.D., is
much over 117 years old.</p>

<p>I took some observations this afternoon in the rear of this
city. I find millions of dollars of iron awaiting the hands of
industry. I am told silver mines abound not far from here. I
was surprised to hear them singing Gospel hymns in the
Roman Catholic Church. I see white Sisters of Charity here,
moving around as in other cities. Yesterday they marched at
least a hundred young ladies up the street, of all colors and
shades, neatly dressed, and the young ladies did look grand.
The priest in charge has been here forty years, and says he would
not exchange Africa for the world—white as he is. He is assisted 
by three other priests.</p>

<p>This morning I had a grand treat. Two of the great granddaughters 
of Rev. Daniel Coker, of Baltimore, one of the chief
organizers of the A. M. E. Church, called upon me to inquire
about any of their relatives in Baltimore. It appears when Rev.
Daniel Coker came here, sixty odd years ago, that he brought
a son with him, a young man; Rev. Daniel Coker died about
1846, his son (Henry) died some years ago, but Henry had a
son, whose name was Hillery T. Coker, who died in his fifty-sixth
year in February last, and was buried by Elder Frederick, as
he was his member. He leaves a wife and two daughters, Jane
Coker, twenty years of age, and Susan Coker, near eleven years,
two beautiful ginger-cake-colored children, and very smart and
bright.</p>

<p>Miss Jane Coker is the interpreter for the United Brethren of
America out among the Sherbro tribe. They preach and talk
to this tribe through her. She is proud of her ancestry and feels
she is of no common blood; she is pretty, modest and thoughtful; 
she wishes to visit Baltimore, but money is wanting. I told
her if she dared to visit Baltimore, Philadelphia, or anywhere the
A. M. E. Church existed, she would never get back; that the
people would feast and honor her to death, because she had the
blood of Daniel Coker in her. Little Susan Coker is anxious to
come back with me, and her mother is willing. She wishes the
child highly educated; she has a bright intellect and a fine head
phrenologically, and could be made a great woman. I may or
may not bring her. It appears that Rev. Daniel Coker and
his son had a number of the Akoo tribe placed under them for



<pb xml:id="p474" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.030.jpg"/>



training and they all took his name, so that the Cokers are
very numerous. One of the preachers I have admitted on trial
in the traveling work is a Coker. He says Daniel Coker was
his grandfather's master—a term here which means boss.</p>

<p>These black Mahomedan priests, learned to kill, walking
around here in their robes with so much dignity, majesty and
consciousness of their worth, are driving me into respect for
them. Some come for hundreds of miles from the country—out
of the bush—better scholars than any in America. What fools
we are to suppose these Africans are fools!</p>

<p>Eighth Letter.</p>

<p>Freetown, Sierra Leone, Africa, November 18, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>The Sierra Leone Annual Conference is over. Thursday, November 10,
the following ministers met in our church here:
H. M. Turner, J. R. Frederick, T. R. Geda, H. M. Steady, David B. Roach, 
Matthew Newland, and we organized and went to
work. The same evening I took into the church, among twenty one others, 
George D. Decker and Isaiah Coker, two preachers
from the Wesleyan Church; one very learned and popular, the
other very strong, and posted in the Timnee language, the
greatest tribe in the vicinity.</p>

<p>The boundaries of the Conference include all the territory of
the leading tribes for three hundred miles, viz., the Timnee, Cosso,
Akoo, Ebo, Sherbo, Mendi, Mandingo, Fullah, Limba and Yennie tribes. 
The king of each has welcomed our church, and the
king of the Timnees has declared our church the church of his
nation.</p>

<p>The Conference remained in session from Thursday, the 10th,
until Monday night, the 14th. We were busy all the time. Our
property here amounts to about $10,000, and membership, including 
the probationers, to 495; our prospects to millions of
members and property. By taking up two local preachers we had
ten ministers to whom I gave appointments. We ordained three
deacons,—I was willing to ordain more, but we did not think it
wise to be too merciful at first,—those we did ordain stood a fine
examination.</p>

<p>A long discussion arose over the name of the Conference, some
fearing if we called it- the Sierra Leone Conference, the country
kings would rule our church out, as some hate Sierra Leone, because 
it is an English colony, and that England is a usurper to claim
territory in Africa. The African kings are willing and are glad
for their black and yellow kinfolks to come home from America,
and teach, preach, work and marry their women; but they want
nothing to do with England, France or Germany. But we named
the Conference the Sierra Leone Conference nevertheless, hoping
to explain away all grounds of fear or apprehension to those
 


<pb xml:id="p475" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.031.jpg"/>



royal heads of the millions of our people. For every ten thousand 
dollars the A. M. E. Church could send here, from seventy five 
to a hundred thousand dollars could be procured to our church.</p>

<p>Elder, now Presiding Elder Frederick, has some of the most
awful church deeds I ever saw; what I mean by awful, is size and
weight; some are four pages of parchment, two feet by twenty
inches; strange to say, too, some of the African kings have
signed their own names. On one of the deeds I see the name of
Scipio H. Robertson. That must be the Scip of Georgia. When
did he slip off and come over here?</p>

<p>Last Sabbath was without doubt the grandest day I ever beheld. 
There must have been three thousand people in and around
the church; hundreds went away for want of out-door room;
many of the colored dignitaries of other churches were present,
civil and military, as well as the heathen themselves. Love-feast
at 6 o'clock in the morning,—the church was crowded by 5 o'clock.
The experiences given were familiar and unfamiliar. Some expressed 
themselves in good English, some in broken English,
others in this and that language. Some twenty languages were
used in giving the experience. But a large number would understand 
everybody and responses would come from all over the
church, and tears would be shed. Never were more languages
used in one love-feast since time began; never were more terms
used to express approval. Great heavens, how white people
on the one hand and scullion Negroes upon the other, have
misrepresented Africa! Some who got up in that love-feast to
talk were what they called heathens, right from the bush, with
a mere cloth over them, and while I could not understand a
word, you could see they were full of the Holy Ghost. I tried
to preach at 10.30 o'clock, Elder Geda at 3 o'clock, and I again
at night I ordained three ministers, took twenty-seven into full
membership. Put my hands on their heads, too. Confirmed
them, if you choose to so call it, and took some forty in on probation. 
We gave the Lord's Supper to 560 persons. Every minister was robed 
and that alone was glory enough for me.
But I cannot picture the day and the scenes. I never expect to
see the like on earth again.</p>

<p>Alpha Mahomed San u Si, one of the Mahomedan bishops,
called upon me at Presiding Elder Frederick's house, to pay his
respects; he speaks English, Arabic, Timnee, Akoo, Su Su, Mandingo 
and the Fullah languages. He came in his splendid robes
and looked grandly. He is a man of rare learning and his bearing 
was kingly. I tried to look big, but felt small, in his presence.
He resembles Bishop Gaines in color, stature, beard, features and
walk—may-be a bit taller; but he is another Gaines; he is about
as proud as Bishop Gaines.</p>

<p>Yesterday afternoon, to my surprise, Dr. I. H. Cold called
upon me (with horse and buggy). I did not know there was a


<pb xml:id="p476" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.032.jpg"/>


horse in the city; he drove me away out in the country. It was
a regular African horse, too, fat as a butter-ball. Such sights as
I saw I will never forget. I went among some country natives
and looked at their thatch-covered huts, and to my surprise, in
some I found looking-glasses, chairs, clocks, furniture, etc. I
saw some nearly naked men and women out on the road,
but in the town they live nicely at home; but another sight which
I had to admire was the erectness with which these men and
women stand.</p>

<p>The native African has no fear, no cowardice, no dread, but
feels himself the equal of any man on earth. The land, as far as
I went, is rich, water streams in abundance, fruits of every kind,
flowers of every beauty, and while I saw many doing nothing at
all, I saw many hundreds at work, and hard at work, too. They
need skilled labor however, skilled farmers. Since I have found
out more, I find horses will live here and be fat. Dogs are like
ours in every particular. The dogs, roosters, goats and sheep all
talk like ours. I told the doctor they were all I could understand. 
I could not understand the people, but he could.</p>

<p>I have just had the honor of my life. King Kobbena Eljen, of
the Kromantie tribe, a powerful tribe on the Gold Coast, who was
captured in the late war with England, and who is here as a
prisoner-of-war, called to pay his respects, through me, to his
race, as he says, "over the sea." He means in America. I
kissed his hands a dozen times, and would have kissed his feet,
had he not said "No, no." The king is 64 years old. He is tall,
erect and majestic, and is deeply concerned about the colored
people in America. He wanted to know when we were coming
home.</p>

<p>During the great Ashantee war he was captured by the English
army, and England tried to get him to sign away his territory
and his people's land. He refused to do it, and they brought
him here to Sierre Leone, as a prisoner, to be held until he
signs away his kingdom. The king says he will die first. If
he would sign the documents, England would send him back at
once in a man-of-war. The African kings and nobility will make
me hate England, grand as old England is in many respects.
The king walks about town, but cannot leave. He is loyal to
his race and to his people. He will give his kingdom to his
children in the United States, but not to England.</p>

<p>Well, the ship has arrived which is to carry me to Liberia, and
having completed my work here, I must close this letter and
begin to pack up. I have not written half, but all I could find
time to write.</p>

<p>Neither Geda nor I have been the least sick yet, after eleven days
hard work, but I have a little headache to-day, for coming home
last night out of a hot church and sitting in a draft, when I was
begged not to do it. The weather is fine and pleasant for summer. 
Off for Liberia.</p>


<pb xml:id="p477" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.033.jpg"/>


<p>I neglected to say, the ministers of the Church of England
have called upon us as other ministers, regardless of all sacerdotal
considerations.</p>

<p>Ninth Letter.</p>

<p>Steamship "Mandingo,"<lb/>
West African Coast, November 21, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>After I closed my last letter at Sierra Leone, I called upon his
excellency, Governor James H. Hay. I was kindly received, and
introduced by Presiding Elder Frederick, who has the respect of
his excellency. He gave me much information about the colony
and showed me the falsity of the deathly and sickly reports current 
about Sierra Leone, in presenting his own fine-looking,
healthy and corpulent person, which several years' residence here
had not intercepted. He told me of a vast deal which I have no
time nor space to write at present; but the whole was full of information, 
and shows progress all along the line. His mansion
is magnificent, overlooks the city, flowers of every variety, shades,
walks, fountains, etc.</p>

<p>The Governor is down upon African slanderers, white or black.
He says, if we had skilled labor and civilization here, Africa
would be the mistress of Continents.</p>

<p>In speaking about black men representing the native African,
as so low and ignoble in other countries, because they had
acquired some intelligence from being brought in contact with the
whites, the Governor said, "How foolish they are. Don't they
know if the black men are nothing here they are nothing everywhere; 
that nothing must proceed from nothing; that if the original 
stalk or trunk is nothing, the offspring or branches will be
nothing too?" He says, " Every black man who berates African
or Africa, berates himself."</p>

<p>The funniest thing that has come under my attention was the
criticism of Dr. Randolph's "Criticism of Bishop Turner,"
published in the Christian Recorder of October 15, by a native-born 
and raised African. He read it and commented most severely,
yet in the most courteous language, which showed his high
literary culture and refinement, until I told him that Dr. J. W.
Randolph was a great linguist, scholar and a D.D. Then he
opened the vials of his literary wrath. He took up his sentences,
analyzed them, denied that he understood the English language,
pronounced his argument coarse and illogical, and pitied the college 
that would confer D.D. upon such a poor scholar. The use
Dr. Randolph had made of the term "nonsense" seemed to fire
every fiber of his soul, the house roared with peals of laughter, so
I need never reply to the doctor. Africa has replied in full.
Several white American missionaries called upon me before I left
Sierra Leone, and gave me some missionary items I did not know.
Those who called upon me consisted of men and women from


<pb xml:id="p478" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.034.jpg"/>


Wisconsin and Nebraska; one was from Ohio—a young, beautiful white lady.</p>

<p>I find the following to be the result: from Nebraska there are
five missionaries here; twenty-seven more coming. From Kansas there are 
nine here, and fifteen coming. From Minnesota there are ten here, 
and eighteen coming. From Ohio there are twelve here. 
From Illinois there are four here. A majority of
these missionaries are white ladies But what beats all is, they
tell me 128 are now being trained, mostly in Chicago, to follow
these. Most every steamer is bringing more missionaries, teachers, 
preachers, dressmakers and tool users. I had been told by
the ship captains of this, coming out from America, but did not
know the extent until now. The singularity of this movement
is, that all of these missionaries should come from the West.
Outside of middle New York State, I find no Eastern, Northern
or Southern whites out here as missionaries. The present programme 
of the missionaries from the West is to establish a line
of mission centers back into the interior for 400 miles, with mission 
houses and schools erected every fifty miles along that line,
so that native runners can carry letters from one camp to the
other.. To extend 400 miles from the sea interiorward will require
eight mission camps or centers. Travelers then can find resting
places for this 400 miles, every fifty miles on their route. They
say the African kings bid them welcome when they are satisfied
they are not Germans, French or English. They think Americans 
will not bother with their territory or slaves. While the
Germans and French do not meddle with their slaves at all, they
wish to gobble up their lands and mines. The English, on the
other hand, are more reasonable in regard to territorial possessions, 
but will free every slave and wife they can. I find that
wherever England holds possessions in Africa there is another
Canadian asylum for the slaves and oppressed—the same as our
American Canada used to be when slavery existed in the United
States. But the Germans and French often return slaves and
wives to their claimants; but England, never. When a slave or
a wife gets into her possessions the whole military and navy protect 
their liberty. And another thing England does that Germany and France 
do not, if England captures a king and holds
him as prisoner of war she treats him royally; she allows him to
walk about, gives him from five to ten dollars a day and provides
a place for him in keeping with his status; if he is an imperial
king, ten dollars a day is allowed; if a large tribal king, five
dollars; if a petty king, three dollars. But all do nothing but
sit and walk about; no shackles, handcuffs or prison cells. God
save old. England, is my prayer!</p>

<p>I am told that the Liberians do about the same in regard to
slaves and wives. But as I will be in Liberia in a few hours, I
will learn more about it.</p>

<p>It is marvelous how white men bow, bend, lift hats and smile


<pb xml:id="p479" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.035.jpg"/>


around colored ladies out here. mean the dressed, civilized
and cultured ladies. Walk with them, sit and talk with them,
and do all the honors they do to white ladies, and seem to be as
natural about it as if they were raised at it. I believe several of
these African ladies rather prefer the white fellows, too. Don't
matter, however, the colored gentry have a nice time with the
white ladies also, when they are about.</p>

<p>I have seen the beauties of nature in its varied tints, colors
and shades. I have looked on and admired the artificial, as well
as the permanent formations, but I have never seen anything to
compare with the ocean here along the African coast after night.
The waves produced by the ship, which roll off on either side,
appear to be studded with millions of glittering gems; the waters
at times would seem to be on fire, yet the fire does not seem to
resemble the fires of earth. I am told if one bathes in the waters
and stands in the dark he will glitter from head to foot. The
waters are full of a phosphoric animalculae called "Medusae,"
and their beauty and splendor in the ocean is literally indescribable.</p>

<p>Rev. Herbert H. Richmond, L.L.D., the District Superintendent 
of the English Wesleyan Methodist Church, has been reading 
"Methodist Polity" for two days and congratulates the author
in high terms. He is going to try to have it made a text-book
in their theological seminaries. The doctor is on his way to
Lagos, where he has not been in twenty years. He does not
want the A. M. E. Church to go where the Wesleyan Church is,
and he says: "Two churches of the same order and faith confuse 
the African kings and they will get mad and drive both out
of their kingdoms if our preachers should get to disputing over
the respective churches." He thinks the A. M. E. Church and
the A. M. E. Zion Church should unite before we come to Africa.</p>

<p>Before I reached Africa proper some English sailors were telling 
me about the limited ability of the native African, stating
that they could not learn this or that, viz., they could not learn
to be engineers, not even firemen, and such stuff. I told them
black men could do anything that white men could do, in the
Southern States. But since I have reached here, I see native
Africans running engines, manning oar and steamboats, and what
is more, here on this steamship, the Mandingo, are two black
ocean pilots and another black man measuring the depth of the
Ocean and guiding the ship amid the dangerous points.</p>

<p>Poor black man, how the world tells lies about you! Well, we
are at Liberia at last. I will close this letter.</p>

<p>Tenth Letter.</p>

<p>Muhlenberg, Liberia, November 29, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I am here in Liberia, and have been for over a week, and have
had a grand time of it. I landed at Monrovia, where I was met


<pb xml:id="p480" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.036.jpg"/>


by Rev. S. J. Campbell and Clemmons Irons, of Charleston, S. C.,
and conducted to the splendid residence of Gen. R. A. Sherman,
the General-in-Chief of the Liberian government, where a grand
welcome was accorded me. But as the little steamboat was
awaiting me, I soon left the city and proceeded up the St. Paul
River, a river that corresponds exactly with the Ohio River
between Louisville, Ky., and Cincinnati, O.; if anything a bit
wider, and, in the main, much deeper, for the St. Paul River at
places is ninety feet deep. But, unfortunately, the rapids set in
about twenty-five miles above Monrovia and stop all decent
navigation; only canoes can be pushed and pulled beyond the
rapids, and that at great labor. Yet, when the rapids are passed,
the river is navigable by small boats to a long distance. The
sceneries along this river are prodigious; the trees of every kind
for miles are so interwoven that they constitute a matted texture,
with an occasional intermediary elevation or hill, just high and
frequent enough to break the monotony and afford beautiful
building sites, where exuberant farms can be cultivated and the
horticulturist can spread himself. All along the river sides, after
leaving the inundated portion, beautiful two- and three-story
brick houses, covered with zinc roofs, with dormer windows often
projecting from the top, and a number of small adjacent houses
meet the eye. I was certainly surprised to see the comfortable
and excellently constructed homesteads which dot the river
banks in all directions.</p>

<p>As you ascend the St. Paul varied settlements can be seen,
bearing principally American names, where houses, streets and
town clusters are visible. The towns and settlements between
Monrovia and the rapids are called by the following names:
New Georgia, Caldwell, Upper Caldwell, Virginia, Brewersville,
Clay, Ashland, Louisiana, New York, White Plains, Millsburg,
Harrisburg, Muhlenberg and Arthington. Indeed, Arthington
is above the rapids, and is the principal seat of the Azor emigrants,
who came out here twelve or thirteen years ago. The conveniences 
for settlement along the St. Paul are far better than
along the Savannah, Chattahoochee, Alabama, Tennessee or Gun powder 
rivers of America. The Delaware River itself has
nothing to boast over the St. Paul; minus the palisades, the
Hudson River has but few advantages over the St. Paul.</p>

<p>I had the pleasure of meeting and riding for several miles with
Mr. Jesse Sharp, of Columbia, S. C. I used to board with his
mother and smile at his beautiful sisters. Mr. Sharp is about
the richest man in the country. His brother James, from whose
house I married, has been dead, he says, many years.</p>

<p>The steamer went ashore at Mrs. Johnson's fine residence, to
allow me to shake the hand of Dr. Edward W. Blyden, who will
soon be Secretary of State, if reports are true. The doctor looks
well and is growing corpulent.</p>

<p>When I disembarked I was met by Mrs. M. L. Bibbs, recently


<pb xml:id="p481" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.037.jpg"/>


of St Paul, Minn.; Wm. Patterson, James Slocum and Stephen
Ficklin, recently of Morrilton, Ark. Mr. Ficklin has a brother,
Samuel Ficklin, a deacon in Beal Street Baptist Church, Memphis, 
Tenn.; also by G. S. Daniels, Abram Tyler and M. S.
Stephens, recently of Barnsville, S. C., and others.</p>

<p>I spent the night at the well-furnished home of Clemmons
Irons. Elder Geda went to Rev. S. J. Campbell's. Next morning, 
quite early, it was announced to me that Brother Campbell
had a conveyance at the door for me. When I came down-stairs,
lo and behold! four men stood with a fine hammock to trot me
over to breakfast at the residence of Brother Campbell. It is
marvelous what strength these native Africans have. But they
will not have it long unless the Mohamedans come to their
rescue. Christian France, Germany, England and Boston are
distributing too much liquor or rot-gut whiskey among them. I
had no idea that Boston, the citadel of freedom, was sending so
many hundred thousand gallons of poison rot-gut to this country.</p>

<p>The son of the late Rev. A. L. Stanford, once a famous preacher
in our Church, but who died out here some five years ago, as one
of the Judges of the Liberian Courts, has grown up to be an industrious 
and bright young man. His name is Willie Francis
Stanford. But it is useless to mention names, as I find bushels
of Americans here. Therefore, let us talk about this beautiful
country.</p>

<p>Liberia is one of the most paradisical portions of earth my
eyes ever beheld. Any person who cannot live here with reasonable 
health cannot exist anywhere. True, there is an acclimating
change most people have to pass through; some do not; if they
do, they are unconscious of it But nature is lavish here with
her stores. I have noticed the following things growing here in
great abundance: coffee, sugar, ginger, ground-nuts, palm oil,
cocoa, rice, cotton, indigo, pepper, corn, ochre, turnips, beans,
cabbage, tomatoes, lettuce, sweet potatoes, oranges, grapes,
lemons, citrons, squashes and heaven knows what else. Also,
cows, tremendous oxen, hogs, sheep, goats, deer, horses, chickens,
turkeys, ducks, geese, rabbits, dogs, raccoons, opossums, honey
bees, fish without end, eagles, parrots in groves, hawks, but no
buzzards and but few snakes. The native heathen and an ant
called the " driver," leave nothing for the buzzards; so they, like
many human buzzards, have all left and given Africa a bad name.
How under heaven some Negroes can come here and after remaining awhile, 
go back to America and give this place a bad
name I cannot understand, unless it be for the reason that they
do not find scullion employment or some white man to curse and
kick them around. Lazy sloths, they could hibernate six
months annually and then live, so far as the bounties of nature
need operate as a factor. I grant, however, that persons coming
here ought to have a little money to start with and a good deal
of self-reliance, a decent amount of race pride and considerable

<pb xml:id="p482" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.038.jpg"/>

common sense. This is no place for the mere kitchen pimp nor
for the Congo Negro. Those who are here from the Congo are
ignored by the native heathen, much more by the regular
Liberians. They sustain the same relation to the higher African
tribes that they do to us in the United States. I find that they
are the lowest of the African races. I mean all that that word
implies, for there are distinct races here. The Mandingo, Vey,
Pessa and Golahs are far above the Congo, Boozie and others I
might name. The Pessa ladies are the most beautifully-built of
any I ever saw—full limbs, round and large chest, plump all over,
indeed; small feet, neat fingers, as though made for the piano,
and are the most industrious possibly of any on the coast and the
most easily civilized.</p>

<p>Natives do all kinds of work and do it for twenty-five cents
per day or five dollars per month. Show them once or twice
anything you want done and they can do it as well as you. I
believe most of them could learn to set type in a day and the
next day print a newspaper.</p>

<p>The man who buys the African heathen for a fool is a bigger
fool than he is.</p>

<p>I dare also to utter another thing, at the risk of being branded
as the victim of superstition. While the white man deals with
the visible sciences, the African here deals with the invisible sciences; 
while the white man manipulates and utilizes forces, the
black man knows nothing of, the black man controls forces that
the white man is ignorant of. I believe that the black man is acquainted 
with secret agents in the realm of nature that the white
man has never dreamed of, and will offset any telegraph, telephone 
or phonograph ever invented by white men.</p>

<p>This is the only country I have ever seen where everybody
could have a stream of water running through his yard. It is
the most perfectly watered region I have ever witnessed. The
water, too, is clear as a crystal, and rapidly flows wherever seen.
The water-power is inestimable—enough to run the machinery
of the world! O, that my race here had the skill to practicalize
it But that time will come in God's own good time—for come
it will, if revelation be true.</p>

<p>I thought when I came to Africa I would see snakes without
end, but I have seen none yet. People who have been through
the woods in all directions tell me that they have not seen a
snake in ten years, some say fifteen years, others say five years.
I have traveled by water and land for miles upon miles, and have
not seen one yet. People from South Carolina, North Carolina,
Georgia, Alabama, and Tennessee say they could see fifty snakes
there, to one here. People here, fifty years old, never saw a boa
constrictor; yet, that there are some, all concede; nor have I
seen or heard a mosquito, though I expected to be almost eaten
up by them.</p>

<p>If some of our rich colored men in the States would come


<pb xml:id="p483" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.039.jpg"/>


here and open up the coal mines at Carrysburg, they would be
worth millions in a few years. The steamships would buy the
coal by millions of tons. The coaling stations at Grand Canary
and Sierra Leone, now supplied with coal shipped from England,
would be transferred to Liberia, and wealth untold would be the
result. They have coal, marble, silver, gold, tin and diamonds,
all in Liberia. I never had over much admiration for Liberia
until since my arrival here. I thought it was a second-class portion 
of Africa, but it is the richest region of the globe I ever
saw. There is no place in the United States that will begin to
compare with it. Any man who will run down Liberia, so far as
its natural resources are concerned, is a fool and an ass; I am
not talking about what I have heard, either, I am speaking of
what I have seen with my own eyes, and handled with my own
hands. I have seen three armies of the little ants called "drivers,"
which travel through the country and destroy every insect, snake
or animal they catch. I unsuspectedly walked into their ranks,
while prowling around in the woods, inspecting things in general. 
But gracious, did I not run, jump, dance and get out of
my clothes in a hurry! I was soon as clotheless as a native African, 
and indeed more so. But the drivers are the friends of the
country, and I admire them for many reasons.</p>

<p>The Annual Conference of the A. M. E. Church, known as the
Liberia Conference, has been organized and has been in session
three days. The prospects for our church are grand. The joy
of the ministers and members is too ecstatic for description;
ministers of other churches have called and made mighty
speeches of welcome.</p>

<p>Eleventh Letter.</p>

<p>Muhlenberg, Liberia, December 4, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I have just strolled as far out in the direction of Boporo—the
Eden of West-Africa—as my strength and convenience would permit. 
I have seen the African in his native town and hut, rather
dwellings, and I have just had a long weep or cry at the grand
field for missionary operation here, and that I am too old now to
engage in it. But if there were roads cut through the country
and bridges for horses and wagons, I would try it as old as I am.
I am sure I could not stand the hills and valleys of this rolling
country traveling on foot, at my age, and then the hammock
system of travel is too cumbersome for regular locomotion. But
Africa is the grandest field on earth for the labor of civilization
and the Christian Church. There is no reason under heaven why
this Continent should not or cannot be redeemed and brought to
God in twenty-five years—say thirty at most
Note the reasons:</p>

<p>First—The African can beat the world in learning to speak the
English language, in which all religious terms are found to convey
Christian ideas.</p>


<pb xml:id="p484" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.040.jpg"/>


<p>Second.—The young African can come out of the bush, and in
a few months at most, sing and play upon the organ any Gospel
song in print, even before he learns to wear clothes.</p>

<p>Third.—The Africans are the most honest people on earth.
Where I am stopping at present, at the Training School of Rev.
David Hay, scores of wild and partly civilized Africans gather
and sleep all about the yards as well as in the piazzas; not a door
or window is shut all night, unless it is raining or windy.</p>

<p>Fourth.—The African is not a pagan, but a child of superstition;
he worships no wooden or brass god, but believes more strongly
in the invisible forces than we do; so it is an easy matter to have
him transfer his faith from superstition to Christ Jesus the Lord.</p>

<p>Fifth.—And here is the crowning phase of this question: The
Africans will give the God-man or God-woman millions of children 
to be instructed and trained to read, write, work, sing, pray,
farm or do anything that will make them useful. When you
approach the older ones, and begin to tell about the benefits of a
civilized life and the virtues of Christianity, they say: "You no
change me now; take all my pickaninnies (children) and teach
them, make them wise and great; not me, I be too old." And
they will give you all their children, and frequently come once a
week and bring food for them to eat. It makes one feel singular
to see the almost naked native African fathers come out of the
bush, and sit around the Training School, and watch their sons as
they walk the yards in decent dress, and read, write, sing, march,
use tools etc.; they are so fond of their children, finally they will
walk off home, possibly having not uttered a word to their child
or anyone else. The African father seems to be soliloquizing
thus;—"Well, I suppose that will be the order of things in the
future; my day will soon be gone, and another dispensation will
be ushered in."</p>

<p>One thing stands to the everlasting credit of the African; he
is anxious to learn; a seeker after knowledge; to-day he is the
most susceptible heathen upon the face of the globe. He is
ready to lay down any habit, custom or sentiment for a better, or
have his children do it, which is the same thing. It is said, that
often those who have been trained at schools, will return to the:
bush and strip off their clothes and go around like the others.
That seems to be true from what I have seen in some, cases. But
what is the result? These very young men become the leaders
and general instructors of their people; they do not forget their
training by any means. They often become the diplomats of
their tribes and negotiate with other tribes and civilized nations.
Their education is not lost, if they go as naked as a skinned
coon.</p>

<p>The Conference has been organized and named the "Liberia:
Annual Conference of the African M. E. Church." Our session!
has been grand in every particular. Rev. S. J. Campbell, our!
chief representative here, is all that constitutes goodness and 


<pb xml:id="p485" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.041.jpg"/>


greatness. He brought nine preachers to the Conference and, in
the main, very decent-looking men. They have some stereotyped
modes of expression and ways of doing things, but we believe
that will soon be overcome. The reception tendered Elder Geda
and myself was superb. Elder Campbell and Rev. June Moore,
of the Baptist Church, made the speeches, and Campbell felt himself 
upon his own ground, and he literally roared. I had no
dream when he was in America that he was so eloquent and
masterly. He has the respect and confidence of the whole community 
and lives in a three-story brick house, with plenty around
him. His wife is a perfect lady and fills her sphere with all
the grace that her position demands. God save Campbell and
Frederick and their wives!</p>

<p>Rev. June Moore is an able and powerful speaker and a noble
representative of the race.
Rev. David Hay (white), of the Lutheran Church, with whom
Geda and I are stopping, is one of God's noblest men. He
and wife have been here eighteen years; he has built five large
houses and teaches a large number of native children. One
house is his residence, containing many compartments; then
a church and school-house together, then a work- and machine-
shop, then a sleeping house for the students, etc. He has
trained a host of heathen children, who are doing much for
the enlightenment of their tribes. He has immense coffee farms,
and the school is self-supporting. He has solved many problems 
and has the confidence of the heathen for a hundred or
more miles back in the country.</p>

<p>Mr. Hay would have Elder Campbell use his church and
buildings for Conference purposes; so that the Bishop would
have every convenience in meeting the Conference without
much walking, and the Conference would have all necessary
committee rooms. People came in from the country every
night to the Conference by crowds and droves. Some were
dressed in fine order and others almost clotheless, but they sang
with a vim and listened with great attention. It certainly looks
peculiar to see people praising God with a bare cloth around
their waists. It only shows that the soul is in the body, and
not in the garments.</p>

<p>Rev. S. J. Campbell was elected a delegate from the Liberia
Conference to the General Conference, about like Elder Frederick 
was at Sierra Leone—got every vote except one, and
that was cast by themselves for another.</p>

<p>I never saw such rejoicing over the presence of a Bishop as
there is in Liberia. The preachers seem to have forgotten God
and gone to Bishop worship. I have reproved them repeatedly,
but it does no good. The ministers of other churches have
shown us marvelous respect. I have ordained six deacons.
Brother Campbell is hard at work on his hundred-acre coffee
farm; has several thousand coffee trees set out; and, if we will


<pb xml:id="p486" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.042.jpg"/>


stand by Africa a few years, the coffee-farm will support the
whole business. I wish our Church in the United States could
but see the coffee-farm Brother Campbell has now growing for
our Church. If Campbell had $5,000, after five years he would
send our missionary treasurer $50,000 yearly.</p>

<p>Oh! how the people of Liberia want a steamship directly
to America. England, France, Spain and Germany all have
scores of steamships laden with goods and whiskey at fabulous
prices; and Yates &#38; Porterfield send only one or two sailships
from New York, and they will ship nothing for the people unless
they themselves are the purchasers. Elder Campbell wanted to
ship a thousand pounds of coffee to Mr. W. H. Amos, of Philadelphia, 
but could not. If the moneyed colored men of America
would band together and go to England and purchase a secondhand 
steamship at one-third its price and start a trade between
here and the United States, they would be worth millions in a
few years. It is a shame before high heaven that we are such
consummate fools. The national government of Liberia is also
unwise for not doing it. The Custom House revenues of the
Liberian government amount, at least, to $300,000 a year, and
she might do it easily enough. But she is so American in her
ideas; she thinks it beneath her national dignity to engage in
commercial enterprise, and here we all are fools together, while
England, France, Spain and Germany are reaping untold millions
that the black man ought to have. I get mad and sick when I
look at the possibilities God has placed within our reach, and to
think we are such big blockheads we cannot see and utilize
them. I have long said that the salvation of the black man was
in connection with this country; I see the wisdom of my position 
now as I never dreamed of before. If the black man ever
rises to wealth, he will either do it in Africa, or as he operates in
connection with Africa. He will never do it trying to be white,
or by snubbing his native country.</p>

<p> Mrs. Phoebe Corzan, formerly Mrs. Phoebe Brown Deputie,
late of Philadelphia, a lady of marked intelligence, tells me that
a few miles beyond where I am at present, in the Gibby mountains, 
about sixty miles from Monrovia, the water is so cool
that it chills one's hands to put them in it, and if people coming
here would leave the coast and go back there, they would never
have any acclimating change at all. Even where I am now I do
not believe I would be sick in forty years, although I may be
mistaken.</p>

<p>The Conference here has ten mission points, and three to be
supplied—making thirteen in all. One point is named after
Bishop Campbell, another after Bishop Shorter and another after
Bishop Cain. Elder S. J. Campbell fought till he got one point
named Eliza Ann Turner Mission; I objected, but the Conference 
overruled me. Our membership here is a little less than
three hundred and fifty.</p>


<pb xml:id="p487" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.043.jpg"/>


<p>Rev. S. J. Campbell is appointed Superintendent of Missions
and chief of the coffee farm and industrial department of the
Liberian Conference, and Rev. T. R. Geda is appointed Presiding
Elder.</p>

<p>Had Geda not come with me I do not know what I would
have done; he has been of incalculable use to me. On committees, 
especially, has he been a great guide. He has demonstrated superior 
business tact and a fine judgment.</p>

<p>Our Conference lasted seven days; indeed, it virtually included
two Sabbaths, and we have certainly had a big time. All kinds
of resolutions of thanks have been passed to the Bishops and the
Mother Church for sending me here.</p>

<p>Quite a settled African lady came out of the bush, with portly
limbs, massive head, all bare except a cloth around the waist,
hair done up in the most ornamental style, pure silver cuffs,
leopard teeth tied and dangling to the elbows, fetish balls fastened
to the rear part of the head, beads strung around the body,
dressed to death after the fashion of the Gollah tribe. She was
introduced to Geda and me, having learned that we had come
from big America. She was a mistress of the Greggree Bush
and counsellor of the big chiefs of her people. The woman
looked frightful and pretty too. She sat with me on the piazza
for some time, then came and walked into my room some time
after without invitation and sat for a time and talked with me
through her interpreter. She never complimented Geda a bit,
but she said I was "a good man and nice heap much, and pretty
all over." Of course, I was glad to hear it, for I had not heard
it before. Her name is Blarbubber, and she is known as the
queen of the Greggree Bush. But I must close till I visit Monrovia, 
which I will do next week, when you will hear from me
again, God willing. Elder S. J. Campbell disapproves of the
way I knock around and the little care I take of myself. He
thinks if I should get sick from any cause it would be charged
to Liberia.</p>

<p>Brother Campbell and wife tendered Elder Geda and myself a
superb dinner a few days ago. Several of his most prominent
neighbors were present—ladies and gentlemen—and the time
passed off grandly. I never saw so much to eat for the same
number of guests.</p>

<p>Twelfth Letter.</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, December 5, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I have descended the St Paul River and am now in Monrovia,
stopping in the beautiful three-story brick residence of General
R. A. Sherman, general-in-chief of the Liberian armies. Every
thing is superb in and outside of this spacious and finely-furnished
palace. I would wager anything, that General W. T. Sherman


<pb xml:id="p488" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.044.jpg"/>


never lived in more style, and I am sure he never possessed anything 
like the social graces of the Liberian General Sherman.
The general somewhat resembles ex-Senator B. K. Bruce in
stature, color, hair and demeanor. He was born in Savannah, Ga.,
is about fifty years of age, and has been here some thirty-seven
years. He has fought many battles, has been wounded repeatedly
and his name is a terror to the native heathen for hundreds of
miles in the interior.</p>

<p>I have seen many sights of interest in the city. Dr. Blyden
carried me through the Kroo Town, introduced me to the king,
with whom I had a long talk. I was surprised at his intelligence
and general information. He was dressed as a gentleman and
very polite. His subjects, or people, treat him with great respect.
The city is laid off" in streets and squares, but not equal in extent,
sometimes the streets curve and, in other cases, they so intersect
one another as to form a triangle.</p>

<p>The houses are built of plaited sheets of bamboo, which they
plait upon the ground with taste and skill, and in some instances
with peculiar art. Then they are set up and fastened to timbers,
and rooms, kitchens, palaver halls, sitting-rooms and such like
are made in the same building.</p>

<p>It is useless to talk about the African having no taste and
pride.</p>

<p>I have found out another thing since I have come to Africa,
gone scores of miles through the interior and noted the tact, taste,
genius and manly bearing of the higher grade of the natives; I
have found out that we poor American Negroes were the tail-end
of the African races. We were slaves over here, and had been
for a thousand years or more before we were sold to America.
Those who think the receding forehead, the flat nose, the 
proboscidated mouth and the big flat-bottom foot are natural to the
African are mistaken. There are heads here by the millions, as
vertical or perpendicular as any white man's head God ever made.
A straight rule laid upon the face of three-fourths of us in America
will touch the nose and mouth only; here are native Africans,
without number, whose nose and chin the rule would touch with-
out touching the mouth, which is always indicative of the highest
type of intellectuality. Some of the most neat and concave feet
are found upon thousands of these Africans. I have seen specimens 
of 19 tribes, and I have not seen over 100 of them constructed 
on as low scale as I have seen in America. An African
said to be 108 years old, said: "We no used to sell  big blood'
African to white man, except we capture him in war." I believe
this old man tells the truth; that during the times of the slave
trade there were no "big blood" first-class Africans sold to the
white man, unless they were war prisoners.</p>

<p>Monrovia far exceeds my expectations. Instead of being low,
swampy and alluvial, it is on an elevated cape, three sides laved
by the ocean and tanned by her breezes, will average about 150


<pb xml:id="p489" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.045.jpg"/>

feet above the sea-level, I think. In the main, the houses are
excellent, two-, three- and a few four-stories high, with sidewalks
very good, but the streets proper are grassy and not kept in regular 
order. As they use no horses and wagons, so the streets are
not needed ; but they are far superior to hundreds of streets I
have seen where horses and mules are used.</p>

<p>In the rear of Monrovia, however, where a branch of the St.
Paul River, called the Stockton Creek, and the Mesurado River
form a confluence, there are some large Mangrove swamps, alluvial, 
soft and lagoonish, which evidently emit a great deal of malaria 
and are highly productive of fever germs when the wind is
blowing from the land side, just as we have in thousands of
places in the United States. There is no remedy for this, for God
is making these two rivers cart dirt from the high lands to fill up
the low; the debris is gradually doing its work, and the people
must await His time.</p>

<p>The Liberia College is situated on the side of Mount Mesurado; 
the curriculum is high and the teachers are well informed;
two more learned professors are being looked for daily. The college 
is a credit to the government of Liberia, for it is a national
institution.</p>

<p>I have had the honor of visiting the executive mansion of the
Liberian government, was received with marked consideration,
and the President, who is a polished scholar, paid me special
attention. I had seen nine Presidents in the United States, but
a real black President was to me a delightful sight. This administration 
is praised and blamed by friends and foes, just as
is the case with our presidents. The Liberian government is
in the hands of the following, who form the executive department: 
His Excellency H. R. W. Johnson, President, born in Liberia; 
Secretary of State, Hon. E. J. Barclay, born in Barbadoes,
West Indies; Secretary of Treasury, Hon. H. W. Travis, born in
Liberia; Postmaster-General, Hon. H. J. Moore, born in Liberia;
Attorney-General, Hon. W. M. Davis, born in Philadelphia, Pa.;
Secretary of the Interior, not filled. The Secretary of the Treasury, 
for the present, does the duties of the War and Naval
Departments. Chief Justice Hon. C. L. Parsons, born in Charleston, S. C.</p>

<p>The President-elect, who will take his seat early in January,
1892, is Hon. J. J. Cheeseman, of Grand Bassa, born in Liberia;
Vice-President-elect, Hon. W. D. Coleman, born in Kentucky.
Mr. Cheeseman is represented as an able man with progressive
views.</p>

<p>I visited the Monrovia cemetery a few days ago, and was
pleased with the tombstones, slabs and shafts I saw commemorating 
the dead. I counted nearly a hundred, some of
which cost over a thousand dollars. I saw the grave of my aunt,
"Hannah Greer," who died about the same time my mother did,
some three years ago. She was about ninety years old; she

<pb xml:id="p490" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.046.jpg"/>


was my oldest aunt of five, and the people here say she was
a grand woman. I hope to send or bring her a marble head
and foot slab from America. I visited also the graves of Hon.
M. A. Hopkins, Hon. and Dr. Henry Highland Garnett, Hon.
Alexander Clark, and Mrs. Mary Garnett Barboza, the distinguished 
daughter of Dr. Garnett. Hopkins, Garnett and Clark
were the three American Ministers of State, who have died
here. There is not a stone, or a shingle, at the foot or head
of the grave of Dr. Garnet,—a shame, a shame, upon us
American Negroes!</p>

<p>For forty years before Mr. Lincoln issued his proclamation of
freedom, Dr. Garnett fought for his race as no other man could,
except Douglass, when the lips of the southern Negro were sealed
and he was gored by the slave-masters to the verge of death. Dr.
Garnett periled life and everything for his freedom; now for us
American Negroes to allow his remains to lie here, as though he
was a dog, is enough to make God blast the whole of us. As I
looked at his grave I wept, and asked God if there was any hope
for such an ungrateful people. If we do not send a tombstone
here to mark this grave, the whole Negro race in America deserves 
the contempt of perdition, to say nothing of heaven.</p>

<p>Hon. C. T. O. King is the agent of the Colonization Society
here. He is a man of excellent parts and evidently understands
himself. Mr. King thinks that some improvements could be made
in the reception of emigrants from America, and I think so too.
But as I will speak about them at the proper place if I live, I will
only say at present, that any persons coming out here should not
come as paupers. While Liberia is the easiest place to make a
living on earth and is the most paradisiacal spot in the world,
all things considered, yet, there is a climatic change which most
people must pass through (many do not), and while they are
passing through it, they need rest and fresh food, which the 
Colonization Society does not provide, nor can it without steamships, 
hence they need money to purchase the necessary food
and often some medicine. Persons should not come here and
expect to be hirelings; for the native stands ready to do all
kinds of work much cheaper and better than we can, except to
do skilled labor. They till the ground and raise all the produce
for twenty-five cents per day, or five dollars per month. A man
coming here with two or three hundred dollars and good sense
may be rich in four or five years. But this is no place for fools
and paupers. The oldest man in Liberia at present is only 
one-hundred-and-twenty-seven years; the oldest woman is one-
hundred-and-twenty. A young man twenty-seven years old has
a wife seventy-two years old, and he is jealous of her and another
fellow twenty-four years old.</p>

<p>The ministers of Monrovia are as follows:—Rev. Garrison W.
Gibson, of the Episcopal Church; Rev. Henry Cooper, M. E.
Church; Rev. Robert J. Clark, Baptist Church; Rev. J. B. Perry



<pb xml:id="p491" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.047.jpg"/>



Presbyterian Church. All these ministers treat Geda and me
with great courtesy. The Episcopal minister could not offer me
his church to preach in, owing to the canons of his connection,
but he urged me to lecture in it, but the M. E. Church pastor
appropriated our service. He is a Christian and a gentleman
of the highest type. Everybody seems to be overjoyed at the
presence of the A. M. E. Church in Liberia, the welcome
appears to be universal. Many desire that it shall be the
National Church, others declare it will be the Continental
Church. They have come after me to organize in Monrovia
at once, but for reasons that I shall tell the bishops, I will not.</p>

<p>A minister of the A. M. E. Zion Church, who had united
with us and claimed to be ordained by one—Elder Cartright-
maintained that his orders were valid, as Brother Cartright was
Superintendent of the Church here and had been authorized by
Bishop Hood to ordain. I denied the right of Bishop Hood
to confer any such authority upon an Elder and rejected his
ordination. I ordained him a Deacon, however, after due 
examination. I am sure Bishop Hood never did it.</p>

<p>The people here think I am a "rough," because I will sit
in the draught, eat all kinds of African food, sleep with the
windows open, walk around barefooted, etc., preach or speak
every night. But I believe some people die here because of particularity. 
I never felt better in my life; but I cannot say how
long this will continue.</p>

<p>They say Hon. Alexander Clarke, who died here, had passed
through the acclimating fever and would have lived easily enough
had he not refused to eat food that would strengthen him; he
confined himself to American hog soup, when the doctor and all
begged him to eat other things. The people here say stinginess
killed him. The report, however, that strong drink killed him
is pronounced a base falsehood. People here say he was purely
temperate.</p>

<p>The night and morning here are as cool as in Washington city
in November. This morning a drink of water chilled my teeth.
But from 11 o'clock to 1 it is certainly hot. I have met no hotter
weather here, however, than I have in the United States.</p>

<p>Thirteenth Letter.</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, December 7, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>The hospitality of the Liberians has no limit; the social forms
here, however, partake largely of those in vogue among the English. 
I infer this from what I have read and heard of English customs more 
than from any personal knowledge. Politeness, style
and dignity are by no means wanting, yet the cast of the American order 
is not prominent. But we Americans have no social
standard. In Liberia breakfast receptions at ten o'clock in the
morning are the rule for distinguished guests.</p>


<pb xml:id="p492" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.048.jpg"/>



<p>It would seem, from all I can learn, that Rev. Daniel Coker
played a prominent part in the early settlement of Liberia. The
first Methodist Church established here was the African M. E.
Church; but by whom established I cannot say. Tradition says
it was afterward sold out to the M. E. Church. Besides the
probability of Rev. Daniel Coker's having established our Church
here, he also played a mighty part among the early settlers of
Sierra Leone. His children and grand-children are found there
to-day.</p>

<p>President-elect Hon. J. J. Cheseman will take his seat early in
January, under very encouraging circumstances. The Kroo
tribe, the most important along the African coast, by virtue of its
maritime character and without whom the ships could do nothing
in commerce, has sent him an address expressing its loyalty to
the Liberian Republic and its desire to co-operate in the maintenance 
of his administration. This tribe will be a mighty support to the 
new president; the more so as it is beginning to
realize the treachery of some of the European nations toward
Africa. The Mandingo, the chief Mohamedan tribe, has also
sent the new president an elaborate communication of congratulation, 
assuring him of its support. This is one of the most
mighty and progressive tribes in Africa and extends back for
hundreds of miles into the interior. Mr. Cheseman has everything 
to hope for, provided he fills the bill of public expectation,
as everybody believes that his administration will inaugurate a
new deal.</p>

<p>The eight years administration of President Johnson, while not
marked, as I am informed, by many brilliant exploits, has, nevertheless, 
held things in such a <sic>statu</sic> quo that the new administration 
can enlarge, if so disposed.</p>

<p>One of the chief deficits of the Liberian Republic is the absence
of a bank. Sierra Leone has at least two banks, and from the
income of Liberia she could have a bank easily enough, if I have
been properly informed, but it is presumed that they understand
their business better than I can. Things may drag along somewhat, 
but Liberia is destined to play a grand part in the future.
Her natural resources are too infinite to remain stagnant forever;
if there has been any lack of foresight in the past, the remedy
will come in God's own time.</p>

<p>Rev. James H. Deputie, of the M. E. Church, a most polished
and Christian gentleman, welcomes the A. M. E. Church to
Liberia as heartily as any of our own ministers. His kindness
to me personally and his congratulations in general to our
Church, secure our gratitude.</p>

<p>Bishop William Taylor, D.D., is not just as popular as I expected 
to find him, among the members and ministers of his own
Church. They say he realizes himself as white, and does not
fail to let them know it, and often gives out utterances from the
pulpit not appreciated by any means. When, in one of the M. E.


<pb xml:id="p493" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.049.jpg"/>


Churches, I spoke of the Bishop as being one of the grandest
divines on earth, I noticed that many frowned at the expression, 
and some took me to task about it, after services were over.
I did not recant, however.</p>

<p>Yesterday I received an invitation, through Dr. Blyden, from
Mrs Jennie Sharp, to visit the female department of Liberia
College, established in 1883. Mrs. Sharp, formerly Miss Jennie
Davis, teacher at Webster Grove, Mo., responded to the call of
Dr. Blyden in 1882 for teachers for the college. She went to
work, not even waiting to be acclimated, and using the material
she had, organized the school, and has continued teaching ever
since, with marvelous success. Many a young wife, now an
ornament of Liberian society, has passed through her hands.
She has nearly fifty girls, both children of the colonists and of
the natives from the interior. There are about ten interior girls,
one a Mandingo and the others from far beyond the Mandingo
districts. These, Mrs. Sharp thinks, belong to the Wahoma
Tribe in East Africa. While these interior girls are pure
African, they show to a demonstration, that all Africans are not
black; some of them are as light as mulattoes, with silky hair.
Astonishing sights will some day be revealed from interior
Africa. Mrs. Sharp deserves great credit for her zeal and enterprise 
in securing and keeping these children. She supports a
number of her pupils at her own expense. I would commend
this institution to the generosity of all friends of female education
in Africa. Any books, clothing or money sent to Mrs. Sharp
will be worthily bestowed. She and her children attend the
Presbyterian Church at Monrovia. Mrs. Sharp came to Africa,
I believe, at the same time Professors T. McCants Stewart and
H. Brown did. She is now the wife of that great business man,
Mr. Jesse Sharp, referred to in a former letter as having come
from Columbia, S. C., forty years ago.</p>

<p>(Since Bishop Turner left Africa he has learned of the death
of Mr. Sharp.)</p>

<p>A Change of Base.</p>

<p>Since writing the above I have left Monrovia and am now in
Sierra Leone again. Dr. Blyden and myself took a German ship,
which carried us eighty miles up the Sherbro River; so I have
been eighty miles in the interior in another direction, up to a
place called York Island. What an immense river this Sherbro
is! The inlets to African cities and towns are innumerable. But
of all the places I have seen in Africa, this is the most unhealthy
region. Eatables are incalculable in variety; provisions of every
kind are abundant; yet, I would not advise any new-comer to
settle up the Sherbro River. White men and ladies, however, are
here apparently reasonably healthy, acting as ship agents and
school teachers.</p>

<p>Dr. Edward W. Blyden, who traveled with me for six days, is


<pb xml:id="p494" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.050.jpg"/>


a marvelous scholar; when he meets an African of whatever
tribe, or a German, Frenchman, Italian, Spaniard or Portuguese,
he talks right along in their native tongue, as though he were
speaking English.</p>

<p>Since I left Monrovia, I have learned that certain African
kings from the Pan Pedro River—the southeastern boundary of
Liberia—have visited Sierra Leone to protest to the British government 
against the occupation by the French of their territory
contrary to their will and without their consent. They claim to
be part of the Republic of Liberia, and decidedly prefer Liberian
rule to French.</p>

<p>One of the most outrageous things of modern times is the way
the French, because they possess the might, have seized upon
over a hundred miles of bona fide Liberian territory, under the
iniquitous regulations by which the European nations have agreed
to partition out Africa, and under which atrocious arrangement
the French are threatening the "Hinterland" of Liberia. The
following notice appeared in the Sierra Leone Weekly News, December 5, 1891:</p>

<p>"The British Commissioners for the delimitation of the English and French 
frontiers arrived here on the evening of December 2, 1891, by the steamship 
Kinsembo, Capt. A. H. Kenny, R. N., and a detachment of Royal Engineers, 
Surgeon Major J. J. Lamprey, Army Medical Staff, and Mr. Scott Elliott, 
attached as botanist to the Commission, from the Royal Gardens, Kew.</p>

<p>"The French officers who form the French Commission are M. Lamadon, Principal
Administrator of the 'Rivieres du sud,' Lieutenant Bransoulie, 15th de Ligne, and
Docteur Bonnefoy, French Navy; they arrived in Freetown from Marseilles on
Saturday morning, per steamship Tiflet.</p>

<p>"The object of the Commission is to define the limits of the French and English
territory to the North of the colony of Sierra Leone, and to establish with 
geographical precision the delimitation already agreed upon by the two governments."</p>

<p>The Commissioners have been to Sierra Leone and arranged
for an exploring journey, by which they will parcel out other
people's country; tribes unwilling to receive them and with whom
they have no quarrel, but whose territory they covet. Will not
the God of Naboth visit these powerful European nations for
these things? Will not the United States government interfere
to prevent Liberian territory from being gobbled up by the
French? Has not the American government the right to help
a feeble nation, founded partly under her patronage; and when
she has in her domain millions of the descendants of Africa, many
of whom are looking to the same Liberia as their future home or
the home of their posterity?</p>

<p>I believe the Judge of all the earth will do right. He will over rule 
the cupidity of man, in the interest of the Negro, in this instance, as 
He overruled the slave trade. Europe thought she
was serving herself by enslaving Africa and her people. Twelve
millions of us in the Western Hemisphere have been brought in
contact with civilization and Christianity, and are being prepared
to take intelligent possession of our fatherland.</p>

<p>Upon my return from Liberia I found Rev. J. R. Frederick,


<pb xml:id="p495" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.051.jpg"/>


Presiding Elder of the Sierra Leone Conference, quite sick with
fever. He is in bed at present, but better, and will be out in a
few days.</p>

<p>Our American representative here, Hon Bolding Bowser, is
a grand man and fills his station with consummate ability. His
wife, Mrs. G. E Bowser, is a lady of fine attainments and uncommon 
sense. Mr. Bowser lets no interest of his government
suffer. He proves beyond all question the ability of the colored
man to look after the interests of our great nation, even though
the nation cares but little for him.</p>

<p>Fourteenth Letter.</p>

<p>York Island, Sherbro River, Africa, December 9, 1891.</p>

<p>Mr. Editor:</p>

<p>I have left Monrovia and am now some seventy-five miles up
the Sherbro River, interior-ward from the ocean. The native
towns and vast population of our people living on each side of
this river, and all through the Bush, is simply wonderful. As
you ascend the Sherbro, every now and then, small inlets can be
seen flowing in from the land, while trees lock their branches
across them, and flower-bearing vines festoon them with garlands 
of fragrant drapery. But, reverberating through and under
these over-arched inlets, you can hear the voices of scores of
natives, as they chant their rowing songs; for the native Africans
sing as they work, especially as they row their boats, till they
burst from under the green sceneries with small canoes laden
with all kinds of fruits; often a Mohamedan priest sits in front,
gorgeously robed, as though he was on watch for whiskey; as
the sixty millions of Mohamedans in Africa hate whiskey as
they do the devil himself. Say what you please about the Mohamedans 
and their plurality of wives (which of course no
Christian can endorse) I verily believe that God is holding these
Mohamedans intact, and that they will serve as the forerunners
of evangelical Christianity; in short, that the Mohamedan religion 
is the morning-star to the sun of pure Christianity. I have
not spoken on any occasion against liquor-drinking in Africa,
but some Mohamedan has come and shook my hand after service, and 
thanked me for fighting whiskey. One thanked me
"for cursing liquor," and, said he, "Our church and religion all
curse it, too; it be our greatest foe." God save the Mohamedans, 
is my prayer, till the Christian Church is ready to do her
whole duty. Beyond the fact that the Mohamedans allow more
than one wife, they are as upright in conduct and civil behavior
as any people in the land.</p>

<p>I regret to say what I am now going to write, but I promised
to do it, and I suppose I had better keep my word:</p>

<p>The leading men, or a large number of them in Liberia, are
disgusted with a majority of the representatives that our govern-


<pb xml:id="p496" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.052.jpg"/>


ment sends over here. They say if our government cannot find
sober, cool-headed, dignified and intelligent representatives of
our own color to send here, ask the President to send white
men. Dr. Henry Highland Garnett is the only man sent here,
whom all join in complimenting, for many years. They say Dr.
Garnett was a gentleman and a diplomat of high order. They
also speak kindly of Hon. Alexander Clark, so far as his sobriety
and morality are concerned, but say that he had no knowledge
of diplomacy. Some of our representatives have so far ignored
the rules of diplomatic dignity or decorum, that they have tried
to force themselves into the President's Cabinet-meetings. But
I will tell no more, as I dislike gossip in any form; yet they
prefer a white man to some of our colored men whom the Presidents 
have sent here.</p>

<p>It appears that the American minister is the Dean of the
Diplomatic Corps at Monrovia, and in any formal meeting or
reception he is the presiding officer, as he ranks the representatives 
of all other nations; therefore he should be a model man
in every respect.</p>

<p>Liberia, as I have said before, is a most beautiful country, and
nature has supplied it with all that heart could wish. I never
wanted to be a young man so badly in my life. I would come
here, and, if I had half as much sense as I have now, I would
be worth a fortune in ten years. Nevertheless, as I have said
before, I would advise no one to come here without a hundred
or two dollars. This is not the place for anyone to come with
no money. Well, if he is a mechanic, viz., carpenter, blacksmith,
painter, tailor, watchmaker, or professional, as a doctor or a
lawyer, he might do well enough; but a mere laborer should
bring some money, for the native African stands ready, ten thousand 
strong, to snatch up all the mere common labor to be done,
at twenty-five cents per day, or five dollars a month; and two
native Africans can do more hard work in one day than five of
our ordinary men, such is their strength and vigor.</p>

<p>As for the acclimating process, nearly everybody must pass
through it, yet all do not have the fever; men, and women too,
who have been here ten and fifteen years, tell me they have
never had anything like fever. But if a person comes here,
young or old, with any chronic disease lurking in his system,
Africa is apt to purge it out, or kill the person in the process
of purgation. At all events, the party will get better or worse.
But if a person comes here healthy, sound and sober, there is no
more danger than in any other change of climate.</p>

<p>One thing the black man has here—that is, manhood, freedom,
and the fullest liberty; he feels as a lord, and walks and talks
the same way.</p>

<p>I notice when the English, or even the cultured Africans,
speak of the colored people coming here from America, or else-
where, returning here, they do not use the terms "emigrate," or


<pb xml:id="p497" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.053.jpg"/>


"African emigration," as we do in America; but they invariably
say, "repatriate," or use the term, the "repatriation of the black 
man," or, as some say, the "Negro;" nor are the terms "emigrate" or 
"immigrate" used, even among the common people,
as they say, "coming home," or "When are you all coming
home?" The native African, from the kings down, cannot realize 
that the black man in America is at home across the sea.</p>

<p>Out of the many receptions given in my honor, or the honor
of the church, and the eloquent addresses delivered upon the
occasions, I will send the two following: they being the only
ones which have fallen into my hands in manuscript. I failed to
get the others by reason of having to leave so soon. The first
was delivered by Rev. June Moore, of the Baptist Church, the
great friend and comrade of Rev. S. J. Campbell, at the opening
of the Liberian Conference; the other at the ten o'clock breakfast 
tendered to Elder Geda and myself at Monrovia, which was
read by Hon. H. W. Grimes.</p>

<p>Address of Rev. June Moore to Bishop Turner, at the Opening of the Liberia Conference, A. M. E. Church.</p>

<p>Rt. Rev. and Dear Sir:</p>

<p>It becomes my duty, in behalf of the ministry and members of the A. M. E. Church,
whose invitation to visit Liberia you have so kindly accepted, to extend you a hearty
welcome to our shores. I have often heard and read with much interest, pleasure and
thankfulness of your devoted labors and zeal for our common race, as well as of your
desire and untiring efforts to impress the Negro of America with a strong and clear
sense of his obligation to God and his race.</p>

<p>I am thankful, too, to our common Father, that your labors have met with so much
success, and I hope that your visit to Liberia may be of much interest to you, and that
your short stay here may encourage us in the great and grand work which lies before
us; believing that on your return to our brethren in America, you will be better prepared 
to lay before them the true condition of Africa—the Old Homestead of our
Fathers, as you now see it.</p>

<p>We are again thankful to our Gracious Father for the gifts and graces with which
He has endowed you. He has evidently set you forth as one of the leaders of our
race, to mark to us a line upon which we are to work.</p>

<p>It affords me much pleasure to say that it is coming clearer and clearer to the minds
of the leading men of our race that we have a distinct work to do for God and the
race, which no one can do but ourselves. May your life be spared for the great work
in which you are engaged!</p>

<p>It is not until we have gotten these grand principles of self-respect implanted in
our hearts, then, and not until then we shall demand respect from all nations. Again
I welcome you to the shores of Africa. Look to the North, South, East and West,
or as far as Africa extends, foreign nations boast in their scramble for Africa, that they
have divided it among themselves. Yet we believe that when we shall have gotten
right with God and with ourselves, all these powers will give way for the peaceful
possession by the sons of Ham.</p>

<p>May the blessings of God rest upon you and the dear brethren in your present work
and may the standard of Emmanuel which you are planting here, rise higher and
higher, until the millions that are now sitting in darkness catch the bright rising of the
Sun of righteousness.</p>

<p>Address.</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, December 5, 1891.</p>

<p>To the Right Rev. Henry M. Turner, D.D., LL.D., Bishop of the A. M. E. Church.</p>

<p>Right Reverend and Dear Sir:</p>

<p>We feel that it would not be fitting for you to leave our shores without our putting
on record the feeling of gratification with which we have seen you among us.</p>



<pb xml:id="p498" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0002.054.jpg"/>



<p>Some of those who are allied to us by ties of blood, but who are divided from us by
the misfortunes which have crushed out of them race pride and self-respect, have
from time to time come among us and left among us sad impressions of the condition
and feelings of our brethren in the United States, and taken back to them evil tidings
of this little Republic, like the ten spies, filling the hearts of the people with fear and
dismal foreboding, and making wider the chasm which divides the scattered children
of Africa from their Fatherland.</p>

<p>In you, however, we rejoice to meet a man of another stamp, and great as is our
pleasure to greet you as an eminent theologian, a profound scholar, a true Christian
and the honored representative of a church which has peculiar claims upon our interests 
and sympathy, we are yet more pleased to greet you as one whose race instincts are 
unimpaired, and who, seeing the weaknesses and shortcomings of your
people, can look beyond them and perceive the elements of greatness which exist in
them, and believe that God, in his wise providence, is fitting them for great things.</p>

<p>To many of us you are personally a stranger, but to none of us are you unknown.
We have heard of your battles for Africa, and the noble efforts which you have put
forth to open the eyes of the descendants of Ham in the United States to their duties,
responsibilities and privileges as such as to induce them to lend a helping hand to us
in Liberia, who are, as we believe, the pioneers of that mighty host of Africa's sons
whose blessed privilege it will be to break the chains of sin and ignorance, with which
Africa's millions have been bound, and win this grand Continent and its magnificent
sons for Christ.</p>

<p>We bid you God-speed as a Bishop and trust that the seed sown by you during
your visit may spring up, bear abundant fruit for Christ and for Africa, and that the
small beginning which you have made, may, under the fostering care of the Almighty,
grow into a powerful African Church.</p>

<p>We bid you God speed as a man who loves his race and trust that you may be spared
to return to your people, encouraged and fortified and bearing to them glad tidings of
great joy, and that you may live to see some of the fruits of your labors in Africa and
for Africa.</p>

<p>We trust that it may be our privilege to see you among us again; but should this
privilege be denied us, we assure you that our hearts go with you and our prayers shall
ascend for you, as for all with whom—although separated from them by leagues of sea
and land—we are co-workers, striving to attain a common goal.</p>

<p>To those of our brethren in the United States who are, like you, lovers of Africa
and their race, we beg you to convey our greetings and assure them that there is room
and work for them here and that should they come among us they will find a hearty
welcome and a home.</p>

<p>We beg Rt. Rev. and Dear Sir to subscribe ourselves your friends and servants.</p>

<p>Signed by</p>

<list>
<item>His Excellency H. R. W. Johnson, President of Liberia.</item>
<item>Hon. H. W. Travis, Secretary of the Treasury.</item>
<item>Hon. H. A. Williams, Mayor of Monrovia.</item>
<item>Rev. G. W. Gibson, Rector of Trinity Episcopal Church, Monrovia.</item>
<item>Edward W. Blyden, D.D., LL.D.</item>
<item>Hon. W. M. Davis, Attorney-General.</item>
<item>Hon. George W. Dixon, Superintendent of the Montserrado Co.</item>
<item>Hon. C. C. O. King, Agent of the American Colonization Society and late Mayor of Monrovia.</item>
<item>Gen. R. A. Sherman, Brigadier-General of Liberian Army.</item>
<item>Rev. F. B. Perry, Pastor of Presbyterian Church, Monrovia.</item>
<item>Hon. H. W. Grimes, Ex-Attorney-General.</item>
<item>Mr. J. B. Dennis, Merchant, and Chief Mechanic.</item>
<item>Rev. Henry Cooper, Pastor of the Methodist Episcopal Church, Monrovia.</item>
<item>J. R. Cooper, Esq., Merchant at Monrovia.</item>
<item>J. C. Dickinson, Esq., Merchant at Monrovia.</item>
<item>Rev. D. Ware, Methodist Episcopal Missionary, Cape Mont.</item>
</list>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
