<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0076">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from the Chief of Administrative Service and President of the Committee Commerce, March 11, 1840</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Niendorf, Nicholas" xml:id="nn">Nicholas Niendorf</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0076</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Chief of Administrative Service and President of the Committee Commerce</title>
<date when="1840-03-11">March 11, 1840</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>FR ANOM</repository>
<collection>Senegal VI</collection>
<idno>6b</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>F. Dupuy</term>
<term>JH Ware</term>
<term>Mr. Guibert</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Gambia</term>
<term>Port of Gorée</term>
<term>Saint Louis</term>
<term>Senegal</term>
<term>United States</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>






</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Chief of Administrative Service and President of the Committee Commerce</roleName>
<placeName>Gorée Port</placeName>
<date when="1840-03-11"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="nn">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2018" who="par">Translated.</change>
<change when="2018" who="sab">Encoded.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="20160614_145014.jpg"/>

<ab>
Sénégal et Dépendances
</ab>

<ab>
Port de Gorée.
</ab>

<p>
Aujourd'hui onze mars mil huit cent quarante,
la commission commerciale de Gorée, s'est réunie, sur
la convocation de son Président, pour entendre la
lecture d'une dépêche ministérielle du 2% Décembre 1839,
relative à la question d'établir l'égalité respective des
taxes affectant le pavillon, à l'égard des navires français
et américains pesant la navigation entre les états-unis
et Gorée et réciproquement.
</p>

<p>
Etaient présents.
</p>

<p>
M. M. Guibert, Chef du service <unclear>admif</unclear>, Président.
ferroliet, négociant
huchard} Marchand
f. Dupuy.} Marchand
Jh Ware} habitant
Jn Dupuy} habitant
</p>

<p>
La Commission ignore quels sont les droits que
l'on paye aux Etats-Unis sur les marchandises qui y
sont admises, mais il faudrait qu'ils fûssent bien
faibles pour qu'il fûssent moindres que ceux perçus
à Gorée sur les produits de l'Union qui sont admises
dans les droits et trouvent portés ci contre
</p>

<!-- This page is continued on a different picture file, "20160614_145014.jpg" -->

<pb facs="20160614_145027.jpg"/>

<!-- This is the same page as "20160614_145014.jpg," but on a different picture file -->

<ab>
<table>
<row><cell></cell><cell>Droits.</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>d'Entrepot</cell><cell>de Consom.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Sucres et cafés</cell><cell>0. 70</cell><cell>1. 40.</cell><cell>les 100.K</cell></row>
<row><cell>Tabac et feuille</cell><cell>1. 30</cell><cell>2. 60.</cell><cell>_ig_</cell></row>
<row><cell>Rois</cell><cell>0. 30.</cell><cell>0. 60.</cell><cell>le Stere</cell></row>
<row><cell>Thé</cell><cell>0. 70.</cell><cell>1. 40.</cell><cell>les 100. K.</cell></row>
</table>
</ab>

<p>
à Gorée sur les produits de l'Union qui sont admis et
dont les droits se trouvent portés ci-contre.
</p>

<p>
Il est bien avéré que les droits perçus à Gorée sont
excessivement faibles, comparativement à ceux perçus
en France.
</p>

<p>
La Martinique et la Guadeloupe expédient
des navires aux Etats-Unis; ces navires lorsqu'ils sont sur
lest ne payent qu'un droit de 0.50, tandis que ceux
expédiés de St Louis vu de Gorée bien que n'étant égalemt.
qu'en lest, sont soumis à un droit de tonnage d'un
Dollar, et cependant lorsque les navires américains
sont admis à introduire aux colonies de l'Ouest des lois,
<unclear>Cabaes</unclear> et provisions ils payent sur ces produits 61%
ce qui est bien plus élevé que les droits perçus a Gorée
sur pareils articles, et sur les farines un droit qui est
de 20. f. au moins par baril.
</p>

<p>
Quant à ce qui est dit relativement à l'exclusion
des navires américains à St Louis, ce n'est pas pour
les <del>su</del> Pays <del>se</del> de L'Union seuls que cette non admission
à lieu, elle s'étend à tous les pavillons et cependant
les autres nations ne se prévalent pas de cela pour
nous faire payer à un taux plus élevé le droit de
tonnage des navires qui sont expédiés du Sénégal, nous
pouvons citer à l'appui de ce que nous avançons, que
les navires français expédiés du port de St Louis, Sénégal,
ne
</p>

<pb facs="20160614_145055.jpg"/>

<p>
ne payant en Angleterre que ce que payent les navires
français partant de tout autre <unclear/>; nous <unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> que les produits <unclear/> <unclear/> de la côte
d'Afrique ne payant en  Angleterre que le meme droit
auquel sont imposés le <unclear/>.
</p>

<p>
En Gambie, à <unclear>Rathard,</unclear> nous ne payons que le
même tonnage et ancrage que les <unclear>nationnaux, nous payons</unclear>
également le même droit que les anglais qui viennent
directement l'Angleterre, et cependant les Anglais ne
sont pas admis à St Louis.
</p>

<p>
La Commission décide à la majorité de quatre
voix sur ses:
</p>

<p>
Puisque les américains ne payent dans notre ile
que le faible droit de <unclear/> par tonneau, et encore sommes
nous dans l'obligation de prendre des <unclear/> en <unclear/>
pour les placer a bord de leurs bâtiments sans en retirer
aucune rétribution; que leur nation par réciprocité ne
perçoive pas d'avantage quand nos navires vont visiter
les ports d'Amérique.
</p>

<p>
Ou bien, que l'on fasse payer aux américains un
Dollar comme ils nous imposant, soit 5. 25; il en
résulterait un grand bien pour le commerce français
les Américains ne viendraient pas en aussi grand nombre
</p>

<!-- This page is continued on a different picture file, "20160614_145114.jpg" -->

<pb facs="20160614_145114.jpg"/>

<!-- This is the same page as "20160614_145055.jpg," but on a different picture file -->

<p>
les Américains ne viendraient pas en <supplied>aussi grand nombre</supplied>
et les proprietaires de navires français étant certaines de
n'avoir pas de concurence, ou d'en avoir une presque
nulle, expédieraient un très grand nombre de navires
ce qui serait avantageux pour notre commerce qui font
souvent ne trouvant pas de frêt au Sénégal pour France
ferait des opérations liées en portant des boeufs aux Antilles
et relevant ensuite pour un des ports de l'Union pour
revenir à Gorée vu à St Louis.
</p>

<p>
Dans l'un ou l'autre de ces deux cas, il en résulterait
un grand bénéfice pour le <unclear>fise</unclear> et dans le dernier un
plus grand bien encore pour la navigation et le commerce
français.
</p>

<p>
Il est une autre observation qui doit surtout être
prise en considération, c'est que les américains ne veulent
le plus souvent recevoir en paiement de leurs <unclear>marches</unclear>
que des espèces qui sortent de la Colonie pour ne plus
y rentrer.
</p>

<p>
Il est à remarquer en outre, que les américains
payent sur les peaux, gommes, <unclear>bois de cail-cedra</unclear> enfin
sur tous les produits qu'ils sont autorisés à exportes,
le même droit que celui auquel les français sont
assujetties
</p>

<pb facs="20160614_145140.jpg"/>

<p>
assujettis à la sortie, même lorsque ces produits sont
dirigés sur les ports français.
</p>

<p>
Le but de la réunion étant rempli, la séance
est levée et le présent Procés-verbal signé les <unclear>jous</unclear> mais
<unclear/> que <unclear>dessus</unclear>
</p>

<p>
<unclear/>
<unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> <!-- These appear to be a series of signatures -->

Le Chef du Serice administratif
Président de la Commission du Commerce.

M. <unclear/> <!-- Signature -->
</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="20160614_145014.jpg"/>

<ab>
Senegal and Dependents
</ab>

<ab>
Port of Gorée.
</ab>

<p>
Today March 11th 1840,
the commercial commission of Gorée, reunited itself, on
the convocation of its President, to listen to the
lecture of a ministerial dispatch from December 2nd 1839,
relative to the question of establishing the respective equality of the
taxes affecting the flag, in regard to the french and 
american vessels weighing the navigation between the United States
and Gorée and reciprocally.
</p>

<p>
were present.
</p>

<p>
Mr. M. Guibert, Chief of the <unclear>admif</unclear> service, President.
ferroliet, negociator
huchard} Merchant
f. Dupuy.} Merchant
Jh Ware} inhabitant
Jn Dupuy} inhabitant
</p>

<p>
The Commission ignores what are the rights that
one pays to the United States on the merchandise that is
admitted there, but it would be necessary that they are made
weak so that they make less than those perceived
in Gorée on the products of the Union that are admitted
in the rights and are found ported opposite
</p>

<!-- This page is continued on a different picture file, "20160614_145014.jpg" -->

<pb facs="20160614_145027.jpg"/>

<!-- This is the same page as "20160614_145014.jpg," but on a different picture file -->

<ab>
<table>
<row><cell></cell><cell>Rights.</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>of Entrepot</cell><cell>of Consom.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Sugars and Coffees</cell><cell>0. 70</cell><cell>1. 40.</cell><cell>the 100.K</cell></row>
<row><cell>Tabacco and veneer</cell><cell>1. 30</cell><cell>2. 60.</cell><cell>_ig_</cell></row>
<row><cell>Kings</cell><cell>0. 30.</cell><cell>0. 60.</cell><cell>the Stere</cell></row>
<row><cell>Tea</cell><cell>0. 70.</cell><cell>1. 40.</cell><cell>the 100. K.</cell></row>
</table>
</ab>

<p>
in Gorée on the products of the Union that are submitted and
of which the rights are found ported opposite.
</p>

<p>
It is well recognized that the rights perceived in Gorée are
excessively weak, comparatively to those perceived
in France.
</p>

<p>
Martinique and Guadeloupe are expediting
vessels to the United States; these vessels when they are on 
ballast only pay a right of 0.50, whereas those
expedited from St Louis seen from Gorée even though not being equal.
that in ballast, are submitted to a right of tonnage of one
Dollar, and yet when the american vessels
are admitted to introduce laws to the colonies of the West,
<unclear>Cabaes</unclear> and provisions they pay on the products 61%
which is much more risen than the rights perceived in Gorée
on identical articles, and on the meal a right that is
20. f. at least per barrel.
</p>

<p>
As for that which is said relatively on the exclusion
of american vessels in St Louis, it is not for
the <del>su</del> Country <del>se</del> of the Union only that this non admission
has place, it extends to all of the flags and yet
the other nations do not claim this in order to
make us pay a higher rate for the right of
tonnage of the vessels that are expedited from Senegal, we
can cite the support of that which we advance, that
french vessels expedited form the port of St Louis, Senegal,

</p>

<pb facs="20160614_145055.jpg"/>

<p>
only paying in England that which the french vessels
pay leaving from completely different <unclear/>; we <unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> that the products <unclear/> <unclear/> from the coast
of Africa only paying in England the same right
to which are imposed the <unclear/>.
</p>

<p>
In Gambia, to <unclear>Rathard,</unclear> we only pay the
same tonnage and anchorage as the <unclear>nationnaux, we pay</unclear>
equally the same right as the english who come
directely from England, and yet the English are
not admitted in St Louis.
</p>

<p>
The Commission decides in the majority of four
voices on its:
</p>

<p>
Then the americans only pay on our island
the weak right of <unclear/> per barrel, and still are
we in the obligation of taking the <unclear/> in <unclear/>
to place them aboard their boats without taking
any retribution; that their nation by reciprocity does
perceive more when our vessels are going to visit
the ports of America.
</p>

<p>
Or, that one makes it paid to the americans one
Dollar like they impose on us, or 5. 25; it would
result in a large good for french commerce
The Americans would not come in as big of a number
</p>

<!-- This page is continued on a different picture file, "20160614_145114.jpg" -->

<pb facs="20160614_145114.jpg"/>

<!-- This is the same page as "20160614_145055.jpg," but on a different picture file -->

<p>
the Americans would not come in <supplied>as big of a number</supplied>
and the proprietors of french vessels being certain not
to have concurrence, or to have one nearly
as bad, would expedite a big number of vessels
which would be advantageous for our commerce that do
not often find freight in Senegal for France
would do operations linked in porting oxen to the Antilles
and raising again for one of the ports of the Union to
return to Gorée or to St Louis.
</p>

<p>
In either of these two cases, it would result in
a large benefit for the <unclear>fise</unclear> and in the last a
an even bigger good for french navigation and 
commerce.
</p>

<p>
There is another observation that must especially be
taken into consideration, which is that the americans only want
the most recent receipt in payment of their <unclear>marches</unclear>
that the individuals that are leaving the Colony to never
return.
</p>

<p>
It should be remarked in addition, that the americans
pay on the skins, rubbers, <unclear>bois de cail-cedra</unclear> at least
on all of the products that they are authorized to export,
the same right that that to which the french are
subjugated
</p>

<pb facs="20160614_145140.jpg"/>

<p>
subjugated at the exit, even when these products are
directed to the french ports.
</p>

<p>
The goal of the reunion being filled, the session
is finished and the present official report signed the <unclear>jous</unclear> but
<unclear/> that <unclear>dessus</unclear>
</p>

<p>
<unclear/>
<unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> <!-- These appear to be a series of signatures -->

The Chief of administrative Service
President of the Committee of Commerce.

M. <unclear/> <!-- Signature -->
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
