<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0058.xml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Henry M. Stanley, "Stanley's Congo and the Founding of Its Free State" (1885)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0058</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Stanley's Congo and the Founding of Its Free State</title>
<author n="Stanley, Henry M.">Henry M. Stanley</author>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1885-10">October 1885</date>
<biblScope unit="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bula Matari</term>
<term>Chief Ngalyema</term>
<term>Stanley, Henry M.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Central Africa</term>
<term>Europe</term>
<term>Isangila</term>
<term>Lower and Upper Congo</term>
<term>Manyanga</term>
<term>Stanley Falls</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
<term>Vivi</term>
</keywords>

    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-04-23" who="pr">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="PAGENUMBER" facs="PDFNAME"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>Stanley's Congo and the Founding of Its
Free State.*

*The Congo and the Founding of its Free State. A story of Work and Exploration.
By Henry M. Stanley. With over one hundred full-page and smaller illustrations, two
large maps, and several smaller ones. In two volumes. Pp. 528 and 483. New York:
Harper and Brothers.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>No one can well fail to acknowledge the invaluable service Hen-
ry M. Stanley has rendered, first, in his exploration of the Congo
region: next, in negotiating with native chiefs and others so as to
make a Congo Free State possible: thirdly, in promoting the Congo
treaty, and getting some of its most important provisions put right
and lastly, in recording all in the two handsome volumes now given
to the public.</p>
<p>We gladly transfer the following review from the September
Missionary Herald to our pages:-</p>
<p>"It was but eight years on the twelfth of August last since the in-
trepid African explorer, Henry M. Stanley, emerged from his perilous
journey through the unknown regions of the Dark Continent, and,
almost dead from fatigue and starvation, reached with his straggling
company the mouth of the Congo. Two years later he appeared at
the mouth of the same river, down which he had sailed with hostile
arrows flying after him from either bank, with the purpose of con-
quering the region, not by force of arms, but by words and acts of
peace. The attempt was bold and praiseworthy, though it impressed
most observers as bordering on the quixotic. Yet only six years from 
the date of his return to Africa he puts forth these two superb vol-
umes, describing the founding of a Free State on the Congo, and no
one can dispute his right to affix to his account the motto: "The
end crowns the work." It is certainly one of the marvels of modern
times that one who but eight years ago revealed to the world the sources
of this mighty river of Central Africa is now able to report that, in
the interests of the International Association, of which he has been
the prinicpal agent, over four hundred treaties have been made,
signed by some two thousand chieftains, great and small, living along
the banks of the Congo, and that at a great European conference, at
which were present distinguished representattives of the principal na-
tions of the civilized world, the Congo Free State was recognized and
its national rights guaranteed. Surely a nation has been born in a
day! If any one suggests that the Congo Free State is in a very infantile
condition, it may be answered that this is no reason why it should
not live and grow. Hercules at his birth might have been stronger
than other babes but his capacities were not to be estimated as if he
were then in the prime of his manhood.</p>
<p>The story told in these volumes of Mr. Stanley is intensely inter-
esting as well as instructive. It is difficult to conceive of a work
requiring more patience and courage than the building of a road by
which steamers and goods can be taken on wagons along the rough
canons which separate the smooth waters of the Lower and the Upper
Congo. For twenty-eight months, Stanley was engaged in this gi-
gantic work without competent European assistants and with a force
of laborers far below his requirements. It is not surprising that the
man who could level a road from Vivi to Isangila, and from Manyan-
ga to Stanley Pool, was called by the natives, Bula Matari, "breaker
of rocks," and that under this name his fame should spread far into
the interior whither he was going. But engineering was only one of
the many talents required for this undertaking. Sometimes rocks
are more easily managed than men. To conciliate chiefs, to make
treaties of peace, including the right to build stations and to trade,
to keep open a long line of communication while still advancing tow-
ard the interior, required skill and persistence such as few possess.
It is not surprising to find Stanley complaining of his European lieu-
tenants as weak and incompetent. A man of his energy would find
few like himself, search where he might.</p>
<p>From a missionary point of view, also, there is much of interest
in these volumes. It is specially pleasant to find that the very tribes
which fought so fiercely when Stanley came down the river in 1877
were with no great difficulty won to friendliness on his return. The
African isnot such a savage as some of us suppose. Some lessons of
value may be learned by missionaries as to methods of negotiating
with chiefs and people. Doubtless the missionaries would reject
some of the methods employed by Mr. Stanley. They would not un-
der any circumstances make presents of ardent spirits, nor would they
continue such a noise as that which frightened chief Ngalyema out of
his wits. But the mingled firmness and suavity which seem general-
ly to have characterized his intercourse with the people are worthy
of much commendation.</p>
<p>While our author certainly believes that there are all the ele-
ments of a great State in this Congo region, he cannot be accused of
concealing the difficulties in the way of developing the territory, of
subduing nature, and of civilizing and Christianizing the people. He
sees in the great basin of the upper river, stretching over one thou-
sand miles from Stanley Pool on the west to Stanley Falls on the
east, many sections that remind him of Eden's loveliness, rich in all
products which give prosperity to a nation; but he clearly shows that
the natives are not hastening to the coast and beckoning to the mer-
chants of Europe and America to send their ships and carry away
this wealth. On the other hand, he tells us that the African is not
easily tamed; that he will have to be taught to work; that it will take
time and much patient labor to develop the resources of the country.
From a report recently made to a department of our Government
a summary of which has been given in the public press, it would al-
most seems that the officer in charge expected on arriving at the
mouth of the Congo to find cargoes of goods waiting for shipment to
America and that it was only necessary to open a trading post to se-
cure a profitable traffic. For any extravagant notions of immediate
returns, Mr. Stanley's book gives no warrant. But we believe that
he has clearly shown that there are in this Congo region all the ele-
ments of a great State, and that whatever power shall wisely and pa-
tiently undertake to develop the region will reap a rich reward."

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

