<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="DAWSON, KENDALL C." xml:id="KCD"><!-- KENDALL C. DAWSON --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KCD"><!-- Corrections, marked up. --></change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<pb facs="10016_001.jpg"/>

<p> Daily Consular and Trade Reports.</p>
<p> Kongo Commerical Opportunities.</p>
    
<p> Future of the Heart of Africa-how Americans may participate. </p>
 
<p>In view of the fact that the status of the Kongo Free State is now
more definitely arranged and that its development is commencing,
Consul-General James A. Smith, of Boma, has preared the following
review of the commercial aspects, and how Americans may best
secure business in that vast region of mid-Africa with 900,000 square
miles of undeveloped territory:</p>
    
<p>The Kongo may soon offer an opportunity for every independent
trader to traffic freely with the natives in the rich commerical products 
of the country, consisting mainly at present of rubber, ivory,
gum copal, palm kernels, and palm oil, the two latter being principally
products of the lower Kongo. Under such circumstances it 
appears important that the American manufacturer should be informed,
so far as is possible at present, of the opportunities which
will be found here to dispose of his goods and the best manner in 
which he can obtain a foothold, and to have clearly pointed out some 
of the difficulties he must encounter and overcome if American trade
in the Kongo is to increase.</p>

<p>Classs of Goods At Present Imported.</p>
    
<p> Importations into the Kongo average at present, in round numbers,
$4,000,000 annually. Of these principal items, comprising, as
will be noted, about 88 per cent of the total, are as follows:</p>
    
<p> Arms and ammunition _____________ $178,000
Clothing______________________________251,000
Food products, mostly canned
meats, vegetables, etc________________ 782,000
Hardware, enameled iron ware,
etc.___________________________________ 156,000
Liquors, including beer ________________ 336,000
Machinery________________________________208,000</p>
    
<p>Metals_________________________________ $212,000
Steamers, boats, and material
for ________________________________________278,000
Tissues, mostly cotton piece
goods________________________________________1,146,000

Total__________________________________________3,547,000</p>
    
<p>So far as the natives are concerned, who are the most important
to consider beacuse the bulk of the furniture trade will be carried on
with them, the items of the greatest interest to the American manufacturer
in the foregoing list are, in the order of their value, cotton
piece goods, bleached and unbleached, prints and dyes; food products,
consisting for the greater part of canned meats and vegetables,
largely consumed, it is true, by the white population at present, but
for which a demand can be created among the natives; clothing; the
bulk of which is cheap underclothing, shirts, shoes, hats, and caps;
hardware, of which an important part is enameled iron ware, plates,
basins, various kitchen utensils, etc.</p>
    
<p> The remainder of the articles are for the larger part imported for
use in building and opening up the country for the whites, construction 
and maintenance of railways, steamer lines, etc. The sale of alcoholic
liquors to natives in the upper Kongo is forbidden by law.</p>
    
<p> Practical Method to Secure Trade.</p>
    
<p>The question of methods to secure trade must be regarded from the
standpoint of the interest of the American manufacturer and not of
the individual small trader. There is but one practical way for the 
American manufacturer to secure and retain a foothold in this market,</p>
    
<pb></pb>
    
<p> Daily Consular And Trade Reports</p>

<p> On the other hand, the right is not extended to the United States,
which is allowed to certain other countries on the basis of reciprocity,
by which dutiable articles serving as samples of specimens are
allowed free entry on the understanding that their identity is preserved
and their reexport accomplished within a stipulated period of
time. This disadvantage is due to the fact that no corresponding
privilege is allolwed to Germany by the United States.</p>
    
<p>American commercial travelers do not enjoy advantages arising
form those agreements with several other countries (France, Great
Britain, Belgium, Switzerland, Sweden, and Austria-Hungary) by
which offical marks for the preservation of the identity of samples or
specimens brought in from and reexported to one of these countries
are recognized.</p>
    
<p>Walnut Crop In France.</p>
    
<p>Good Growing Season-- Probable Yield of Different Qualities.</p>
    
<p>Vice-Consul T.W. Murton, of Grenoble, submits the following
report, dated July 25, on the growing crop of walnuts in that
consular district in the French valley of the Isére:</p>

<p>The weather thus far having been variable and temperate, with
frequent copious rainfalls and comparative freedom from excessive
heat and the damaging hail and thunderstorms that usually follow,
vegetation has prospered, and all standind fruit crops, grapes more
especially, give promise of excellent yields. As to walnuts, while
the fruit-bearing trees of the finer qualities, commercially known
as Mayettes, Franquettes, and Parisiens, are luxuriantly foliaged and
healthy in appearance, it is not expected that the production in nuts
will much exceed half and average crop, or, say, from 15,000 to 20,000
bales of 100 kilos each (1 kilo = 2.2 pounds). The fruit is well developed,
being unusually large for the season, and promises to be of 
excellent quality. The reason assigned for so small a crop is the prolonged
drought of 1906, from the effecrs of which the trees have not
yet entirely recovered.</p>

<p>Of the smaller varieties, known as Chabertes and employed
exclusively for confectionary purposes, a plentiful crop is expected-
estimated at 45,000 to 50,000 cases of 25 kilos each. The quality also
should be good, always provided weather conditions continue favorable
for the growing crops until maturity. In such case harvesting
time will be in advance of last year by about fifteen days.</p>

<p>German Canal Liability Decision.</p>

<p>A report from Consul-General Richard Guenther states that the
Supreme Court of the Empire, the highest judicial body in Germany,
has jut rendered an important decision. The lighter of a private
shipping firm was injured in the Kaiser Wilhelm Canal by a steamer
which got loose from its moorings. The Government declined paying
damages and disclaimed liability as the regulations for the traffic
through the canal contain the stipulation: "The German Empire
assumes no responsibility whatsoever to recompense for any damages
which vessels passing through the canal or lying on the roadsteads at
either end may suffer, etc." The lower courts before which this case
had been tried decided against the Government and, on appeal by
the latter, the Supreme Court has now affirmed that decision.</p>

<pb></pb>

<p>Daily Consular And Trade Reports</p>

<p>which promises results materially inccreasing American foreign trade
here and which will eventually make the venture worth while. It is
not likely that American goods will ever reach this market to any
large extent except directly through an American company located
here. Every trading house already established in the lower Kongo-
English, French, German, Dutch, Portugese, or Belgian- is interested,
primarily, in pushing the sale of the goods of its own nation.
The large concessionary companies are all Belgian, they purchase the
greater part of their supplies in Belgium, and their barter goods are
mostly Belgian. As a Belgian colony, the future administration will
be interested first of all in encouraging and broadening the market
for Belgian manufactures.</p>

<p>Geographical position and direct lines of steamers from almost all
the countries named are other important factors favorable to their
trade development here. For these reasons, I believe, there is but one
practical and efficient way by which we can succeed in gaining a firm 
foothold here-namely, through the organization of an American
tradiing house composed prefereably of a combination of various 
American manufacturers of or dealers in the different lines of merchandise
it is found profitable to handle, and interested therefore
before all in introducing and pushing exclusively American goods.
A number of general stores should be established in favorable localities,
with a central distributing warehouse and store at Leopoldville.</p>

<p>Distribution of Supplies-Competent Salesmen</p>

<p>The company should own and operate its own steamer of steamers
on the upper river for the transport of its goods and distribution to
the various stores established, as well as the carrying to Leopoldville
of the merchandise received in exchange-rubber, ivory, etc. The
network of navigable waterways furnishes the most convenient
means of communication at present, but freight rates on the steamers
belonging to the State are high and porterage "a dos d'homme" is
slow and uncertain and must eventually be done away with entirely.</p>

<p>A thoroughly efficient and practival business man should be sent
out to study the general situation, the wants of the natives, manner 
of packing goods for tropical countries, etc., and decide as to the 
most favorable localities for the establishment of the stores. The
preliminary work would doubtless require fully a year's time. Cotton 
piece goods will form the principal article of commmerce at first, but
it would be unwise for the company to confine itself to any one line.
Through contact with the whites the material wants of the natives 
will gradually increase, and the company must be prepared to supply
these wants in every direction.</p>

<p>Difficulties To Overcome</p>

<p>In the absence of money as a circulation medium of trade, and the
entire ignorance of the greater part of the natives in the upper
Kongo as to its value of use, the trade in the beginning will be simply
a question of barter. For this reason, perhaps, the greatest difficulty 
which a trading house will meet with at first will be to persuade the
native to bring in his produce in exchange for goods offered. Some
time must necessarily elapse and a constantly humane, just, and gen-</p>

<pb></pb>

<p>Daily Consular And Trade Reports.</p>

<p>erous treatment invariably accorded to the native before he will begin
to realize the material advantages to be gained by himself in trading
with the white man. Once he is certain of this the most difficult
obstacle to trade will have been overcome.</p>

<p>An American house without experience in Africa will have to compete
with English, French, German, Dutch, Portugese, and Belgian
companies and in the eastern districts with Indian and Arab traders,
many of them long standing in the lower Kongo, familiar with 
the country and the ways of the natices, speaking og the commercial
language, etc. Many of these traders will doubtless enlarge the field
of their operations in the upper Kongo. The Germans are already
preparing for the opening up on the country to trade, as I learn that
a German house at Matadi, backed by official encouragement, is to
place a steamer at once on the upper river and commence operations
by selling goods along the river direct fromj the steamer in exchange
for ivory.</p>

<p>Another difficulty is the absence of direct lines of transportation.
American sailing ships already, I beleive, come to the Sierra Leone and 
the West Coast with cotton good and petroleum, and their itinerary
might, it would seem, be extended to the lower Kongo. </p>

<p>General Observation.</p>

<p>In the development of the country the native must necessarily play
an important part. His labor is absolutely essential to the future
welfare of the colony, and he will be the principal purchaser of 
foreign goods. In a colony of at least 20,000,000 blacks, who will be
brought, as the country is opened up, more and more into constant
contact with white civilization, and whose material wants will in
consequence continually increase, the future market will be one of 
constant growth and practically unlimited extent. If the United
States is to share in this market in any appreciable measure the
present is the time to make a beginning. It is the man who is the 
first on the ground who will have the advantage in an experience
gained in dealing with the native, and who will consequently secure
the larger and more profitable share in the trade. The difficulties
do not appear by any means insurmountable. Enterprise directed
intelligently, patience, and tenacity are required here as everywhere
else to secure and hold a market against active competition.</p>

<p> The opportunityis a grand one and should not be neglected. A
consular officer can do no more than point this out. It remains for
American manufacturers to take advantage of the situation and
make a beginning here at the earliest possible moment. Details as
to prices of cotton piece goods, etc., can not be given because, 
dependent as they are upon the cost of transport, they vary widely in 
different sections and have been, up to the present time,  more of less
arbitrary.</p>

<p>Mails for Tahiti.</p>

<p> In relation to a report that corresponence destined for Tahiti is 
frequently missent to Seattle, Wash., for dispatch, the Post-Office
Department announces that mails for Tahiti are dispatched only by 
steamers sailing fromo San Francisco, and that the mails referred
to must therefore be forwarded to San Francisco.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
