<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1128">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Ezekiel E. Smith to Alvey A. Adee, January 3, 1890</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1128</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Ezekiel E. Smith to Alvey A. Adee, January 3, 1890</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 5</biblScope>
<date when="1890-01-03">January 3, 1890</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Braxton</term><!-- Mrs. -->
<term>Cand, Robert</term>
<term>Cooper, Emma A.</term>
<term>Davis, E. S.</term>
<term>Davis, William M.</term>
<term>Dickens, Y. C.</term>
<term>Douglas, John B.</term>
<term>Douglas, Mary</term>
<term>Douglas, Mary M.</term>
<term>Douglas, Robert I.</term>
<term>Euphemia, Mary</term>
<term>Fuller, Alice</term>
<term>Fuller, Anna W.</term>
<term>Gibson, Joseph M.</term>
<term>Houston, Anna V.</term>
<term>Howard, Thomas W.</term>
<term>Leone, Lewis R.</term>
<term>Leone, Louisa</term>
<term>McIntosh, Mary</term>
<term>Melville, Benjamin V. R.</term>
<term>Nimms</term><!-- Mrs. -->
<term>Perkins, N. L.</term>
<term>Powell, Maria Q.</term>
<term>Weaver, Clara Fuller</term>
<term>Weaver, Lincoln Napoleon</term>
<term>Woods, Sarah J.</term>
<term>Woods, Tyson</term>
<term>Yates, Sarah C.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Greenville (Liberia)</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Montserrado County (Liberia)</term>
<term>Sinoe County (Liberia)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Ezekiel E.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1890-01-03"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77728466">Adee, Alvey A. (Alvey Augustus), 1842-1924</persName>
<roleName>Second Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1890-02-08"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-04" who="#kln">Review and edits.</change>
<change when="2022-09-21" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll5-2109.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Feb 8 1890</note>

<p>No. 49</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, January 3rd, 1890.</p>

<p>Mr. Ezekiel E. Smith,<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Last Will and Testament of Mrs.
Alice Fuller</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2108.jpg"/>

<p>No. 49.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the  United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, January 3rd, 1890.</p>

<p>Honorable Alvey A. Adee,<lb/>
Second Assistant Secretary,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor respectfully to
acknowledge the receipt of your No. 9.
Despatch of November 16th 1889, instructing
me to procure a copy of the "Last
Will and Testament" of Mrs. Alice Fuller,
who died in this city in the month
of June 1888.</p>

<p>In compliance with said instruction 
I have procured and inclose 
herein a copy, or said "Will."</p>

<p>I am,<lb/>
sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Ezekiel E. Smith,<lb/>
U.S. Consul General.</p>

<p>Enclosures one.</p>

<p>Copy of the Last Will
and Testament of Mrs. Fuller.</p>

</div1>

<pb n="Roll5-2111.jpg"/>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<p>In the name of God Amen I Alice Fuller of the City
of Monrovia County of Montserrado and the Republic
of Liberia being of Sound disposing mind but
feeble in body do make public and declare
this to be my Last Will and Testament in Manner
following</p>

<p>1st After all my just debts and funeral expenses are
paid, I give and devise my half Lot on Broad
Street in the City of Monrovia to Clara Fuller
Weaver wife of Lincoln Napoleon Weaver to her and
her heirs forever, free from all control or disposal
of her husband to have and to hold the same to
her and her heirs forever.</p>

<p>2nd I give and devise to Mrs Sarah J. Woods wife
of Tyson Woods of Cape Palmas, one of my Town
Lots located if I recollect rightly in the Town
of Greenville Sinoe County to have and to hold
to her and her heirs forever and
I give and devise the other two Lots located
in said Greenville, one to my dear friend Emma
A. Cooper and the other to my dear friend
Sarah C. Yates to have and to hold the said
property to each in severalty to them and their heirs</p>

<p>3rd I give and bequeath to Benjamin V. R. Melville, all
my right and Title to the house in Front Street in
Monrovia that I am now having built and I also
give and bequeath to him Two Hundred dollars
in order to help him to finish said House</p>

<pb n="Roll5-2112.jpg"/>

<p>4th I have several orders coming out from America
and England and when they come and are
disposed of I give and bequeath an equal 
share of the proceeds to the said B. V. R. Melville
Anna W. Fuller his mother, my friend Sarah C.
Yates, and my friend Maria Q. Powell and
a <sic>Potion</sic> of said proceeds I wish to go to my
friend Mrs Braxton But fifty six dollars
of the money in these orders belong to Anna
W. Fuller and the above division of proceeds
cannot be made until after her said money
are deducted out of the proceeds.</p>

<p>5th I give and bequeath all my new goods now
in the house where I am living to my friends
Anna W. Fuller B. R. Melville Maria Q. Powell
Sarah C. Yates and Mrs Braxton to be divided
in equal shares to all except Mrs Braxton
who is to have a lesser share than the others</p>

<p>6th I give and bequeath to my dear friend Emma
A. Cooper my large show case now in her
possession, and anything else of mine that
she may want; and also my Scales.</p>

<p>7th I give and bequeath to my friend Y. C. Dickens
my small scales now in his possession</p>

<p>8th I have (Eighteen hundred dollars) $1800
now in the East Brooklyn Saving Bank
which I wish to remain there on interest
for two years after my death, at which time
I want it divided. and I give and bequeath

<pb n="Roll5-2113.jpg"/>

out of said money (Five hundred dollars) to my
afflicted Sister Mary Douglas residing in
<sic>Charlstone</sic> South Carolina, and I request
Messrs Yates &amp; Porterfield of 59 South St New York
who now have my Deposit Book in their
possession to find out my said sister and pay
over said money to her in person or to her
legal representative, and to my nephews
Robert Cand John B. Douglas of the City of Washington
D.C. U.S.A. I give and bequeath Two
hundred dollars each out of said money
to be paid to them by Messrs Yates &amp; Porterfield,
and I give and bequeath to Mary M. Douglass
wife of Robert I. Douglass my brother one hundred
dollars $100 out of said money, and out of the
remainder of said money I give and bequeath
to my friend Maria Q. Powell one hundred dollars
and to my friend Sarah C. Yates one hundred dollars
and to my friend Emma A. Cooper one hundred dollars
and to my friend Anna W. Fuller one hundred dollars
and also one hundred dollars to my friend B. V. R. Melville
also Fifty dollars to my dear friend Mrs Nimms
also I give to Joseph M. Gibson Fifty dollars
also to Mary Euphemia daughter of W. M. &amp; E. S. Davis
Fifty dollars to Mary McIntosh daughter of
Anna V. Houston I give Fifty dollars and to
Louisa Leone daughter of the late Lewis R. Leone
I give Fifty dollars also I give Fifty dollars
to my friend Thomas W. Howard

<pb n="Roll5-2114.jpg"/>

I give and bequeath the above several sums
of money to the several persons above named
in the order named The above erasure and
alteration were made before this was signed
Ye name Wm M. Davis and Benj. V. R. Melville
to be Executors of this my last will and Testament</p>

<p>Monrovia June 14th 1888 (Signed) Alice Fuller</p>

<p>Signed Sealed and delivered in presence of us
and declared by the said Alice Fuller to be
her last will and testament in presence of us
who at our names as witnesses</p>

<p>Emma A. Cooper<lb/>
Sarah C. Yates</p>

<p>A true copy from the original the
2nd day of Jany 1890</p>

<p>N L Perkins<lb/>
Clk Mo. &amp; Pro. Ct Mo. Co.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>