<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0931">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader, June 30, 1876</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0931</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1876-06-30">June 30, 1876</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Campbell, Frank</term>
<term>Cuff, W. E.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>New York</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1876-06-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66848474">Cadwalader, John L. (John Lambert), 1836-1914</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1876-08-16"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-08" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1079.jpg"/>

<p>No. 18.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the<lb/>
United States Republic of Liberia</p>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
to the<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington U.S.A.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Transmitting Report for the Quarter ended June 30th 1876.</p>

<p>Inclosures:</p>

<p>No. 1. Letters received.<lb/>
 " 2. " sent.<lb/>
 " 3. Statement of Salary Account<lb/>
 " 4. Arrival and Departure of American vessels.<lb/>
 " 5. Voucher No. 1.<lb/>
 " 6 " " 2. &amp; 3.<lb/>
 " 7 " " 3.<lb/>
 " 8 Sheriff's certificate<lb/>
 " 9 Copy of Account Current as reported to the Fifth Auditor<lb/>
 " 10 Copy of Invoice Book</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1080.jpg"/>

<p>No. 18.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United<lb/>
States Monrovia, Liberia 30th June 1876</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to transmit herewith my report for the quarter ended this day. It is desired to respectfully invite attention to the enclosed copy of my "Account Current" as transmitted to the Fifth Auditor of the Treasury; see inclosure No. 9. for the purpose of explaining that $20.25, with I therein credit Government is balance of one month's extra wages collected by me during December 1875 at the discharge from the barque Jasper of W.E. Cuff an american seaman; which extra wages was accounted for in my report of the 31st December 1875; but has remained in my possession until the present time. In the month January 1876,

<fw type="address">Honorable, John L. Cadwalader<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington U.S.A.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1081.jpg"/>

1876, Frank Campbell, a seaman belonging to the same vessel was on shore drunk and riotous at Monrovia, at a late hour of the night of the day on which his vessel had taken out her clearance from the authorities here, and the ship's papers had been delivered to the Captain from this Consulate. After repeated complaints to me of the disturbance to the quiet of the place by Campbell's noisy drunkenness. I attempted to persuade him to board his vessel. But failing in the attempt thus to persuade the drunken man, I requested the <sic>Sherriff</sic> to arrest Campbell to and deliver him to the Captain on board the "Jasper" then under sail and endeavoring to depart for New York. The baneful nature of climatic influences here, and the long intervals between the visits of American vessels to this quarter, decided me that it was economic and humane to force Campbell to depart in his ship for New York, than to allow him to remain and risk his life in this climate; please see inclosures Nos 7. and 8. (The account, shown by the same copy of Account Current, for Desk book case, and office chair; was made by me under the following <catchwords>circumstances</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1082.jpg"/>

circumstances. Upon my return to my post of duty now more than one year since, I found my books and Archives, especially the calf bound statutes of the United States, attacked and to some extent being destroyed by a white ant which abounds in this country, and is very destructive to books, papers, and wood of almost every kind. After an unavailing effort to rid the Consular Archives of this vermin; I determined that as my office was greatly in need of a bookcase in which to preserve the Archives, being furnished only with a table, an old chair, and a worm and ant eaten boxlike bookcase; that I might be justified in procuring the means made of foreign wood, and therefore distasteful to their vermin, to preserve my Archives from destruction. Hence, I purchased the articles of office furniture enumerated in Inclosure No. 6. And have drawn against my allowance for contingent expense for $93.50, draft dated April 2ond 1876: in part payment of the cost thereof; and have now most respectfully to request <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1083.jpg"/>

the Department to allow the whole amount as already paid by me.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir:<lb/>
With considerations of esteem<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>