<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Consolar Bureau
February 11th 1874

Subject: the office of Vice Commercial agent at Sierra Leone

Upon the <unclear/> of H. Rider, <unclear/> Commercial agent at Sierra Leone J.B. Upton was appointed Vice Commercial agent on February 20, 1871 and the usual certificat was issued <unclear/> Upton unites from Sierra Leone March 30, 1871 ack. the receipt of notice of appt and says that the condition of his health compels him to have for America when he will see his bond. He <unclear/> his arrival at New York on August 29,1871, and that he fed opt othr. Am. Hogan in charge of the office. He has not informed Department of his return to his fast nor of his intention to return.

Upon W.Hogan appointment his comission was made out as Consul; he made no nomination for Voce Consul; but on having his past he states (August 7 1873) state W.Nathanial Lyons will be opt in change. Then dispatch was ordered "fired" and no action was taken    where U.Hogan was appointed Consul, the name of W.Upton C.A. <unclear extent=two words/> think have out of the Register <unclear/>
A.B. Wood

to MsHard agent for Hogan Ms. of Ms.Hard reply endeavors are it. and copy of the <unclear/> new <unclear/> for this first time endorse 14.5.

I have reasons to believe thata private afreement existed bywhich most harris he was to take the <unclear/> expenses but I have not seen my document being on this print

I <unclear/> your instructions in this matter, and have th honor to p<unclear/>

Sir,
Your most obedient servant
<unclear/>
Acting U.S. Consul

No.1 Copy <unclear/> Acting U.S. Consul to Gov't in Chief
2 Reply to above
3 <unclear/> his Esq
4 <unclear/> his reply
5 amount of expenses for which esqre in mase
6 officials recognition of <unclear/> by authorization

tht he will give me such advice and assistance in the rather, as him high official position will unable him to do.

I have the honor to be 
Sit
Your obdt Servt
Hath Lyon
Acting U.S. Consul
Vice Consul for Spain plus Potugal
and for Italy and the Netherland