<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0004">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John H. Smyth to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen, October 2, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0004</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">John H. Smyth to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen, October 2, 1882</title>
<title level="m">Apropos of Africa: Sentiments of Negro American Leaders on Africa from the 1800s to the 1950s</title>
<author n="Smyth, John H., 1830-1888">John H. Smyth</author>
<editor n="Kilson, Martin">Martin Kilson</editor>
<editor n="Cromwell, Adeleide">Adeleide Cromwell</editor>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Frank Cass &amp; Co. LTD.</publisher>
<date when="1969">1969</date>
<biblScope unit="page">94-97</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Frelinghuysen, Frederick T. (Frederick Theodore), 1817-1885</term>
<term>Gardiner, Anthony W.</term>
<term>Havelock, Arthur Elibank, Sir, 1844-1908</term>
<term>Macaulay, G. M.</term>
<term>Sandoh, Morannah</term>
<term>Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895</term>
<term>Smyth, John H., 1830-1888</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>Europe</term>
<term>Freetown (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>United States</term>
<term>West Africa</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-14" who="#kln">edited encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">scanned, OCRed, and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p94" facs="teaa.en.book.0004.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Dispatches from United States Ministers to Liberia,
1863-1906.</p>

<p>Roll 7-9, Vol. 9, May 9, 1882-October 7, 1884.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="text">

<p>No. 12. Jno. H. Smyth* to Frelinghuysen,<lb/>
October 2, 1882.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Very recently I had an interview with His Excellency the President
of the Republic of Liberia, at which meeting that gentleman took
occasion to express serious apprehensions with respect to his government 
being able to retain possession of the north western territory
of Liberia, on account of the threatening demonstration made in the
naval armament attendant upon the visit of Her Britanic Majesty's
Consul for Liberia, the Governor of the West African Settlements,
Hon. Arthur E. Havelock, C.M.G., but these apprehensions were
augmented by the conference held here in Monrovia March 1st, when
it was developed that the purpose of England was to take from the
Liberian nation their purchased territory unjustly, wrongfully, upon
the pretext that the native races were dissatisfied with Liberia's
control, and that by his instructions, Her Majesty's Government had
long desired that Sierra Leone and Liberia should be conterminous,
that the colony of Sierra Leone needed elbow room on the coast, and
being able to satisfy the need, England was determined to make the
territories conterminous, by fixing the boundary and that in him
(the Governor) had been vested the authority of the "solution of the
long pending North Western Boundary of the Republic."</p>

<p>The papers with reference to the conference and subsequent correspondence, 
copies of the originals in the archives of Sierra Leone
and the Liberian Foreign Office being enclosed herewith obviate
the necessity of anything more than a passing allusion, since you Sir,
will be competent to make comment and approach a proper decision
as to the matter; and if not incompatible with the relation of a foreign
mutual friend of England and Liberia, you will make such suggestions
favorable to the Negro nation's rights as may tend to a final and
speedy settlement of the matter in justice and equity to both nations,
should you feel called upon to interpose, and your suggested views
should be heeded.</p>

<p>This, I am advised, is the desire of the President.</p>

<fw type="footnote"><note>* See p. 48 for biographical sketch of John H. Smyth.</note></fw>

<pb xml:id="p95" facs="teaa.en.book.0004.002.jpg"/>

<p>Since you have ample knowledge of this boundary matter, and I
am in possession of facts which may not have before been known to
the Department, I improve this occasion to very briefly call attention
to such as have become known to me.</p>

<p>England has never had nor does she now pretend to have any right
or color of claim to the territory in dispute. Being the self constituted
censor in matters of title as to weak and heathen peoples, she feels it
to be her high mission to go beyond the limitations of other nations
by interference with the concerns of weak and heathen peoples,
where such interference is most likely to be followed by material
benefits to England. In this particular instance, it is indubitable
that if Liberia be ousted of her possession and right, the aboriginal
races, with the territory will become vassals and the land, the property 
of Her Majesty's colonial government of Sierra Leone, and the
rich oil and forest possessions will be guarded and protected for
the enrichment of England with little reference to whether the Negro
is <sic>benefitted</sic> or not. While there can be no doubt from West African
precedent but that England will, should she take this territory (in
this instance) afford more immediate and ample facilities for cultivation 
among the native races of Western civilization than Liberia
can now afford, yet she is likely to make the Negroes here subservient 
to her too frequently incompetent and unsympathetic British
representatives and traders, and thereby destroy that self dependence
that heathen and barbarous races must in a measure retain in taking
upon themselves alien civilizations; if they are to amount to anything
more than a servile and an imitative class. In other words, the
benefits of such control will be on the side of the civilizer, England,
and the civilized will possess doubtful good, questionable advantage.
With nations as with the individuals, elevation should be from within—by 
growth, not from without—by mounting upon others.</p>

<p>The native races are not dissatisfied with the control of the civilized
Negro state. And, if they were, neither England nor any other nation 
has a right, unless injured by such control, to relieve them of it,
or by consent of the governing state. Three years ago it was my pleasure 
to visit, incognito, some of the native races resident in the
disputed territory, and I found contentment and plenty among them
in the towns and villages. It was a year of successful crops, and although 
native wars were then in action, yet the Liberian citizen had
immunity from molestation so long as his relation was that of a neutral. 
Trade in the civilized settlements suffered in consequence of the
wars, but the same condition of affairs existed then in the native
settlements to the east of Sierra Leone, and the military force at

<pb xml:id="p96" facs="teaa.en.book.0004.003.jpg"/>

command was not competent to stop the wars, and trade languished 
at times in Freetown. These temporary suspensions of trade
will continue to occur from time to time until the influence of civilization 
shall gradually destroy heathenism and though the work of
peaceful change be slow, it is all the more permanent. War force
cannot but pander to the worst instincts of heathen races, as it does
to the baser instincts of civilized nations.</p>

<p>But the enclosure of the convention made between the Liberian
Peace Commission and the native chiefs of the disputed territory
(No. 8) speaks with more force than I can against the statement made
on the side of the British officer, (No. 7) in refutation of the assertion
that the native races are dissatisfied with Liberia's control. The agreement 
entered into by Governor Havelock and the natives, stripped
of the glamour which surrounds it, is but a cajoling of the people
into a sale of what is not theirs, for a deferred consideration, and
the contingency upon which it depends may happen at any time, and
cause a discontinuance of the stipendiary bribes offered and given.</p>

<p>A better lesson in duplicity was never given than the one taught in
the convention <sic>betweeen</sic> Governor Havelock and the native chiefs
of the disputed territory.</p>

<p>To say the least, the Commissioners of 1879, with our distinguished
naval officer, Commodore Shufeldt, with persons and papers produced, 
and in the soil in dispute, were, in the opinion of any unbiased 
mind, more competent to pass upon the subject than the
Governor in the absence of the original testimony.</p>

<p>As to the proposal of President Gardner, I am advised that it was
made under duress, and with a consciousness that the nation in its
representative capacity would oppose it, and hence the effort made
to gain time by referring it to the Senate, which will convene in
December next.</p>

<p>While European nations have done much for Africa and the world
by affording information concerning the ancient and mysterious
land—geographically and as to its native races, still seizure was not
the controlling motive in the researches of these people. Europe
needed a means of perpetuating her own material well being, which
overcrowded communities denied. And if to attain the end in view,
Africa has suffered in proportion as she has been <sic>benefitted</sic>, it is
not surprising. In the light of the foregoing, it is but reasonable
to conclude that, when our country shall be induced to take an active
interest in Liberia, or any other portion of the African continent
that interest will be unselfish, philanthropic and sincere; or when
America shall seek the commerce of Africa, she will do so with no

<pb xml:id="p97" facs="teaa.en.book.0004.004.jpg"/>

design of acquiring colonial possessions, and she will be more just
than others in her dealings with native races.</p>

<p>Please find the following enclosures: number 1 a note as to the
prospective conference and its object; number 2, proposition of the
British Governor, number 3, the reply to the Governor's proposition
by the Secretary; number 4, the President's proposal; number 5 &amp; 6,
letters to Morannah Sandoh by Governor Havelock and G. M.
Macaulay, number 9 the consent of H.M.'s Government to wait the
action of the senate.</p>

<p>With sentiments . . .<lb/>
Jno. H. Smyth</p>

<p>P.S. There is a prospective result that may be looked for to follow
the taking from Liberia of this long possessed disputed territory;
the lowering of her prestige among the native races within Liberia
and contiguous to Liberia. Power always commands respect. Denude 
Liberia of any portion of her territory, and she so far is injured,
and falls in the estimation of native races. Should England take
the disputed territory, and the native races be forced into a recognition 
of a foreign, alien power, they will never <hi rend="italics">feel</hi> any respect for it.
The change must affect injuriously Liberia, and injuriously the
aboriginal Negroes' self respect.</p>

<p>The civilized Negro in Africa under foreign domination, as the
civilized Negro out of Africa under like control, suffers in his liberty,
because it has not the element of imperium. "Imperium et Libertas"
must be the motto and the practice of the Negro, if he is to have self
respect; if he is to merit the respect of others.</p>

<p>I hope it may be found in consonance with the foreign policy of our
Government to aid Liberia in a retention of her self respect unimpaired, 
her control of her territory, her prestige which is the consequence 
of her control.</p>

<p>J. H. S.</p>


</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>