<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0246">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- DOCUMENT TITLE + DATE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Etienne to Under Secretary of State, August 14, 1889 --></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0246</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Roncière Lenour to Mister Director of the Colonies--></title>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 119</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT FROM --></placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT TO --></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-11" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2018" who="sab">translation</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0246.001.jpg"/>

<p>En réponse à diverses questions posées par M. le
Ministre des Etats-Unis d'Amérique, il lui est fourni les
renseignments suivants:</p>
    
<p>I.- Le Commerce est absolument libre dans l'Etat Indépendant
du Congo. Tout particulier peut vendre aux habitants
toutes marchandises et leur acheter les produits de leur
travail. Toutefois, le trafic des armes à feu perfectionnées
est interdit. La vente des spiriteux aux indigènes est
également prohibée dans presque tout l'Etat, à l'exception
d'une partie du Bas Congo.</p>
    
<p>Il va de soi que pour se livrer sur une propriété
à une exploitation quelconque, il faut au Congo comme
partout ailleurs, l'autorisation du propriétaire. Aussi les
produits, notamment l'ivoire et le caoutchouc, provenant des
forets de l'Etat ne peuvent être récoltés sans l'autorisation
du propriétaire. Cette autorisaion s'accorde, en ce
qui concerne les forêts non vendues ni concédes, aux sujets
de toutes les nationalités, dans les bassins des rivières
Kassï, Sankuru, Lubefu, Loango, Djuma, Ubangi, sur les rives du Congo
en aval des Falls, dans le bassin de la Lulonga, de
l'Ikelemba et du Ruki. (Décret du 30 Octobre 1892 sur l'exploitation
du caoutchouc et disposition ultérieurs).</p>
    
<p>II.- Il n'a pas de formalités à remplir pour exercer
un commerce quelconque. S'il s'agit de l'établissement
d'une société commerciale, les statuts de cette société
doivent être déposés au greffe du Tribunal de première instance,
à Boma.</p>
    
<p>Les associations religeuses ne son reconnues légalement
que par l'octroi de la personification civile; celle-
ci se demande par requête adressée au Gouverneur Général,
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0246.002.jpg"/>
    
elle s'accorde par décret du Roi-Souverain.</p>
    
<p>Les importations et exportations de marchandises sont
soumises aux formalités douanières indiquées dans les règlements
ci-joints (Annexes I et II).</p>
    
<p>III.- Toute personne qui désire acheter ou prendre en
location des terres autres que celles sur lesquelles il
existe, au profit de tiers, des droit de propriété dûment
enregisterés, doit en faire la demande soit au Secrétaire
d'Etat à Bruxelles, soit au Gouverneur Général à Boma. </p>
    
<p>IV.- Les principales taxes à acquitter au Congo sont
1o le rix d'achat ou de location des terres, si elles 
appartiennent au domaine de l'Etat. (Annexe III_)</p>
    
<p>2° La taxe d'enregistrement et les frais de mesurage de
ces terres (Voir annexe IV ci-jointe, pages 8 et 12);</p>

<p>3° Les impositions directes et personnelles (Voir annexe V
ci-jointe);</p>
    
<p>4° les droits sortie et d'entrée (Voir annexes I et II
ci-jointes);</p>

<p>5° La taxe domaniale sur le caoutchouc. Cette taxe est de
0,25 frs. par kilogramme de caoutchouc récolté. Le caoutchouc
provennant des territoires en aval du Stanley-Pool,
des rives de l'Ubangi n'est pas soumis à cet impôt;</p>
    
<p>6° Taxe sur le recrutemont des travailleurs (Voir annexe
VI, ci-jointe, page 151).</p>
    
<p>Toutes ces taxes peuvent être modifiées par la loi,
sauf les droits d'entrée qui ont été établis d'accord avec
les puissances.</p>
    
<p>V.-Les lois congolaises, conformément à l'Acte de 
Berlin, ne contiennent aucune distinction relativement à la
nationalité des particuliers ou des sociéties.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0246.001.jpg"/>
        
<p>In response to the varying questions asked by Mr. 
Minister of the United States of America, he provided him the 
following statements:</p>
        
<p>I.- The Commerce is absolutely free in the Independant State 
of the Congo. All specifics can sell to the residents 
all goods and buy the products of their 
work. However, the trafficking of advanced firearms 
is prohibited. The spirited wind of the natives is
equally prohibited in the almost the entire State, with the exception 
of one part of the Bas Congo.</p>
        
<p>It goes without saying that with a property 
in an ordinary exploitation,  il faut au Congo comme
partout ailleurs, the authorization of the property. Also the
products, notably they ivory and the rubber, come from the 
State forests and cannot be harvested withouth authorization
from the owner. The authorization granted, with what 
concerns the unsold or conceded forests, to the subects 
of all the nationalities, in the river bassins 
Kassï, Sankuru, Lubefu, Loango, Djuma, Ubangi, on the Congo rivers 
downstream of the FAlls, in the Lulonga bassin, 
in the Ikelemba and the Ruki. (Decreed the 30th of October 1892 on the exploitation 
of rubber and the later placement).</p>
        
<p>II.- There are no formalities to fulfill for excercising  
any commerce. If one acts to establish 
any societal trade, the status of this society 
must be deposed to the courts administration service of the Tribunal to the primary authority,
in Boma.</p>
        
<p>The religious associations don't legally recognize 
that by the grant of the civil personification; this 
one demands by the adressed request to the Governor General,
        
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0246.002.jpg"/>
        
she grants by the order of the Sovereign King.</p>
        
<p>The imports and exports of merchandise are 
subject to the formalities of customs officers indicated in the regulations 
enclosed (Annexs I and II).</p>
        
<p>III.- Every person who wants to buy or take 
other land for lease on which it 
exists, for the profit of the outsiders, the owner's rights duly 
noted, must do it the demande either to the Secretary 
of State in Brussels, or the Governer General in Boma.</p>
        
<p>IV.- The principle taxes to acquit in the Congo are 
1o the price of purchasing or from renting the proptery, if they 
belong to the domaine of the State. (Annex III_)</p>
        
<p>2° The registration fee and the metering expenses of 
these properties (See annex IV attached, pages 8 and 12);</p>

<p>3° The direct and personal imposisitions (See annex V 
attahed);</p>
        
<p>4° The exit and entrance fees (See annexs I and II 
attached);</p>
        
<p>5° The state tax ont he rubber. This tax is 
0.25 frs. per kilogram of harvested rubber. The rubber 
originating from the territories downriver of Stanley-Pool,
the Ubangi rivers is not subject to this tax;</p>
        
<p>6° Tax on the recruitment of the workers (See annex
VI, attached, page 151).</p>
        
<p>All of these taxes can be modified by law, 
with exception to the rights of entrance that has been established in accordance with
the powers.</p>
        
<p>V.-The Conglese laws, in accordance with the Act of  
Berlin, contain no distinction relative to the 
nationality from particulars or from societies.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
