<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0285">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J.M. Preston to William H. Seward, June 23, 1865</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0285</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <title level="a">Despatch from J.M. Preston to William H. Seward, June 23, 1865</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gaboon, 1856-1888 T-466</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-466, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1865-06-23">June 23, 1865</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>



<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Preston, J.M.</persName>
<roleName>Hon.</roleName>
<placeName>Gaboon</placeName>
<date when="1865-06-23"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Seward, William H.</persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10" who="#unm"></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

Dear Sir:

The 
vacancy in this Cuncl. Agency caused by the 
resignation of the May estof. which I mentioned 
in despatch No. 2, gives me an opportunity here in the United States 
without infringing the might of anyone, of saying 
a few words on the U.S. commerce with this port 
and the suiall need there is for a cosular officer.

The trade has been gradually decreasing for 
a number of years. For the last three years, on a 
average three vessels about 600 tons in all a year 
have come this way from the bright of Benin,
to land a few passengers and a little freight and 
to buy a few thoudand billets of Borovod can 
article. I believe, not dutiable, and of which a few 
congors would glut the market to complete their 
cargoes of Coffee, Camwood, Palm-oil or bought 
along the coast from Monrovia to Feruaudo PO.

There is no prospect of the prade reviving 
The Ivory trade is pushed to its which extend .
It is in the hands of the English, who can 
produce the Articles narters for is cheaper
more inferior in quality than the American Can.

The India-rubber id being rapidly exhausted 
Barewood is still plenty; but the French 
authorities here prevent all vessels from going 
up the river to trade + thus getting mean the 
Barwood, and even small boats must procure 
carry the French flag. This causes delay 
and increases the price.

American vessels of late, for the sale of 
despatch, but of the English factories have. 

Thus trade does not require the presence 
of a Condul Rev.

The officer at Gaboon san viot-ruour*
about cargies, taken aboard at ports North of 
this, so as to forward frauds on the revenue*.
Besides the greater number of vessels return
to the States from ports North of this, at which 
here has not the opportunity of certifying 
even to the best of his knowledge to the 
cargos shipped. 

The number of American Citizen residents
here has also decreased. Their relations with the 
authorities have been for the last fifteen years 
of the most friendly character, and are likely so 
to remain on their part there had never been a 
desire for a consular officer at Gaboon.
There are a few Americans at lemisco*, but 
they are under Spanish rule. They may be 
intefered with; but they could not be much 
assisted by a consul in a French port, if they 
are.

Should the United State again send a Aquaron
to the West Coast of Africa to corperate with 
England in supporting the Slave trade, a consul 
at Gaboon would be of very little use. For several
degrees North+ South of this part there is no 
foreign slave trade, except what is carried 
on in small schomers about from the Porteguese 
islands of Prince amd St.Lenard. The slave trade squadrum
route have no businep in a french
port, where the trade is prohibited.

Fernando Po, as being already a depot
for coals, and the Southern terminal of the 
line of Mail Steamer, and also mean the 
parts in the Bight of Benin, where the 
trade is carried on, would become a endevours 
for our vessel.

In time I do not see what American interest
can be advances by the U.S. Comml. Agency. 
at Gaboon; nor what interest would be in
any way prejudices by its disconinuance.

I have done only what I consider my duty 
to my Country in communicatiing the above 
of understanding these representations you wish 
to continue it, I an ready to welcome and 
assist you appointed as far as I can; or 
I should feel myself honored in subserving 
the interests of the United States here, and 
would if appointed Commercial Agent discharge 
the duties of the office to the best of 
my ability. I am free to confess that I 
desire to urge why it should be conferred 
upon me rather than another.

I have the honor, to be, you obedient Servant,
J.M.Preston.

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>

<p></p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
