<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Civil Commandents Office
No. 41 Balagna 22nd March 1869

Sir,

On Saturday the 6th March I was waited on by David C. Miller late Master of the American barque "gem" who informed me that his vessel had been loss on the reefs on the West side of the island of 'Orange' on the <unclear> receiving </unclear> of the both March that he with 3 of his Sailore had arrived as this port in a small boat and that he was <unclear> divisions</unclear> of making a declaration before me relative to the loss of his vessel. A copy of the declaration I herewith enclose marked A Knowing that a brig called the "Potomac" belonging to the same owner as the "Gem" was at <unclear/> I dispatched the 3 Sailors to that place the same evening with the <unclear/> Colonial Secretary

Freetown

a letter to the Governor of <unclear/> reuesting that the 3 mn might be allowed to go on board the "Potomac" <unclear/> in Portuguese Waters. This request was granted, but on the night of the 10th, instant the <unclear extent=three words/> sent book to me accompanied with the enclosed hole marked and from the Master of the "Potomac". 

On the 8th, instant the other boat <unclear extent=three words/> in the declaration reached this port. In all the boats contained 10 persons, of these 10 individuals I was send on to Freetown to be handed over to the American Consul by ths mi the <unclear> undercautioned </unclear> namely

<!-- bracket around numbers 1-7, titled "AB." -->

1. W.H. Tracey 1st Officer
2. Alesauder Foreman 2nd Officer
3 John Brown
4. Henry Clark
5. G.E. Linsco
6. E.J. Jones 7. John McDonald

The steward by name John Lass has gone with Captain Brown of the "Potomac" and also a native who was engaged whilst on the rivers. 

The late Master of the "Gene" is still here and intends refirming to America by the frst <unclear> via reiverpool at his at his own response. 
</unclear>

The Crew saved their clothing - no lives were lost and the Ships papers were alo saved. 

The Charges incurred by the Colonial Government on behalf of these distressed seamen will be forwarded in my Douchers by the meet opportunity.

I have to
Signed "J.Craig Loggie"
Acting Civil Commandant
Bulama