<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0904">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward, December 31, 1862</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0904</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 2</biblScope>
<date when="1862-12-31">December 31, 1862</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hanson, Abraham</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1862-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-04-16"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-05" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0078.jpg"/>

<p>No. 7.</p>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency,<lb/>
Monrovia, Dec 31st., 1862.</p>

<p>To the Honorable William H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State of U.S. of A.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to
enclose herein, duplicate copies of the Message
of His Excellency, S. A. Benson, President of Liberia,
to the Legislature.</p>

<p>I also have the honor to enclose duplicate
copies of a "Prospectus" of a plan for
the promotion and extension of Commerce, between
Great Britain, and the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>I have the honor to remain,<lb/>
With Sincere Respect,<lb/>
Your very Obedient Servt.<lb/>
Abm Hanson,<lb/>
U.S. Com. Agent.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0079.jpg"/>

<note>U.S. Commercial Agency
Monrovia December 31, 1862<lb/>
Abm Hanson Com. Agent</note>

<note>No 7<lb/>
2 Enclosures<lb/>
Received</note>

<note>Annual Message of
President to Legislature of Liberia</note>

<note>Prospectus of a scheme 
of British capitalists for
enlargement of their commerce
with that coast of Africa</note>

<note>Received at Statistical Office May 16/63</note>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0080.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<note>Copy of the Original Prospectus as published in England.</note>

<head type="main">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Incorporated under the Joint Stock Companies' Act of 1856 and 1857, whereby the liability of the Shareholders is limited to the amount of their Subscriptions.</p>

<p>CAPITAL £250,000, in 25,000 SHARES of £10 Each.</p>

<p>FIRST ISSUE 12,500 SHARES.</p>

<p>£1 to be paid on application, and £1 10s. on allotment. The holders of such first Shares to have the preference, pro rata, in all further issues. No call to exceed £2 10s. per Share, nor to be made except at an interval of at least three months from any previous Call.</p>

<p>If no allotment be made, the Deposit will be returned in full.</p>

<list>
<head>Directors.</head>
<item>Thomas Bazley, Esq., M.P., Manchester.</item>
<item>Thomas Bradshaw, Esq., Temple.</item>
<item>George Braginton, Esq., Torrington, Devon.</item><item>Thomas Briggs, Esq., Prestwich Park, Manchester.</item>
<item>Henry Brownrigg, Esq., 33, Lime Street, E.C.</item>
<item>Thomas Clegg, Esq., Manchester.</item>
<item>Frederic Doulton, Esq., M.P., Lambeth.</item>
<item>Ambrose Emerson, Esq. (Messrs. Newby, Carson &amp; Co., Gresham House, E.C.)</item>
<item>Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, F.R.G.S., J.P., Cardiff.</item>
<item>Gerard Ralston, Esq., Consul-General for Liberia, 21, Tokenhouse Yard, E.C.</item>
<item>(with power to add.)</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Bankers.</head>
<item>The London and Westminster Bank, Lothbury, E.C.</item>
<item>Solicitors. Messrs. Cotterill &amp; Sons, 32, Throgmorton Street.</item>
<item>Brokers. Messrs. Huggins &amp; Rowsell, 1, Threadneedle Street.</item>
<item>General Manager. J. B. Langley, Esq.</item>
<item>Secretary. F. W. Stone, Esq.</item>
<item>Shipping and Insurance Agent. Charles Kitto, Esq.</item>
<item>Temporary Offices. 41, Gresham House, E.C.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Prospectus.</head>

<p>The object of the Company is–To establish Trading Stations, Factories, and Depots on the Coast of Western Africa, and by means of organized Agencies, to bring down and collect for shipment at such stations, the valuable products of the Interior; to import Goods, and introduce Machinery for cleaning and pressing Cotton, and for other purposes; and generally to enter into Commercial relations with the Native Traders, by means of barter traffic or otherwise; and thereby to open up, in exchange for British manufactures, a practically illimitable market for Cotton and other products–and to secure their transmission to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>The capabilities of Africa to meet the commercial requirements of Europe are evidenced in the variety of its productions, and the increasing extent of its trading operations; and it has long been a matter of surprise, that the encouragement of Native industry should have been left to associations of a philanthropic character, or to a few Merchants intent upon the enormous profit which exclusive dealings with the Natives incontestably afford.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0081.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Cotton.</head>

<p>The cultivation of the Cotton Plant, and the employment of African labour on its native soil, have already been sufficiently tested. There is abundance of labour seeking employment, a fertile soil well adapted for its growth, and a population actively alive to what will benefit themselves. <hi rend="italics">No expensive or uncertain experiments are required to test the ability or the will of the Natives to supply this country with cheap and good cotton.</hi> The testimony of the officers of the Niger expedition concurs with, and confirms, the evidence of Dr. Livingstone, and other African travellers, that indigenous Cotton is growing in abundance throughout vast districts, covering many thousands of miles of territory, and only waits to be gathered. Some Tribes of the Natives are largely engaged in manufacturing Cotton into clothing for their own use. It is calculated that more than 200,000 pieces of these cloths are annually exported from Africa into the Brazils. In fact, only buyers on the spot are wanted to take from the Natives what they have to offer, giving in exchange manufactured goods suitable to their requirements.</p>

<p>In a letter from Dr. Balfour Bakie, in command of the Niger Expedition, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, which Lord Russell caused to be inserted in the <hi rend="italics">London Gazette</hi> of August 29th, 1862, he emphatically urges his Lordship "to call attention, in England, to the peculiar eligibility of this portion of Central Africa (Bida Nusse), as a Cotton field." Again, speaking of Sudan, and the Yoruba country, he proceeds to say–Here Cotton is already in abundance, and cultivated by a people able and willing to work, and accustomed to its habits and rearing; nothing is required but increased demand, means of purchase, cleaning and shipment. The rest would speedily follow."</p>

<p>Another practical authority–Mr. Clegg, of Manchester, who has an establishment at Abeokuta, states–"for very many years my instructions have been to cease buying Cotton, when more than a halfpenny per pound in the Seed, and my young Africans have again and again written to say, that at that price for more was brought to them than they could buy."</p>

<p>Mr. I. Lyons McLeod, Hon. Secretary to the African Aid Society, in a Letter to the <hi rend="italics">Times</hi>, March 28th, 1861, writes–"It is a well-attested fact, that from Western Africa (shipping port Lagos), Cotton in abundance maybe purchased at 2d. per lb., and allowing for exorbitant overcharge for cleaning freight, &amp;c., it may be sold from the same locality in Liverpool at 4½d. per lb. This Cotton is equal in quality to New Orleans at 6½d. per lb., proving beyond doubt, that from Western Africa, which is nearer to our shores than the Cotton districts of America, we may obtain the same amount of Cotton for £20,000,000, for which we are paying the Slaveholders of the United States £30,000,000. In Western Africa–the Yoruba Country, and along the valley of the Niger," (the localities above referred to by Dr. Balfour Bakie)–"the Natives are ready to supply any amount of Cotton for Manchester and Glasgow Manufacturers."</p>
<p>These testimonies appear to demand the most serious attention and consideration at the present crisis.</p>

<p>The supply of Cotton from the Southern States (which till a recent date formed 80 per cent. of our consumption), cannot be fully renewed for several years; part of the crop of 1861 has been burned, and the remainder may never reach us. In 1862, it is believed, that only about one-fourth of the usual crop has been sown, and it is not likely that a larger area can be placed under Cotton Culture in 1863; so that, if the Civil War were to be ended by any means to-morrow, the full supply of American Cotton could not be resumed till September, 1864. Till that date, the price of middling and ordinary Orleans are not likely to fall below One Shilling per pound.</p>

<p>There is abundant evidence to show that India cannot for many years supply the quantity or quality required. The Egyptian supply is the only one which might be supposed likely to compete with that imported from West Africa; but the Egyptian Cotton imported into England has never hitherto reached 200,000 bales in any one year, and if doubled (which it cannot be for two or three years), it will not suffice to make up the deficiency created by the reduced supplies of ordinary Americans. Besides, the average price of <sic>Egytian</sic> Cotton has been 8d. per pound for several years. African Cotton, equal to middling Orleans, can be delivered in Liverpool, at a cost to the Importer of Fourpence Halfpenny per pound. In the seed, in Africa, it may be procured in unlimited quantities at about one Halfpenny per pound; cleaned Cotton about Threepence. Payments being made in barter, the profits on the Goods reduce the cost price of the Cotton considerably.</p>

<p>It is not the intention of the "West Africa Company" to become <hi rend="italics">Cultivators of Cotton</hi>; the Company will simply be <hi rend="italics">Purchasers of Cotton</hi>, which will be brought down to their Stations by the Native Traders, and thence Shipped to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>Several well-known Firms, having used African Cotton in their Manufactories, are able to report favourably of its quality working.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0082.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">General Trade.</head>

<p>The Company will not, however, depend on Cotton alone for realising the good dividend on the capital employed. The interchange of commodities will be widened to the largest possible extent, so as to include every other product of Africa, which will pay an enhanced value in this country. These products, which consist chiefly of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, Gold Dust, Ivory, Hides, Indigo, Copper, Ground Nuts, Pepper, Arrowroot, Gums, Dye Woods, Ostrich Feathers, Timber for Shipbuilding, and other articles of commerce, equally suitable to the requirements of our markets, will also be made the media of trade, so as to suit the industry and keen trading instincts of the various classes of Native producers. The fact that the production of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, and other valuable articles, is in excess of the local demand, can be shown by the latest and most indubitable authorities. The Rev. Samuel Crowther, writing to the Church Missionary Society lately, states, "at the Delta of the Niger alone, millions' worth, in red Oil and black Oil from the kernels of the Palm nut, rot away annually for want of inducement to collect them."* From an official document received through the Board of Trade, it appears that in 1856 upwards of 220,000 tons of these kernels, from which Oil of the value of £3,789,000 might have been extracted, were actually thrown away on the coast. The amount thus lost represents in actual value a sum of upwards of a Million Sterling more than all the tallow exported from Russia in that year; and when it is considered that the tallow was paid for in cash, and that the bulk of the trade with Africa may be carried on by barter of the manufactures of Manchester, Glasgow, Birmingham, the Potteries, and Sheffield, it is impossible to overrate the benefits which will accrue to this country by developing the resources of Western Africa.</p>

<p>As there is no currency in the Country, trade is conducted by means of barter, so that a market for English productions </p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>