<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0090">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Augustus Archer Silva to Grant &amp; Brodie, November 15, 1869</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Sims, Lee-Ann L." xml:id="ls">Lee-Ann L. Sims</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0090</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Letter from Augustus Archer Silva to Grant &amp; Brodie</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">2</biblScope>
<date when="1869-11-15">November 15, 1869</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Gomes da Silva, José</term>
<term>King Catende</term>
<term>King Chindo</term>
<term>King Manguangua</term>
<term>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term>Soares da Costa Magalhães, Albino José</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Puto Ambaca (Angola)</term>
<term>Cape of Good Hope</term>
<term>Cazengo (Angola)</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Cuanza River</term>
<term>Dondo (Angola)</term>
<term>Kazembe</term>
<term>Malanje (Angola)</term>
<term>Mozambique</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>Zambezi River</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Silva, Augustus Archer</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent for Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda, Angola</placeName>
<date when="1869-11-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Grant</persName>
<persName>Brodie</persName>
<placeName>London, England</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-06-25" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and addition encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="ls">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.001"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<opener><dateline>St. Paul de Loanda<lb/>
15th November 1869.</dateline>

<address><addrLine>Messrs Grant Brodie &amp;ca</addrLine>
<addrLine>London</addrLine></address>
</opener>

<p>Dear Sirs</p>

<p>On the 15th of last month, while
at Dondo, I met a merchant by name José
Gomes da Silva, who related to me a most
interesting account of his travels through
the interior of Africa, as far as the
upper bank of the Zambeze river, on a
mission for the purchase of slaves, for
the estate of Albino José Soares da
Costa Magalhaes, a well known coffee 
planter of Cazengo.</p>

<p>On my enquiring if he 
had heard any news of the whereabouts of
Dr. Livingstone, he told me that he had
heard he was killed, and related a very
startling account of the circumstances connected
with, and leading to his death.</p>

<p>Although interested at the time, I paid
little more attention to the subject, until
my return to Loanda; a few days afterwards
I read an article in the "Times" of Sept
<unclear>7th</unclear>, which convinced me that no reliable
information had reached England, <unclear>regarding</unclear>
<unclear>the existence</unclear> of Dr. Livingstone

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.002"/>

since 1868.</p>

<p>Sr Gomes da Silva, arrived in
Loanda two days after me, and I embraced
the opportunity to envite him to my
house, with a view of obtaining from
him all the information he possessed
regarding the unhappy fate of Dr. Livingstone.
He readily complied with my request,
and I was so convinced of the
truth of his statement, that at my request
he addressed me a letter on the subject, a 
copy of which I beg to enclose, knowing
that any thing which may tend to throw
light on the fate of that distinguished
traveller must be of the greatest interest
to you and your countrymen.</p>

<p>Snr Gomes da Silva states
that after a dangerous journey he crossed
the River Congo on a bridge made of
trunks of trees, in the territory of Lucuna.
near to King Catende; three days afterwards,
taking the sun as his guide, he
proceeded in a south-easterly direction,
and after a March of twelve days through
many large and wonderful plains, he
arrived at the town of King Manguangua
on the banks of the River Zambesi,
having expended ninety five days in travelling
from Malange in the province of Angola.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.003"/>

<p>On the 15th June 1868, two months after his
arrival there, it came to his knowledge that
an ambassador (Cacuata) with five hundred
natives had arrived at King Chindo's, who
reigned on the opposite bank of the Zambezi,
in order to pay the customary tributes to 
his superior <unclear>Muata</unclear> Invo, the ambassador
being from the King of Cazembe.</p>

<p>His curiosity induced him to invite
to King of Cazembe's ambassador, to come and
see him, and as it was on his way the ambassador
accepted the invitation, bringing with
him the five hundred natives who had 
accompanied him.</p>

<p>In the course of some conversation 
which he had with the ambassador,
regarding the roads which lead to Mozambique,
it <sic>accurred</sic> to him to enquire concerning
Dr Livingstone, when the ambassador immediately
replied "dont speak to me of the 
great fetish" and then enquired if he were
any relative of his. Being alarmed at the 
manner and tone of this remark he did
not think it advisable to continue the conversation.</p>

<p>The ambassador however remained
with him several days, and Snr Gomes da Silva's
kind hospitality soon won the confidence of
his guest, who one evening invited him to his

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.004"/>

hut, where were prepared two calabashes of cacollo,
an intoxicating drink made from fermented
honey, and then he was enabled to obtain
further information regarding Dr Livingstone.
The ambassador, having sent away his <sic>servent</sic>,
and speaking in a manner calculated to impress
the greatest secrecy, gave Snr da Silva
the following information regarding the death
of Dr Livingstone.</p>

<p>Referring to Dr Livingstone, he
said that the Calunga was a great fetishman
that he spoke every day with the
sun, never slept in houses, was not afraid
of wild animals; that he kept one in a
box, and never gave it any thing to eat, but
would open the box, always when he wanted
know the right road, and never asked
this information from any one else; at times
he would open large rolls of paper, and 
would talk to them with great earnestness;
he would cross rivers without a canoe, and 
did many other things equally astonishing.</p>

<p>In his previous travels when
he crossed from Puto-Ambaca (St Paul de
Loanda) he had already, among the natives,
the reputation of being a great calunga or
wizard, as the ambassador said about that
time no one dared look him in the face
from the impression they entertain of his

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.005"/>

supernatural powers.</p>

<p>It seems that on his journey
from St. Paul de Loanda to the East Coast
he encamped for the night in the district
of Cazembe, twenty day journey from the
spot where they now were, and a few days
after his departure, one of the King's
sons took ill suddenly, and died; the king attributing
his death to the evil influence of
Dr Livingstone whom he accordingly sent after
to destroy. Dr Livingstone was too far advanced 
be overtaken, and thus escaped, although
this circumstances was in the end the cause
of his death, although long afterwards.</p>

<p>It was on his present expedition, that 
he again came into this district, and the
King being informed of the approach of the
great Calunga, sent out at once to meet him,
and presented him with a cup of "muange,"
a poisoned drink, the effect of which, in the
belief of the natives, decides the guilt or 
innocence of the accused, and thus certain
death awaits the suspected, such was the
unfortunate result to Dr Livingstone, and
while suffering from the effects he was
<gap extent="one line" reason="poor image"/>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.006"/>

since denied, but received no further information.</p>

<p>Horrible as this story may appear,
yet from the several interviews I had
with Snr Gomes da Silva, and the earnest attention
I paid to repeated narrations of his
story, and the exactness of each repetition,
the locality from which he derived his information,
the intense anxiety exhibited by 
the ambassador to ensure secrecy from his
own tribe, together with the fact, that
Dr Livingstone was supposed to be in that
vicinity at that time, from all these facts
combined I am inclined to attach credence
to the story of Snr Gomes da Silva, and
to believe that a sorrowful light of truthfulness
has been thrown on the fate of 
this illustrious traveller.</p>

<p>You will observe from the
foregoing that Dr Livingstone's reputation
of being a Calunga or wizard among the
native tribes of the interior of Africa, dates
from his journey from the Cape of Good
Hope to St. Paul de Loanda. All African
traders are aware that a horrible death
awaits the unfortunate native who is accused
of witch-craft. Travellers on the Quanza
<gap extent="several words" reason="poor image"/> with the famous
<gap extent="one line" reason="poor image"/>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0090.007"/>

been hurled, after having been dragged bound
hand and foot for many miles, therefore
it is not improbable that Dr Livingstone
ended his valuable life a victim to 
native superstition.</p>

<p>It is a matter of regret
to me to be the medium of information of
so sad a nature, but while deeming it my 
duty to give publicity, to so important a
revelation, I trust that intelligence received
from other quarters will prove the statement
I have written to be unreliable, and that
Dr Livingstone is still spared and destined
some day to return to his country.</p>

<closer><salute>I am<lb/>
Dear Sirs<lb/>
Yours Faithfully</salute>
(Sgd) <signed>Augustus Archer Silva</signed></closer>


</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
