<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fr.letter.0055.xml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter to Citizen Minister of Foreign Affairs, September 11, 1848</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Niendorf, Nicholas" xml:id="nn">Nicholas Niendorf</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">fr.letter.0055</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter to Citizen Minister of Foreign Affairs</title>
<date when="1848-09-11">September 11, 1848</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>FR ANOM</repository>
<collection>Afrique VI</collection>
<idno>8 Liberia</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bougainville, Chaigneau</term>
<term>Hotham</term>
<term>Montagniès de la Rogue</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Colony of Monrovia</term>
<term>Republic of Liberia</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>






</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Paris</placeName>
<date when="1848-09-11"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Citizen Minister of Foreign Afairs</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="nn">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">Translated and encoded header information.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">Edited encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr"  type="document">

<pb facs="20160613_162422.jpg"/>

<ab>
Ministère
de la Marine
et des Colonies
</ab>

<ab>
Direction des Colonies
</ab>

<ab>
Bureau du Régime Politique
et du
Commerce.
</ab>

<ab>
au Sujet de la déclaration
d'indèpendance de la
République de Liberia.
</ab>

<ab>
Paris, le 11 <del>Sepember</del> <add>Septembre</add> 1848.
</ab>

<p>
Citoyen Ministre et cher Collègue,

La Colonie de Monrovia fondée en juin
1822, à la côte occidentale d'afrique, par une
société américaine, pour servir de secours aux hommes
de couleur affranchis, aux Etats unis, s'est déclaré
indépendante de cette société en août 1849, et s'est
constituée en Etat Souverain, sous le nom de République <!-- 'République' is split and hyphenated between 'Répu-' and 'blique'. -->
de Liberia.
</p>

<p>
Le 2 Septembre suivant, le Gouvernement
de Liberia a notifié officiellement à Mr. Chaigneau
commandant de la Corvette de Guerre française,
Bougainville en station sur ce point, la déclaration
d'indépendance de la Colonie. Il a adressé en
même temps à cet officier un exemplaire de la
constitution votée le 29 juillet précédent, et une
carte du territoire de la République.
</p>

<ab>
En
</ab>

<ab>
au Citoyen Ministre des Affaires Etrangères.
</ab>

<pb facs="20160613_162438.jpg"/>

<p>
En transmettant le 21 février 1848,
ces documents au Ministre de la Marine et des 
Colonies, le commandant des forces navales
françaises sur la côte occidentale d'afrique, a
fait savoir que le commodore Hotham, au nom
du Gouvernement Britannique, et l'officier américain
placé à la têt de la station des Etats-Unis, ont reconnu
la République de Liberia, et qu'ils ont donné l'ordre
d'en saluer le pavillon.
</p>

<p>
Mr. Montagniès de la Rogue s'est abstenu
de faire la même manifestation, jusqu'à ce qu'il
eût reçu les instructions du Gouvernement.
</p>

<p>
Mon avis est qu'il y a lieu de prescrire à son
successeur, Mr le Capitaine de vaisseau Baudin, de
procéder immédiatement à la reconnaissance de la
nouvelle République. Mr Montagniès de la Rogue
n'y a vu qu'une seule difficulté. Elle consiste en
ce que le chef d'un village africain, enclavé dans
les limites du territoire de la République de
Liberia, a conclu avec l'officier qui commandait la
station française, un traité en vertu du quel ce chef
</p>

<ab>
se
</ab>

<pb facs="20160613_162446.jpg"/>

<p>
se considère comme sujet de la France, et <unclear/>
ne pas vouloir accepter les lois du Gouvernement
de Liberia.
</p>

<p>
Je ne crois pas qu'il y ait des <unclear>réserves à</unclear>
faire au sujet de cet incident. Le Gouverement
de Liberia, remplit à la côte d'afrique une mission <!-- 'mission' is split and hyphenated between 'mis' and '-sion' -->
de consideration qu'il est digne de la République
fraçaise d'encourager. En <unclear>votre l'insistance </unclear> de <unclear>notre</unclear>
commerce nous commander d'entre <unclear>sans notre</unclear> <unclear/>
relations officielles avec cet êtat, afin que les <unclear/>
<unclear>remements</unclear> d'Angleterre et d'Amérique <unclear>que se faissait</unclear>
<unclear>puit</unclear> accorder en notre absence des <unclear/> <unclear>communications</unclear>
qui ne nous seraient point également accordé.
Enfin le souvenir des <unclear>embarras que nous sont</unclear>
<unclear>suscités</unclear> à la côte d'Afrique, les <unclear>esclaves</unclear> <unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> et <unclear/>, doit il me semble <unclear/> <unclear>indiquer</unclear>
de rien faire qui puisse, nous <unclear/> des <unclear>differentés</unclear>
du même genres.
</p>

<p>
Je vous prie, citoyen Ministre et Cher
collegue,

<!-- No Signature -->
</p>

</div1>
<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="20160613_162422.jpg"/>

<ab>
Minister
of the Navy
and the Colonies
</ab>

<ab>
Direction of the Colonies
</ab>

<ab>
Office of the Political Regime
and
Commerce.
</ab>

<ab>
on the subject of the declaration
of independence of the
Republic of Liberia.
</ab>

<ab>
Paris, <del>Sepember</del> <add>September</add> 11th 1848.
</ab>

<p>
Citizen Minister and dear colleague,

The colony of Monrovia founded in June
1822, on the west coast of Africa, by an
American society, to serve as assistance for the 
emancipated slaves, in the United States, declared itself
independent of this society in August 1849, and constituated
itself as a Sovereign State, under the name of Republic <!-- 'République' is split and hyphenated between 'Répu-' and 'blique'. -->
of Liberia.
</p>

<p>
The following September 2nd, the government
of Liberia officially notified Mr. Chaigneau
french lieutenant commander of war,
Bougainville in station at this point, the declaration
of independence of the colony. It addressed at the
same time to this officer a counterpart of the
constitution voted the preceding July 29th, and a
map of the territory of the Republic.
</p>

<ab>
En
</ab>

<ab>
to Citizen Minister of Foreign Affairs.
</ab>

<pb facs="20160613_162438.jpg"/>

<p>
In transmitting February 21st 1848,
these documents to the Minister of the Navy and the 
Colonies, the commander of the french naval
forces on the west coast of Africa, 
informed that the commodore Hotham, in the name of
the British government, and the american officer
placed at the head of the station of the United States, recognized
the Republic of Liberia, and that they gave the order
to recognize its flag.
</p>

<p>
Mr. Montagniès of the Rogue abstained
from making the same manifestation, until he
received the instructions from the Gouvernement.
</p>

<p>
My opinion is that there is place to prescribe to his
successor, Mr Captain of vessel Baudin, to
proceed immediately to the recognition of the
new Republic. Mr Montagniès of the Rogue
only saw a single difficulty there. It consists in
what the chief of an African village, isolated in
the limits of the territory of the Republic of
Liberia, concluded with the officer who commanded the
french station, a treaty in virtue of which this chief
</p>

<ab>
se
</ab>

<pb facs="20160613_162446.jpg"/>

<p>
considers as the subject of France, et <unclear/>
did not want to accept the laws of the government
of Liberia.
</p>

<p>
I do not believe that there are any <unclear>reservations to</unclear>
make on the subject of this incident. The government
of Liberia, fills a mission on the coast of Africa <!-- 'mission' is split and hyphenated between 'mis' and '-sion' -->
of consideration that it is dignified of the French
Republic to encourage. In <unclear>votre l'insistance </unclear> of <unclear>our</unclear>
commerce we command to enter <unclear>sans notre</unclear> <unclear/>
official relations with this state, so that the <unclear/>
<unclear>remements</unclear> of England and America <unclear>que se faissait</unclear>
<unclear>puit</unclear> accorded in our absence of the <unclear/> <unclear>communications</unclear>
that would not be equally accorded to us at all.
Finally the recollection of the <unclear>predicament that we</unclear>
provoked on the coast of Africa, the <unclear>slaves</unclear> <unclear/> <unclear/>
<unclear/> and <unclear/>, must it seem to me <unclear/> <unclear>to indicate</unclear>
nothing to do that could, nous <unclear/> the <unclear>differentés</unclear>
of the same type.
</p>

<p>
I urge you, citizen Minister and dear
colleague,

<!-- No Signature -->
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
