<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0971">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to Charles Payson, April 17, 1879</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0971</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to Charles Payson</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1879-04-17">April 17, 1879</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1879-04-21"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Payson, Charles</persName>
<roleName>Third Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1879-05-26"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-11" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2099.jpg"/>

<p>No. 12.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, La., Apr. 21st, 1879.</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to the Ass't Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Copies of the Acts of 1878-9 and President's Proclamation, sent.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2100.jpg"/>

<p>No. 12.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, La., Apr. 21st, 1879.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to transmit the following inclosures, the Acts of 1878-9 passed by the Legislature of the Republic of Liberia, and a Proclamation by Hon. G. W. Gardner, President of Liberia, the same being with reference to the enforcement of an existent amendment to a law, and has special reference to "original invoices," as to their making out, and certification by Liberian Consuls at <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. F. W. Seward,<lb/>
Ass't Sec'y of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2101.jpg"/>

the place or places of shipment of goods, and the liability of parties for neglect of the same.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obd't serv't,<lb/>
Jno H Smyth,<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl.</p>

<p>Inclosures:</p>

<p>1 Acts of 1878-9 - Liberian Legislature<lb/>
2 Proclamation of President.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2102.jpg"/>

<head type="main">A Proclamation!</head>

<p>WHEREAS the Legislature at the Session of 1877-78 amended the Act entitled "An Act to repeal 'An Act authorizing Specific duties on certain articles imported into the Republic of Liberia, and the collection of the same:" So as to provide that all original invoices of goods to be landed in this Republic be made out in the English Language, and also be certified by the Liberian Consul at the port or ports from which such goods and merchandise are shipped:–</p>

<p>AND WHEREAS it is the duty of the Executive to see that the laws are enforced and duly observed:–</p>

<p>AND WHEREAS it has come to the knowledge of the Government that there are parties who seem disposed to ignore the act above cited and who present invoices <sic>with out</sic> the Consular Certificate required by law:</p>

<p>THEREFORE, I hereby proclaim, by the power vested in me by the Constitution and laws of the Republic of Liberia, that the above cited amendment is in full force and effect; and that all Collectors of Customs at the several ports of entry within the Republic are commanded to observe the same; and further that from and after receiving and assessing duties on invoices not certified, according to the aforesaid Act, except from ports where there is no Liberian Consul, shall be regarded as aiding and <sic>abbetting</sic> the contravention of the Revenue laws and shall be dealt with accordingly:</p>

<p>AND FURTHER all Consignees and Importers within the Republic who shall, after the 30th day of April afore mentioned, present invoices of goods, merchandise &amp;c., not certified in accordance with the Act above said, shall for such a breach of the Act, be dealt with under the laws for the protection of the Revenue.</p>

<p>AND FURTHER all Collectors of Customs who shall have such invoices presented to them, shall at once give information of the same to the District Attorney verified by oath, who shall proceed against such as against any other violators of the Revenue Laws.</p>

<p>Given at Monrovia under my hand and the Seal of the Republic this 19th day of March, in the year of Our Lord One thousand Eight hundred <sic>ond</sic> Seventy nine, and of the Independence of the Republic the Thirty Second.</p>

<p>Anthy. W. Gardner,<lb/>
President.</p>

<p>L. S.<lb/>
G. W. Gibson,<lb/>
Secretary of State.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<div2 type="cover">

<pb n="Roll3-2103.jpg"/>

<head type="main">Acts Passed by the Legislature of the Republic of Liberia During the Session 1878-1879.</head>

<head type="sub">Printed by Authority</head>

<head type="sub">Monrovia: T. W. Howard, Printer.<lb/>
Government Printing Office<lb/>
1879.</head>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll3-2104.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Acts.</head>

<p>Resolution recommending an Amendment to the Constitution of Liberia.</p>

<p>Whereas under the present Constitution of the Republic of Liberia, the Executive power is prohibited from granting pardons in cases of impeachment, and offenders in high places can only be reached and punished by resort to actions of impeachment; and yet as a young and growing people, it is not conducive to the well being and best interest of this Republic to be fettered with the common law practice of other nations, in such cases, which make the judgment irreversible: Therefore,</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled,–</hi>and passed by the concurrence of two thirds of the members of each branch of the Legislature, That the following shall form the last paragraph of the first section of Article III to wit: Any person or persons who has or have been impeached, or who may be impeached hereafter for any official misconduct in office, or for high crimes and misdemeanors, within this Republic, shall be privileged after the expiration of seven years from the time of impeachment to petition the Legislature of the Republic of Liberia for restoration to all the rights and privileges of any other good citizens. And should it appear to the Legislature that the person or persons thus petitioning has or have shown sufficient evidence of reformation and repentance, then and in that case the Legislature may by Joint Resolution, to be adopted by a two third vote of the members of each branch of the Legislature, restore and grant unto the person or persons petitioning, all the rights privileges and immunities guaranteed to all other good citizens. Resolved further, that this amendment to the Constitution of the Republic <sic>or</sic> Liberia pass each branch by a two third vote as required by the second section of Article II of the Constitution; and that the said amendment be submitted to the people for their vote at the biennial election to be held in May 1879 in the several counties of this Republic;

<pb n="Roll3-2105.jpg"/>

and the ballots shall be written Adoption or no Adoption.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>A resolution tendering the Thanks of the Government and people of Liberia to Mr Edward S. Morris for his devotedness and zeal in behalf of Liberia.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec 1 That Mr. Edward S. Morris of Philadelphia is entitled to the thanks of the Government and people of Liberia which are hereby tendered to him, for his energy devotedness and zeal in behalf of Liberia at the American Centennial Exhibition in 1876, especially for his indefatigable efforts and printed publications to disseminate a knowledge of the excellent and Superior qualities of the Liberian Coffee: and the President is hereby requested to transmit a copy of this resolution to Mr. Edward <sic>S</sic> Morris as a tribute of our thanks to him for his labor in behalf of Liberia.</p>

<p>Approved Dec. 18th 1879.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>An Act establishing and fixing an export duty on Coffee Scions and dried Coffee.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec. 1. That from and immediately after the passage of this Act all persons, whether Liberian citizens or foreigners, who may desire to export Seed Coffee hulled, green, or dried, shall be required to pay a duty of one dollar and fifty cents (1.50) for each and every bushel; and if unhulled, on every bushel fifty cents [50] and on each and every scion exported, there shall be collected five cents [.05] on each plant; and on all trees whether bearing berries or not, a duty of fifty cents <sic>[50)</sic> each, and on all dried and cleaned coffee intended for table purposes, there shall be assessed and collected a duty of one quarter of a cent (¼) on each pound so exported.</p>

<p>Sec. 2. It is further enacted, that it shall be the duty of any person or persons who may desire to export hulled or unhulled Coffee seeds, green or dried, to report the same to a Collector of Customs, whose duty it shall be to instruct the Wharfingers to examine into the correctness of said report, and if found correct, said wharfinger shall certify the same, and upon which certificate the Collector of Customs

<pb n="Roll3-2106.jpg"/>

shall assess the export duty as is provided for in the first section of this Act, and for any violation of any of the provisions of this Act by any exporters the offender or offenders upon being convicted before any Court having competent jurisdiction, shall forfeit and pay into the Treasury of the Republic, or any of the Sub Treasuries, a sum of not less than One hundred dollars nor more than five hundred dollars, and on failure to pay said fine, with all costs of prosecution, to be imprisoned in the common jail in irons for a term of not less than three calendar years. Any law to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Approved Dec. 26, 1878.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>Resolution authorizing the Secretary of State to have reprinted five hundred copies of the compiled Statute Laws of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>Whereas it is evident from the repeated application of citizens throughout the Republic of the Statute Laws of Liberia, and the impossibility of their being supplied, and to prevent parties from being convicted by repealed acts–Therefore,</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec. 1. That from and immediately after the passage of this Resolution, the Secretary of the State, shall have struck off Five hundred copies of the printed Statute. Laws of the Republic of Liberia for the use of Government.</p>

<p>Sec. 2. That the Secretary of State shall deposit in the Treasury Department of Montserrado County–Two hundred copies; and the Sub-Treasurer's Department of Grand Bassa, Sinoe and Maryland one hundred copies each, to be disposed of according to the laws governing the same.</p>

<p>Sec. 3. That the amount of Eighteen hundred dollars [$1,800.00] be and the same is hereby appropriated for the performance of the same.</p>

<p>Sec. 4. And the President is hereby authorized to draw for the same on the Public Treasury for the monies not otherwise appropriated.</p>

<p>Any law to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Approved Decr. 28, 1878.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>An Act for the relief of several citizens of Philadelphia, Maryland County who have sustained the loss of their property and have been deprived of their town lots on account of the late Grebo War in the year 1875.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2107.jpg"/>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia, in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec. 1. That immediately after the passage of this Act, the President be, and he is hereby fully authorized to instruct the Superintendent of Maryland County to have surveyed and laid off in town lots, all that portion of land lying and being on the South side and opposite the Mount Vaughan, known as Jack's hill, for the benefit of the said citizens of Philadelphia to be exchanged for town lots in Philadelphia.</p>

<p>Sec. 2. And it is further enacted that such individuals as have sustained the loss of their property, and sacrificed their lots shall appear before a Justice of the Peace for the county aforesaid; and having made oath that he or they were citizens of the aforesaid settlement, and have sustained the loss of their lots on account of the unprotected state which they were in, shall receive certificates from the said Justice of Peace for the same.</p>

<p>Sec. 3. And it is further enacted that immediately after the survey of said lots, the parties shall be entitled to a deed, in fee simple on payment of the usual fees. Any law to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Approved, Decr. 26, 1878.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>An Act incorporating the first Presbyterian Church of Greenville in Sinoe County.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec. 1. That from and immediately after the passage of this Act, the first Presbyterian Church in Greenville, Sinoe County is hereby chartered, incorporated and declared to be a body, politic: that is to say, Louis Sherman, Stephen J. Crayton, Jacob J. Ross, Gibson H. Montgomery and Rufus Kennedy, Elders, Deacons and Trustees of the aforesaid Church and their successors in office is constituted a body corporate and politic, to have perpetual succession by the name and style of Trustees of the first Presbyterian Church of Greenville Sinoe County, to have full power to sue and be sued, plead and be impleaded, to take, hold possess and enjoy Real and Personal Estate by grant, purchase, demise or otherwise, with full power to sell and convey the same whenever the circumstances of said corporate Body shall make it conducive to its interest, in any amount to exceeding One hundred and fifty thousand dollars, and to have full right and privilege to do all the other acts and things 

<pb n="Roll3-2108.jpg"/>

usual to be done by similar bodies, corporate and politic</p>

<p>Any law to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>

<p>Approved Decr. 28, 1878.</p>

<p>––o––</p>

<p>An Act chartering the City of Harper in Maryland County.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">It is enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:–</hi></p>

<p>Sec. <sic>1</sic> That the inhabitants of the city of Harper, in the County of Maryland be and they are hereby considered a body politic and corporate, under the name and style of Mayor, Aldermen, Common Councilmen and Freemen of the city of Harper, county of Maryland and by such name, and may sue and be sued, implead and be impleaded, and o all other acts that are usually done by such Corporate bodies.</p>

<p>Sec. 2. The Common Councilmen shall consist of nine members, residents of the City of Harper, of whom one shall be chairman.</p>

<p><sic>3rd.</sic> The city of Harper shall have jurisdiction within the Corporate bounds of said city. The corporate bounds shall be one mile in width and two miles in length, running in a direct line from the west extremity of West Harper to Wilson's hill on East Harper.</p>

<p>Sec. 4th. The corporation aforesaid shall have full power and authority to make and fulfil contracts, and take and hold real and personal Estate to the value of Twenty thousand dollars [$20,000] and levy all such taxes as may be necessary for City purposes; shall pass all necessary Municipal laws and ordinances: said Body politic, shall have full power to settle its own rules of proceedings; to appoint its own officers, regulate its own fees, and <sic>and</sic> other necessary acts, not incompatible with the general laws of this Republic.</p>

<p>Sec. <sic>5th</sic> All ordinances and municipal laws established by the Common Council shall be subject to the approval or disapproval of the Mayor; if disapproved, his objections shall be made to the Common Council within three days, and if not returned within said three days such delay shall be equal to approval, provided however such delay be not occasioned by the adjournment of the Common Council. The Common Council may, nevertheless, by a two third vote of its members, pass any law independent of the Mayor's approval.</p>

<p>Sec. 6th. The first Election of city officers shall take <sic>blace</sic> on the first <sic>monday</sic> in March, Eighteen hundred and seventy nine (1879) and all other Elections shall take place on the second <sic>monday</sic> in April in each year (excepting the Mayor who shall be elected biennially and shall be conducted according 

<pb n="Roll3-2109.jpg"/>

to the laws governing Elections for the state officers under such modifications and restrictions as the Common Council may ordain. The elective officers shall be one Mayor, four aldermen and nine common councilmen, all of whom shall hold their offices for the term of one year; excepting the Mayor, who shall hold his office for the term of two years unless vacated by resignation, removal or death. Vacancies may be supplied by special elections to be ordered by the Common Councilmen. No person shall be eligible to the office of Mayor who is not a resident of the City of Harper, and who does not possess unencumbered real estate to the value of Five hundred dollars. No persons hall be a common councilman who is not a resident of said city and who does not possess unencumbered real estate to the value of Two hundred dollars.</p>

<p>Sec. 7th. There shall be a city court which shall be composed of three Aldermen one of whom shall be Chairman, whose duty it shall be to try and determine all cases coming into the same, except such as may be taken therefrom by appeals as is hereafter provided for. The aldermen shall, within the precincts of the city, exercise the functions of a Justice of the Peace whose duty it shall be to try and determine all petty offenses, and appeals may be had from their decisions to the city court and from which appeals may also <sic>he</sic> had to the county court.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>