<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0321">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Henri de Merode-Westerloo to Edouard de Grelle-Rogier, April 30, 1893</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, encoding, and translation</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0321</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from Henri de Merode-Westerloo to Edouard Degrelle-Rogier</title>
<date when="1893-04-30">April 30, 1893</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 323, Liasse 445</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Allard</term>
<term>Kasson</term>
<term>Lambermont</term>
<term>Leghait</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Chicago</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Washington</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>African</term>
<term>Belgian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>de Merode-Westerloo, Henri</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
<date when="1893-04-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>de Grelle-Rogier, Edouard</persName>
<roleName>Count</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-12" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2018" who="pr">Transcribed, translated, and encoded header information.</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.001.jpg"/>

<p>Ministère
des
Affaires Étrangères
Cabinet. I
1 Annexe
Bruxelles, le 30 Avril 1893</p>

<p>Monsieur le Comte,
A la suite de la communication que vous lui
avez adressée le 18 Août dernier, au sujet du Congrès
d'Ethnologie africaine qui se réunira à Chicago pendant
l'Exposition Universelle, mon honorable prédécesseur n'a pas
manqué de faire connaître à notre Ministre à Washington
que l'invitation d'assister au Congrès ayant été adressée au
Roi- Souverain sous forme de circulaire imprimée, le
Gouvernement de l'Etat Indépendant du Congo
estimait qu'il n'y avait pas lieu de donner suite à une
demande qui ne lui était point parvenue d'une façon
régulière.</p>

<p>Depuis <unclear/> Leghait est revenu sur cette
affaire dans des lettres particulières adressées au Baron
Lambermont dont les passages suivants sont extraits:</p>

<p>Monsieur le Comte de Grelle-Rogier,
<unclear/>
Bruxelles</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.002.jpg"/>

<p>M. Kasson m'a dit qu'il comptait
prendre la parole au Congré pour exposer la situation de
l’État du Congo. Je lui ai fourni à ce sujet toutes les
informations que je possédé (Bulletins officiels- Rapport
de M. Allard dans le Recueil consulaire &amp;c), mais
si vous aviez quelques renseignements particulières à lui
communiquer, cela pourrait être utile á la cause en
faveur de laquelle il parlera.- Ce congrés d'ethnologie
africaine s'ouvrira sans doute vers le milieu de l'été
ainsi qu'une vingtaine d'autres Congrés. Ils n'ont aucun
but patriotique ou déterminé et ne sont appelés qu'á
entourer l'exposition d'une auréole intellectuelle et morale."</p>

<p>"J'ai l'honneur de vous transmettre la
demande- (l'original de cette demande se trouve annexé
á la présente dépêche)- qui vient de m'être adressée de
prendre la parole le 14 Août prochain à Chicago afin
d'inaugurer le Congrés africain par un discours du
Représentant du Souverain qui a le plus contribué á
porter la civilisation en Afrique et pour présenter les
Belges qui viendront (on le suppose du moins) exposer
l'ouvre glorieuse du Roi.</p>

<p>"J'ai accusé réception de cette invitation
en remerciant et en disant qu'en ma qualité de Ministre
de Belgique exclusivement, je ne pouvais répondre á
leur gracieuse invitation qu'aprés avoir pris les ordres du
Gouvernement du Roi.</p> <fw type="catch">"Il</fw>


<p>"Il semblerait utile que dans une Conférence
sur l'Afrique quelqu'un de compétent fût changé de
parler spécialement de la création et du développement de
l’État Indépendant.</p>
    
<p>"Quoique ce Congrés ne soit comme je
vous l'ai dit, qu'une réunion académique sous but 
déterminé, il est toutefois á examiner s'il ne serait pas
de notre intérêt de chercher á en tirer un avantage
pratique en lui donnant du relief et en eu profitant
pour populariser l'ouvre du Congo dans un pays dont
l'appui peut nous être utile."</p>
    
<p>Notre Ministre á Washington a pour
instructions de se rendre á l'invitation officielle qu'il a reçue
l'assister aux cérémonies de l'ouverture de l'Exposition qui
aura lieu dans les premiers jours du mois de Mai. Le séjour
qu'il fera à Chicago à cette occasion sera de courte durée; il
rejoindra son poste dés que les cérémonies dont il s'agit seront
terminées. Ses instructions, d'après la communication que vous m'avez
faite le 18 Août <unclear extent="one word"/>, n'ont pu prévoir l'hypothèse d'un voyage á
Chicago au mois d'Août prochain.</p>
    
<p>Je vous prie, Monsieur le Compte, de vouloir 
bien me faire part des observations que les renseignements qui
précédent vous auraient suggérées et d'agréer les assurances
de ma haute considération.</p>
    
<p>Merode Westerloo</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.003.jpg"/>

<p>Chicago, U.S.A., April 15th, 1893<lb/>
151 Washington Street.</p>

<p>Dictated.</p>

<p>Hon. Alfred Le Ghait, E.E.&amp;M.P.<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Dear Sir:-</p>

<p>In our daily program, which we will soon send you, we
plan to give the forenoon of the first day, Monday August 14th, to
the reception of the members of the Congress on Africa and to
addresses of response. In behalf of the Committee I write to 
invite yourself to respond on the part of that distinguished land
which you represent so honorably to the government of the United
States. We think that it would be the fitting and gracious thing
for one in your position to speak the opening word for those of 
your country, who are to bring to this Congress their contributions
of wisdom in support of the example of their illustrious King, who
still keeps himself on the lead in this process of re-discovering
Africa. We hope that you will give our earnest request an affirmative
reply. May we not hear from you without delay?</p>

<p>Respectfully yours,<lb/>
Jos. E. Roy<lb/>
Chairman</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.004.jpg"/>

<p><unclear extent="entire document"/></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.004.jpg"/>

<p><unclear extent="entire document"/></p>

</div1>


<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.001.jpg"/>

<p>Ministry
of
Foreign Affairs
Cabinet. I
1 Annex
Brussels, April 30 1893</p>

<p>Mister Count,
Following the communication that you had addressed
to him last August 18th, on the subject of the Congress
of African Ethnology that will meet in Chicago during
the Universal Exposition, my honorable predecessor did not
fail to inform our minister in Washington
that the invitation to attend the Congress having been addressed to the
Sovereign King under form of printed memorandum, the
Government of the Congo Free State
estimates that there was not place to follow up on a
demand that was not sent to it at all in a regular
fashion.</p>

<p>Since <unclear/> Leghait returned on this
affair in the letters particularly adressed to the Baron
Lambermont from which the following passages are pulled:</p>

<p>Mister Count of Grelle-Rogier,
<unclear/>
Brussels</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0321.002.jpg"/>

<p>"Mr. Kasson told me that he was planning
to take the floor at Congress to expose the situation of
the State of the Congo. I supplied to him on this subject all the
information that I possess (Official bulletins- Report
of Mr Allard in the consular collection &amp;c), but
if you had some particular information to communicate
to him, that could be useful to the cause in
favor of that which he will speak.- The congress of African
ethnology will open without doubt toward the middle of the summer
just as twenty-some others Congress. They have no
patriotic goal or determined and are only called to
enforce the exposition of an intellectual and moral aureole."</p>

<p>"I have the honor to transmit to you the
demand- (the original of this demand is found annexed
to this dispatch)- which has just been sent to me to 
speak the 14th of next August in Chicago in order
to inaugurate the African Congress by a discourse of the
Representative of the Sovereign who contributed the most to
bring the civilization to Africa and to present the
Belgians who will come one can suppose at least to expose
the glorious work of the King.</p>

<p>"I accused reception of this invitation
in thanking and in saying that in my quality as Minister 
of Belgium exclusively, I could not respond to
their gracious invitation until having taken the orders of the
Government of the King. </p>


<p>"It would seem useful that in a conference
on Africa someone competent changed the
speaking especially of the creation and development of
the Independent State.</p>
    
<p>"Though this Congress is as I
told you, that an academic reunion under the determined 
goal, it is however to examine if it would be
of our advantage to search to take practical 
advantage in giving it relief and in profiting
to popularize the work of the Congo in a country where
the support could be useful to us."</p>
    
<p>Our Minister in Washington has for
instructions to face the official invitation that he has received
to assist him in the ceremonies of the opening of the Exposition that
had place in the first days of the month of May. The stay
that he will make in Chicago at this occasion will be of short duration; he
will rejoin his post as soon as the ceremonies of which it is question are
terminated His instructions, according to the communication that you had
with me the 18th of August, could not predict the hypothesis of a voyage to
Chicago in the month of next August.</p>
    
<p>I pray you, Mister Count, to
to share with me the observations that the information
preceding you would have suggested and to accept the assurances
of my highest consideration.</p>
    
<p>Merode Westerloo</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
