<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Rec in May 19 <unclear> Monday </unclear>

Counsulate of the United States of America at Sierra Leone 22nd March 1862

Bothurst
<unclear/>

<!-- label patch plastered on letter cuts off upper right section of letter -->

<unclear> With Compliments from Geo. Wetyerioh to John H. Harnell Esqr</unclear>

I have the honor to forward and to the Department of state by the <unclear/> Boston, Sparks, master the loca Ordinances of the colony of Sierra Leone up to the 31st December 1860. These properly should have been forwarded through the acting U.S. Counsul at Gambia under whom, I at present hold my appointment but as the only communication between this port and the Gambia is through the English mail packets, I thought I should be justified in forwarding direct to save expense. I desire most respectfully to lay

Hon. William H. Seward 
Secretary of State 
Washington D.C.

before you the following request and earnestly hope that it may <unclear/> with your favorable attention, is is that I may be appointed Counsel of the United States for this Colony and its dependencies, and receive a commission as such.

The following are my reasons for wishing this appointment, the French and Spanish consular officers now in this place arrived here as vice consuls, about the time I received my commission as Consular agent, which was in the month of September 1860, I was recognized by the Governor of the colony as vice consul of the United States, and consequently, however, both gentlemen ave received commissions from the respective government appointing them Counsuls with salaries, to the French consul; including goes about <british lb/> 900, and to the Spanish consul <british lb/> 1000.

The acting consul at Gambia is an Englishman, there being no American in that place, I am an American, native born, my birth-place being Salem, Massachusetts. I have been a resident of this colony for about three years and expect to remain here a number of years longer, such being the case it is very unpleasant to hold an inferior position in the service of my own Governemnt subject to an Englishmen holding a superior office, more especially as the English generally, at the present time, are not disposed to be very friendy towards our free Northern States.

Sierra Leone has a population of about 45,000 souls, and is frequently terned the Metropoles of thee West Coast of Africa, and commercially it is an important and rising place, the Americans do a large busines shere and there are frequently from Eight to Ten American veels in the harbor, Gambia is a smallplace of about how inhabitant, with very little American Commercial intercourse. 

Port Praya, Gambia and Liberia ar places of less importance have superior consular officers.

Should the appointment be given to me, I shall pay the stictest attention to all the duties required of me, having an earnest desire to increase the commercial importance of our country. 

I have the honor to be Ser
Your most obde- servant
Henry Rider 
U.S. Consular Agent