<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0309">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from the Vice-Governor General to the Secretary of State, August 9 1907</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, encoding, and translation</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0309</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Vice-Governor General to the Secretary of State</title>
<date when="1907-08-09">August 9, 1907</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 239, Liasse 205</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Consul General of the United States</term>
<term>Phillips, Ross</term>
<term>Secretary of State</term>
<term>Sims</term>
<term>Smith, Allwoord</term>
<term>Vice-Consul General</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Brussels, Belgium</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Matadi</term>
</keywords>

<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Vice-Governor General</roleName>
<placeName>Boma</placeName>
<date when="1907-08-09"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-12" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2018" who="pr">Translated.</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">Encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.001.jpg"/>

<p>État Indépendant
Du 
Congo<lb/>
Gouvernement Local<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 1567<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse la date et le numéro
4 Annexes<lb/>
OBJET:
Voyage Consul d'Amérique.</p>
    
<p>Boma, le 9 Août 1907.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Secrétaire d’État,</p>

<p>J'ai l'honneur de porter à votre connaissance
que le Consul Général des États-Unis
d'Amérique a quitté Boma, le 1er de ce mois, pour
un voyage dans le Haut-Congo; il est accompagné
du Vice-Consul Général Adjoint.</p>
    
<p>Je vous prie de bien vouloir trouver,
sous ce pli, en copie, les deux télégrammes que
j'ai adressés au Commissaire de district du
Stanley-Pool, ainsi que la lettre No 4768 aux
chefs territoriaux et commandants de camps.</p>
    
<p>J'aurai soin de vous donner connaissance
des renseignements qui me parviendraient
éventuellement au sujet du déplacement de ces
deux agents consulaires.</p>
    
<p>Le Vice-Gouverneur Général,<lb/>
<unclear extent="signature"/></p>
    
<p>P.S.-Je vous prie de bien vouloir trouver,
sous ce pli, en copie, le rapport, que je
viens de recevoir de Commissaire de
de district de Matadi, au sujet de la
visite de M. Smith dans cette localité.</p>

<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Secrétaire d'Etat
Bruxelles.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.002.jpg"/>

<p>Copie No 4708 F.</p>
    
<p>Boma le 29 Juillet 1907.</p>
    
<p>Messieurs,</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous faire savoir que Monsieur le Consul Général des États-
Unis d'Amérique, Smith, accompagné du Vice Consul Général adjoint Memminger,
quittera Boma prochainement pour se rendre dans le Haut-Congo.</p>
    
<p>Je vous prie de recommander aux agents qui auront à trouver en relations
avec eux de les recevoir avec les plus grands égards et de leur prêter toute
l'assistance, compatible avec les lois et règlements de l’État, pour exécuter
leur voyage dans de bonnes conditions.</p>
    
<p>Fuchs.</p>
    
<fw type="footer">A tous les chefs territoriaux et Commandants de camps.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.003.jpg"/>

<p>Copie.</p>
    
<p>Télégramme.</p>

<p>Commissaire district Leopoldville</p>
    
<p>No 522F.-Pour information Consul Amérique demande à visiter magasins, prisons
etc. I'y autorise.</p>
    
<p>Fuchs.</p>
    
<p>Copie.</p>
    
<p>Telegramme.</p>
    
<p>Commissaire district<lb/>
Léopoldville.</p>

<p>No 517 Consul Général États-Unis Amérique et Consul Général Adjoint quittent
Boma ce jour, arriveront incessamment Kinshasa Leur accorder toutes facilités
possible Me faire savoir date de leur départ de Léopoldville Ignore itinéraire
de leur voyage.</p>
    
<p>Le 1er Août 1907<lb/>
Fuchs.</p>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.004.jpg"/>

<p>copie 1265</p>

<p>Matadi le 7 Août 1907.-</p>

<p>Monsieur le Gouverneur Général,</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de porter à votre connaissance qu'à l'arrivée à Matadi de
Monsieur le Consul Général des États-Unis, Monsieur Allwoord Smith, je suis
allé le saluer à bord du vapeur "Léopoldville" J'en ai profité pour lui faire
connaître que j'eus été heureux de lui rendre les services qui pouvaient faciliter
son passage à Matadi. Il ma vivement remercié mais n'a pas eu recours
aux facilités que je lui offrais.-</p>

<p>Quoiqu'il n'avait promise une visite pour 6 heures du soir il s'est 
présenté avec le docteur Sims à 2 1/2 heures et a profité de cette visite pour
me demander des renseignements sur le mode d'impôt employé dans le district
sur le résultat des recensements de la population sur le taux de l'imposition
et son rendement espéré Je n'ai pas cru devoir lui refuser ces renseignements
donnés d'une façon générale et sous réserve de votre approbation puisqu'en
somme ils appartiendraient au domaine de la publicité dès la mise en recouvrement
des rôles.- J'ai eu l’occasion de faire ressortir que l'impôt en numéraire
rencontrait la faveur de nos populations et M le consul général avec
le docteur Sims ont constaté eux mêmes la modicité du taux comparé à celui
d'autres colonies africaines.-</p>
    
<p>Le docteur Sims m'a demandé si le Gouvernement n'exigeait pas d'impôt en
nature notamment la fourniture d'arachides. J'ai fait remarquer que cet impôt
avait été abandonné depuis deux ans De même le consul de façon incidente voulait 
savoir si la perception de l'impôt avait reçu un comencement d'exécution
Je lui ai répondu que c'était la chose impossible la perception étant subordonnée
à l'approbation Gouvernementale des rôles.-</p>
    
<p>Le Consul g'a demandé aussi s'il m'était possible de lui
montrer nos magasins des produits à nui j'ai áccédé volontiers. Son attention
portait surtout sur le mode d'emballage la forme et la qualité des différentes
gommes. Il ne m'a pas demandé des renseigments sur les quantités transitées.</p>
    
<p>Le docteur Sims qui en l'occurence m'a paru être quelque peu la guide
du consul m'a fait connaître le désir de celui ci de visiter la maison
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.005.jpg"/>
    
de détention Je n'ai pas cru devoir m'y refuser estimant qu'un refus eut pu
être mal interprêté. Rendez-vous a été pris alors pour 5 heures les consuls
ayant à 4 heures une conférence avec le R Ross Phillips de la B.M.S.-</p>
    
<p>La visite de la prison a été assez sommaire, elle s'est borné à un
local sur la constatation du consul que les lits de camp étaient simplement
en bois je lui ai fait remarquer que les prisonniers disposaient de couvertures
places d'ailleurs à la tête du lit. Le consul a trouvé que le nombre de prisonniers
n’était pas très grand en considération surtout de l'etendue du district.-
Il m'a demandé quelle était leur ration la durée moyenne de détention
enfin des renseigments sur le réglement de la prison. J'ai eu l'accasion de
lui signaler aussi le projet d'agrandissement de la maison de détention</p>
    
<p>Il s'est encore enquis du salaire et du rationnement des nos
travailleurs, de la facilité à trouver la main d'oeuvre etc Pour conclure je
crois que le consul Général Allwood Smith a quitté Matadi en emportant
une impression favorable</p>
    
<p>l'agent d'administration de 1re classe
ff de Commissaire de district<lb/>
(s) Koolen.-</p>

</div1>


<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.001.jpg"/>

<p>Independent State
of the
Congo<lb/>
Local Government<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 1564<lb/>
Recall in the response the date and the number
4 Annexes<lb/>
Subject:
Voyage Consul of America.</p>
    
<p>Boma, August 9th 1907.</p>

<p>Mister Secretary of State,</p>

<p>I have the honor to bring to your knowledge
that the General Consul of the United States
of America left Boma, the 1st of this month, for
a voyage in the Upper-Congo; he is accompanied
by the General Vice-Consul Deputy.</p>
    
<p>I pray that you find,
under this letter, in copy, the two telegrams that
I addressed to the Commissioner of the district
Stanley-Pool, as well as the letter No 4768 to the
territorial chiefs and commandants of the camps.</p>
    
<p>I will take care to give you knowledge
of information that will be potentially
sent to me on the subject of the displacement of these
two consular agents.</p>
    
<p>General Vice Governor,<lb/>
<unclear extent="signature"/></p>
    
<p>P.S.-I pray that you find,
under this letter, in copy, the report, that I
have just received from the Commissioner of
the district of Matadi, on the subject of the
visit from Mr. Smith in this locality.</p>

<fw type="footer">Mr. Secretary of State
Brussels.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.002.jpg"/>

<p>Copy No 4708 F.</p>
    
<p>Boma July 29th 1907.</p>
    
<p>Misters,</p>
    
<p>I have the honor to inform you that Mister General Consul of the United
States of America, Smith, accompanied by Assistant General Vice Consul Memminger,
will leave Boma shortly to go to the Upper-Congo.</p>
    
<p>I pray you to recommend to the agents that will have to find in relation
with them to receive them with the largest regards and to loan them all
assistance, compatible with the laws and regulations of the State, to execute
their voyage in good conditions.</p>
    
<p>Fuchs.</p>
    
<fw type="footer">To all the territorial chiefs and commandants of the camps.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.003.jpg"/>

<p>Copy.</p>
    
<p>Telegram.</p>

<p>District Commissioner Leopoldville</p>
    
<p>No 522F.-For information American Consul demands to visit markets, prisons
etc. I authorize it.</p>
    
<p>Fuchs.</p>
    
<p>Copy.</p>
    
<p>Telegram.</p>
    
<p>District Commissioner<lb/>
Léopoldville.</p>

<p>No 517 General Consul United States of America and General Consul Deputy leave
Boma this day, and will arrive shortly in Kinshasa accord to them all possible
facilities Inform me on the date of their departure from Léopoldville Ignore itinerary
of their voyage.</p>
    
<p>The 1st of August 1907.<lb/>
Fuchs.</p>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.004.jpg"/>

<p>copy 1265</p>

<p>Matadi August 7th 1907.
Mister General Governor,</p>
    
<p>I have the honor to bring to your knowledge that at the arrival to Matadi of
Mister General Consul of the United States, Mister Allwoord Smith, I
went to greet him aboard the steamboat "Léopoldville" I profited to make known
to him that I was happy to render him services that could facilitate
his passage in Matadi. He swiftly thanked me but did not resort
to the facilities that I offered to him.-</p>

<p>Though he had not promised a visit for 6 in the evening he presented 
himself with doctor Sims at 2 1/2 hours and profited from this visit to
ask me for the information on the method of tax employed in the district
on the result of the census of the population on the rate of the imposition
and its expected yield I did not believe to have to refuse him this information
given in a general fashion and under reserve of your approval since in
sum they would belong to the domain of the publicity from the appearance in covering
the roles.- I had the occasion to emphasize that the tax in money
met the favor of our populations and Mr Consul General with
Doctor Sims noted themselves the modestness of the rate compared to that
of other African colonies.-</p>
    
<p>Doctor Sims asked me if the Government did not require tax
had been abandoned for two years Likewise the consul in incidental fashion wanted
to know if the perception of the tax had received an onset of execution
I responded to him that the impossible thing was the perception being subordinated
to the Governmental approval of the roles.-</p>
    
<p>The Consul asked me as well if it was possible for me to show
him our produce stores to <unclear>moi</unclear> I decided willingly. His attention
brought particularly on the mode of packaging the form and the quality of the different
resins. He did not ask me for information on the quantities transited.</p>
    
<p>Doctor Sims who in the occurrence seemed to be somewhat the guide
of the consul let me know the desire of his to visit the house
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0309.005.jpg"/>
    
of detention I did not believe to have to refuse myself estimating that a refusal could have
been wrongly interpreted. Meeting was taken thus for 5 hours the consuls
having 4 hours a conference with R Ross Phillips of the B.M.S.-</p>

<p>The visit of the prison was rather basic, it was limited to a
local on the observation of the consul that cots were simply
wooden I remarked to him that the prisoners disposed of covers
placed elsewhere at the head of the bed. The consul found that the number of prisoners
was not very big in special consideration of the extent of the district.-
He asked me what their ration was during the average time of detention
Finally the information on the regulation of the prison. I had the occasion to
signal to him as well the project of enlargement of the house of detention</p>
    
<p>He questioned again the salary and of the rationing of our
workers, of the facility to find the work force etc To conclude I
believe that the General Consul Allwood Smith left Matadi in bringing
a favorable impression</p>
    
<p>Administration agent of 1st class<lb/>
ff of Commissioner of district<lb/>
(s) Koolen.-</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
