<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1344">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to John Hay, May 7, 1880</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1344</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to John Hay</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1880-05-07">May 7, 1880</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</term>
<term>Howard</term>
<term>Squire, George L.</term>
<term>de Vignaux</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Arthington (Liberia)</term>
<term>Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Bathurst (Gambia)</term>
<term>Brewersville (Liberia)</term>
<term>Buffalo (New York)</term>
<term>Cape Mount (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Le Havre (France)</term>
<term>Paris (France)</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
<term>West Indies</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>France</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Kroo</term>
<term>Mandingo</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Episcopal</term>
<term>Islam</term>
<term>Methodist</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1880-05-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76456718">Hay, John, 1838-1905</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1880-06-07"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-01" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2281.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Jun 7 1880</note>

<p>No. 52.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the U.S.,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia,<lb/>
May 7, 1880.</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to the Ass't Sec'y of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Report for the Liberian fiscal year–ended Sept. 30, 1879.</p>

<p>Synopsis:</p>

<p>Agriculture, manufactures, mines, fisheries, forests, commerce, imports, exports, emigration, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2282.jpg"/>

<p>No. 52.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia,<lb/>
May 7, 1880.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to respectfully lay before you the following facts as to the several subjects, agriculture, manufactures, mines, fisheries, forest, commerce, imports &amp; exports, and emigration for the Liberian fiscal year which ended September 30th, 1879.</p>

<p>One of the chief agricultural productions, as will be observed in the accompanying statements of <catchwords>Return</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. John Hay,<lb/>
Ass't Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2283.jpg"/>

Return of Trade with the United States is, coffee. The current market price of the product is from 18 to 22 cents per lb. The yield for the last fiscal year which is being gathered up to now, and will continue to be taken from the trees until the rains begin next month is something remarkable, exceeding in quantity and quality all other preceding years. And although many thousand pounds more of coffee will be put upon the market than at any other time, yet the whole amount produced is inconsiderate when the capacity of area and the fecund quality of the soil are considered. <catchwords>The</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2284.jpg"/>

The great difficulty in approximating the capacity of the soil, the capacity of the Liberian people is due to the now appreciation by them of the fact that their lot has been cast in an agricultural region of Africa; and in planting and cultivating coffee they are impatient, unwilling to live in the future. Coffee from scions cannot be made to pay in a shorter time than three years, nor a profitable industry in less than 4 or 5 years. Too few Liberians are willing to plant and bide their time for increase.</p>

<p>I refrain from enlarging upon the subject of Coffee, as my predecessor has written up the plant <catchwords>and</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2285.jpg"/>

and its culture pretty fully; but will mention a fact that has recently come to the notice of coffee growers, and which may be regarded as <sic>phenominal</sic>. Says a planter of large experience: 'I have noticed in the last year that the coffee tree has shown what is to us planters a new <sic>developement</sic>. In former years, say ten years ago, we picked no coffee in the rainy months, June, July, August, September &amp; October, but since that time coffee seemed to ripen a little during those months, and last year the trees were in bloom during those months, though <sic>sparcely</sic>. I picked berries off the trees each of those months, and commenced to pick <catchwords>in</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2286.jpg"/>

in November regularly, and have continued to do so every month up to the present, April, hence the coffee crop this season which should end in March–will not end before May 1880. The trees bloomed in December, January and in February and in March and scatteringly up to April. So we have a good deal to learn yet about this coffee tree. This is the heaviest crop we have had.'</p>

<p>My reason for remarking that some of the present crop will be superior to any Liberian coffee before exported is due to the absence heretofore of machinery, proper hulling machinery, without which <catchwords>the</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2287.jpg"/>

the best dried coffee looses much of its otherwise rich flavor from being broken in process of preparation for the market.</p>

<p>Through an advertisement in the American Mail &amp; Exp't Journal, Mr. M. A. Aenmey the U.S. Vice Consul Gen'l was induced to purchase of George L. Squire &amp; Bro. of Buffalo, N.Y., a huller and separator which have enabled him to put the best hulled coffee on the market. So much pleased are the farmers with the work done by the Squire huller, and its cheapness and excellent structure–as compared with the English hullers that several orders for two horse power <catchwords>machines</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2288.jpg"/>

machines have already been sent to this American firm.</p>

<p>Complaints are often made as to labor, but these are generally unfounded. Labor is easily secured in all the civilized portions of Liberia, and there are few uncivilized parts; but perhaps in no place is compensation for work smaller and certainly more uncertain. While the price of native labor is ostensibly from 3 to 5 dollars per month, these amounts are seldom paid in money, but as a rule–in goods or food, and large profits are realized by the employers by this system, the benefits of which are doubtful, as they (the farmers) are seldom able to <catchwords>get</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2289.jpg"/>

get hands from the particular tribe or tribes from which their just paid employees come, as these laborers "spoil the names" of their employers as good masters. Further trouble is the absence of good understanding, of confidence between the merchant class and the agricultural class, and hence the system of advances are unknown.</p>

<p>Sugar cane grows here in greatest <sic>luxurience</sic>, and the sugar produced is of very superior quality. Little is exported. If sufficient capital were expended on the necessary machinery for refining the product there would be no sugar imported into Liberia, but <catchwords>much</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2290.jpg"/>

would be exported, and would shortly be a source of wealth to the people. An English gentleman, with very large West India experience in the culture of sugar, informed me that the Liberian cane and sugar were very superior to that of the West India Islands.</p>

<p>Nothing has been done nor is anything being done in the way of developing the mineral resources of the country. And–unless the precious metals, gold and silver, are by accident discovered near, very near the surface, little may be expected to be done in mining without aid from without. In this connection–I call your attention to <catchwords><sic>to</sic></catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2291.jpg"/>

to the statute of 1869 upon this subject, which is in full force now. This statute is epitomized in my No. 52, diplomatic series, which I had occasion to mention in connection with the convention sought to be made by Messrs Howard and de Vignaux, Liberian Consuls at Paris &amp; Havre &amp; the President of Liberia.</p>

<p>East from the port of Bassa, I am advised–that the mountains and hill are rich in varied colored marble.</p>

<p>There is no system as to the matter of fisheries–although the sea, and principal rivers of the Republic produce sufficient <catchwords>fish</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2292.jpg"/>

fish for home consumption and exportation. Fishing is controlled, on the coast, exclusively by the Kroomen.</p>

<p>The forests, or "bush" as wooded places are designated by Americo Liberians and natives, bound in various and valuable trees, for building purposes, for furniture and decoration. There are the following named woods, gums, black &amp; white, the former resembling the American walnut somewhat in color, but of a richer and deeper color, heavier than lignum vitae, and impervious to the ravages of the termites or "bug a bugs", the destroying ant <catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2293.jpg"/>

of this portion of West Africa, mahogany, rose wood which is a very solid wood and of remarkable weight, cherry–a beautiful red wood, cedar of a delicate pink and white color, which is used with beautiful effect for ornamentation for paneling, brimstone and whistmore which are use <sic>comonly</sic> in frame structures, a pine wood similar to the pine of Maine, ebony &amp; oak woods. These woods average from 2 or 4$ per square foot.</p>

<p>The word which is well known to commerce is the cam which is valuable for dyeing purposes. The price has fallen within <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2294.jpg"/>

the past year from $150.00 per ton to $90.00. Should the market rise within the present year there is little doubt but that this wood will command a higher price than ever.</p>

<p>Most of the trees have been destroyed within five miles of the settlements of Americo Liberians, and the roots are now being dug up to satisfy the commercial demand, and virgin forests must be sought interiorward. Without facilities of transportation other than the backs and heads of men, this particular industry will be lost to the commerce of Liberia.</p>

<p>The oil palm tree–better known to commerce than any other of the inhabitants of the forest, <catchwords>has</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2295.jpg"/>

has been the source of annoyance to the trading class of Liberia. The price of oil has fallen from forty cents to 33⅓ cts. per gallon. This has been on account of the general depression in Europe. To induce the native population upon whom the traders depend for this commodity, to bring their oil to the factories, and to sell it at a reduced price, is a most difficult matter. They know nothing, comparatively, of the European markets, and care nothing about the price the trader gets for his oil when casked and shipped.</p>

<p>At Grand Bassa troubles <sic>occured</sic> between the factory men <catchwords>and</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2296.jpg"/>

and the natives, last year, and on the refusal of the latter to sell oil at the traders prices, in not a few instances, the oil was taken from the natives vi et armis, and they driven off and in some cases–beaten. A connection of traders was called at Bassa to settle the price of oil, but the men who procured the oil were neither notified nor invited to the conference.</p>

<p>The oil is paid for ordinarily in goods, and when 40¢ per gallon was paid, the goods amounted to 20¢ only in honest valuation, and now that 33⅓ cents per gal. are paid in goods, the fair valuation is about 16¢. The native <sic>peo</sic> <catchwords>people</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2297.jpg"/>

people have not a very exalted opinion of the merchant class' honest dealing.</p>

<p>The kernels of the palm constitute quite as important an article of trade as the oil.</p>

<p>Sufficient soap might be made from the oil of the palm to form a permanent and fairly profitable industry. The mandingoes sell a soap of their own manufacturing, excellent for ordinary purposes, and a very good article for the bath.</p>

<p>There are two species of the kola, the red &amp; the white, well and generally known in Africa. These trees grow in Liberia, at <catchwords>Cape</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2298.jpg"/>

Cape Mount, in the neighborhood of the St. Paul's river, and in the eastern part of Liberia and eastward of the Republic. The nut or fruit of this tree is coveted in West Africa and throughout the Soudan by the natives, and forms an important product of internal commerce. The kola is said to be a preventive against hunger. The average price per bushel is 6 shillings ($1.50). At Bathurst, Gambia, the nut is frequently retailed at two cents each. It is regarded as a mark of friendship to be presented a kola. A very little is done here in this trade.</p>

<p>There were two <sic>emigra</sic> <catchwords>emigrations</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2299.jpg"/>

emigrations during the fiscal year just completed;–the majority of the emigrants were Negroes. The number of mulattoes was notably small, and some of those have since returned to the United States, some have died, and the few remaining have very poor health. There is an exception here and there. These people in addition to the African fever to which all must defer, both the emigrant and the native, borne with varying severity, are sadly annoyed with sores upon their bodies and limbs, while the blacks, unless diseased when they come here, with ordinary care, acclimate <catchwords>easily</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2300.jpg"/>

easily; readily enter upon the lands given them by the Government and become industrious citizens.</p>

<p>The settlements of Brewersville and Arthington, mark a new era of emigrant life in Liberia. The emigrants in these places, particularly Brewersville, do not follow the practice of the old and older emigrants in other parts of the Republic, who imitated and continue to imitate the Southern white people of the United States among whom they lived, by having many servants, by having native people do the work for them that they <catchwords>themselves</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2301.jpg"/>

themselves should do for themselves. On the other hand they have played the part of masters to their personal injury as citizens, and to the detriment of the State by reason of their poverty. The recent emigrants to these places are poor but industrious, and have cleared the primeval forests, built houses, planted their lands, and are happily sustaining life by the fruits of their labors. Under wisely made and executed laws these people must become valued citizens.</p>

<p>It is a matter of regret as to both these settlements, which are back from the Atlantic <catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2302.jpg"/>

to the east and on and near the highways that lead to the interior, to the Soudan; and which as a consequence are traversed by Muhammadan and pagan Negroes; regret that the Christianity of these Negro emigrants does not inspire respect for them in the pagan nor the followers of Islam, on account of its want of cohesiveness, and the absence of the element of unity and brotherly love. In illustration, at Brewersville there is an adult population of 300, and there are five church organizations, two Methodists, totally distinct organizations, and three other religious <catchwords>denominations</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2303.jpg"/>

denominations. The Christian system of training of these people make them sectarian; yet their general intelligence and their instincts are such that, they would willingly waive their differences, if they could escape the influence of those whose religious ambition to be 'spiritual leaders', causes them to serve their personal interests as 'religious leaders' at the expense of the Christian advancement of community. Add to this, the fact that the benefactions in money and missionaries sent here for the 'spread of Christianity among the heathen', and the problem of Liberia's

<pb n="Roll3-2304.jpg"/>

Liberia's evangelization of the Natives–may be better understood than heretofore, and surprise may not be felt in remembering the very slow progress made here by Christianity.</p>

<p>It is pleasing to note the facts that the educated clergymen of Monrovia, headed by the eloquent native gentleman, Rev. Pitman and the Americo Liberian Rev. Gibson, the former a methodist and the latter an episcopalian, are making an earnest effort to remove the barriers that separate Christian sects here, and to form a Liberian or Negro church to unite <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2305.jpg"/>

the people in one church who are Christians, and those who are disposed to become Christians. Should the labors of these patriotic Liberians and loyal Negroes succeed, an important step will have been taken, a vantage ground gained which the pagan will not dispute, and which will have a more salutary influence in developing the "vital principle" of Muhammadanism than all the missionary labors that have been carried on, and that have failed in Liberia.</p>

<p>The prospect of the transfer from Europe and America to the almost virgin soil of <catchwords>Africa</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2306.jpg"/>

Africa of sectarianism and schisms which distinguish Christianity in those countries, is, to say the least, anything but hopeful for the well being of the Negro races of Africa. 'Set bounds to our passions by reason, to our errors by truth, and to our schisms by charity'; and then the Christian work begun in the 14th century in West Africa, which failed, and attempted so often since by influences foreign to Africa, with like result, will begin to be successful and tend to successful accomplishment of African Christianity and <sic>Afri</sic> <catchwords>African</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2307.jpg"/>

African civilization throughout the continent.</p>

<p>The day big with promise for Africa will have arrived, when the civilizations of Christianity shall have learned that God was here in the Negro before Europe emerged from its heathenism, is here now, and that the inscriptions upon the Assyrian tablets are prophetic, that, "the word of the Lord shall live in the mouth of the dark races, which He hath made'; and shall have realized that Africa's greatest need is that her races be taught the art of language (<sic>gramatical</sic> construction) arithmetic and the higher mathematics, <catchwords>geography</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2308.jpg"/>

geography (of Africa first), history and the mental sciences; and that her people have the bible translated into their tongues, and read in the schools and the colleges and the churches by foreign Christians without note and without comment.</p>

<p>I regret to be under the unpleasant necessity of stating that no reliable statistics are made and kept of the number of domestic and foreign vessels which enter and clear from the ports of Liberia, nor accurate data of the amount and value of imports and exports. I have in the statement of 'Return of Trade with the United States' appended to this re- <catchwords>report</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2309.jpg"/>

report, marked enclosure #1, furnished reliable data in the general of the value of American imports and Liberian exports by American bottoms, and the number of American vessels entered and cleared, although I am quite confident that large quantities of American manufactured articles &amp; products are imported to Liberia through European sources. My inability to present fully the facts, makes it difficult, impossible, to determine with accuracy what America sends to Liberia, or Liberia sends to the United States.</p>

<p>It is within the limits of probability, to say, that Amer- <catchwords>America</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2310.jpg"/>

America furnishes between ⅓ and ½ of the articles that constitute the stock in Liberian trade without receiving credit for it.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Jno. H. Smyth,<lb/>
U.S. Consul Gen'l</p>

<p>Inclosure</p>

<p>1 Return of Trade with the United States</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>