<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0243">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter to the Minister, July 1899</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0243</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter to the Minister</title>
<date when="1899-07">July 1899</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasses 115-122</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Brussels</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>South Carolina</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Brussels (Belgium)</placeName>
<date when="1899-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Minister of the United States</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information</change>
<change when="2019-01" who="#caa">translated</change>
<change when="2019-01-11" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0243.001.jpg"/>

<p>Bruxelles, le Juillet 1899.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre</p>

<p>J'ai eu l'honneur de recevoir la lettre en date du 19 <unclear>du</unclear>
mois <unclear>du</unclear> par laquelle Votre Excellence a bien voulu me demander des
renseignements sur les conditions climatériques des différentes
régions de l'Etat du Congo et sur la possibilité pour un groupe
de jeunes de l'Etat de la Caroline du Sud de se créer une
position en Afrique.</p>

<p>Je ne crois mieux pouvoir répondre à la première question
de Votre Excellence qu'en mettant à sa disposition un exemplaire
du "rapport sur le climat, la constitution du sol et l’hygiène
de l'Etat Indépendant du Congo" qui a été présenté au Congres
national d’hygiène et de climatologie tenu à Bruxelles en 1897.</p>

<p>En ce qui concerne le possibilité d'établissement sur le
territoire de l'Etat, les recensements annuels constatent une
augmentation constante et progressive des résidents étrangers,
s'adonnant pour la plupart au commerce, quelques'uns aux métiers
manuels.</p>

<p>Il y a lieu de remarquer que la presque totalité des commerçants
ou trafiquants sont agents de sociétés ou de compagnies
commerciales.</p>

<p>Les professions dites libérales ne sont guère représentes
au Congo.</p>

<p>Quant à ce qui concerne l'admission aux services, soit civils,
soit militaires, de l'Etat, services pour lesquels la connaissance
de la lange française est de rigueur, elle s'obtient sur requête
adressée à Monsieur le Secrétaire d'Etat.</p>

<p>Je ne puis à cet égard m'abstenir de signaler à Votre Excellence
l'existence d'un grand nombre de candidatures déjà introduites,
et ayant par conséquent le bénéfice de la priorité.</p>

<p>Je saisis ...................</p>

<fw type="footer">Légation des Etats Unis d'Amérique.</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0243.001.jpg"/>

<p>Brussels, July 1899.</p>

<p>Mr. Minister,</p>

<p>I had the honor of receiving the letter on the date of the 19th of this month
by which your Excellency wanted me to ask for
information on the different climatic conditions in the regions
of the Congo state and on the possibility for a youth group from 
South Carolina to create a position in Africa.</p>

<p>I cannot believe responding to the first question 
of your Excellency in putting to his disposition an exemplary 
climate report, the constitution of the soil and hygiene 
of the Independent State of Congo "who was presented to 
the national Congress of hygiene and climatology held in Brussels in 1897.</p>

<p>This concerns the possibility of establishing on the
State's territory, the annual recorded census
on the constant improvement and progressiveness of foreign residents
indulging for the most part in commerce, in a practical person's trade.</p>

<p>It was remarked that the near totality of traders
or traffickers are agents of societies or commercial
companies.</p>

<p>The professionals say liberals are hardly not represented
in Congo.</p>

<p>As for those concerning the admission of services, either
civil or military, of the State, services of which the knowledge 
of the French language is rigorous, they obtain on the requested
addressed to Mr. Secretary of State.</p>

<p>I may not to this regard abstain myself from signaling to your Excellency
the existence of a big number of candidates already introduced,
and having by consequence the benefit of the priority.</p>

<p>I knew.....................</p>

<fw type="footer">Legation of the United States of America</fw>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
