<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="DAWSON, KENDALL C." xml:id="KCD"><!-- KENDALL C. DAWSON --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<pb facs="1018_001.jpg"/>

<p>REPORT ON VISIT TO BOSTON AND NEW YORK.
JANUARY 11-18, 1907.
******</p>
    
<p>The Catholic movement seems to have produced the most
excellent results upon the President and the Secretary of State as well
as upon the Senate, and I am specifically glad to be able to report the
success of my mission to Boston which is not only the centre of the anti-
Congo agitation but is also the home of the electors of Senator Lodge
who has brought in the Resolution against us.</p>
    
<p>Boston is the centre of the Baptist missionary societies and
of many fantastic "reforms" movements but there is also a strong and 
growing Catholic element there whose influence in politics is sought 
even by Senator Lodge and other "puritans". During my visit to Boston
I have been fortunate enough to interest the strong Catholic element
in our cause and to around them to active work in our behalf.</p>
    
<p>His Grace, Monsignor O'Connell, Archbishop of Boston, received
me most sympathetically and has promised me his support. The
Catholic "Federation" of that district has already sent to the President
and to the Senate a petition in our behalf.</p>
    
<p>Last Monday night in Boston I met the High Council of the
Massachusetts Catholic Order of Foresters, which represents one hundred
thousand of Senator Lodge's electors and as a result, chiefly through
the sympathetic aid of the Rev/Father O'Neil, Spiritual Advisor of the
Order, they took up the cause of the Congo and adopted resolutions in 
our favor which were at once transmitted to the President of the United
States, the Secretary of State, to the Senate, to Mr. Lodge, and other</p>
    
<pb></pb>
    
<p>Senators. The Order of Foresters also desire that a copy of their 
resolution should be presented to His Majesty, and I have the honor
to transmit a copy herewith, with the suggestion that some acknowledgment
and response be sent the Order through us, as soon as possible.</p>
    
<p>The Boston "Alumni Sodality" also took a great interest in the
matter. The question was presented to them throught the Rev. Father
Dennis T. O'Sullivan who has spoken publicly in favor of the Congo 
on several occasions. I understand that the "Alumni Sodality" is
sending to the Government petitions in our favor as a society and 
that the individual members are also working for us.</p>
    
<p> The Catholic Union which has among its members some of the
most important Catholic citizens of Boston has also taken up our
cause. They will have a lecture and discussion on the Congo as soon
as possible and will then probably adopt resolutions similar to the
resolutions adopted by other Catholic societies. The President of 
the Catholic Union has taken a person interest and may be expected
to aid us in every way possible. </p>
    
<p>The "Federation" of Boston is to hold a meeting tonight
(January 20) to discuss the French Church question and also the
Congo and still further action may be expected from them to promote
our interests.</p>
    
<p>I also had several meetings with Mr. Matthew Cummings, the
President of the Irish Society known as the "Ancient Order of Hibernians".
He is an important politician in Boston and the Hibernians
constitute a well-known and influential society of about two hundred
thousand men. He manifests a deep interest in our case and promised
me to bring the matter up before the High Counil of the Order last
night, when they probably will have adopted resolutions in our favor
to be sent to the President, Secretary of State and the Senate.</p>
    
<p>It seems thus that we have aroused a strong element in our
favor in Boston and have, by my visit there, secured the active help
of between three hundred thousand and four hundred thousand of Mr. 
Lodge's own electors. This is sure to have a good effect on Lodge 
as well as us on the other Senators. We have secured a strong support
even in the midst of the enemy's camp.</p>
    
<p>In addition to this aid from the State of Massachusetts I 
have been able, through the help of the Rev. Father Shanley, to secure 
important assistance from the neighboring State of Connecticut.</p>
    
<p>Petitions to the President and to the Senate were sent, at my
request, form several Catholic Association of that State, among others
from the "St. Peters Corporate Society" numbering nearly five thousand
members, and the matter is brought to the attention of other societies
which may be expected to act soon.</p> 
    
<p>In addition to these societies I was enabled while on this
trip to get into communication with the "Catholic Young Men's National
Union" numbering fifty thousand, which without loss of time, sent
an expression of its sentiments in our favor to Washington by telegram.</p>
    
<pb></pb>

<p>-3-</p>

<p>Father Shanley also requested the "Catholic Temperance
Association Union of America" which has ninety thousand members
to take similar action. I have not yet received offical notice but
it is probably that they have taken the requested action by this
time.</p>
    
<p>In New York i found that the agitation which we had started
<choice> <sic> amont</sic> <corr>among</corr></choice> the Catholic societies is still continuing satistisfactorily and
I am endeavoring to encourage the movement there as much as possible.</p>
    
<p>The Catholic movement has not only intimidated our enemies
in the Senate and encouraged our friends in the same body, but it
has also encouraged our friends everywhere and especially our friends
in the new Concessionary companies who seem now disposed to work 
harder for us politically than they were four years ago at the time
of the Kowalski-Wack publications. I seized the opportunity while 
in New York to urge them to greater endeavor. I think that the very
fact of the existence of the American Concessionary Companies has been
an influence in our favor and has had some effect in making the Government
and the Senate more conservative but I hope now to get the
people interested in the companies to work more actively. At my
suggestion the American-Congo Company has employed as one of its agents
Mr. S.P. Verner, who has been in the Congo several years and whose
name is well known to the Chevalier de Cuvelier. As Verner is impartial
and honest and knows about the true condition of the Congo
I have urged upon the Company that they should allow Verner to go to
Washington at once and see the President, the Secretary of State and
various Senators in order to put the true state of affairs before them.</p>

<p>I have found every where I have been in this country in the
past four weeks that the defence of the King Sovereign's administration
by Cardinal Gibbons has made a deep and lasting impression.</p>

<p>I feel assured that it is the Catholic movement that has held
the Senate in check for the past several weeks. The Resolutions of 
Societies, and the petitions of individuals, as well as certain person
influence and personal letter written by friends of Senators
have undoubtedly produced a very favorable effect. If we can continue
the movement with sufficient vigor we may be able to avert any action
by Congress, but, in any event, the expression of opinion which we
have placed before Congress and before the Government is sure to have
a decided effect in modifying any hostile action which the Government
may have momentarily comtemplated while under the pressure of the
Baptist and other Protestant missionaries.</p>

<p>While on this trip in the North I have still continued to
keep in communication with the individuals and societies in the West 
whom I visited two weeks ago, and I shall continue to encourage them
to keep up the movement they have started in favor of the Congo.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley
Consul General.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
