<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.fr.letter.0001 -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- DOCUMENT TITLE + DATE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Etienne to Under Secretary of State, August 14, 1889 --></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp><!-- IF TRANSLATION INCLUDED, USE: transcription, translation, and encoding -->
<name n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME" xml:id="INITIALS"><!-- FULL NAME --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.fr.letter.0001 -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Dispatch from Augustus Archer Silva to William H. Seward--></title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<!-- WHAT LANGUAGE IS THE DOCUMENT IN? SEE ALSO: fr, French -->
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PEOPLE NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PLACES NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<!-- IF THIS IS NOT A LETTER, DISPATCH, OR CORRESPONDENCE OF SOME KIND, DELETE <correspDesc> -->

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT FROM --></placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT TO --></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="yyyy-mm-dd" who="#INITIALS"><!-- THE WORK YOU'VE DONE. EXAMPLE: transcribed and encoded --></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/><!-- REPLACE x WITH THE NAME OF THE IMAGE -->

<!-- BEGIN TRANSCRIBING -->

Sir,

In the short interview with which you honored
honored me on Friday last. I informed you that had been
commmissioned by the President of Liberia to apprehend
your government with the hope that you would be
indiced* to make in----- on con---
will prevent foreign chaos from making 
approachments* on our territoty.

Unfortunetly for me, the presence of business did 
not permit of your giving me time to lay the *faito 
before you and you told me to call the next day, which
I did and called again on the following Monday 
and Tuesday; but with no better success coming to the 
great pressure of business in youir office.

As I had to leave your city, on Tuesday last *Li
bold adopts this method of laying the matter before
you, trusting that you will be kind enough to give it 
your consideration.

In the year 1885 a French Man of War came in to
the harbour of our caprifal**, Monveria and the Revenue 

The Honorable James G. Blaine,
Secretary of State
Washington D.C. 

mander?*

mander?* cat upon the President. During the conversation
the commander said that he had stopped 
at *Rerseby- a place within our boundray line and 
had an interview with the chiefs. The President said 
Why did you open there and have that interview? Do 
you not know that territory belongs to Liberia?" The
commander replied that he did not know it belonged to Liberia 
and that he had been his** by his government 
stop these and have that interview.

After the departure of the vessel, the President said 
our representative in Paris to call the attention of 
the French Government to thr action of their office and 
to point out the fact that our boundary in the Southeast 
extended to the Ban Pedro Riveria as you will see 
by referring to the Imperial Atlas in your office and 
that they had virtually admitted it by their Natural Chant*
amd otherwise.

Thw French Government then claimed that they 
had commercial treaties with the chiefs of Berrby*
as old as 1846- I think; but we have been of Cession*
of that territory made to us far back as 1836, **

We laid this matter before your government and dusted
for your kind offices; and in a Despatch to W. M. Lean
dated, Janurary 13th, 1886, W. Bayand instilled here to 
interview and to say to the French Government "We exercise 
no protection over Liberia; but the circumstances , the
Republic *niginated thpugh the colonization of 
American citizens and was established under the 
festering sanction of this Government give us the rights 
as the next friend of Liberia to aid her in preventing any 
encrodment** of foreign powers on her territorial 
soverneignty and in settling any dispute that may arise.
The Southeastern boundary at the River San Pedro has (?*MA)
been questioned and the powerful sanction of general 
admission for many years".

The matter has remained in (*abeyamceas) we cupped*
since that time; but it lately came to our knowledge that 
one Captain Binger- who was a permeant officer in 
the late expedition against the King of Duhouoey -- claim
to have made explorations in the near and Southeast
of Liberia and he has published, in a "Supplement Le Temps 
Mans 1890, a mafu** refreshing Liberia as a very
Manrew** eefiq* along the coast, represneting the country in
the immediate near of Liberia as far as Musandar** explored"
country and liable to become a Protectorate of France,--
although our W.B. Anderson had explored that country as 
far as *Musardin and published an account of this journey 
and cutting off our territory on thr Southeast up
to the Cavalla River thus taking the very territory in dispute
and which in Bayaid says belongs to us by "the powerful
sanction of general admission for many years". The territory was taken
from is in represented in his map of French Senitor

Whilst the French have not as yet made an appearnoment** 
towards taking posession of the territory 
yet, the Secretary under the circumstances we feel

warran

warran**----(line unclear)
Friend" and asking you to make such a demenstration 
in our favor as will prevent Foreign Governments 
from making and encrachment** on the territory.
If your powerful Government would make us a present 
of one of your smallest steam-gunboats to be used in 
guarding our coast from foreigners and preventing
them from settling 
   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
