<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

West Coast of Africa, Sierra Leone
September 1854

The Humble Memorial of the undersigned the commander of vesels belonging to citizens of the United States of America; Merchants: super cargos traders and others citizens of America trading or residing on the West Coast of Africa.

Humbly Sheweth, 
That we your memorial isles have after much consideration on the subject matter of this petition come to the unanimous conclusion that it is our duty to the Government of which we are citizens to report the very unsatisfactory position in which the representation of the American Governement stands in the Colony of Sierra Leone.

That notewith standing the very important an extensive commerce between the United States and West Coast of Africa, and particularly with this Colony it is a singular fact that there has never been a Consul not event Consulate Agent appointed by the United States Government as its representation here.

That on the 11th of Augut 1853 Commander J Mayo of the United States Flag Ship "Constitution" having ue regard to the interests of his Government was pleased to appoint Captain John Etting Taylor an American citizen and Merchant residing in ths Colony as acting Consul on the West Coast of Africa.

That such acting appointment has never been confirmed by the Governemnt of the United States not legally recognized by the English Government.

That although the American Government has at at all times sanctioned those acts pertaining to the consulship, which have been performed by the acting Consul and bearing in mind the fact that the local authorities in the Sierra Leone have hither to recognized Captain Taylor as acting Consul , yet we regard it as unsafe to permit matters to remain as they now are, in as much as it is in the <unclear/> of the English Government whenever it may think proper to decline any further recognition of the authority of the preset acting Consul.

That your memorialists desire to bear testimony to the srict attention which the acting Consul has at all times paid to the requirements of the commanders of american vessels and Amercan citzens generally on this part of the Coast and to his sensitive regard for the dignity and honor of the Union.

Your memorialists therefore pray that the United States Government will be pleased to confer this appointment of Consul of the United States Governemnt on this Coast on the present acting Consul. And your memorialists will ever pray so. 

<unclear extent=two words/>
Master of the <unclear extent=two words/>

Jamce Gains
Master <unclear/> "Carwest"
George Willar 
Master Bourque Aaron J. Harvey
John <unclear extent=four words/>
Honor <unclear/>
W.B.Wetts Mol.Doq. Cincinnatti Ohio
John H. Louis <unclear/> Mays
Charles H. Nelson Ser. HoN. Gambrill
William E. Cousins Shipthe Watson
A.M Grindle
By Enterprise of New York
Jaime Lord
<unclear extent=five words/>
H P West, <unclear/> of Breg "Z cno"
N. York

