<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0006">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, "Some Noted Negroes of the Past" (1907)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0006</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Some Noted Negroes of the Past</title>
<author/>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<date when="1907-07">July 1907</date>
<biblScope unit="page">1-13</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>   
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Albert, Prince Consort, consort of Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1861</term>
<term>Atambala</term>
<term>Bailey, Matisen F.</term>
<term>Bell, James Madison, 1826-1902</term>
<term>Bolivar, William C.</term>
<term>Brodie, George W.</term>
<term>Brown, John, 1800-1859</term>
<term>Campbell, Robert</term>
<term>Crowther, Josiah</term>
<term>Crowther, Jr, Samuel</term>
<term>Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891</term>
<term>Day, William Howard, -1900</term>
<term>Delany, Martin Robison, 1812-1885</term>
<term>Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895</term>
<term>Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870</term>
<term>George, Henry</term>
<term>Harris, James Henry</term>
<term>Longstreet, Augustus Baldwin, 1790-1870</term>
<term>Murray, Daniel Alexander Payne, 1852-1925</term>
<term>Shadd, Abram D.</term>
<term>Shadd, Isaac D.</term>
<term>Toussaint Louverture, 1743?-1803</term>
<term>Whipple, Alfred</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="places">
<term>Abeokuta (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Bathurst (South Africa)</term>
<term>Brazil</term>
<term>Canada</term>
<term>Cape Verde</term>
<term>Cheyney (Pa.)</term>
<term>China</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Funchal (Madeira Islands)</term>
<term>Georgia</term>
<term>Gulf of Guinea</term>
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Harper's Ferry (W.Va.)</term>
<term>Ilorin Province (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Lagos (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>London (England)</term>
<term>Niger Valley</term>
<term>Ogun River</term>
<term>Philadelphia (Pa.)</term>
<term>Santa Cruz de Tenerife (Canary Islands)</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Aku</term>
<term>Egbas</term>
<term>Zorubas</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Religious Society of Friends</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-04" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Some Noted Negroes of the Past.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Besides the men and women fairly well known to the person 
of average information by reason of their appearance,
more or less fully and frequently, in the pages of history or
current literature, there are characters not a few deserving of
public presentation, whose names are hidden away in fugitive
pamphlets, old books out of circulation, or in the memories
of contemporaries still alive, but soon to pass because of age.
These names ought to be preserved to history and to the Negro
race, for it is not so rich in heroic personalities that it can afford 
to let one pass from existence for lack of a biographer, or
at least an index finger pointing to the place in some musty corner 
of an old library where the facts can be found.</p>

<p>The names of men like Douglass in America, Dumas in
France, or Toussaint L'Ouverture in Hayti, are safely history's; 
there are others full worthy of an equally honorable,
if not an equally illustrious, page, from whom the obscuration
of the studied silence of Caucasian book-makers must be
lifted.</p>

<p>It has been said, and is to a degree true, that the Negro

<pb xml:id="p2" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.002.jpg"/>

is so busy making history that he has not time to write it. It
may state a fact, but it declares a deficiency also; for the men
and deeds, noble though they be, that die for want of a chronicler, 
exercise no influence in fixing the capacity of a race, refuting 
the malicious diatribes of a priori dogmatists, inspiring
the hopes of following generations, or justifying the faith of
sturdy friends. Men, therefore, like Daniel Murray and Wm.
C. Bolivar, who are devoting all their leisure moments to the
discovery of such persons and to the unearthing of creditable
records too long buried, are of a class which is doing more valuable 
work for race vindication than most of the men who
regard the deed without the record.</p>

<p>The writer, acknowledging the inspiration of their example 
and mindful of the mission of the A. M. E. Review,
has, in this series, attempted to "lend a hand."</p>

<p>The first person to whom the reader's attention is directed is</p>

<p>Robert Campbell.</p>

<p>In 1858, a year previous to that made memorable in
American history as the time when John Brawn's raid at Harper's 
Ferry precipitated the "irrepressible conflict" that destroyed 
human slavery, a body of earnest humanitarians met
together and formed what they called the "General Board of
Commissioners" to plan and provide for an exploration, scientific 
and anthropological, of that part of Central Africa occupied by 
the Egbas and Zorubas. The purpose was not avowedly, 
to ascertain the fitness of that region for the residence of

<pb xml:id="p3" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.003.jpg"/>

the American Negro, though, doubtless, that had a large unacknowledged 
place in their minds.</p>

<p>The gentlemen forming this Board of Commissioners
were men well known in their day around Philadelphia and
the North. William Howard Day, President; Matisen F.
Bailey, Vice President; Geo. W. Brodie, Secretary; James
Madison Bell, Treasurer; Alfred Whipple, Auditor; Dr. Martin 
R. Delany, Special Foreign Secretary; Isaac D. Shadd,
who subsequently took Mr. Bailey's place as Vice President;
Abram D. Shadd and James Henry Harris.</p>

<p>All of these men had shown a profound interest in the
promotion of the political and general interests of the colored
inhabitants of North America, especially of the United States
and Canada. After due deliberation, it was decided to organize 
"The Niger Valley Exploring Party" for the purpose
of visiting the Niger region to make a topographical, geological
and geographical examination of it; to inquire also into the
state and condition of the people of the valley, with such other
scientific inquiries as might be deemed expedient for the
purpose of science and for general information; but it was explicitly 
stated that the expedition had no reference to an emigration movement, 
the board being, in fact, opposed to the idea.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it would require a stretch of faith not likely
to be exercised by our readers who know of the oppression
and interest of the Negro in America at that time, to ask them
to believe that this party of Negro explorers were going out

<pb xml:id="p4" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.004.jpg"/>

for pure love of science and in absolute disregard of the fitness
of Africa as a haven for their kinsmen in tribulation.</p>

<p>Among the five chosen for this work was Professor Robert Campbell, 
of whom we write. He was one of the earliest
and most eminent scientists produced by the Negro race in
America, holding at the time of his appointment the professorship 
of Science in the famous Institute for Colored Youth,
Philadelphia, recently removed from that city to Cheyney,
Pa., about 20 miles away, where it still flourishes under the
management of the Friends.</p>

<p>It was because of Professor Campbell's scientific attainments 
that he was selected for the exploring party, for it was
desired that the observation should not be superficial or hasty,
but thorough and competent.</p>

<p>He was not a full-blood Negro, but a quadroon, resembling
in personal appearance a Scotchman in cast of face and in his
raw-boned frame. His eye was keen and piercing, his nose
thin and sensitive, well bridged and straight. The mouth was
thin and straight-lined, the chin pronounced and inclined to
be square; the cheek-bones prominent; while a mustache and
scrawny, scattering beard covered his lower face. Altogether,
his was the make-up to undertake the arduous duties assigned
him, and right joyfully did he undertake them, when, having
crossed to Liverpool, he set sail on the second stage of his
voyage June 24, 1859, touching at Funchal, Madiera, Santa
Cruz, Teneriffe and Cape Verde, before anchoring in the port.
of Bathurst, Gambia.</p>

<p>We are indebted to his own account of this memorable

<pb xml:id="p5" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.005.jpg"/>

trip for most of the interesting facts we are able to present.
On his return, he published a brief, but very satisfactory, account 
of the country, the tribes and their customs; an account
that loses none of its interest read by the light of more ambitious 
volumes in these later days when Africa and everything
African is being examined with a microscope and raked with
a fine-toothed comb.</p>

<p>Landing at Lagos on the Gulf of Guinea, after a stay of
some weeks awaiting Dr. Martin R. Delaney, his companion
explorer, in vain, he began his journey inland up the Ogun
river, having for his first objective the native town of Abbeokuta. 
He was fortunate in making the acquaintance of Rev.
Samuel Crowther, the gifted native preacher and scholar, since
made Bishop of Niger by the Episcopal Church—a man as
brilliant as he is black. The two sons, Samuel and Josiah
Crowther, decided to accompany Prof. Campbell, and together
they set out. In due time they arrived at Abbeokuta and were
given an audience with the King, who regarded their mission
with great favor.</p>

<p>A digression which Prof. Campbell makes in his narrative 
is of much interest as showing that the idea that Negroes
always pay more deference to white men because they are
white than to colored men, is false and the result of slavery
rather than any innate sense of inferiority in the black man.</p>

<p>On this point, he says:</p>

<p>"The natives generally at first regarded me as a white
man, until I informed them of my connection with the Negro.
This announcement always gained me a warmer reception."</p>

<pb xml:id="p6" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.006.jpg"/>

<p>"The reader here will permit me to digress to explain a
matter respecting which there has hitherto been some misconception. 
It has been asserted that the native African does not
manifest under any circumstances the same deference for colored 
men as he does for white men; and so fully is this believed, 
particularly in the United States, that both my colleague, 
Dr. Delaney, and myself were frequently cautioned
respecting the danger to which we should be exposed in consequence 
of our complexion. It is indeed true that more respect 
has been accorded to white men, on account of their superior 
learning and intelligence, than to the generality of semi-civilized
black men from the Brazils and other places, who
now live in the Aku country; but it is a great mistake to think
that the same is withheld from colored men similarly endowed
with their .white brethren. Let any disinterested person visiting 
Abeokuta place himself in a position to notice the manner
in which such a person, for instance, as the Reverend Samuel
Crowther, or even his son of the same name, each a pure Negro, 
is treated, and he would soon perceive the profound respect 
with which Africans treat those of their own race worthy
of it. The white man who supposes himself respected in Africa, 
merely because he is white, is grievously mistaken. I
have had opportunities to know, that if he should, presuming
on his complexion, disregard propriety in his bearing towards
the authorities, he would receive as severe rebuke as a similar
offense would bring him. in England. One of the chiefs of
Abbeokuta, Atambala, was with us one day when a young
missionary entered and passed him with only a casual nod of

<pb xml:id="p7" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.007.jpg"/>

the head. As soon as he was seated the haughty old chief
arose and said, in his own tongue: 'Young man, whenever any
of my people, even the aged, approaches me, he prostrates himself 
with his face to the ground. I do not expect the same
from you or from civilized men, (oyibo), nevertheless remember 
always that I shall demand all the respect due to a chief of
Abbeokuta. A sufficient apology was given, and the matter
ended, not without, it is hoped, teaching a salutary lesson."</p>

<p>This incident gives us an insight into the distorting effects 
of slavery. Men who have seen white enthroned and
made the standard of all excellence learn to depreciate, if not
despise, black; which, indeed, was the aim of those who deprived 
their fellow-men of God-given liberty. It is a travesty
upon reason and good judgment to distort and deform a human 
being's conceptions by a false system of training and then
point to the resulting product as the outcome of "race traits
and tendencies;" yet this is exactly what American opinion
does.</p>

<p>Possibly no question has been more hotly debated than
the Negro's ability of self-government. The Reconstruction
regime is always put to do service to demonstrate his inability;
but Professor Campbell found a degree of social and political
efficiency among the Aku nation, of whom the Egbas form a
part, that was truly wonderful. Besides, it had the rare
merit of being indigenous to Africa, thus discrediting another
stock explanation of whatever merit Americans see in a Negro
—that of "mere power to imitate."</p>

<pb xml:id="p8" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.008.jpg"/>

<p>Professor Campbell informs us that—</p>

<p>"Viewed as to its power of enforcing order, and affording 
security for life and property, the government of Abbeokuta 
is as efficient as a civilized government can be, and it 
accomplishes these ends with the greatest ease and simplicity.
Punishment is always summary and certain; notwithstanding,
nobody complains of injustice. The penalty for theft is extreme, 
being either decapitation or foreign slavery. Before
the advent of missionaries and civilized people adultery was
sometimes also a capital offense; now it is modified to heavy-
fines, the amount of which is always proportioned to the position 
and wealth of the offender. Cases of adultery often occur, 
and must be expected until they are taught to abandon
the disgusting system of polygamy.</p>

<p>"The tenure of property is as it is among civilized people,
except as to land, which is deemed common property; every
individual enjoys the right of taking unoccupied land, as much
as he can use, wherever and whenever he pleases. It is deemed
his property as long as he keeps it in use; after that, it is
again common property. This custom is observed by all the
Akus.</p>

<p>"The surviving relatives of one buried on any lot of
ground have a right to that ground, which nothing can tempt
them to relinquish, and from respect to the sentiment, no one
would invade on any pretext, particularly when the deceased
-was a mother or father. Mr. S. Crowther, Jr., has long desired 
to possess a strip of land contiguous to his place of business, 
but no offer of money can induce the owner to part with

<pb xml:id="p9" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.009.jpg"/>

it, although he is very poor; because his father lies buried
there."</p>

<p>Surely, here is the source of Henry George's single tax
theory which is intended to take from a man all idle land,
leaving him only as much as he can use profitably; yet observe
how filial regard, and respect for the dead, make a beautiful
exception to the general law in Africa by setting apart forever
burial grounds. Nothing quite like it can be found outside of
China, where veneration for parents approaches ancestor worship. 
Certainly America, which runs a street right over the
bones of a hero to make way for traffic, cannot match it.</p>

<p>A little further on, our author gives us an amusing instance 
of that universal jealousy that seems to exist among
physicians of every race and kind. The sprightly recital cannot 
be improved upon. Says he:</p>

<p>"There are many doctors—physicians, I might have said
—throughout the Aku country; and they are as jealous of their
profession, and as opposed to innovation in practice as the most
orthodox disciple of Aesculapius amongst us can be. Shortly
after the return of Mr. S. Crowther, Jr., from London, where
he received the training of a surgeon, several of these doctors,
hearing that he was prescribing for many who were before
their patients, assembled en masse in the market place, and after 
due deliberation issued an "injunction" that he should
forthwith abandon his practice. Some of the foremost of them
were deputed to communicate the decree of the faculty. They
were cordially received and heard with patience. After some
conversation, Mr. C. informed them that, he was willing to

<pb xml:id="p10" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.010.jpg"/>

obey, but only after a trial on both sides should prove him to
be the less skilled in the mysteries of the profession. To this
they consented. Time was given for preparation on both
sides. In the afternoon the regulars appeared, clothed in their
most costly garments, and well provided with orishas or charms
attached to all parts of their persons and dress. In the meantime 
Mr. Crowther had also prepared to receive them. A table
was placed in the middle of the room and on it a dish in which
were a few drops of sulphuric acid, so placed that a slight motion 
of the table would cause it to flow into a mixture of chlorate of 
potassa and white sugar. A clock was also in the room,
from which a small bird issued every hour and announced the
time by cooing. This was arranged so as to coo while they
were present. Mr. Crowther then made a brief harangue, and
requested them to say who should lead off in the contest. This
privilege they accorded to him. The door was closed, the curtains 
drawn down. All waited in breathless expectation.
Presently the bird came out, and to their astonishment cooed
twelve times, and suddenly from the midst of the dish burst
forth flame and a terrible explosion. The scene that followed
was indescribable; one fellow rushed through the window and
scampered; another in his consternation overturning chairs.
tables and everything in his way, took refuge in the bedroom, 
under the bed, from which he was with difficulty after
wards removed. It need not be added that they gave no more
trouble, and the practice they sought to break up was only the
more increased for their pains."</p>

<p>Prof. Campbell, pursuing the purpose for which he was

<pb xml:id="p11" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.011.jpg"/>

sent out, collected much valuable information about the form
of government, the grades of native officials, native food and
cooking, clothing, skill in iron working, shrewdness in trade,
native notions of honor, slavery, polygamy, military genius and
funeral rites. In almost all of these specifications he shows
the innate ability, ingenuity and initiative of the African who
had not come in contact with Caucasian instruction. The
whole showing is in disagreement with American ideas.</p>

<p>Those readers interested in philological investigation are
told of the richness of the Aku vocabulary. In methods of
salutation alone they have more than a score of words. For
instance:</p>

<p>"Equals meeting will simply say, acu; but one addressing
a superior affixes some word to acu, thus, acabo, (acu abo*)
acuni, etc. The superior usually salutes first, and when the
disparity of position is great, the inferior prostrates. The
young always prostrate to the aged. Women kneel, but never 
prostrate. Sons, without reference to age or rank, prostrate
to their mothers or senior female relatives. They never suffer
anything to interfere with the observance of these courtesies.
There is an appropriate salutation for every occasion; for instance: 
acuaro, good morning; acuale, good evening; acushe,
for being industrious; acabo, or acuabo, (ua as diphthong),
for returning from a journey; acatijo, for long absence; acujoco, 
for sitting or resting; acudaro, for standing or walking;
acuraju, expressive of sympathy, in distress or sickness; acuero, 
for bearing a burthen; acuale jo, for entertaining a stranger.

<fw type="note">*One vowel dropped for euphony.</fw>

<pb xml:id="p12" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.012.jpg"/>

So rich is the language in salutations, that the above list could
have been increased indefinitely."</p>

<p>So great a variety in the language of politeness would
indicate a Chesterfieldian people, and truly it is so, for we are
informed that not even a Frenchman is more polite than these
untaught Africans. Even two strangers never pass without
saluting, and the most scrupulous attention is paid to the social
position of persons saluted. An old man, whose age and position 
as selector of the successor to the king entitled him, by
native custom, to require the prostration of all who came into
his presence, refused to allow the king to pay this act of deference; 
but the king insisted. Then began what must have
been a most amusing contest between the two, each seeking,
on every meeting, to approach the other unawares and prostrate 
himself first.</p>

<p>They could frequently be seen stealthily creeping upon
each other, hiding behind bushes or huts, to be the first to
throw themselves on the ground before each other.</p>

<p>After gathering much valuable data for the General
Board of Commissioners who had sent him out, and pushing
his explorations as far inland as Ilorin, notwithstanding serious 
hindrances from native wars, Professor Campbell reached
Liverpool on his return May 12, 1860, having been from home
about one year.</p>

<p>Proceeding to London with Dr. Martin R. Delaney, his
fellow explorer, be reached there in time to attend that famous
session of the International Statistical Congress, over which
the Consort Prince Albert presided, and from which Judge

<pb xml:id="p13" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0006.013.jpg"/>

A. B. Longstreet, delegate from Georgia, retired in high
dudgeon because Dr. Delaney was seated on the platform, a
fact to which Lord Brougham called admiring attention.</p>

<p>It will be remembered that the General Board of Commissioners 
who sent out Professor Campbell and Dr. Delaney
disclaimed any intention of encouraging or arranging for emigration 
to Africa, yet after having made the exploration Professor 
Campbell announced his intention to make Africa his
home. In the wisdom of this course both of the explorers
agreed. Indeed, they proceeded to negotiate a treaty with
the tribes they visited, stipulating four things:</p>

<p>1.  The kings and chiefs agreed to grant them on behalf
of the African race in America, the right of settling in any
part of their unoccupied territory.</p>

<p>2.  These settlers were to be governed by their own laws
and customs.</p>

<p>3.  The settlers were to have "intelligence, education, a
knowledge of the arts and sciences, agriculture, and other
mechanical and industrial occupations, which they shall put
into immediate operation by improving the lands and in other
useful vocations."</p>

<p>4.  The laws of the natives were to be respected, and
matters of dispute between natives and settlers were to be settled 
by commissioners equally chosen.</p>

<p>These few glimpses of Professor Robert Campbell show
him to have been a very capable man in his chosen field of
science, observant as a traveler and entitled to some rating as
to statesmanship. Certainly, his love and loyalty for the
Negro stood out above all else.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
