<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0258">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Lambert Tree to Edmund Van Eetvelde, Administrator General of Foreign Affairs, December 23, 1887</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0258</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from Lambert Tree to Edmund Eetvelde, Administrator General of Foreign Affairs</title>
<date when="1887-12-23">December 23, 1887</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 120</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Billington, A</term>
<term>Stanley, Henry M</term>
<term>Vangels</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bangala</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
<term>St Paul de Loando</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>American</term>
<term>English</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Tree, Lambert</persName>
<roleName>Resident Minister</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
<date when="1887-12-23"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Van Eetvelde, Edmund</persName>
<roleName>Administrator General of Foreign Affairs</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-16" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template, organized file</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information.</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.001.jpg"/>

<p>Legation of the United States of America.</p>

<p>Brussels December 23, 1887</p>
    
<p>Sir:</p>
    
<p>In accordance with instructions from my
Government, I have the honor to bring to your
attention, a case of flagrant wrongs, which
are said to have been inflicted upon the
American Baptist Missionary Union,
composed of American citizens, and engaged
in missionary work in the Congo Free State by
Officials of the State.</p>
    
<p>It appears from a letter addressed by the 
Reverend A. Billington, representative of the
Union at Stanley Pool, to the American Consul
at St. Paul de Loando a copy of which I enclose 
herewith, that the Union owns a small Steamer <fw type="catch">on</fw>
    
<fw type="footer">To Mr. Edmund Van Eetvelde<lb/>
General Administrator of the
Department of Foreign Affairs and of Justice
of the Independent State of the Congo</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.002.jpg"/>
    
on the waters of the Upper Congo, called the
"Henry Reed," for the purpose of conveying missionaries
and their goods to its Stations. That in April
last Mr Henry M. Stanley arrived at Stanley 
Pool and applied for the use of the Steamer
but that the circumstances or the missionaries
were such that they could not do as he wished;
that he - Stanley - thereupon in the most 
arbitrary and lawless manner attempted
to take the Steamer by force, by placing an
armed band at the entrance of the Mission
Station, and another at the place where the
Steamer was at anchor, and then sent 
a letter demanding the instant surrender
of the Steamer; in case of non-compliance
his officers had orders to enforce the demand
at any risk either to Mr. Billington or those
concerned. That before anything was done, <fw type="catch">the</fw>
    
the Chief of the Station of the Congo Free State, at
Stanley Pool, protested against Mr Stanleys
action in the name of the State, and the armed
forces were withdrawn. The Chief of the Station
then applied for the Steamer, but the circumstances
remaining unaltered, the missionaries were
obliged to refuse its use. That it however
became so clear to them from conversations
and correspondence, that the Steamer would
be taken, that they ultimately handed her
over to the authorities of the Free State under
protest, for Mr. Stanley's use for the space 
of 45 days.</p>

<p>Thus it appears that while the
Chief of the Station ostensibly protested against
the threatened violence of Stanley as evidenced
by his posting an armed force at the entrance 
of the Mission, and another at the place <fw type="catch">where</fw>
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.003.jpg"/>
    
where the Steamer was at anchor and
his unwarranted and insolent demand
for the instant surrender of the private property
of these missionaries, yet it is entirely apparent
from the Statement of Mr. Billington that
he aided and abetted Stanley in his
lawlessness, and that these missionaries
were obliged to deliver their property up to
the authorities of the Free State for the use
of Stanley because they could not help
themselves.</p>
    
<p>But another an still more serious 
and flagrant wrong to these missionaries
by persons connected with the Government
of the Congo Free State remains to be stated.</p>
    
<p>It seems that the steamer was kept
considerably beyond the 45 days by Mr <fw type="catch">Stanley</fw>


Stanley, and then when she had been sent
away by him to be returned to her owners,
the American Baptist Missionary Union,
she was seized before reaching Stanley Pool
by another officer of the Free State.</p>
 
<p>This seizure was made at Bangala by
Lieut Vangels. This officer, it appears, first
applied for the use of the Steamer of the English
Baptist Mission, she being there at the time,
but on being refused he at once marched
20 armed soldiers on board the "Henry Reed."
His action was protested against by some of those
in charge of the Steamer but without effect
and up to the 3rd of August - the date of the 
letter - she had not been returned to her
owners.</p>
 
<p>Assuming the facts to be correctly <fw type="catch">stated</fw>
 
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.004.jpg"/>

stated, and there seems to be no present reason
to doubt that they are, I desire most earnestly
to remonstrate in the name of my Government,
against the arbitrary and lawless acts of 
interference with the enjoyment of the rights 
of private property by the persons connected
with the Government of the Independent State
of the Congo, as indicated by the circumstances
I have detailed.</p>
 
<p>The Government of the United States
could not fail to regard with profound regret
and displeasure such abuses of the rights
of any of its citizens in the Congo Free
State by officials of the State, and especially
in the case of the unselfish and self sacrificing
men, who, braving the dangers of climate
and the privations incident to a savage <fw type="catch">and</fw>


unsettled country, have posted themselves 
there, as aids of humanity and religion.
No settlers could be more valuable to the
Government of the New Country in its efforts
to spread the blessings of civilization, or are
entitled to greater protection and more tender
consideration at the hands of the Governmental
authorities than the brave and single-minded
men and women who are occupying the
field of the Congo State as missionaries and
no missionaries more than those who go
from America. They go from, and are citizens
of a country, whose Government was the
first to recognize the Congo flag, and which 
has been unfaltering in its sympathy
and aid towards the establishing of a
liberal and civilized Government in <fw type="catch">that</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.005.jpg"/>

that remote quarter of the world.</p>
    
<p>I am instructed to ask that the Government
of the Independent State of the Congo will immediately
take steps to cause the restoration of the Steamer 
in question to her legitimate owners, the
American Baptist Union, at Stanley Pool,
and that the Government will cause a searching
investigation to be made of the arbitrary acts
said to have been done in this regard, by the
authorities of the State. Also that a prompt
and effective reparation be made for any
injury done to the owners by reason of the
forcible seizure of the Steamer.</p>
    
<p>I avail myself of the opportunity to
renew to you, Sir, the assurances of my most
distinguished consideration.</p>
    
<p>Lambert Tree</p>
    
<p>Enclosure<lb/>
Copy of letter from A. Billington to the American Consul
at St. Paul de Loando dated August 3rd 1887.</p>
    

<p>Copy</p>
    
<p>American Baptist Missionary Union<lb/>
Stanley Pool, Congo Free State<lb/>
August 3rd 1887.</p>

<p>To the American Consul,<lb/>
St. Paul de Loundo.</p>
    
<p>Sir:</p>
    
<p>The above Society has a small Steamer on the
waters of the Upper Congo, for the purpose of conveying
Missionaries and their goods to its Stations. It did 
not occur to us to be necessary to have "papers" on
our Steamer still a few weeks ago. It has however
recently become necessary. In the first place for the
protection of the Mission property and in the second
place, because, that after the 1st Sept. 1887, we
are compelled to fly the flag of the "Congo Free State"
but we are not allowed to fly any other flag until we
have the proper papers of our nationality on board.</p>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0258.006.jpg"/>
    
<p>In April last when Mr. Stanley arrived here, he
applied for the use of our steamer, but our circumstances
were such that we could not do as he wished
he then attempted to take the steamer by force,
by placing an armed band at the entrance of
our Mission Station, and another at the place
where our steamer was at anchor and then sent
in a letter demanding the instant surrender of
the steamer; in case of my not complying his
officers had orders to enforce the demand at any
risk either to myself or those concerned.</p>
    
<p>Before anything was done, the Chief of the
Station of the "Congo Free State" at this place,
protested against Mr. Stanley's action in the name
of the State, and the armed forces were withdrawn.
The Chief of the Station of the Free State then
applied for the steamer, but our circumstances
remaining unaltered we were obliged to refuse.</p>
    
<p>It however, became very clear to us from conversation
and correspondence that the steamer would be
taken, so that we ultimately handed her over to
the Free State under protest for Mr. Stanley's
use for the space of 45 days. She was kept



considerably beyond this time by Mr. Stanley but 
after she had been sent away by him to be
returned to us, before reaching here she was
seized by another officer of the Free State.</p>
    
<p>This seizure took place at the State Station
Bangala by Lieut. Vangele. This officer first
applied for the use of the steamer of the English
Baptist Mission, she being there at the same 
time, but being refused at once marched 20
armed soldiers on board the "Henry Reed."
His action was protested against by some of those
in charge of the steamer but without effect and
the steamer has not yet been returned to us.</p>
    
<p>It was only yesterday that we received the
decree of the King respecting flags, and now at once
write to ask if you will kindly arrange for us to
get the "Papers" as early as possible that we may
be able to use the American Flag.</p>
    
<p>I enclose particulars of the steamer and
hope they will meet all requirements.</p>
    
<p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,<lb/>
A. Billington<lb/>
Member of the American Baptist Missionary
Union and in charge of the said Steamer</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
