<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0228">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley, Consul of the Congo Free State, February 10, 1905</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="KCD">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0228</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley, Consul of the Congo Free State</title>
<date when="1905-02-10">February 10, 1905</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 229, Liasse 182</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Cullom</term>
<term>King Leopold II</term>
<term>Moncheur, Baron</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Liverpool</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Washington</term>
</keywords>


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>American</term>
<term>Belgian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Whiteley, James Gustavus</persName>
<roleName>Consul of the Congo Free State</roleName>
<placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
<date when="1905-02-10"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-24" who="#kln">named file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0228.001.jpg"/>

<p>Confidential.</p>

<p>223 West Lanvale Street.<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland,<lb/>
February 10, 1905.</p>

<p>Dear Sir:-</p>

<p>In accordance with the wish of His Excellency, Baron Moncheur,
Belgian Minister at Washington, I have the honor of calling your attention
to the enclosed documents.</p>

<p>Among them you will find a copy of the Memorial of the Congo
question presented to Congress by Senator Cullom on behalf of the Belgian
Protective Association of America. The object of the Memorial is
to refute the charge brought against the Administration of the Congo
Free State and the Government of His Majesty, King Leopold II, by certain
Missionary Organizations inspired partly by discontented missionaries but
chiefly by rubber merchants of Liverpool.</p>

<p>The other document which I hand you is a form of Petition endorsing
the above mentioned Memorial, and it is desired that you will
endeavor to secure for it the largest possible number of signatures of
influential persons, both Belgians and American business men.</p>

<p>There has been recently formed in New York by a number of well 
known men, a society called the Belgian Protective Association of America,
and you will find enclosed a short memorandum stating the objects of the 
organization, its by-laws, and the names of a few of its prominent members.
About 200 members have been already enrolled in New York. It is contemplated
to make this organization permanent so as to be available, not
only in the present of circumstances, but also in the future, for the cultivation
of friendly and commercial relations between the United States, 
on the one hand, and Belgium and the Congo Free State, on the other. I
request that you will be kind enough to form a branch of the Belgian Protective
Association in your Consular district, and that you will return
me the Petition with the signatures of your member properly affixed, and
also that you will forward a list of the membership of your branch to
the Secretary of the Belgian Protective Association, 83 Worth Street,
New York City.</p>

<p>For obvious reasons it is thought desirable that His Majesty's

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0228.001.jpg"/>

Consuls should not appear too conspicuously in the organization and for
this reason it would be well, wherever practicable, to select as the active
officers of the Branch prominent business men not connected with
His Majesty's Service.</p>

<p>I suggest that, if possible, you induce some of your influential
friends to write personal letters to their Senators and Representatives
endorsing the Memorial and the Petition of the Belgian Protective Association.</p>

<p>I avail myself of this opportunity to thank you on behalf of
Baron Moncheur, as well as on my own account, for the interest you have
taken in the defense of His Majesty's Government in the Congo, and</p>

<p>With high appreciation of your courtesy,<lb/>
I remain,<lb/>
Yours faithfully,<lb/>
James Gustavus Whiteley<lb/>
Consul for the Congo Free State.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
