<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0199">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Minister of Colonies in Brussels, October 3, 1911</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab"></name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0199</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Minister of Colonies in Brussels</title>
<date when="1911-10-03">October 3, 1911</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 241, Liasse 219</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>American Consul, R.</term>
<term>Albert, N'Zao Makwala</term>
<term>Benza, Paulo</term>
<term>Dedé, Thomas</term>
<term>Deleval</term>
<term>Deuster, Commissioner General</term>
<term>Janssens, C.L.</term>
<term>Lutete, Thomas</term>
<term>Minister of Colonies in Brussels</term>
<term>Paeli, Chief</term>
<term>Schmidt, Section Chief</term>
<term>Vice Consul General of the United States of America</term>
<term>Vice Governor General</term>
<term>Zenga, Paul</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bas-Congo</term>
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Brussels</term>
<term>Leange</term>
<term>Lukula</term>
<term>Maba</term>
<term>Maduda</term>
<term>Punze</term>
<term>Tshela</term>
<term>Tuidi Zambi</term>
<term>United States of America</term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Vice Governor General</roleName>
<placeName/>
<date when="1911-10-03"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Minister of Colonies in Brussels</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-09" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">transcribed, translated, encoded.</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Corrections, marked up.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="fr">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.001.jpg"/>

<ab>CONGO BELGE
GOUVERNEMENT LOCAL
5em Direction
Justice
No 1925</ab>

<ab>Objet:
A propos du voyage du 
Vice-Consul Général des
E.U.d"Amérique dans le Mayumble</ab>

<ab>MINISTERE DES COLONIES
1e Direction Générale
1e Direction- 1 Division
No d'ordre 1314
Entrée le: 5-10-1911</ab>

<ab>MINISTRE <unclear>DES COLONIES</unclear>
<unclear>INDICATER GÉNÉRALE</unclear>
No 11139 <unclear>3 OCT 1911</unclear></ab>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre,

Comme suite à ma lettre No1427/Bdu 10 juillet der-
nier, j'ai l'honneur de vous faire parvenir, sous ce pli, en co- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
pie, la lettre No3546 du 1 Septembre 1911, ainsi que ses
annexes, de M. le Commissaire Général, commissaire de district 
du Bas-Congo, relative à des plaintes de 2 chefs médaillés du
Mayumbe, centre le Vice-Consul Général des États-Unis d'Améri- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
que a Boma. </p>

<p>L'Adjoint Supérieur Deleval se trouve en ce moment
dans la région, a l'effet d'y précéder à une enquête, afin d'é- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
tablir le bien fondé de ces réclamations.</p>

<p>Je ne manquerai pas, Monsieur le Ministre, de vous 
tenir au courant des résultats de cette enquête, aussitôt que
ceux-ci serent en ma possession.</p>

<p>Je porte le cas Dedé à la connaissance de Monsieur
le Procureur Général</p>

<p>Le Vice-Gouverneur Général</p>
<p><unclear>Litistay</unclear></p>

<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Ministre des Colonies
BRUXELLES</fw>


<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.002.jpg"/>

<ab>Boma, le 1re Septembre 1911</ab> <!-- date is cut off at top of page. -->
<ab>No 3546</ab>
<ab>2 annexes</ab>
<ab>Objet:
Plainte du Chef de Maduda</ab>

<p>Monsieur le Gouverneur Général

J'ai l'honneur de porter a votre connaisance que le 
chef investi de Maduda, le nomme Paul Zenga, et arrivé à Boma pour
se plaindre des difficultés que lui causent les missionnaires pro- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
testants qui dit-il, incitent ses administrés a la désobéissance,
et aussi certains propos tenus par le consul des États Unis et
qui seraient de nature à diminuer son autorité.
</p>

<p>J'ai interrogé ce chef et j'ai fiat acter ses declara- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
tions, Je vous en remets ce-joint le procès-verbal.</p>

<p>J'ai assuré le chef de la protectien de l'auterité, dans
tout ce qu'il fera pour l'exécution de la loi, et je lui ai confir- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
mé les pouvoirs disciplinatres qui lui sent accordé par le décret
du 2 Mai 1910, tout en lui conseillant de n'en user qu'à bon es-
cient et avec modération.</p>

<p>Je l'ai engagé à rester une couple e jours a Boma afin 
de se tenir éventuellement à la disposition de l'auterité, pour le
cas où ee nouveaux renseignements devraient être demandés.</p>

<p>Je reçois, au moment où j'achève cette lettre, une lettre 
du chef de secteur du Mayumbe, qui se rapporte à des faits connexes
a ceux que je vous indique ci-dessus. Je joins la copie de cette
lettre et je vous tiendrai qu courant de la suite.</p>

<p>Le Commisaire Général
(Sé) Deuster</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.003.jpg"/>

<p>Lukula, le 30 Août 1911</p>
    
<p>No. 16</p>

<p>OBJET:<lb/>
Rapport lettre sur route
de Tshela à Lukula par
Maba</p>

<p>Monsieur le Commissaire Général</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de porter à votre connaissance que je
suis rentré à Lakula par les chefferies de Maba, Leange, Tuidi Zambi et
Punze. J'ai fait cette tournée, en suite des déclarations qui me fit le
chef Thomas Lutete lors de sa visite à Tshela.</p>

<p>Il aurait reçu dans sa chefferie, la visite de Monsieur
le Consul d'Amerique accompagné d'un Missionaire de Vungu lui servant
d'interprête.</p>

<p>Ce dernier demandait partout à son passage, de quelle
façon l'en administrait leur territoire et en outre, quel nombre de coups
de fouet les chefs appliquaient quand les indigénes ne payaient pas
leur impôt.</p>

<p>Des questions relatives au recrutement travailleurs par
les Agents de la Colonies furent également posées.</p>

<p>Je fis remarquer à Thomas Lutete la gravité de ses declarations
et il me déclara les maintenir.</p>
    
<p>Il a du reste, ainsi que le chef médaillé Paoli de Moduda
l'intention pour ce motif; de se rendre prochainement à Boma. Il se
plaint également d'un nommé Thomas Dedé, cathéchiste de la mission de
Kinkenzi, qui se permet beaucoup d'exactions dans sa chefferie et de reconnaitre
son auterité de chef médaillé</p>
    
<p>Beaucoup de sous-chefs indigénes ayant à s'en plaindre
il me demande si vous ne pourriez lui envoyer un magistrat, afin de
mettre une fois pour toute cet homme à la raison. Il y est question d'ar-
restation de chef pour non règlement de compte ensuite d'un jugement
rendu dans une palabre par le nommé Thomas Dedé, etc. etc.</p>

<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Commissaire Général
commissaire de district du Bas-Congo 
Boma</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.004.jpg"/>

<p> Il me demande également si en vertu de son autorité de
chef médaillé il n'aurait pas en ce cas, le droit de procéder à l'expul-
sion de ce dernier de son territoire.</p>

<p> Je lui demandais beaucoup de calme et ne pas
agir avant d'avoir réponse de ma part.</p>

<p>J'ignore, Monsieur le Commisaire Général, s'il 
n'y a pas un peu d'exagération dans ces déclarations, ne m'étant pas
suffisamment arrêté chez lui, mais y retournerai dans quelques semaines
aux fins d'y faire une enquête plus approfondie.</p>

<p>Le Chef de Secteur.
(Sé) Schmidt.</p>


<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.005.jpg"/>

<!-- the beginning of this document must not have been copied at the archives -->

<p>mois de septembre, nous Jansssens C.L. Chef de Secteur de deuxième
classe, délégué par Monsieur Deuster, Commissaire Général, Commissaire 
de district du Bas-Congo, Boma</p>

<p>Avons precédé par l'intermédiare de l'interprête
N'Zae Makwala, Albert à l'interrogatoire de Paule Benza, chef
investi de la Chefferie de Maduda, et avons entendu ce qui suit:</p>

<p>Q. De quel vous plaignez-vous?</p>

<p>R. Je me plains de ce que les missionaires protestants sont venus
dans mon village et on dit à mes noirs de ne plus m'obeir et 
que, si un chef disait à un de ses hommes de ne plus travailler que
celui-ci pourrait refuser.</p>

<p>Q. Quel est le nom de missionare qui a prononcé ces mots?</p>

<p>R. Ave.</p>

<p>Q. Savez-vous pourquoi il a dit cela?</p>

<p>R. Non, je ne le sais pas</p>

<p>Q. Vous parliez également du Consul d'Amerique; qu'est-ce qu'il
vous a dit lors de son passage dans votre village?</p>

<p>R. Le Consul d'Amerique est arrivé dans mon village; l'a fait réunir
les indigénes et, par l'intermédiare de son interprête, a dit
aux noirs de lui raconter tout ce que leur chef faisait. Il ajouta
qu'il êtait venu à l'insu du Gouverneur Général et qu'il etait
plus malin que le Gouverneur Général.</p>

<p>Le Consul dit aux indigénes qu'ils avaient su 
voir qu'il avait anneté tout ce qu'ils avaient dit et que maintenant,
il allait fair une letter pour le Gouverneur Général et une
pour son pays</p>

<p>Q. Vous avez prononcé le met chicette; avec quoi ce mot avait-il
rapport?</p>

<p>R. Le Consul ajouta encore que, bien que le Gouverneur leur avait 
désigné un chef médaillé, ils ne seraient pas obligé d'aller travailler
si celui-ci le leur ordennait et qu'il ne pourrait pas
donner de la chicette; s'il le faisait, ils n'auraient qu'a venir
se plaindre chez lui</p>

<p>Q. Avez-vous encore quelque chose a ajouter?</p>

<p>R. Mes indigénes ont demandé au consul ce qu'il irait faire avec
leurs déclarations; sur quoi, il a répondu qu'il les enverrait en
Amérique et que moi comme chef, ne pourrais pas donner du fouet  <!-- cut off last line? -->
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.006.jpg"/>
    
terprête Zae et le chef Paulo Banza signent avec nous</p>

<p>(Se) Janssens</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="translation" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.001.jpg"/>

<ab>BELGIAN CONGO</ab>
<ab>LOCAL GOVERNMENT</ab>
<ab>5th Direction</ab>
<ab>Justice</ab>

<ab>No 1925</ab>

<ab>Subject:
A propos du voyage du 
Vice-Consul General of the
U.S. of America in Mayumble</ab>

<ab>MINISTER OF COLONIES
1st Direction General
1st Direction- 1 Division
No of order 1314
Dated: 10-5-1911</ab>

<ab>MINISTER <unclear>OF COLONIES</unclear>
<unclear>GENERAL INDICATOR</unclear>
No 11139 <unclear> OCT 3 1911</unclear></ab>

<p>Mister Minister,

Following my letter No. 1427 last July 10, 
I have the honor of transmitting to you, under this letter, a 
copy, of letter No. 3546 from September 1, speaking of these 
annexes, of the Commissioner General, commissioner of the Bas-Congo 
district, relating to the complaints from 2 decorated Chefs from
Mayumbe, center the Vice-Consul General of the United States of Ameri- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
ca in Boma. 
</p>

<p>The Deputy Superior Deleval is found at this moment 
in the region, to the effect of the investigation here, in order to es- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
ablish a good foundation of his claims.</p>

<p>I will not forget, Mister Minister, to keep 
you aware of the results of this investigation, as soon as 
they are in my possession.</p>

<p>I'm bringing the Dedé case to the knowledge of the
Prosecutor General</p>

<p>Le Vice-Governor General</p>
<p><unclear>Litistay</unclear></p>

<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Ministre des Colonies
BRUXELLES</fw>
</div1>

<div1 type="translation" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.002.jpg"/>

<ab>Boma, September 1, 1911</ab> <!-- date is cut off at top of page. -->
<ab>No 3546</ab>
<ab>2 annexes</ab>
<ab>Subject:
Complaint of the Chief of Maduda</ab>

<p>Mister Governor General, 

I have the honor of brining to your attention that the
Maduda chief in power, named Paul Zenga, arrived in Boma to 
complain of the difficulties caused by Protestant miss- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
ionaries who tell him, incites his citizens to disobedience,
and also certain words held by the consul of the United States 
that would be diminishing your athority. 
</p>

<p>I questioned this chief and recorded his declar- <!-- word is hyphenated between these lines. -->
ations, I enclosed the minutes attached.</p>

<p>I assured the chief that his authority will be protected, in  
every action he will do to execute the law, and I confirmed   
that the disciplinary powers that are accorded to him by the discretion 
of May 2, 1910, advising him not to abuse it, to use it
wisely and with moderation.</p>

<p>I encouraged him to rest a couple days in Boma in order 
to eventually grasp the <unclear>l'auterité</unclear> disposition, should
we ask for new details.</p>

<p>I revieved, the moment I finished this letter, a letter
from the chief of Mayumbe, that relates the facts connected
with those that I indicate above. I added a copy of this
letter and I will keep you informed of what happens next.</p>

<p>Commissioner General
(Sé) Deuster</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.003.jpg"/>

<p> Lukula, 30 August 1911</p>
    
<p>No. 16</p>

<p>SUBJECT:<lb/>
Letter report on the 
Tshela route to Lukula by way of 
Maba</p>

<p>Mr. Commissioner General</p>
    
<p>I am honored to bring to your attention that I have 
returned to Lakula by the Maba, Leange, Tuidi Zambi and
Punze chiefdoms. I took this journey, following the declarations of
Chief Thomas Lutete during his visit to Tshela.</p>

<p>In his chiefdom, he would have received Mr. American Consul, accompanied by
the Vungu Missionary acting as an interpreter.</p>

<p>The latter asked throughout his travels, in what
way they manage their territory and moreover, how many times the
chiefs whipped the natives when they did not pay their tax.</p>

<p>The Agents of the Colonies posed equally relative questions to the
recruitment workers.</p>

<p>I pointed out to Thomas Lutete the gravity of his declarations
and he told me to keep them.</p>
    
<p>He has furthermore, as well as the decorated chief Paoli de Moduda,
the intention for this motive; to return to Boma next. He complains
equally of the named Thomas Dedé, Catechist of the Kinkenzi mission,
who authorizes a lot of abuses in his chiefdom and to recognize 
his authority of being a decorated chief.</p>
    
<p>A lot of indigenous subchiefs having complained about it
he asks me if you could not send him a magistrate, in order for
all men to see reason for once. There is a question of the
chief's arrest for the settling of accounts then a judgment
arrived in a palaver by the name of Thomas Dede, etc. etc.</p>

<fw type="footer">Mr. Commissioner General
commissioner of the district of Bas-Congo
Boma</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.004.jpg"/>

<p> He also asked me if in virtue of his authority as
a decorated chief he would not have it in this case, the right of proceeding of the expul-
sion of the last of his territory.</p>

<p> I asked him to be calm and to not 
act before having responded to my part.</p>

<p>I ignored, Mr. Commissioner General, that if there 
is not a little exaggeration in his declarations, not giving me 
sufficient stop in his area, but I will return there in a couple weeks
at the end of a deeper investigation there.</p>

<p>The Sector Manager.
(Sé) Schmidt.</p>


<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.005.jpg"/>

<!-- the beginning of this document must not have been copied at the archives -->

<p>month of September, we Jansssens C.L. Sector Chief of the second 
class, drowned by Mr. Deuster, Commissioner General, Commissioner 
of the District of Bas-Congo, Boma</p>

<p>Proceeded through the interpretor 
N'Zae Makwala, Albert interrogates Paule Benza, appointed
chief of the Chiefdom of Maduda, and heard the following:</p>

<p>Q. What are your complaints?</p>

<p>R. I take issue with what the Protestant missionaries have brought 
to my villiage and say to my people to no longer obey me and 
that, if a chief says to one of his people to only work that 
they could refuse.</p>

<p>Q. What is the name of the missionary who says these words?</p>

<p>R. Ave.</p>

<p>Q. Do you know why he says this?</p>

<p>R. No, I don't know why</p>

<p>Q. You also speak about the American Consul; what did he 
say to you at the time of his visit in your villiage?</p>

<p>R. The American Consul arrived in my villiage; gathered the 
natives and, through his interpretor, said 
to the people to report everything their chief did. He added 
that he came by the <unclear>insu</unclear> of the Governor General and that he was 
more clever than the Governor General.</p>

<p>The Consul said to the natives that they could
see that he had annotated everything they said and that now,
he went to make a letter for the Governor General and one 
for his country</p>

<p>Q. You mentioned the <unclear>chicette</unclear>; with whom did he 
speak?</p>

<p>R. The Consul added again that, although the Governor had them 
designated a decorated chief, they would not be obligated to go to work
if they ordered them and if he could not 
give the chicette; if he did it, they would not come 
to complain here</p>

<p>Q. Do you have anything more to add?</p>

<p>R. My natives have asked the consul what he will do with 
their declarations; on what, he responded that he would send them to 
America and that me as chief, could not whip  <!-- cut off last line? -->
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0199.006.jpg"/>
    
interpretor Zae and the chief Paulo Banza sign with us</p>

<p>(Se) Janssens</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
