<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">en.zanzibar</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Dispatch from Augustus Archer Silva to William H. Seward--></title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from U.S. Consuls in Zanzibar, Br. Africa, 1836-1906</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M468</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="roll">4</biblScope>
<date when="1886-07-01">July 1, 1886</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02" who="#pr">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="130809.jpg"/>

<p>Introduction</p>

<p>On the 5 rolls of this microfilm publication are reproduced
11 volumes that contain mainly despatches, with enclosures, ad-
dressed to the Department of State by U.S. consular officials
at Zanzibar, Zanzibar, British Africa, between April 27, 1836,
and June 7, 1906.</p>

<p>The despatches, with few exceptions, are arranged in chron-
ological order. At the beginning of Roll 1 are reproduced se-
lected pages from 23 State Department registers of correspondence
that constitute a register of despatches from Zanzibar between
April 27, 1836, and June 7, 1906.</p>

<p>Interspersed throughout the series are such documents as
occasional memoranda prepared by other State Department offi-
cials and letters from private citizens of the United States.</p>

<p>The consular post at Zanzibar was established on March 11,
1836, and the appointment of Richard P. Waters as the first con-
sul was confirmed on the same day. During the period 1836-1906
several special agents from the Department of State were sent to
the consulate: Robert W. Shuffeldt, 1878; Frederic M. Cheney,
1886; and Augustus C. B. Govea, 1888. The post was closed tempo-
rarily between November 1894 and August 1895.</p>

<p>Some of the subjects to which the despatches relate are
shipwrecks, desertions, and mutinies and other disturbances on
U.S. vessels; the repression of the slave trade and the aboli-
tion of slavery, 1846-97; concessions granted on the East Afri-
can Coast to foreign governments; the establishment of the
British Protectorate, 1890; and the African expiditions of
John H. Speke and James A. Grant, 1862-63; Baron Karl K. von der
Decken, 1865; David Livingstone, 1866-73; and Henry M. Stanley,
1871-72 and 1874-89. Included also are photographs of Zanzibar
taken during a skirmish between the Sultan's forces and the
British forces, 1896, and issues of the Gazette for Zanzibar and
East Africa and the Bombay Government Gazette.</p>

<p>Many despatches are transmittal letters for enclosures of
a routine nature forwarded by consular officials to the Depart-
ment of State, such as reports on consular fees received and on
trade. In accordance with departmental policy adopted in 1870,
however, most statistical enclosures were removed from their
covering letters and distributed among other records of the De-
partment of State or sent to other departments of the Government.</p>

<p>The records reproduced in this microcopy are part of the
records in the National Archives designated as Record Group 59,
General Records of the Department of State.</p>

<pb facs="130913.jpg"/>

<p>National Archives Microfilm Publications</p>

<p>In the same record group are several series of volumes con-
taining additional documents on relations between posts in the
western aread of the Indian Ocean and the United States. There
are microcopies available on despatches from U.S. consular offi-
cials at Aden, Aden, 1880-1906 (T-503); Bombay, India, 1838-1906
(Microcopy 168); Lourenco Marques, Mozambique, Prtuguese Africa,
1854-1906 (T-171); Mahe, Seychelles Islands, Indian Ocean,
1868-88 (T-437); Muscat (Masqat), Oman, 1880-1906 (T-638), for 
1836-57 see Zanzibar (Rolls 1-3 of Microcopy 468); Port Louis,
Mauritius, Mascarene Islands, Indian Ocean, 1794-1805, 1817-1906
(Microcopy 462); St. Denis, Réunion Island, Mascarene Islands,
Indian Ocean, 1880-92 (Microcopy 463); and Tamatave, Madagascar,
1853-1906 (T-60). Complementary to the despatches are instruc-
tions to the consuls. Other related records are notes from the 
foreign mission of Zanzibar in the United States to the Depart-
ment of State, 1843-1905 (Roll 3 of T-953).</p>

<p>The method of arranging the consular and diplomatic series
cited above was discontinued in 1906 when the Department of
State adopted the practice of filing incoming and outgoing cor-
respondence, memoranda, and other documents by subject.</p>

<p>In the Department of State decimal file, 1910-29, also in
Record Group 59, are additional documents relating to Zanzibar.
Some documents are in the series relating to internal affairs of
British Africa (Roll 33 of Microcopy 583), and other documents
are in the series concerning political relations between British
Africa and other states (Microcopies 584 and 585).</p>

<p>In Record Group 84, Records of the Foreign Service Posts
of the Department of State, in the National Archives, are rec-
ords originally kept at U.S. diplomatic and consular posts.
Among them are records of the post at Zanzibar, 1834-1918, and
at other posts in the western area of the Indian Ocean. One vol-
ume of documents from Zanzibar is included in records of the 
post at Mombasa, Kenya, British Africa, 1901-26.</p>

<p>The records reproduced in this microcopy were prepared for
filming by Ralph E. Huss, who also wrote these introductory re-
marks and provided the other editorial material.</p>

<pb facs="131306.jpg"/>

<p>No 96
United States Consulate
Zanzibar, July 5th 1886.</p>

<p>F. M. Cluney Consul
<unclear/>
Department of State
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Subject
New treaty</p>

<p>Enclosures:
New treaty between the U.S.
Government and <unclear/>
<unclear/> of Zanzibar</p>

<pb facs="131313.jpg"/>

<p>United States Government
Zanzibar July 5th 1886
To the <unclear/>
<unclear>Fluid</unclear> Assistant Secretary of State
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Sir.
I have the honor to acknowledge
dispatch no 43, dated May 6th
1886 from the Department of State
incosing a draft of a new treaty
and a "Full Power" from the Pres-
ident for me to conclude the
same.</p>

<p>I at <unclear/> placed myself in
communication with His High-
ness the Sultan of Zanzibar and
sent him a draft of the proposed
treaty.</p>

<p>His Higness expressed himself
as very <unclear/> gratified that the
United States Government was
willing to make a new treaty
to his advantage. The treaty was
immediately drawn up in the <unclear/></p>

<pb facs="131322.jpg"/>

<p>English and <unclear/> languages, and
on the third July it was signed
by myself and H. H. <unclear/> Sec-
retary, who was H. H. Plenipotentiary.</p>

<p>The treaty was made in du-
plicatel one copy is inclosed
with this dispatch and the other
is in His Higness possession.</p>

<p>I have <unclear/> over <unclear/> the
English <unclear/> treaties and I
cannot see that thus in any ad-
vantages that they get that is not
<unclear/> us.</p>

<p>His Highness the Sultan did
not <unclear/> one question, but ordered
the treaty got ready.</p>

<p>I am greatly indebted to one
Kanji Ragpah, a native <unclear/>
new who is an intimate friend
of the Sultan, in getting the treaty
through so quickly.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be Sir
Your obedient servant
F. M. Cheney
US Consul</p>

<p>Enclosures
Treaty between the US of America
and the Sultan of Zanzibar</p>

<pb facs="131413.jpg"/>

<p>No 98
United States Consulate
Zanzibar, August 15th 1886</p>

<p>To the Hon.
Third Assist. Secretary of State.
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:
I have the honor to request the
Department of State to inform me
if any allowance will be made <unclear/>
for making the new treaty with the
Sultan of Zanzibar.</p>

<p>I consider that such work is
outside of the line of a Consul's duty
and it made a great deal of extra
work and trouble, as is always the
case in these Oriental countries.</p>

<p>The Treaty was to be got through
in a great hurry and it was only
from my being a very old friend of
the Sultan that it was finished
in so short a time.</p>

<p>The salary of this Consulate
is only $1000. for <unclear/> and I
consider that $500 would be a fiar
recompense for my outside work on this
new treaty.</p>

<pb facs="131420.jpg"/>

<p>My address is the United States
in <unclear/>
<unclear/> Av.
New York, NY
I have the honor to be Sir
Your obedient servant
F. M. Cheney
US Consul</p>

<pb facs="131815.jpg"/>

<p>No. 101
US Consulate
Zanzibar Sept 8 1886</p>

<p>E.C. Roper Jr.
actg US Consul</p>

<p>To The Department of State
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Subject.
Enclosing letter from the
Sultan of Zanzibar</p>

<p>Enclosures</p>

<pb facs="131831.jpg"/>

<p>No. 108.
United States Consulate
Zanzibar Sept 8 1886
To the Hon
Third Assist. Secy of State
Washington DC</p>

<p>Sir:
I have the honor to enclose
herewith a letter from the
Sultan of Zanzibar to the
Department of State, a copy of 
which he has sent to this Consulate
and which I have translated
and also enclose herewith.</p>

<p>The sum and substance of
this communication is, a request
of our Government to sanction
a tax on his own subjects, which
I have assured His Highness will
be undoubtedly granted time.</p>

<p>The Germans and English as
a pretence for making trouble with
the Sultan, claim that he has no
right to levy any taxes or duties
or any produce rained in the Sultanate</p>

<pb facs="131837.jpg"/>

<p>Sultanate of Zanzibar other
tahn is specified in the new
treaties, or on his own subjects.
The Sultan claims that he has
a right to tax his own subjects
as he pleases and produce belong-
ing to them.</p>

<p>This is a matter which
does not in the <unclear/> concern
Americans or American interests
in any way and which I
assume that our Government
will not care for me to take any
part in troubles likely to arise
from this dispute.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be
Sir
Your obdeiant servant
E. D. Roper Jr.
actg US Consul</p>

<p>Enclosures
1/ Letter from the Sultan of Zanzibar
2/ Translation of above letter.</p>

<pb facs="131906.jpg"/>

<p>Translation of a Letter from the
Sultan of Zanzibar to the Secretary of State
Washinton-Sept 7 1886
Verbatim.</p>

<p>In the name of God the <unclear/></p>

<p>To His Excellency the noble, the liberal
and learned minister of Foreign Affairs of
the United States of America, may God prolong
his life in unblemished glory!</p>

<p>We had the honor to inform you in a
telegram of the 6th of August that we directed
a letter to your Excellency, this is the letter.</p>

<p>We have the pleasure to inform your
Exellency, that the new treaties with England
and Germany and the new clauses of duplicate
concluded with your country entered in force
on the 19th of August 1886 corresponding to the
<unclear/> New Year and that the Custom
Hour is in our own hands.</p>

<p>I have to inform you that in the new
treaties are not mentioned fifty five articles
of produce of our grant and on which we al-
ways had 5% duty- this produce has nothing
to do with the imports and exports by Europeans
<unclear/></p>

<pb facs="131924.jpg"/>

<p>it concerns only my own people, who
do not pay any other taxes, so we continue
to tax the fifty-five articles of produce as before
at 5%.</p>

<p>We send you the names of the fifty-
five articles of the named produce in a list
joined to the letter and ask you to consider
it and sanction it. Salaam!</p>

<p>This letter was composed on the 7th
of September corresponding to the 6th of Jul-Hay
1303 of the Hejira.

Signed- <unclear/>
Sultan</p>

<pb facs="131945.jpg"/>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
