<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="DAWSON, KENDALL C." xml:id="KCD"><!-- KENDALL C. DAWSON --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="10017_001.jpg"/>

<p>Consulat Genéral
De L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Chevalier-</p>

<p>Je me fais un plaisir de vous annoncer que
Monsieur le Sénateur Aldrich a commencé prendre un
intérêt spécial au Congo. Pendant l'année passée il s'est
montré assez bienveillant et, de temps en temps, il nous
a fait des services d'ami. Tout dernierement j'ai entamé
avec lui la question de caoutchouc et il s'y intéresse
beaucoup.</p>

<p>Monsieur Aldrich et son gendre Rockefeller (fils) sont
des chefs d'un petit mais très puissant groupe qui prend
un grand intérêt au caoutchouc. Récemment ils ont organisé
une compagnie de trente million de dollars pour exploiter
le caoutchouc de Mexique et d'Amerique du Sud. Suivant ce
qu'ils me disent c'est probable qu'ils désireront s'intéresser
au caoutchouc du Congo d'une manière quelconque.</p>

<p>Monsieur Aldrich a découvert un nouveau procédé par
lequel on peut, avantageusement, extraire du bon caoutchouc
des mauvaises herbes ou des plantes tropicales qui ne
contiennent qu'une petite partie de caoutchouc- qui, en effet
ne contiennent que dix pour cent de caoutchouc sur quatre-
vingt-dix pour cent de matière inutile. </p>

<p>Ils font des expériences depuis cinq annees et, enfin,
ils ont trouvé un procédé qui n'est pas cher. Ils ont déjà
opéré a des plantes de Mexique et ils me disent qu'ils
peuvent produire la quantité énorme de quatre tonnes par jour.</p>

<p>Le Sénateur Aldrich m'a parlé de quatre tonnes par jour.
d'opérer son procédé au Congo et j'ai écrit à Monsieur le
Commandant Liebrechts en lui demandant quelques renseignements
exacts sur les herbes du Congo.</p>

<p>C'est possible que nous avons au Congo une herbe ou une</p>

<p>Monsiur le Chevalier du Cuvelier
Bruxelles.</p>

<pb></pb>

<p>Consulat Général
De
L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>

<p>plante quelconque- meme un plante qui ne contient plus que
dix pour cent de caoutchouc - qui repond au but.</p>

<p>Si on peut extraire du caoutchouc des herbes congolaises
qui jusqu'a present sont restées infructueuses voila une
bonne affaire pour le Congo au point de vue commerciale.</p>

<p>En tout cas - si le procédé reussit au Congo ou non-
le vif interêt du Senateur Aldrich et de Monsieur Rockefeller
au sujet est une bonne affaire pour le Congo au point de
vue politique, et c'est sur cette phase de la question que
je desire specialement tirer votre attention.</p>

<p>Le Senateur Aldrich est tres riche, s'interesse au
nombreux monopoles, et il est très puissant au Senat. Il est
"Republican", et on l'a appelé "The Boss of the Senate".</p>

<p>Rockefeller est, comme vous savez, tres riche fils de
Rockefeller du "Standard Oil Company", et gendre de Monsieur
Aldrich. Il est jeun, serieux- beaucoup trop serieux- et
un "Baptist qui semble prendre un vif interêt aux affaires
religeuses. Il a été dans les rangs de nos adversaires,
et je puis vous dire en confience que, l'annee passée, il a
tenté de gagner les sympathies du Senateur Aldrich pour les
missionaires baptistes anti-congolaises-heureusement sans
reussir.</p>

<p>Si Senateur Aldrich et groupe desireront s'interesser
au caoutchouc du Congo, d'une manière quelconque, la bonne
volunté de Sa Majesté leur sera tres utile. Monsieur Aldrich
le sait bien et ce fait ne le fera pas moins amical au Congo.</p>

<p>Quant à Monsieur Rockefeller ce fait lui donnera, peut-être,
un nouveau point de vue et une nouvelle manière de penser.</p>

<p>Vous reconaitrez l'importance de regarder cette affaire
comme confidentielle pour le moment.</p>

<p>J'ecris a Monsieur le Commandant Liebrechts aujourdhui, et,
naturellement j'ai parle au sujet à Monsieur le Baron Moncheur
aussi confidentiellement.</p>

<p>Veuillez agreer, Monsieur le Chevalier, l'assurance de 
mes meilleurs sentiments.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">
        
<pb facs="10017_001.jpg"/>
        
<p>Consulate General
of the Independent State of the Congo. 
Baltimore.</p>
        
<p>Sir Knight-</p>
        
<p>It gives me pleasure to announce to you that 
Mr. Senator Aldrich started to take a 
special interest in the Congo. During last year he 
showed himself to be rather benevolent and, from time to time, he performed
friendly services for us. Most recently I began the 
discussion of rubber with him and he was interested in it
a lot.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Aldrich and his son-in-law Rockefeller (son) are 
the heads of a small but very powerful group taking 
a great interesst in rubber. Recently they organized 
a company of 30 million dollar to run 
the Mexian and South American rubber. Next what
they told me is that it's likley that they will want to be interested 
in the rubber from the Conge in some way.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Alrich descovered a new manner by 
which one can, to your advantage, extract some good rubber 
from the bad herbs or tropical plants that only 
contain one small part of rubber- that, in effect,
only contain ten percent of rubber over 
90 for 100 of useless material. </p>
        
<p>They've made experiments for five years and, finally,
they found a method that isn't expensive. They have already
worked on Mexican plants and they tell me that they
can produce an enormous quanity of four tons a day.</p>
        
<p>The Senator Aldrich spoke to me about the four tons a day.
To work his process in the Congo and I have written to Mr. 
Major Liebrecht in asking him some exact
details on the plants from the Congo.</p>
        
   <p>It's possible that we have a herb or one in the Congo</p>
        
<p>Sir Knight of the Cuvelier
Brussels.</p>
        
<pb></pb>
        
<p>Consulate General 
of
the Independent State of the Congo.
Baltimore.</p>
        
<p>any plant- even a plant that only contains 
10 percent of rubber- that respond to the goal.</p>
        
<p>If one can extract the Congolese herbs from the rubber 
that up until the present are rested fruitless here a 
good business for the Congo from the commercial point of view.</p>
        
<p>In any case- if the process suceeds in the Congo or not- 
the keen interest from the Senator Aldrich and Mr. Rockefeller
in this subject is a good business for the Congo in a political
point of view, and it's on this phase of the issue that 
I want to specially draw your attention.</p>
        
<p>The Senator Aldrich is very rich, interested in a 
number of monopolies, and he is very powerful int he Senate. He is
"Republican", and is called "The Boss of the Senate".</p>
        
<p>Rockefeller is, as you know, the very rich sone of 
Rockefeller form the "Standard Oil Company", and the son-in-law of Mr. 
Aldrich. He is young, serious- too serious- and 
a "Baptist qui semble prendre un vif interêt aux affaires
religeuses. He was in the ranks of our adversaries, 
and I can tell you in confidence that, last year, he tried
to win the sympathies of Senator Aldrich for the
anti-Congolese Baptist missionaries without 
sucess.</p>
        
<p>If Senator Aldrich and group want to interest themselves
in rubber in the Congo, in any way, the willingness 
of His Majesty will be very useful for them. Mr. Aldrich 
knows it well and this fact will not make it less friendly in the Congo.</p>
        
<p>As for Mr. Rockefeller this fact will give him, maybe,
a new perspective and a new manner of thinking.</p>
        
<p>You will recognize the importance of watching this affaire 
as confidential for the moment.</p>
        
<p>I'm writing to Mr. Major Liebrechts today, and, 
naturally I talked about the subject to Mr. Baron Moncheur
also confidetially.</p>
        
<p>Please accept, Sir Knight, the assurance of 
my best sentiments.</p>
        
<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
