<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0295">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley to Adolphe de Cuvelier, January 22, 1907</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0295</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley to Adolphe de Guvelier</title>
<date when="1907-01-22">January 22, 1907</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 121</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Cummings, Matthew</term>
<term>de Cuvelier</term>
<term>Fox</term>
<term>Gibbons</term>
<term>Kowalski-Wack</term>
<term>Leopold, King</term>
<term>Lodge</term>
<term>Maes</term>
<term>McFaul</term>
<term>Messmer</term>
<term>Moncheur</term>
<term>O'Connell</term>
<term>O'Neil</term>
<term>O'Sullivan, Dennis T.</term>
<term>Shanley</term>
<term>Verner, S. P.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Boston</term>
<term>Brooklyn</term>
<term>Brussels</term>
<term>Chicago</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Connecticut</term>
<term>Denver</term>
<term>Louisville</term>
<term>Massachusetts</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Philadelphia</term>
<term>Rochester</term>
<term>St. Louis</term>
<term>Washington</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>American</term>
<term>Belgian</term>
<term>French</term>
<term>Hibernian</term>
<term>Irish</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Catholic</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
<term>Protestant</term>
<term>Puritan</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Whiteley, James Gustavus</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
<date when="1907-01-22"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>de Cuvelier, Adolphe</persName>
<roleName>Knight</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-11" who="kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="par">Transcribed, translated, and encoded header information.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.001.jpg"/>

<p>CONSULAT GENERAL
DE
L'ETAT INDEPENDENT DU CONGO.
BALTIMORE.</p>

<p>15 FEV 1907</p>

<p>le 22 janvier 1907</p>

<p>Monsieur le Chevalier-
J'ai l'honneur de
vous transmettre <unclear/> des
deux "memorandum" sur le
mouvement catholique que
j'ai envoyé au Baron Moncheur
et au Roi.</p>

<p>La mouvement a eu une
pleine <unclear>reussite</unclear>. Comme
vous voyez par "le memorandum"
nous avons déjà gagné l'appris</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.002.jpg"/>

<p>de plus de deux million
citoyens americains, il
n'y a pas du doute
c'est la force du <unclear/>
catholique qui a <unclear/>
l'attitude du gouvernment
americain.</p>

<p>Veuillez agreer, Monsieur
le Chevalier, l'assurance
de ma consideration la
plus distinguée.
James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.003.jpg"/>

<p>Consulat Général
De 
L'État Indèpendant Du Congo,
Baltimore.</p>

<p>Memorandum on the Catholic Movement in Favor of Congo.</p>

<p>The "Congo Reform Association" has from the beginning,
made its campaign on religious lines. Its agents here are all
protestant ministers, they hold their meeting in churches and
use the societies and organizations of these churches to gather
petitions, to form <sic>committies</sic> and to carry on their propaganda.
It is they who have made it a religious war and they have been
trying to prevent the Catholic Church from realizing that they
have declared war, while they know that the organization of the
Catholic Church is the most powerful body that could oppose them.
The Church has, however, been on guard for the past two years.
In December, 1904, I was invited to attend a council of the most
important dignitaries and laics of the Church to tell them the
Congo situation and since that time they have stood ready to help
us if the necessity should arise.</p>

<p>We had hoped to be able to manage the campaign alone
without their open aid, and we could have done it not been
for this unfortunate Kowalski-Wack affair. The scandal created
by the publication of that affair almost absolutely tied the hands
of our friends in the Senate and created a prejudice against us
in the minds of Senators who otherwise would have been indifferent
or even friendly. Our enemies, taking advantage of the moment,
were pushing the Lodge Resolution. The only thing to prevent the

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.004.jpg"/>

adoption of that resolution was to bring some new and powerful
force to our aid, and the most powerful organization available
was our natural ally, the Church. Fortunately at that moment
our enemies made the mistake of openly attacking the Cardinal
Gibbons. That gave us an opening. The Cardinal replied to the 
attack by a strong defense of the King-Sovereign's administration.
The statement was published all over the country and immediately
had a good effect not only upon Catholics but also upon protestants,
for the Cardinal is greatly admired and respected by all
creeds. The newspapers referred to the Cardinal's utterance in
their editorials and became more cautious and conservative in regard
to intervention in the Congo. The statement had also undoubtedly 
a very favorable effect on the Government at Washington and we
have reason to believe that since that statement appeared (post
hoc ergo propter hoc) the President has taken a more favorable
attitude. There is no doubt that the President and his party pay
great heed to the opinion of the Cardinal and of the Catholic hoping
to gain the political support of the Catholic vote.</p>

<p>The statement of the Cardinal was not enough, however.
It motified the attitude of the Government, but according to the 
views of the most astute politicians among our friends, there was
every probability that the Lodge Resolution would be adopted by
the Senate Committee. The only card left for us to play (and it
is the card most feared by our enemies) was the influence of 
the Catholic Church.</p>

<p>The Catholic Church represents to the American politician 
powerful factor in the politics and a great number of votes. It is 
the only thing to offset the numerous petitions coming into the
Senate from small Baptists, Presbyterians and other churches which
also represent votes to the politician. The politician is governed
by fear of his electors. If he is petitioned by a number of his
electors from small Baptist churches to meddle with the Congo he
will be inclined to do it unless he is made aware that he will
offend other voters. We had to make him aware of this. Calling
to our aid the Catholic societies with their large membership of
American voters was our only chance to restrain the Senate from
rash action against us. It is well known in the United States
that every politician is afraid to meddle with any question which
may offend Catholic votes.</p>

<p>This step was thought a wise political move by our friends
here who best understand the politics of this country. Baron

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.005.jpg"/>

Moncheur and I cabled what steps we were about to take and received
no objections form Brussels. I obtained the approval and 
support of the Highest dignitaries of the Church and then immediately
started to set in motion our friends of the Catholic,
Belgian and Irish societies throughout the country so that they
might protest to the American Government against intervention in
Congo affairs. Fortunately the Senate had adjourned for a holiday
of two weeks at Christmas. This gave me time, by travelling night
and day to cover several thousand mils of territory, to communicate
with such men as Archbishop Messmer, Bishop McFaul, Bishop
Fox, Bishop Maes and about ten other Bishops besides laics of 
importance and also with the heads of various societies of laymen
and with other organizations.</p>

<p>As a result there have been placed before the President
and the Government and before the Senate (upon the reassembling
of the Senate a few days ago) petitions in our favor from individuals
and societies representing nearly two million American 
citizens urging the American Government to refrain from any
interference with the Congo.</p>

<p>As well as I can ascertain the following petitions
representing the sentiments of nearly two million are by this time
already before the Government and Congress:</p>

<list>
<item><sic>Amiercan</sic> Federation of Catholic Societies representing 1,500,000 members</item>
<item>Order of Foresters representing 125,000 members</item>
<item>Catholic Knights of St. Louis</item>
<item>Belgian Society of Chicago</item>
<item>Belgian Protective Society of Denver</item>
<item>Belgian Protective Society of New York</item>
<item>Belgian Union of New York</item>
<item>Belgian Beneficial Society of New York</item>
<item>Several Catholic Societies of Rochester, State of New York.</item>
<item>Individual letters from influential citizens, bishops, laics, &amp;c.
to the President, the Secretary of State and Senators.</item>
<item>Petitions and protests from 700 or 800 citizens of Denver, New
York, Rochester, Louisville and Philadelphia.</item>
</list>

<p>This expression of sentiment in our favor is now before
the American Government representing nearly two million American
citizens.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.006.jpg"/>

<p>In addition we expect that in the next few days there will
reach the American Government the Senate petitions in our favor
from:-</p>

<list>
<item>The Federation of the State of New York</item>
<item>The Federation of the County of New York</item>
<item>About 40 different societies in New York and Brooklyn</item>
<item>About 400 or 500 individual citizens of New York</item>
<item>About 200 or 300 citizens of Chicago</item>
<item>Ancient Order of Hibernians representing 250,000 members</item>
<item>Central Verein representing 100,000 members</item>
<item>Catholic <sic>Bortherhood</sic> of America representing 65,000 members</item>
<item>Catholic Knights of America representing 20,000 members</item>
<item>Western Catholic Union representing 7,000 members</item>
<item>Bohemian Catholic Union representing 10,000 members</item>
<item>Catholic Knights of Ladies of America representing 8,000 members</item>
<item>Women's Catholic Order representing 50,000 members</item>
<item>Irish Catholic Union representing 10,000 members</item>
<item>44 Federation Societies in 44 different States representing 10,000 members</item>
</list>

<p>The above societies are expected not only to petitions in 
favor of the Congo to the President, the Secretary of State and
the Senate <sic>Committe</sic> on Foreign Affairs but also to write to the
Senators form their respective States.</p>

<p>This is a powerful movement we have started. It gives
us the most powerful support we can have. It will not lose us
any of our protestant supporters and it can cause no harm to any
one except to the enemies of the Congo. Our Catholic support
cannot in any way cause embarrassment to the American Government,
if that Government is well disposed toward the Congo. It is
possible that the American Government, if it wishes to meddle in
the Congo, should have preferred that we should not make any 
resistance or any show of strength. If the American Government is
well disposed toward us it will be glad to see us bring <sic>our</sic> all our
forces for this will strengthen the American Governments hand
against the anti-Congo agitators. The only real objection the
American Government could have to such a demonstration is that
(if it is illdisposed towards us) fear of the Catholic vote would
prevent it from carrying out its intention and from taking on
extremely hostile attitude towards us.</p>

<p>It will be observed that in all this movement I have
kept in the background and made it appear that the Catholic movement
was entirely spontaneous. </p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.007.jpg"/>

<p>Our movement may not be entirely successful. We are working
against great odds on account of the Kowalski-Wack affair.
If we succeed it will be snatching victory out of defeat.
In any case, even if the Lodge Resolution is adopted, the fact
that we have Catholic support will undoubtedly prevent the American
Government from any extremely aggressive movement which it might
wish to take.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

<p>Seventh January. </p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.008.jpg"/>

<p>Massachusetts Catholic Order of Foresters.</p>
    
<p>Boston, Mass., Jan. 16, 1907.</p>

<p>His Majesty, King Leopold,
Belgium</p>

<p>His Majesty:-</p>

<p>The High Standing Committee of the Massachusetts
Catholic Order of Foresters, representing 100,000 souls, in meeting
assembled January 14th, 1907, endorsed the following resolution:-</p>

<p>WHEREAS it has come to our knowledge that accusations
have been made against King Leopold's administration of the
Congo Free State.</p>
    
<p>WHEREAS we believe that these accusations are unfounded
and are inspired by religious jealousy and by the desire
of a certain strong nation to extend its power in Africa.</p>
    
<p>Be it resolved, and it is hereby resolved:</p>
    
<p>That we deprecate the use of means such as have marked
the action of our protestant bretheren in this matter; the defaming
of an individual is a serious breach of Christ's Commands;
the defaming of a whole nation and of a Christian King is most
serious.</p>
    
<p>Resolved, second, that relying on the testimony
of trustworthy Catholic Bishops and missionaries in the Congo, of
travellers who have visited the country and who know the actual
conditions prevailing there, and of the impartial commissioners
who recently reported on the subject, we see no greater reason
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.009.jpg"/>
    
for an international investigation of King Leopold's rule in the
Congo than for an international investigation of the administration
of any other Power in Africa.</p>
    
<p>Resolved, third, that no body of men will go farther
to redress the human misery than members of this organization.</p>
    
<p>Resolved, fourth, that we extend to the caluminated
King our sympathy with him in this matter in which he has been so 
unjustly <sic>occused</sic>.</p>
    
<p>Resolved, fifth, that copies of these resolutions
be sent to the President of the United States, the Secretary of
State, the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, the two Senators
from Massachusetts, and to His Majesty, King Leopold.</p>
    
<p>Attest--<lb/>
(signed) John J. Leonard<lb/>
High Secretary-Treasurer.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.010.jpg"/>

<p>Report on Visit to Boston and New York, January 11-18, 1907.</p>
    
<p>The Catholic movement seems to have produced the most
excellent results upon the President and the Secretary of State as well
as upon the Senate, and I am specifically glad to be able to report the
success of my mission to Boston which is not only the centre of the anti-
Congo agitation but is also the home of the electors of Senator Lodge
who has brought in the Resolution against us.</p>
    
<p>Boston is the centre of the Baptist missionary societies and
of many fantastic "reforms" movements but there is also a strong and 
growing Catholic element there whose influence in politics is sought 
even by Senator Lodge and other "puritans". During my visit to Boston
I have been fortunate enough to interest their strong Catholic element
in our cause and to arouse them to active work in our behalf.</p>
    
<p>His Grace, Monsignor O'Connell, Archbishop of Boston, received
me most sympathetically and has promised me his support. The
Catholic "Federation" of that district has already sent to the President
and to the Senate a petition in our behalf.</p>
    
<p>Last Monday night in Boston I met the High Council of the
Massachusetts Catholic Order of Foresters, which represents one hundred
thousand of Senator Lodge's electors and as a result, chiefly through
the sympathetic aid of the Rev/Father O'Neil, Spiritual Advisor of the
Order, they took up the cause of the Congo and adopted resolutions in 
our favor which were at once transmitted to the President of the United
States, the Secretary of State, to the Senate, to Mr. Lodge, and other
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.011.jpg"/>
    
Senators. The Order of Foresters also desire that a copy of their 
resolution should be presented to His Majesty, and I have the honor
to transmit a copy herewith, with the suggestion that some acknowledgment
and response be sent the Order through us, as soon as possible.</p>
    
<p>The Boston "Alumni Sodality" also took a great interest in the
matter. The question was presented to them through the Rev. Father
Dennis T. O'Sullivan who has spoken publicly in favor of the Congo 
on several occasions. I understand that the "Alumni Sodality" is
sending to the Government petitions in our favor as a society and 
that the individual members are also working for us.</p>
    
<p>The Catholic Union which has among its members some of the
most important Catholic citizens of Boston has also taken up our
cause. They will have a lecture and discussion on the Congo as soon
as possible and will then probably adopt resolutions similar to the
resolutions adopted by other Catholic societies. The President of 
the Catholic Union has taken a person interest and may be expected
to aid us in every way possible.</p>
    
<p>The "Federation" of Boston is to hold a meeting tonight
(January 20) to discuss the French Church question and also the
Congo and still further action may be expected from them to promote
our interests.</p>
    
<p>I also had several meetings with Mr. Matthew Cummings, the
President of the Irish Society known as the "Ancient Order of Hibernians".
He is an important politician in Boston and the Hibernians
constitute a well-known and influential society of about two hundred
thousand men. He manifests a deep interest in our case and promised
me to bring the matter up before the High Council of the Order last
night, when they probably will have adopted resolutions in our favor
to be sent to the President, Secretary of State and the Senate.</p>
    
<p>It seems thus that we have aroused a strong element in our
favor in Boston and have, by my visit there, secured the active help
of between three hundred thousand and four hundred thousand of Mr. 
Lodge's own electors. This is sure to have a good effect on Lodge 
as well as us on the other Senators. We have secured a strong support
even in the midst of the enemy's camp.</p>
    
<p>In addition to this aid from the State of Massachusetts I 
have been able, through the help of the Rev. Father Shanley, to secure 
important assistance from the neighboring State of Connecticut.</p>
    
<p>Petitions to the President and to the Senate were sent, at my
request, form several Catholic Association of that State, among others
from the "St. Peters Corporate Society" numbering nearly five thousand
members, and the matter is brought to the attention of other societies
which may be expected to act soon.</p> 
    
<p>In addition to these societies I was enabled while on this
trip to get into communication with the "Catholic Young Men's National
Union" numbering fifty thousand, which without loss of time, sent
an expression of its sentiments in our favor to Washington by telegram.</p>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.012.jpg"/>

<p>Father Shanley also requested the "Catholic Temperance
Association Union of America" which has ninety thousand members
to take similar action. I have not yet received official notice but
it is probable that they have taken the requested action by this
time.</p>
    
<p>In New York I found that the agitation which we had started
<sic>amont</sic> the Catholic societies is still continuing satisfactorily and
I am endeavoring to encourage the movement there as much as possible.</p>
    
<p>The Catholic movement has not only intimidated our enemies
in the Senate and encouraged our friends in the same body, but it
has also encouraged our friends everywhere and especially our friends
in the new Concessionary companies who seem now disposed to work 
harder for us politically than they were four years ago at the time
of the Kowalski-Wack publications. I seized the opportunity while 
in New York to urge them to greater endeavor. I think that the very
fact of the existence of the American Concessionary Companies has been
an influence in our favor and has had some effect in making the Government
and the Senate more conservative but I hope now to get the
people interested in the companies to work more actively. At my
suggestion the American-Congo Company has employed as one of its agents
Mr. S. P. Verner, who has been in the Congo several years and whose
name is well known to the Chevalier de Cuvelier. As Verner is impartial
and honest and knows about the true condition of the Congo
I have urged upon the Company that they should allow Verner to go to
Washington at once and see the President, the Secretary of State and
various Senators in order to put the true state of affairs before them.</p>

<p>I have found every where I have been in this country in the
past four weeks that the defence of the King Sovereign's administration
by Cardinal Gibbons has made a deep and lasting impression.</p>

<p>I feel assured that it is the Catholic movement that has held
the Senate in check for the past several weeks. The Resolutions of 
Societies, and the petitions of individuals, as well as certain person
influence and personal letter written by friends of Senators
have undoubtedly produced a very favorable effect. If we can continue
the movement with sufficient vigor we may be able to avert any action
by Congress, but, in any event, the expression of opinion which we
have placed before Congress and before the Government is sure to have
a decided effect in modifying any hostile action which the Government
may have momentarily contemplated while under the pressure of the
Baptist and other Protestant missionaries.</p>

<p>While on this trip in the North I have still continued to
keep in communication with the individuals and societies in the West 
whom I visited two weeks ago, and I shall continue to encourage them
to keep up the movement they have started in favor of the Congo.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley<lb/>
Consul General.</p>

</div1>
<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.001.jpg"/>

<p>CONSULATe GENERAL
OF
THE CONGO FREE STATE.
BALTIMORE.</p>

<p>15 FEV 1907</p>

<p>January 22 1907</p>

<p>Monsieur le Chevalier-
I have the honor to
to transmit to you <unclear/> the
two "memorandums" on the
catholic movement that
I sent to the Baron Moncheur
and to the King.</p>

<p>The movement had a
full <unclear>success</unclear>. As
you see in "the memorandum"
we already won l'appris</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0295.002.jpg"/>

<p>of more than two million
american citizens, there
is no doubt
it is the force of the <unclear/>
catholic that <unclear/>
the attitude of the american
government.</p>

<p>Please accept, Mister
Knight, the assurance
of my most distinguished
consideration.
James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>