<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


Microcopy No. T-438 DESPATCHES FROM UNITED STATES CONSULS IN SIERRA LEONE, 1858-1906 Roll 1 Volume 1 February 22, 1858- March 28,1881 THE NATIONL ARCHIVES NATIONAL ARCHIVES AND RECORDS SERVICE GENERAL SERVICES ADMINISTRATION Washington: 1960 Vol. 1 Sierra Leone Feb. 22, 1858 June 30 1882

You will at once see Sir, that the position which I now hold Acting Consul an Acting for and without  appointment from the United States Government, but merely by the nomination of the Commodore before-named invests me in strict law with no actual legal authority. I am recognized as Acting counsul by the local Government, as it seems to me, merely through courtesy, and I cannot close my eyes to the fact, that, had I attempted to make any stand in opposition to the Government in recent cases of aggresion by British Cruizers on American Vessels in the Coast, any further recognition whatever of me even through courtesy would have at once ceased. 

As you are aware, the several vessels seized on the Coast  on the alleged ground of being engaged in the Slave Trade are all sent  to the Colony for adjudication, or, I should rather observe for condemnation.

I stake the liberty of enclosing for your inspection a List of the Prizes taken by H. R. Majestys Cruizers and sent into this Port. I will also mention that during the period I have been Acting Counsel there have arrived in this Port  no fewer than 120 American Vessels comprizing a Tonnage of over 25000 Tons, and with crews consisting of 1100 men, exclusive of three United States Ships of War. 

You will have in mind for, that the British Government do not fail, to maintin a Counsel at Liberia, and it is I am sure almost unnecessary for me to remark in Point of Comparison with Sierra Leone, Liberia sinks into insignificance. 

Under the circumstances I have disclosed to you I venture to submit, for your consideration my lengthenend service as Acting Counsel and inadequacy of pay I have received through fees alone and which have been considerably reduced by resent Acts of Congress.

I earnestly trust Sir, that you will see the urgent necessity  for appointing a Counsel at this place, and that in the exercise of your <unclear=one word/>, you will be pleased to counsel such appointment on me with <unclear extent=two/> as you may, think proper to itain the dignity of our great nation. 

I have the honor to be, Sir, With high respects, Your most <unclear=one word/> honorable Servant Jno E Taylor Acting United States Counsel.