<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


Consulate of the United States
of America at Sierra Leone
31st December 1861

Sierra Leone yearly report

I have the honor to forward the following report in acordance with the consular instructions as contained in the 153rd and 154th sections of the consular regulations.

The colony of sierra Leone <unclear> ceded </unclear> to the English in the year 1787 by the native <unclear extent= two words/> embraces an extent of aout 5 or square miles, its southern point- <unclear extent=three words/> in about 8 <degree sign/>  10' in latitude and its southern point <unclear> freelines</unclear> lies in about 8 <degree sign/> 30' it is mostly mountainous land having an elevation of from <unclear/> to 25 ou feet above thee level of the sea, it was first <unclear> nettlect by a fiarty of </unclear> few blacks from Nova Scotia in the year 1792 and their descedents are to this day called letters, in the Colony. 

The colony is divided into four districts the 1st and 2nd Eastern comprisig the vilages of Kessy, Welington, Hastings, Newlands, Allentown, Rokelle, Frasertown, Denham, and Waterlou, the mountain district comprising Wilberforce, Merrytown, Aberdeen Gloucester, Bathurst, Request and Charlotte, the Banana islands, dependencies of the Colony are also included in this district and included in this district and have the small vilages of Dublin and Ricketts on them, the Western district includes the vilages of Hamilton, York, Goodrich and Heut, each district is under the charge of officer styled manager who is accountable to the colonial government in Freetown the sea-pert and capitol of the colony. 

The government of the colony is <unclear> vestel</unclear> in the Goverbot, and a council of fewer members, all of whom hold colonial appointments under the Leone government wit the exception of one, a merchant of the colony, the following are the gentlemen of the council, John Carr Chief Justice E.H. Beccler, Bishop, A. ityjames Queens advocate Gov. N. Nicel Colonial secretary, T Commissing Collector, R. Bradshaw Colonial Surgeon, and Cader Hedder merchant, all of whom are styled <unclear> favorable </unclear> , they are only responsible to the home governemnt, and the laws they pass and submitted to the Queen and confirmed by the before the colonists are aware of their entrance, people of the colony have no <unclear> choice </unclear> whatever in their government, neither in the election of the members of council above mentioned. 

The commerce of the colony has fallen off considerably the past year in consequence of the American difficulties, and a failure of the ground-nut crop.

For a <unclear/> of the imports and exports of this colony I would refer you to the snnul report from this consulate for this yer 1860.

The imports from the United States for the present year show a fair average with those of past-years of the general state of commerce is taken int considertion, the colony being to a great extent dependent on the United States for several of the staple articles of its trade our difficulties have naturally interfer with the general facilities of trade, the following table given . correct <unclear> eden </unclear> of the imports for the present year.

Table of Imports 
Article Quantity Value 
Tobacco 609 <unclear/> $182,700 00
N.E. Rum 2267 Barrels 30,000 00
Flour 1030 do 8,240 00
Bread 510 do 3,100 00
Shingles 450,000 2,250 00
Boards 482,000 fest 12,320 00
Cotton Cards 113 Cases 226 bag 904 00
Tabacco 200 Bales 3,000 00
Cotton Goods 160 Packages 17,600 00
Beef 60 Barrels 900 00
Smoke Herring 1287 Boyes 643 50
Soap 250 do 1500 00
Candles 115 do 575 00
Total of Value $263,742 50

With the above imports we have <unclear> undry small consequments</unclear> of Quincy bays, Corn meal Alewives, Mackerel. Sactfish, Herring in barrels, Gunpowder, Bulten, Cheese, <unclear>Lord; Biscuit, Herouni Vil, Heroo Lamer Pamilo, Maucula hemp cpldage, Quince, Potatoes, Pork, Hames Oars, Chaves, Bedstend, Plat-form Seales, Jruvall Boats, Brown, and Nleite Bitters, Ceder Medicines, Coal-tor, For, Pitch, Nails, Trunks Cigards se, se, se. community  in the aggregate to about $50,000.00 giving a ground total of $313,742.50. </unclear>

The exports to the United States for the same year show the following, requires; vig-

Table of Exports
Article Quantities Value 
Hides 104,605 wight 1,043,450 ths $153900 00
Palm Vil 583 Casks 68940 gals 34,470 00
Ginger 201 Tons 19807 00
Ground0nuts 15000 Beerfeels 7500 00
$215,677 00

Bender there the following articles are chipped in small quanitities Camwood, Aloe Copper, Old competition Ivory, Coffee, Hove, Leopard skins shelled, Pepprs, Arrowort, Old fro se, se, se valued about 30,000 00

Grand total of exports $245,677 00

The excess of importations over exportations s accounted for, by vessels taking Hecie and Native gold, which is not reportd, an also by the rshipment of <unclear/> goods in the <unclear> source </unclear> bottoms adjacent rivers.

The subjournal table will show the amount of American Courage employed in the trade between this colony and the United States. 

Arrivals
No Vessels Tonnage No Men
23 47,799 196
Departures
25 5,215 215

The ground-nut drop for the past year has been a complete failure, ingood seasons this is a very important item in the commerce of the colony and attract a large amount of French Tonnage for its exportation, this article inds its best market in France and in consequennce of the very heavy differential duties in that country imported on all foreign vessels the carrying is <unclear> unpologized, unauthorized </unclear> by French shipping. 

There has been considerable of the land about this colony ceded to the English during the past year.

The territory in the Sherbio country known as Revels was ceded to this colony by Thomas Stephen Caulker, Sherbio chief, and H.W.S.S Falcon, Commander Henerage took formal possession of it o the 28th of March by <unclear> leorsting </unclear> the English flag and firing a royal salute.

Tuesday April 2nd A treaty was concluded, between Governor Hill of this colony and a native chief styling himself Bek-Cantah King of Luia. By this treaty a portion of the Luia country directly inland of the colony, about 16 miles long and 10 miles wide is ceded to the colony, the King of Luia receiving an annual stipend of L 100 as an equivalent

Msny of the cheifs of the Luia country and especialy those those owning the particular portio of land refuse to acknowledge the treaty as they were not consulted with regard to it and the so-called King of Luia had not the power to make much transfer of their country without their consent.

These chiefs have without doubt the best-side of the argument as the stipulations of the treaty were agreed to at a public meeting in Freetown where Ben cautah and the cheifs with them had no option but to ngin any article <unclear> megible </unclear> just before them. On expidition was fitting out at this port for the purpose of furnishing the, chiefs of the Luia country who had been quietly of several outrages upon quiet Sierra Leone traders, Ben-Cantah and a few chiefs with <unclear/> came to town, voluntarily to beg their country might-not be invaded and to <unclear/> the illegal acts above referred to advantage was taken of their <unclear/> in town to oblige them to <unclear/> the beauty, instead of the expedition invading their territory and these dictating the <unclear/> there was the power to enforce it. As the chiefs in possession of the land disputes the English right to it, ar was declared against them, and after six weeks hard fighting the people were expolled with great loss of life and sacrifice of great number of their towns which were destroyed by fire. An other difficulty also arises from treaty, it is that the giving of the land to the England stops a much frequented slave path of the tribes of the coast above and below the colony infaclit is then only communication and being deprived of it causes diseation and quareling among themselves. The war with the Luia country has not been out all <unclear> peopular </unclear> in the colony.

In the earl part of November last a very large extent of country was ceded to this colony and is nowunde its jurisdiction, it comprises nearly all of the Sherbo Country which includes the Sherbo island the Turtle islands, Bagre, MMammon Bagre and Bailey rivers with their dependencies and all lands adjacent to Bends the land ceder in March last.

On the 6th of August cart-Lagos a territory a short distance down the coast was ceded to the English by Docermo King of Lagos, we now hear reports of trouble the, as he has become dessertified with what he then did. A few days <unclear/> a company of voldiers passed down the Gambia.

The French are very deserous of aquiring territory on this chart and consquently look with a jealous eye on the late acquistions to the British crown. 

The American difficulties having excited the fears of the cotton consumers in England, they are making every effort to be less dependent on the United State for supply. A company has been recently formed in England styles the British and New African Cotton Company with a capital of <moneypound/> 100,000 among other objects in view, is that of <unclear/> 10,000 acres of land in Sierra Leone fo the purpose of raising Cotton by free labor. Cotton of a very fair quality grows spontaneously in the Sherbo, use all lots of which has already found its way to the English market.

There have been but Eight cases of slave adjudicated in the counts of this colony for the last year and two only of there had slaves on board,

The "Clara Windson" arrived January 1st with 590 slaves on board the had when taken 677, 87 having died on the passage to this part. 
The "Flight (formerly the "Fairy" of New York) arrivd May 31st with 509 slave on board, she had when taken 539, 37 having died on the passage. Of the slaves arriving here five hundred were sent to the Gambi February the 21st, three hundred and ninety five sent to the West Indies in the ship "Paterson" which ruled November 27th. Presidents of the colony have taken severl of the children to being them up as servants, and there are yet guide a number let in the year at Rissy, enclosed is the form of certificate given to them on emgrating.

Among the arrvals of vessels to this prt the past years were 50 English, 18 French and 3 Spanish <unclear/> of war, during a <uncear/> of three years in this part not a single American ship of war has visited the harbr, it is very desirable they should call at time as our commerce is quite important and should not be left altogether without protection, I am frequently asked by residents,why, <unclear/> the importance of out <uncear/> intercourse with the Colony a vessel of the United States is never seem im their watens? 

The <unclear/> was amon the native chiefs island of the colony the colonal was wih the Luia people, the American difficulties, stopping the supply of American gords which are staple articles of trade, the fears of war between Great Britain and the United States, altogether have a very depressing efect upon business generally.

The colony is now mourning for the Prince Counsout, <unclear extent= two words/> doing, and every-over looking anxiously for the news by the next Royal mail <unclear/> Four English ships of war in the harbor.

Henry Rider M.J. Consular Agent