<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0278">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- DOCUMENT TITLE + DATE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Etienne to Under Secretary of State, August 14, 1889 --></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0278</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Roncière Lenour to Mister Director of the Colonies--></title>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 226, Liasse 167</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PEOPLE NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PLACES NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT FROM --></placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT TO --></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-30" who="kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0278.001.jpg"/>

<p>Personnelle</p>

<p>223 West Lanvale street<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland,<lb/>
Etats-Unis d’Amérique<lb/>
le 28 décembre 1918.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre,</p>
    
<p>A mon retour aux Etats-Unis j'ai trouvé que nos
ennemis ont déjà recommencé leur campagne contre la colonie.
Le révérend Johnson, de Boston, et le révérend Joseph Clark,
missionaire baptist au Congo (toujours compères de cette
comédie) sont allés à Monsieur Root, Secrétaire d'Etat,
pour se plaindre, au nom de la "Congo Reform Association",
contre les conditions d'annexion. Monsieur Root a reçu la
députation mais n'a pas repandu à leur discours. (annexe 1)</p>
    
<p>Les organes de la "Congo Reform Association" ont aussi
renouvellé leurs attaques en disant que l'annexion n'a pas
changé la situation et en insistant sur une conférence internationale.
(annexe 2.)</p>
    
<p>Dans ces circonstances j'ai saisi l'occasion de ma rentrée
de donner une entrevue à la presse et de jeter du jour sur la
question. Presque tous les journaux importants de New York et
de Baltimore ont publié cette entrevue, sous des formes diverses.
Dans quelques-unes il y a des inexactitudes, mais sans importance.</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous faire parvenir sous ce pli; quelques spécimens
de cette entrevue. Votre Excellence remarquera que j'ai tiré

<fw type="footer">Son Excellence
Monsieur Renkin
Ministre des Colonies.</fw>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0278.002.jpg"/>
    
attention spéciale sur la générosité du Roi en dotant la
Belgique d'une pareille colonie; sur la régime strictement
parlementaire qui commence; sur la personalité du nouveau
Ministre des Colonies; et sur la modification d'opinion qui
s'est opéré chez Monsieur Vandervelde.</p>

<p>Je vous prie de vouloir bien pardonner la signature que
je fais de la main gauche à cause d'une fracture du bras
droit que j'ai reçu en tombant avec mon cheval.</p>
    
<p>Beuillez agréer, Monsieur le Ministre, l'assurance de ma
considération la plus distinguée.</p>
    
<p>Whiteley</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0278.001.jpg"/>

<p>Private</p>

<p>223 West Lanvale street<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland,<lb/>
United States of America<lb/>
28 December 1908.</p>

<p>Mr. Minister,</p>
    
<p>Upon my return from the United States I found that our 
enemies have already started their campaigns against the colony. 
The reverend Johnson, of Boston, and the revered Joseph Clark,
baptist missionary in the Congo (always friends of this 
comedy) went to Mr. Root, Secretary of State, 
to complain, in the name of the "Congo Reform Association",
against the conditions of annexation. Mr. Root received the 
deputation but did not extend to their speech. (annex 1)</p>
    
<p>The organs of the "Congo Reform Association" have also 
renewed their attacks saying that the annexation has not 
changed the situation and emphasized an international conference
(annex 2.)</p>
    
<p>In these circumstances I seized the opportunity of my return 
to give an interview to the press and shed light on the 
issue. Almost all the important New York and Baltimore 
journals and published this interview, under different forms.
In a few there are some inaccuracies, but nothing significant.</p>
    
<p>I have the honor to transmit herewith; some examples 
of this interview. Your Excellence will see that I pulled

<fw type="footer">Your Excellence  
Mr. Renkin
Minister of the Colonies.</fw>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0278.002.jpg"/>
    
special attention on the generosity from the King by giving
Belgium such a colony; on the strictly parliamentarian 
regime that begins; about the new personality 
of the Minister of Colonies; and about the modification of opinions that 
happened at Mr. Vandervelde's.</p>

<p>I urge you to forgive the signature that
I made with my left hand because of a fracture on my right 
arm that I received falling off my horse.</p>
    
<p>Please accept, Mr. Minister, the assurance of my 
most distinguished consideration.</p>
    
<p>Whiteley</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
