<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0966">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to Charles Payson, January 1879</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0966</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to Charles Payson</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1879-01">January 1879</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</term>
<term>Barclay, Ernest James</term>
<term>Hyndman, Edward</term>
<term>Ramos</term>
<term>Springle</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1879-01"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Payson, Charles</persName>
<roleName>Third Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1879-03-14"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-10" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2081.jpg"/>

<p>C. No. 7.</p>

<p><del>Legation</del> Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, Jan'y 1879.</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to 3d Ass't Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Case of Edward Hyndman, late mate of the schooner "Cupid."</p>

<p>Synopsis:</p>

<p>Claim of Thirty two dollars as balance due him as wages withheld by me; the facts and circumstances of the case set forth.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2082.jpg"/>

<p>C. No. 7.</p>

<p><del>Legation</del> Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, Jan'y 1879.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Your No. 1, dated December 19, 1878, received, and in reply, I have the honor respectfully to submit the facts and circumstances of the case of Edward Hyndman, late mate of the schooner "Cupid."</p>

<p>Sixty two dollars were not at any time deposited with me to the credit of said Hyndman, by the captain of the "Cupid." Sixty dollars were paid me on account of wages of Edward Hyndman as mate, by captain Springle of schooner "Cupid."</p>

<p>After paying of this amount, $30. to Hyndman, at his request, in presence of the captain, I did retain $30. at his Hyndman's request, and on his application for this balance, $30., did refuse to pay him, and still refuse.</p>

<p><catchwords>On</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. Chas. Payson,<lb/>
Third Ass't Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2083.jpg"/>

On the 16th of September, 1878, four days after the destruction of the "Cupid", captain Springle of said schooner accompanied by said Hyndman, called at the Legation, and Springle informed me that Hyndman had not received any advanced wages, and had drawn no money from the time of his shipment up to the time of the destruction of the "Cupid." He said he desired to pay him (Hyndman) what was due him in my presence, whereupon I calculated the amount due to be $62.00/100.</p>

<p>Sixty dollars were handed me by captain Springle as the money of Hyndman, which I received, and receipted for, and was requested by Hyndman to let him (Hyndman) have $30. and to retain the balance ($30.) subject to his <unclear>call</unclear>.</p>

<p>The amount due from the captain was $62.00, but said he to me and Hyndman that he had no more money with him, but if Hyndman would go with him to Mr. <sic>Earnest</sic> Jas. Barclay (the agent of captain Springle for the sale of the cargo) he would pay him the $2.00, at his (Springle) request, as B. has the money for the sale of the <catchwords>cargo</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2084.jpg"/>

cargo, which had not been paid over. I have no information as to whether Hyndman ever received the $2.00 which would have made the $62. due him. Mr. Barclay's temporary absence from Monrovia presents me from learning the fact as to the payment or non payment of the $2.00.</p>

<p>Up to this time I had supposed Hyndman, like the crew, to have been destitute, and he shared the lodgings and provisions which had been furnished them.</p>

<p>After receiving his money, he said he would continue to mess with the men, and did so up to the time, and after his conviction with <unclear>Ramos</unclear> of conspiracy to set fire to the "Cupid."</p>

<p>After judgement and his committal, in consequence of the bad food given the prisoners, by the jail authorities, they were still, (Hyndman, <unclear>Ramos</unclear>) fed from the mess of the crew as before at the expense of the United States; notwithstanding the fact that I had desired Mr. Aenmey, V.C. Gen'l <catchwords>not</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2085.jpg"/>

not to feed them, they being prisoners of the Liberian government. By reference to my No. 10, dated Oct. 3, 1878, the facts as to the trial and conviction are set forth in extenso.</p>

<p>On the refusal of Hyndman after his release, and others to be sent home with captain Hubbard of the "Fury", I discontinued the rental of lodgings for them and further support.</p>

<p>In my No. 9, dated Oct. 30, 1878, you will observe the manner in which the men were provided for, as to lodgings and food.</p>

<p>As I held in my possession $30.00 of Hyndman's wages, I aggregated the cost of providing for the men, I equalized him with the others with whom he had elected to mess, and paid from his money in my custody, his pro rata share, which was $26.25/100, and there was left a balance of $3.75 in my hands to his credit, subject to his demand.</p>

<p>On the 9th of October, I sent him (Hyndman), at his request to Sierra Leone to the U.S. Consul, the probability of getting a ship there, bound to U.S. being greater than here.</p>

<p><catchwords>He</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2086.jpg"/>

He sailed in the steamer "Loanda", and I paid the purser of said steamer $5.00 for his fare and gave Hyndman 25¢ for purpose of his food.</p>

<p>The day before sailing he requested of me his money, $30. not $32., and thereupon I deducted for his lodging and board Twenty six 25/100 doll's, and handed him the balance $3.45. So that, he is really indebted to the U.S. $1.25; for I should have applied the balance to defray his transit to Sierra Leone, but that I had not determined to send him there until Oct. 9, when he met me at the post office and desired me to send him by the steamer which had just arrived, and I forgot to call his attention to the $3.75, I had given him on the 8th of October.</p>

<p>As an additional verification of the facts and circumstances as stated, and an evidence that he had no claim for $30. nor $32., please find enclosed his receipt in full for the $30 written by me, read, acquired in, and signed by him, which ought, taken together with the foregoing, to <sic>estopp</sic> him from further pretensions of claim upon me for money not his.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your very obd't serv't<lb/> 
Jno. H. Smyth.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2087.jpg"/>

<note>Inclosure:</note>

<note>1 Receipt of Edward Hyndman.</note>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Oct 8, 1878</p>

<p>Received of Capt. Springle sixty dollars for and on account of Edward Hyndman, being amount due him for wages up to the time of the destruction of the schooner Cupid Sept. 12 '78</p>

<p>Paid to Edward Hyndman $30
Sept. 16, 1878, and 3.75
Oct. 5, 1878 after deducting for rent of lodgings and board twenty six 22/100, 26.25</p>

<p>Jno H Smyth<lb/>
Minister &amp;c</p>

<p>Received balance due me $3.75</p>

<p>Edward Hyndman</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>