<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Conditions in the Congo State: Grounds for Action by the United States Government (1904)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0020</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Conditions in the Congo State: Grounds for Action by the United States Government</title>
<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>Judd &amp; Detwiler</publisher>
<date when="1901">1904</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-13" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Conditions in the Congo State</p>

<p>Grounds for Action by the United States Government</p>

<p>Synopsis of Case</p>

<p>With Citations from State Papers and Other Sources</p>

<p>Washington, D.C.<lb/>
Judd &amp; Detweiler, Printers<lb/>
1904</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p2"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Important Dates in the Development of the Congo State.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The founding of the Congo State resulted from the opening of Central Africa through the explorations of Mr. Henry M. Stanley. An association was quickly formed, under the leadership of King Leopold of Belgium, for further exploration, with a view to occupation of the country. The association, having received recognition by the Powers, became the Congo State.</p>

<p>Mr. Stanley arrives at the mouth of the Congo, completing his journey across Africa, August 12, 1877.</p>

<p>Comité d'Etudes du Haut-Congo, formed by King Leopold for study of conditions in the Congo territory, November 20, 1878.</p>

<p>Stanley revisits central Africa, under the auspices of the Comité, August, 1879, to June, 1882; December, 1882, to January, 1884.</p>

<p>The Comité becomes Interenational Association of the Congo, January, 1883.</p>

<p>Tentative treaty of England with Portugal, recognizing Portuguese claims in West Africa as opposed to those of International Association, February 26, 1884.</p>

<p>Recognition of International Association of the Congo by the United States Government, April 22, 1884.</p>

<p>The Association promises to France a reversionary interest in its territories, April 23, 1884.</p>

<p>International Association recognized by Germany, November 8, 1884.</p>

<p>International Conference of fourteen Powers convenes at Berlin for consideration of problems in Congo territory, November 15, 1884, to January 26, 1885.</p>

<p>International Association recognized by Great Britain, December 16, 1884; by Italy, December 19, 1884; by Austro-Hungary, December 24, 1884; by other Powers, December 27, 1884, to February 23, 1885.</p>

<p>The king bequeaths to Belgium the succession to his interests in the Congo State, August 2, 1889.</p>

<p>International Conference convenes at Brussels to devise measures for suppression of slave trade, November 22, 1889, to July 2, 1890.<lb/>
At this Conference the Congo State seeks and gains permission for imposition of import duties.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

</div2>

<pb n="p5"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>Conditions in the Congo State.</p>

<p>Grounds for Action by the United States Government.</p>

<p>A Synopsis of Case as viewed by the Conference by which Memorial of April, 1904, was addressed to Congress. *</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Societies composing the conference appear in the case not primarily as complainants, but as transmitters of testimony received by them which their moral responsibility requires them to make known (1).</p>

<p>The Defendant in the case is King Leopold, not Belgium (2).</p>

<p>THE CASE UNIQUE.</p>

<p>A single man claims unlimited sovereign power and proprietorship in a territory embracing one million square miles.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>* For Memorial see <hi rend="italics">Senate Documeent No. 282, 58th Congress, 2d session.</hi></note>

<note>1 For relation of missionaries to the issue, see in general pp. 16, 17 of Memorial. Cf. Rev. J. H. Weeks in letter to Congo officials: "I deeply regret having to write this letter to you but I cannot sit quietly and see these unfortunate folk crushed out of existence by oppression and cruelty without making a protest in the name of religion and humanity."</note>

<note>Compare also: "A white officer unacquainted with the missionary whom he was addressing, after a cruel raid, jokingly remarked that he had killed many people and secured a fine lot of curios. He said that while his soldiers were firing upon the villages the people ran wildly about, crying, 'Sheppite, Sheppite.' It was their name for Rev. W. H. Sheppard, whom they were beseeching to come to their aid."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Cited in Memorial to Congress, p. 17.</hi></note>

<note>2 "The union between Belgium and the new State shall be exclusively personal."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Action of Belgian Parliament, April, 1885.</hi></note>

<note>Belgium holds treaty relations with the Congo State substantially identical with those sustained by other Powers.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p6"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>THE ORIGINAL RECOGNITION OF THE CONGO STATE.</p>

<p>This recognition secured through professions of philanthropy and interest in the promotion of unrestricted commerce for all nations (3).</p>

<p>THE REQUEST MADE IN MEMORIAL.</p>

<p>Congress is asked to take action in promotion of an impartial investigation of present conditions in the Congo State.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Grounds upon which the request is made:</hi></p>

<p>I. An impartial inquiry is demanded in view of prevalent reports of grave abuses in the administration of the Congo State.</p>

<p>The reports are sufficient in volume and definiteness to justify and require impartial investigation.</p>

<p>They present a dreadful catalogue of alleged wrongs, involving accusation of excessive cruelties, massacres, mutilations, cannibalism, and the threatened extermination of tribes and depopulation of large territories.</p>

<p>They imply not exceptional instances of inhumanity but its prevalence throughout the vast rubber district, as the result of the system maintained by the State.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>3 "Our only program, I am anxious to repeat, is the work of moral and material regeneration."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">King Leopold, 1885.</hi></note>

<note>"The objects of this Society are philanthropic. It does not aim at permanent political control but seeeks the neutrality of the valley."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Message of President Arthur, December, 1883.</hi></note>

<note>"The fundamental idea of this program is to facilitate the access of all commercial nations to the interior of Africa."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Prince Bismarck's opening address as President of Berlin Conference</hi></note>

<note>Compare also represeentatations made at Brussels:&#8212;</note>

<note>"When we have made sufficient progress in all directions to allow of the natives asking for our protection, and when we are strong enough to grant it, no one will venture any longer to capture or transport slaves."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Report Congo Administration, read at Brussels Conference.</hi></note>

<note>"For Belgian trade, as for that of traders of every nationality established in our territories, we have an equal solicitude. All appreciate the security they enjoy under the Congo Government."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of Representative of Congo State in Conference at Brussels.</hi></note>

<note>Compare also Supplement, ¶'s 1, 2.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p7"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The witnesses represented in the reports include:</p>

<p>(1.) Missionaries of all American and English Societies having work in the Congo and of all stations of these Societies which are in the vicinity of the rubber-producing district (4).</p>

<p>The missionary a reluctant witness. It is his desire and it is for his interest to seek the favor of government. The peril of charge of disloyalty (5).</p>

<p>The silence of Belgian missionaries not unnatural, in view of their two-fold relation with the king (6). Their testimony, if favorable to the Government, should not fail of consideration in the impartial inquiry sought.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>4 See Memorial to Congress, pages 7, 23-52.</note>

<note>See, also, "King Leopold's Rule in Africa," by E. D. Morel, and "Civilization in Congo Land," by H. R. Fox Bourne.</note>

<note>5 "The Governor made inquiry concerning the atrocities which he had reported and finally said to him: 'If you continue to demand investigation in these matters, we will make a charge against you. The natives say you have told them not to being India rubber to the State.' He denied this, but was again threatened by the Governor, who said: 'That means five years' imprisonment.'"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">From interview with Rev. E. V. Sjoblom, Ikoko, Africa.</hi></note>

<note>Compare report of Governor General of the Congo State in recent issue of <sic>Officiel</sic> Bulletin: "Certain officers have complained of the arrogant attitude the native population assumes when it has been subjected to certain influences. Once cannot escape the fact that this situation reveals itself in the neighborhood of certain * * * missionary posts. * * * I have already called the attention of the Government to this grave situation and to the measures it is likely to entail if it continues. Already our local officers have found it necessary to act in order to safeguard the authority of the State, and if it is necessary the Governor General will consider the advisability of making use of the means that the decree of September 15, 1889, puts at his disposal in the case of strangers who use their influence over the natives against the State."</note>

<note>Compare letter of Rev. Mr. Harris, written at Baringa, July 2, 1904,&#8212;printed in London <hi rend="italics">News</hi>:</note>

<note>"I called the judge's attention to the imprisonment of women and children who would not be released until their husbands and fathers satisfied the rubber demand. * * * In June sentries were sent into the towns with instructions to forbid any individuals going to the mission schools and services. Thus instead of two hundred or three hundred we had not a soul."</note>

<note>6 "The Belgian missionaries are subjects of their king, which at once makes their position very difficult. Then again, all these Belgian establishments on the Congo receive grants from the Congo Government, and it would be a very serious matter, indeed, for them if they were to say publicly what they know to be the case and what some of them privately write to their friends."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">E. D. Morel in "New York Evening Post," Octo., 1904.</hi> C. f. Debate in Belgian Parliament. Supplement, ¶s 54-67.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p8"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>(2.) Witnesses of many callings&#8212;travelers, explorers, consular residents, and men formerly agents of the State (7).</p>

<p>The testimony of Mr. Glave, an honored companion of Mr. Stanley (8).</p>

<p>The detailed report of Roger Casement, British Consul, after a journey made through interior districts (9).</p>

<p>Testimony of M. Pickard, a Belgian Senator (10).*</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>7 See, e.g., testimony of Mr. Ewart S. Grogan in "From the Cape to Cairo;" Mr. Pickersgill, British Consul, in "Official Report, 1898;" Col. Williams, an ex-officer in King Leopold's army, "Affairs of West Africa," page 320; Major Parminter, "Civilization in Congo Land," pages 132-'4; M. Moray, ex-agent of Concessionaire Co., "Civilization in Congo Land," page 52; M. Pickard, Belgian Senator, "En Congolie," pages 95-97; Mr. Joseph Conrad, novelist, quoted in London <hi rend="italics">Morning Post,</hi> October, 1904, etc. See, also, "King Leopold's Rule in Africa," by E. D. Morel, and "Civilization in Kongo Land," by H. R. Fox Bourne.</note>

<note>8 Mr. E. J. Glave, having been associated with Mr. Stanley in the earlier days in Africa, revisited the Congo after an absence of six years. His record of his experiences as he made his way over the route followed previously with Mr. Stanley is given in articles "New Conditions in Central Africa," in the <hi rend="italics">Century Magazine,</hi> volumes 53, 54. At first he is perplexed and incredulous. Successive entries in his journal show the growth of his deep indignation and abhorrence. For citations, see Memorial to Congress, pages 7 and 9, and pamphlet "Treatment of Women and Children in the Congo State," pp. 3, 5-10.</note>

<note>For warm commendation of Mr. Glave by Stanley, see "Introduction" to Glave's volume, "Six Years in the Congo."</note>

<note>9 "Meanwhile Mr. Roger Casement, permanent British Consul in the Congo State, an official 'of wide African experience,' had been conducting a personal investigation in the Upper Congo. The appalling account of his experience is now before the world."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">"King Leopold's Rule in Africa," p. xiv.</hi></note>

<note>"Mr. Casement has never forgotten, in the course of his report, that he was a machine sent to record in a spirit of calm judicial impartiality the sights he witnessed, and he preformed his task with marvelous self-restraint."</note>

<note>"The British Government has placed in the hands of all the Powers the report of Mr. Casement. The British premier declared publicly that the proof of the existence of grave abuses was overwhelming."</note>

<note>"We submit herewith his painstaking and comprehensive testimony, the straightforward, regretful fidelity of which, we think, cannot fail to be apparent to every fair-minded reader."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Memorial to Congress, p. 9.</hi> For document, see Memorial, pp. 72-136.</note>

<note>10 After a journey in the Congo State in 1896, M. Pickard writes of the "mutilated forests where until lately villages had nestled; great heaps of cinders amid desolated palm groves and trampled-down banana fields." He adds: "The terror caused by the memory of inhuman floggings and massacres haunts their brains, and they go as fugitives to the hospitable bush or across the frontiers."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">"En Congolie," p. 95.</hi></note>

<note><hi rend="italics">* For remarkable debate in Belgium Parliament, see Supplement, ¶'s 54-67.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p9"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Counter-testimony explained in part as relating to other than the rubber districts (11)  as due to admiration for public works from which the native derives no advantage (12) or as former earlier testimony afterward repudiated (13).</p>

<p>The later judgment of Mr. Stanley (14).</p>

<p>Testimony favorable to the Congo State should receive recognition in the impartial investigation asked. It does not constitute a reason for refusing investigation.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>11 Compare Sir Harry Johnston, quoted as a defender of the king: "My own reports on the administration of the Congo Free State referred only to a small portion of the northeastern zone." See, also, statement of Mr. Grenfell and other members of "Natives' Protection Commission," in White Book, Africa, page 21, No. 10&#8212;that "it was only possible for them to act within the very narrow scope of their personal experience in the lower country, far removed from the immense rubber districts."</note>

<note>12 Compare expression in editorial in <hi rend="italics">N. Y. Times</hi>, October 1, 1904:</note>

<note>"We have examined with some care the statement of the Belgian Minister to this country in the current number of the <hi rend="italics">North American Review</hi> with reference to "Conditions in the Congo Free State." If the article was intended as a refutation in advance of the memorial that will be laid before the President by Mr. Morel, the honorary Secretary of the Congo Reform Association, we fear that it will prove inadequate. It can be admitted without hesitation that the commercial progress of the Congo State is all that Baron Moncheur represents it, without meeting the charges of cruelty and greed that are brought against the Belgian officials in the Congo State. These charges have been brought forward by the Congo Reform Association in detail and with evidence of much apparent force."</note>

<note>Compare statement of Mr. Casement as to native hospital and Government works at Leopoldville: "The native hospital is an unseemly place. I found seventeen sleeping-sickness patients, male and female, lying about in the utmost dirt * * * one (a woman) had fallen into the fire just prior to my arrival. She had been well bandaged, but was still lying out on the ground, with her head almost in the fire. * * * All were very near their end, and two days later I found one of them lying dead out in the open. * * * In somewhat striking contrast, * * * I found within a couple of hundreds of yards the Government workshop for repairing and fitting the steamers. Here all was brightness, care, order, and activity, and it was impossible not to admire and commend the industry which created and maintained this useful establishment."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">For full statement, see page 74, Memorial to Congress.</hi></note>

<note>13 Compare Sir Harry Johnston: "In the Itura District I saw nothing to take exception to, but the report of Consul Casement, whom I know to be a competent, trustworthy, and absolutely impartial official of great experience in various parts of Africa, convinces me that the charges of maladministration of native affairs in the north and central parts of the Congo Free State are only two well founded."</note>

<note>14 "The last year of his (Stanley's) life was certainly embittered by the growing conviction that he had been the indirect means of placing in the Congo basin a power more unscrupulous and disastrous in its result than might have grown up under the flag of Islam."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Sir Harry Johnstone, an intimate friend of Mr. Stanley, in "Good Words," August, 1904.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p10"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>THE POSITIVE TESTIMONY TO THE EXISTENCE OF GRAVE WRONGS IS REINFORCED BY ACKNOWLEDGED FACTS WHICH GIVE PLAUSIBILITY TO REPORTS OF PREVALENCE OF ATROCITIES.</p>

<p>(1.) The avowed policy of the king is that of taxation by enforced labor (15).</p>

<p>(2.) In securing enforcement of labor, the king's policy is that of pitting representatives of one tribe against other tribes (see Verner, article in <hi rend="italics">Forum</hi>) July, 1904 (16).</p>

<p>Native soldiers, regular and irregular, number nearly 30,000, being greatly in excess of the military force of colonial powers in West Africa (17).</p>

<p>The soldiery described by Mr. Glave and M. Pickard as of savage ferocity (18).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>15 <hi rend="italics">The king's defence of the policy of compulsory labor.</hi></note>

<note>"The legality of taxes is not affected by the mode of payment.</note>

<note>"As they (the natives of the Congo) have no money, a contribution in the shape of labor is required from them.</note>

<note>"Payment of taxes is obligatory everywhere, and <hi rend="italics">non-payment involves measures of compulsion."&#8212;Reply of king's representative to British Parliament.</hi></note>

<note>16 "The secret of the king's success is in controlling the natives by pitting one tribe against another.</note>

<note>"As soon as any district had been brought under the control of the whites, and the natives had been rendered tractable, the soldiery was immediately recruited from the latter, and was almost always sent away to distant tribes, which it could be used to subjugate and control. This last policy is the keynote of the whole system. Leopold governs one African tribe with soldiers recruited from another. Many a State post has been manned by less than half a dozen white men with hundreds of these black soldiers in the midst of hostile population. It is a most extraordinary phenomenon. The adage 'divide and conquer' was never better illustrated."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">S. P. Verner (quoted as defender of Congo State) in Forum, July, 1904.</hi></note>

<note>17 The army outnumbers the force maintained in West Africa by England, France, and Germany combined.</note>

<note>18 "Their ferocity equals that of a pack of hounds hunting their quarry."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">M. PIckard, Belgian Senator, "En Congolie," p. 201.</hi></note>

<note>"The black soldiers are bent on fighting and raiding; they have good rifles and ammunition * * * and want to shoot and kill and rob, whether the victim be man, woman, or child."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">E. J. Glave, Century Magazine, volume 53, p. 908.</hi> Cf. in Supplement, ¶'s 55-57.</note>

<note>Compare description of <hi rend="italics">sentry</hi> given by Mr. Pickersgill, in "Report on Congo Independent State." "A sentry on the Congo, is a dare-devil aboriginal, chosen, from troops impressed outside the district in which he serves * * * armed with a rifle * * * . He is located in a native village to see that the labor for which its inhabitants are responsible is duly attended to. If they are India rubber collectors, his duty is to send the men into the forests and take note of those who do not return with the proper quantity. In every matter connected with the Government he is the <hi rend="italics">factotum</hi>, as far as that village is concerned, of the officer of the district."</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p11"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>(3.) The great excess of exports over imports an indication of abnormal and oppressive conditions (19).</p>

<p>(4.) The king's persistent opposition to an impartial investigation, which should secure him a notable vindication, is not easily accounted for upon the theory of innocence of wrong.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Neither members of Congress nor our citizens are asked to accept the reports of atrocities as conclusive. The request made in the memorial asks only that Congress shall favor an impartial investigation of existing conditions.</hi></p>

<p>THE INADEQUACY OF ANY INVESTIGATION CONDUCTED BY THE KING.</p>

<p>The king himself the accused party.</p>

<p>The natives dare not give testimony in an investigation conducted by the government under which they suffer.</p>

<p>Instances of intimidation (20).</p>

<p>The proposal of investigation by the king "at once a confession of the need of inquiry and an attempt to prevent it."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">New York Times</hi> (21).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>19 Of ten African possessions of European powers all but two show a large excess of imports over exports. The Congo State shows (1889-1902) imports of $17,500,000; exports, $37,000,000. Of this importation 70 per cent. represents supplies for Government, stores for the railway, arms, and ammunition. During the four years cited exports in the Congo State have increased by 40 per cent.; imports diminished by 25 per cent. "These figures alone show wherein the policy of King Leopold, as applied in the Congo, differs from that of every civilized administration. The India rubber which comes from that great country, where the native alone can gather it, is not bought, but forced out of the people by the lash and rifle."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">E. D. Morel, article in "Boston Transcript," October 24, 1904.</hi> cf. Supplement, ¶ 69.</note>

<note>20 The victims of a shocking outrage, when told by an amazed visitor that they should complain to the State, replied: "We should not be believed; they would put us in chains at once," and when told they should carry the bodies of their murdered dead in canoes to the official, they replied: "We never could get past the sentries."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Memorial to Congress.</hi></note>

<note>"The chief informed the sentinel that he would report to the commissary that the sentinel had killed his father * * * then he went away from the village. * * * But the sentinel caught the chief * * * they flogged him until the blood streamed down his back. * * * The soldier took his gun and leveled it close to the chief's heart. The chief stood shivering with fear, and the sentinel said: 'I can kill you if I like.'"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Rev. E. V. Sjoblom (deceased), late of Ikoko, Africa.</hi></note>

<note>21 For full statement see Supplement, ¶ 3.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p12"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>THE CLAIM MADE BY THE KING THAT SUBMISSION TO AN INTERNATIONAL INVESTIGATION IS INCONSISTENT WITH THE SOVEREIGNTY OF THE CONGO STATE.*</p>

<p>The sovereignty of the Congo State is definitely limited by engagements made with the Conference of Berlin and the Conference of Brussels (22).</p>

<p>The Conferences declared themselves guardians of the people of the Congo basin (23).</p>

<p>These Conferences definitely reserved the right to review and revise the agreement entered into by their members (24).</p>

<p>The king conceded the guardianship of the Powers by appealing to the Conference at Brussels for such revision of the action at Berlin as would permit imposition of import duties.</p>

<p>Promotion of the well-being of the natives was involved as definitely in the engagement at Berlin as provision for freedom of trade; and investigation of reported dereliction respecting either feature of the engagement falls within the jurisdiction of the Powers with whom the engagement was made.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>* For amazing claim that even Belgium may not make inquiry regarding conditions in the Congo State, see Supplement, ¶ 64.</note>

<note>22 "The Congo State is sovereign no less than the other countries. * * * Her sovereignty is merely <hi rend="italics">confined by certain limits,</hi> of which one is formed by article IV of the general act of Berlin."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of representative of Austro-Hungary, Conference of Brussels, June 17, 1890.</hi></note>

<note>See like statement by Congo representative at Brussels, Supplement, ¶ 4.</note>

<note>23 "With regard to these native populations, the Conference must assume the position of an official guardian. * * * The necessity of insuring the preservation of the natives, * * * the obligation to instruct them and initiate them into the advantages of civilization, * * * are unanimously recognized."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">General Act of Berlin Conference.</hi></note>

<note>Compare in Supplement, ¶'s 5, 6. "to watch over * * * the native tribes."&#8212;For similar attitude at Brussels, compare language of Act in Supplement, ¶ 41, "Efficiently protecting the aboriginal population."</note>

<note>24 "The signatory powers of the present General Act reserve to themselves the right to introduce into it subsequently, and by common accord, such modifications and improvements as experience may show to be expedient."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">General Act of Berlin Conference, Article 36.&#8212;For corresponding action at Brussels see Supplement, ¶ 7.</hi></note>

<note>For definition of status of Congo State by Belgian jurist see Supplt., ¶ 8.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p13"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>II. An international inquiry is demanded, not only for investigation of reports of atrocities, but for consideration of other issues with which a commission created by the king is obviously incompetent to deal.</p>

<p>(1.) THE KING'S CLAIM OF EXCLUSIVE OWNERSHIP OF A VAST TERRITORIAL DOMAIN, AS RESPECTS BOTH LAND AND PRODUCTS.</p>

<p>800,000 square miles of territory are held to be the king's property, the natives being represented as robbers if using or selling its products, and the foreign trader being subject to punishment if attempting to buy any product of the native (25).</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">This involves for the natives:</hi></p>

<p>Permanent loss of ancestral rights to gather products, to fish and hunt.</p>

<p>Permanent denial of hope of acquiring lands or the privilege of trading.</p>

<p>Deprivation of healthful motives for labor.</p>

<p>Subjection to force as the alternative for healthful motives.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>25 <hi rend="italics">The king's defence of his policy as to trade.</hi></note>

<note>"The native who collects on behalf of the owner does not become the owner of what is collected, and naturally cannot dispose of it to a third party. * * * Never in the Congo * * * have requests to buy natural produce been addressed to the rightful owners. * * * The only attempts have been to buy the produce that has been stolen. * * * <hi rend="italics">There are no longer any unappropriated lands there</hi> (in the Congo State)."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">There are no longer any unappropriated lands there</hi> (in the Congo State)."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Reply of king's representative to British Parliament.</hi></note>

<note>"The policy of appropriation of the natives' land and the products thereof is the key to the whole Congo problem.</note>

<p>"Hitherto the native had been looked upon by the merchants established in the country as the owner of the products of the soil which the merchants wished to acquire by legitimate purchase, as everywhere else in Western Africa. Commercial relationship had been established in the ordinary way, and long before the Congo State had come into existence, the native, attracted by the merchandise offered for sale by the white man, gathered the produce of the forests and brought it to the factory for sale. * * * The native is relegated from the position of owner of the forest products, which he has been accustomed to sell, to that of a lawless and ownerless serf on the estate of 'Bula Matadi.'"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Morel in Leopold's Rule in Africa, pp. 32. 33. cf. Supplement, ¶ 9.</hi></p>

<note><hi rend="italics">For general view of promises and performance as to trade, see Supplement, s 68-77.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p14"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p><hi rend="italics">The policy involves for all peoples:</hi></p>

<p>Closing of the door to commercial fields representing a territory four times as large as the German Empire and rivaling China in latent possibilities (26).</p>

<p>Disappointment of the reasonable expectation of large expansion of trade for European Powers and for the United States, created by the representations made by the Congo government (27).</p>

<p>Infidelity to the definite understanding (28) reached at the Conference at Berlin and violation of pledges made to that Conference (29) and to the individual Powers (30) by which freedom of trade was guaranteed for all peoples (31).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>26 "The importance of <hi rend="italics">the rich prospective trade</hi> of the Kongo Valley has led to the general conviction that it should be open to all nations on equal terms."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Message of Pres. Arthur, Dec., 1884.</hi> Cf. Supplt., ¶'s 10-12.</note>

<note>27 "Soon these millions of people inhabiting the interior of Africa will, under the inspiring influence of civilization, became <hi rend="italics">purchasers of every kind of provision, manufactured goods, agricultural implements, etc.,</hi> and I can see no reason why <hi rend="italics">the people of the United States should</hi> not <hi rend="italics">come in for a large share of the valuable trade</hi> which must soon be developed in this region."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Letter of Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Tisdel, 1884.</hi></note>

<note>See address of Mr. Stanley at Manchester, England, Supplt., ¶ 13.</note>

<note>28 It is plain that freedom for the individual trader and trade with the natives, was contemplated. Cf. Supplement, ¶'s 69, 70.</note>

<note>"No doubt whatever exists as to the strict and literal sense which should be applied to the term 'in commercial matters.' It refers * * * to traffic, to <hi rend="italics">the unlimited power of every one to sell and to buy, to import and to export products and manufactured articles. * * * No privileged situation can be created under this head.</hi> The way remains open without any restrictions to free competition in the domain of commerce."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Report of Commission at Berlin Conference.</hi></note>

<note>"It is not sufficient for all our merchants to enjoy equally the right of buying the oil, gums, and ivory of the country, and to sell goods of an equivalent value <hi rend="italics">which the natives receive in exchange.</hi> It would only be a paltry outlet for the vast productive forces of Europe and America. Productive labor must be seriously encouraged, and the means of the inhabitants of acquiring the products of civilized nations be thus increased."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of Mr. Kasson at Berlin.</hi></note>

<note>Compare Mr. Stanley, Supplement, ¶ 14; see also statement at Brussels, Supplement, ¶ 15, as to great development of trade then reached.</note>

<note>29 "The trade of all nations shall enjoy complete freedom." "No power shall be at liberty to grant either monopolies or privileges * * * in commercial matters."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Act of Berlin, Articles I and V.</hi></note>

<note>30 See, e.g., in Treaty of State with Great Britain, Supplement, ¶ 16.</note>

<note>31 See supplement, ¶'s 17, 18, 19, 20; cf. 21.</note>

<note>On complete destruction of trade, see ¶'s 72, 73, 74.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p15"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The claim that sovereignty involves the right to wholesale monopolization of the territory and its products cannot be regarded as valid in the case of the Congo State.</p>

<p>If so extreme a claim, involving complete extinction of native rights, were tolerable in respect of sovereign Powers in general, when assuming administration over a dependent people in a newly-opened territory, it would appear to be voided in this instance by the limitation upon sovereignty involved in the engagements made by the Congo State with the Powers (32). For this policy of monopolization is plainly antagonistic to that material and moral well-being of the people which the State pledged itself to conserve (33), as well as to rights in trade guaranteed to other nations.</p>

<p>In any view, it would appear that this monopolistic system is so related to engagements made by the State that it should receive the attention of the Powers committed to guardianship of the native people.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>32 "It would appear that the special conditions under which the Congo State came into existence * * * the obligations which it voluntarily assumed as a signatory of the Berlin act * * * placed it in a different position from that held by other States."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">H. Fox Bourne.</hi></note>

<note>33 "Freedom of trade was * * * established (by the general act of Berlin) <hi rend="italics">in the interests</hi> not only of civilization, but <hi rend="italics">of the native races of Africa, with a view to improve their lot  and to hasten their progress</hi> toward a better state."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Lord Vivian in Brussels Conference, July 2, 1890.</hi></note>

<note>The broad distinction between the holding of public lands <hi rend="italics">for</hi> the people, with a view to their ultimate benefit, and the holding of all lands <hi rend="italics">from</hi>  the people with a view to the sovereign's enrichment, should not be forgotten. Cf. Supplement, ¶ 62. See general ¶'s 60, 61.</note>

<note>"The interpretation of territorial sovereignty in terms of absolute ownership reduced in the course of three hundred years the free population of Europe to a condition of feudal servitude. By a similar fiction King Leopold has reduced the whole population of the Congo to a condition of slavery."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">R. E. Park.</hi></note>

<note>"As for the villagers themselves, they are no longer men, but weary slaves. All day long, and for days together, in the forests getting rubber, striving to satisfy an insatiable demand, unmercifully flogged if the amount gathered falls short of the amount required, wandering ever further afield, away from their homes, unable to attend to their plantations, demoralized, degraded, all the manhood driven out of them."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">E. D. Morel in "King Leopold's Rule in Africa," p. 38.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p16"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>(2.) THE KING'S ASSERTION OF SOVEREIGN RIGHTS, UNLIMITED BY ANY FORM OF RELATION TO THE POWERS (34).</p>

<p>This creates occasion for judicial decision as to the international relations of the king's government.</p>

<p>Possibly it should involve consideration of certain questions never yet adjudicated by the Powers.</p>

<p>In what way did the rule of the "International Association" become the independent unlimited sovereignty of the head of that Association? (35).</p>

<p>Does the power&#8212;pertaining only to absolute despotism&#8212;of bequeathing sovereignty at will belong to the king and to his successors?</p>

<p>Where are the "Free States" whose existence was affirmed when original recognition was given the International Association of the Congo? (36).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>34 "A heresy in international law has been imagined, viz., that a State, <hi rend="italics">the independence and sovereignty of which are absolute,</hi> should at the same time <hi rend="italics">owe its position to the intervention of foreign powers."&#8212;Reply of king's representative to British Parliament, September 17, 1903.</hi></note>

<note>35 There is no record of action by the Association, which had been recognized as a State. Apparently the only action taken was that of the Belgian Chamber of Representatives and Senate, which on the 28th of April, 1885, and 30th of April passed the concurrent resolution: "His Majesty, Leopold II, King of the Belgians, is authorized to be the king of the State formed in Africa by the International Association of the Congo." Notification to the foreign powers of the king's action was made on the 1st of August, 1885.</note>

<note>By what authorization did the king, when becoming ruler, assume the position of an absolute sovereign rather than a position allied to that held by him in Belgium as "one of the trustees of the national sovereignty"? Cf. Prof. Cattier, pp. 20, 21, <hi rend="italics">"Leopold's Rule in Africa."</hi></note>

<note>36 "The International Association of the Congo hereby declares that by treaties with the legitimate sovereigns in the basins of the Congo * * * there has been ceded to it territory for the use and benefit of <hi rend="italics">free States established and being established</hi> under the care and supervision of the said association"&#8212;Mr. Sanford, representing International Association, in exchange of declarations with the United States.</note>

<note>See language of Act of Recognition by the United States, "the interests of <hi rend="italics">the free States there established.</hi>" Supplement, ¶ 22.</note>

<note>You were designated as agent to the States of the Congo Association because it was believed here that <hi rend="italics">the residents of the region</hi> adjoining and including the Congo valley <hi rend="italics">seemed on the verge of establishing constitutional States</hi> by progressive movement in that direction.&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Tisdel, commercial agent</hi>, December 12, 1884.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p17"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Is the king legitimate successor to whatever powers were given by native chiefs to that "Societé d'Etudes du Haut-Congo"&#8212;an organization which in receiving their allegiance committed itself to pledges which the king apparently has not fulfilled? (37).</p>

<p>The existing situation gives to these issues a grave importance not recognized when the king was supposed to be loyal in purpose to all professions of the International Association. The Powers should decide whether they are debarred now from considering them.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Consideration of these questions relating to fundamental international jurisprudence, and the rendering of judgment upon the commercial policy of the king, obviously lie outside the jurisdiction of a local tribunal created by the king, and require the convening of an international body.</hi></p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>37 Compare: "They pledge the association 'to promote to its utmost the prosperity of the country,' and 'to protect its inhabitants from all oppression.'"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">H. R. Fox Bourne, "Civilization in Congo Land," p. 44.</hi></note>

<note><hi rend="italics">For sample of the treaties, see Supplement, ¶ 78.</hi></note>

<note>See statement of Mr. Fox Bourne: "As regards another treaty, which was abandoned after the exposure of its character, we had a report from the British consul at Loanda. * * * The chiefs, to whom the treaty was correctly translated, were much surprised at the conditions, and declared that they never understood the full meaning of the treaty imposed upon them; that they had no wish to sell their lands on those terms; that they were given to understand that the expedition intended to establish a factory, and not that they were to prohibit others putting trading houses in their district or to be called upon for men to construct roads."</note>

<note>Compare letter of Mr. Tisdel, commercial agent of United States, to Mr. Frelinghuysen, June 29, 1885: "There is no government of any kind in the Valley of the Congo. Makoko and other great kings claim absolute control over many tribes, but such is not the case. * * * A treaty made between a white man and one of the kings cannot be depended upon. If land is transferred to you today by treaty * * * I may come along tomorrow, and, with two or three bottles of gin, I can purchase the same land from the same king with whom you have dealt. I repeat, there is no government in the Valley of the Congo."</note>

<note>"Most of the treaties were in respect of lands <hi rend="italics">in Lower Congo,</hi> already put to considerable use by the Dutch, Portuguese, French, and English traders."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Civilization in Congo Land, p. 68.</hi></note>

<note>"Most of the treaties were probably as valid as such documents generally are, implying, as they do, the assent of native communities to the surrender or weakening of their rights and privileges by chiefs not competent to take such action and not themselves aware of the consequences of their rash proceedings."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Civilization in Congo Land, p. 45.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p18"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>RELATION OF THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT TO THE ISSUE PRESENTED BY CONDITIONS IN THE CONGO STATE.</p>

<p>THE SUCCESS ACHIEVED BY THE INTERNATIONAL SSOCIATION OF THE CONGO IN GAINING RECOGNIZED STANDING AS A STATE ADMINISTERING GOVERNMENT IN THE CONGO TERRITORY IS TRACEABLE IN A MARKED DEGREE TO THE FAVOR AND ACTIVE AID EXTENDED TO THE ASSOCIATION BY THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT.</p>

<p>Approving the enterprise for neutralization of the newly opened territory in Africa, and for the uplifting of its people, in which the International Association professedly was engaged, our Government lent its influence strongly in support of this enterprise (38).</p>

<p>Our Government was first among the Powers to extend recognition to the International Association of the Congo (39).</p>

<p>This action by our Government resulted in defeat of the effort of Portugal to maintain its claims in the Congo basin and in ultimate recognition of the International Association by European Powers (40).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>38 "It was evident that soon the territory would be exposed to the dangerous rivalries of conflicting nationalities. There was even <hi rend="italics">danger of its being so appropriated as to exclude it from free intercourse for a large part of the civilized world.</hi> It was the earnest desire of the Government of the United States that these discoveries should be utilized for the civilization of the native races and for the abolition of the slave trade. * * * He (the President of the United States) regards this local government as an assurance * * * that the blacks will learn from it that the civilization and the dominion of the white man mean for them peace and freedom and the development of useful commerce, free to all the world."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Address of Mr. Kasson at Berlin Conference, second session.</hi></note>

<note>39 For language of Act of Recognition see Supplement, ¶ 22. Cf. 24, 25.</note>

<note>For naturalness of appeal to U.S. see Supplement, ¶ 23.</note>

<note>40 "This (the treaty of Great Britain with Portugal) seemed to be the death blow to the work of the Association; but, however dark the future of the African Association might seem, there was soon to be a change, for in April, 1884, the United States recognized the flag of the International Association."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Dr. J. S. Reeves in "Internat. Beginnings of Congo State."</hi></note>

<note>"The recognition by the United States was the birth into new life of the Association, seriously menaced as its existence was by opposing interests and ambitions."&#8212;Mr. Stanley, "The Congo," vol. 1, page 383.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p19"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Our associate representative in the Berlin Conference was chosen because, through his connection with the International Association, his appointment would secure representation for that Association in the Conference (41).</p>

<p>In the Berlin Conference request was made, in the name of the President of the United States, that the International Association should be granted by the Powers the largest possible concession of territory (42).</p>

<p>The influence of our representatives at Berlin was confessedly great, both within the Conference and in outside negotiations, in securing adjustment of difficulties between the International Association and the Powers with a view to full recognition of the Association, and in shaping the general action of the Conference (43).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>41 "After careful reflection upon the probable phases of discussion and the central position in them of the African International Association in antagonism with Portugal and France, I believed it would be beyond doubt useful to have the assistance of Mr. Sanford, who has successfully presented the claims of that Association to me for recognition. Even a stronger motive was the usefulness of an associate * * * who can devote his time to those outside preliminary conversations which often shape the action of the Conference in advance."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Kasson to Mr. Frelinghuysen. October 24, 1884.</hi></note>

<note>Compare Mr. Kasson's note to Mr. Stanley: "It is believed the International Association would also desire your presence here."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">October 20, 1884.</hi></note>

<note>42 "He (the President of the United States) desires to see in the delimitation of the region which shall be subjected to this beneficent rule (of the International Association of the Congo) the widest expansion consistent with the just territorial rights of other governments."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Kasson at Berlin Conference, second session.</hi></note>

<note>43 "So marked was the acceptance by the Conference of the views presented on the part of the United States that Herr Von Bunsen, reviewing the action of the Conference, assigns after Germany the first place of influence in the Conference to the United States."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Kasson in North American Review, February, 1886.</hi></note>

<note>"The protocols show how many clauses were changed on the suggestion of the American Minister."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Kasson in N. A. Review, February, 1886.</hi></note>

<note>Compare statement of Mr. Sanford as to the service rendered by him at Brussels. See Supplement, ¶ 26.</note>

<note>In general for influence of United States Government <hi rend="italics">in re</hi> Congo State, see Supplement, ¶ 27.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p20"/>

<pb n="p20"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>THE RIGHT OF A PARTY, INFLUENCED BY QUESTIONABLE PROFESSIONS AND APPARENTLY DEFEATED IN A NOBLE PURPOSE, BELONGS TO THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT.</p>

<p>THE RIGHT AND LEGAL STANDING OF A MEMBER OF THE FAMILY OF NATIONS BELONG TO THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT (44).</p>

<p>This must be held to involve a right to show favor to a proposition for inquiry into current  reports of atrocities in the Congo State.</p>

<p>It must be held to involve also, if conditions are thought sufficiently serious, right of protest, and, in the last resort, of intervention.</p>

<p>THE RIGHT AND LEGAL STANDING BELONGING TO ALL POWERS WHOSE ACTION GAVE TO THE CONGO STATE ITS RECOGNIZED STANDING OBVIOUSLY ARE SHARED BY THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT.</p>

<p>This recognition was secured to the Congo Government by action of individual Powers and not primarily by any Conference as such (45).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>44 "The claims of common humanity give both duties and rights to all of the organized peoples of the world."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Boston Herald, November, 1904, editorial on Russo-Japanese war.</hi></note>

<note>Compare "Man-hunting is an act of treason against humanity. * * * It is the negation of all law, of all social order. It must be suppressed wherever this is possible on land as well as on sea."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Report of Commission at Berlin Conference.</hi></note>

<note>45 "It is impossible for us to determine the due and proper weight to be given by government to the declaration and claim of right to advantages guaranteed by the Act of Berlin pertaining to neutrality. * * * But this reservation is wholly distinct from the recognition of the sovereign status of the Independent State of the Congo, which does not rest upon the conventional arrangements contemplated by the Conference of Berlin."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Bayard to Mr. Tree, Minister to Belgium, 1885.</hi></note>

<note>"The relationship of recognition and earnest good will is complete of itself and apart from any conventional relationship flowing from or defined by the General Act of the Conference at Berlin."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Bayard to Mr. Van Eetveld, Secretary of State for Congo Government. See page 62, "Foreign Relations of U.S.," 1885.</hi></note>

<note>"When the Berlin Conference opened * * * the International Association * * * had been recognized by three powers. During the two months that intervened before the promulgation of the General Act the very important negotiations were to be perfected by which the Association was to be recognized by all the powers."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Dr. Reeves in J. H. Studies.</hi></note>

</div2>

<pb n="p21"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Conferences at Berlin and Brussels dealt with issues which, in international relations, are of a subordinate character. They restricted themselves definitely to the framing of rules and measures of administration to be applied in a certain defined territory (46).</p>

<p>The recognition given the International Association at the close of the sessions of the Berlin Conference, in receiving its adherence to the action of that Conference, was given definitely on the ground of recognition of the Association by the individual Powers (47).</p>

<p>Whatever right belongs to any Power to inquire into more fundamental issues connected with the status and rule of the king, or to express interest in the discharge of its just responsibilities by the State, belongs to the United States Government.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>46 "All questions of forms of government and of territorial right or jurisdiction were excluded from the consideration of the Conference."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Kasson in North American Review, February, 1886.</hi></note>

<note>"The members of the Conference will have an opportunity of agreeing among themselves upon questions connected with the delimitations of the colonial establishments of their countries; * * * but it does not come within the attributes of the Assembly to decide upon the validity of previous deeds of possession."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">From address of Prince Bismarck at the opening of the Berlin Conference, November 15, 1884.</hi></note>

<note>Compare Lord Vivian at Brussels Conference, November 23, 1889: "A document * * * has been distributed * * * by the Portuguese which prejudges questions of territorial rights. * * * I have to inquire whether it is not a fact that to allow such a document * * * would be quite at variance with the well-recognized principle that all such questions are beyond the powers of the Conference."</note>

<note>"The Conference * * * is not entitled to pronounce on the rights which any power may have over this or that territory or on the validity of titles."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Baron Lambermont, President of Brussels Conference, November 23, 1889.</hi></note>

<note>47 "The recognition of the association by all the individual Powers was followed by the recognition of it by the Berlin Conference."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Dr. Reeves in "J. H. Studies."</hi></note>

<note>Compare letter from king's secretary to Prince Bismarck, President of the Conference at Berlin: "The International Association of the Congo has successively concluded with the Powers represented at the Conference of Berlin (with one exception) treaties * * * recognizing its flag. * * * There is every reason to hope that negotiations * * * with the remaining power will shortly terminate favorably. The Conference * * * would, I venture to hope, consider the accession of a power * * * as a further pledge of the fruits its important labors must produce."</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p22"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>THE RIGHT AND LEGAL STANDING INVOLVED IN ACCEPTANCE OF A RELATION OF CONCERN AND GUARDIANSHIP TOWARD THE PEOPLE DWELLING IN THE TERRITORY OCCUPIED BY THE CONGO STATE APPEAR CLEARLY TO BELONG TO THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT.</p>

<p>This relation, though declined by the United States at Berlin (48), because of unwillingness to assume in full the obligations which ratification of the Berlin act was thought to involve (49), would appear to have been accepted at Brussels.</p>

<p>The failure of our Government to ratify the action of Berlin was not regarded, either by the king or by European Powers, as repudiation of the central aims of that Conference. For the king, when reconvening at Brussels the Powers participating in the Conference at Berlin, included the United States Government in the invitation extended, and the Powers gave to our Government cordial welcome to the meeting at Brussels and urged earnestly our full participation in its action (50).</p>

<p>Our non-ratification of the general Act of Berlin was not thought by our Government to involve denial of concern in the action of the Congo State and the well-being of its people, for we accepted the invitation extended by the king, and participated with the other Powers in the Conference at Brussels.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>48 The President of the United States, while expressing satisfaction with the result reached at Berlin (see Supplement, ¶ 28), did not submit its action for ratification by the Senate.</note>

<note>49 <hi rend="italics">"As the treaty embraced matters with which our Government did not wish to deal,</hi> it was not presented to the Senate by the President."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Committee on Foreign Affairs, in report to House, Sept. 22, 1890.</hi> Cf. Supplt., ¶ 39.</note>

<note>Compare Message of President Cleveland, December, 1885: "Their signatures were attached to the General Act (of Berlin), thus making the United States appear <hi rend="italics">without reserve or qualification</hi> as signatories." Compare, also, statement of Mr. Bayard, Supplement, ¶ 29.</note>

<note>50 For words of President of Brussels Conference, see Supplement, ¶'s 30, 31. Compare "With extreme satisfaction," Supplement, ¶ 38.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p23"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Conference at Brussels in its essential purpose was practically a continuation of the Conference at Berlin (51). While dealing with a larger territory than the international basin of the Congo, it gave to the interests of that territory a foremost recognition (52), and while addressing itself primarily to suppression of slave-raiding, it recognized this work as giving specific expression to its general concern for the well-being of the native people (53).</p>

<p>Like the earlier Conference, the Conference at Brussels defined requirements imposed upon and accepted by the Powers administering government in the designated territory, and received from them an engagement to fulfill these requirements (54). Its attitude and action throughout were those of conceded interest and authority in protection of the dependent people living within this territory and in maintenance of rights of trade.</p>

<p>While the representatives of the United States Government at Brussels guarded carefully against any form of action which might be interpreted as ratification of the action at Berlin and acceptance of all its implied obligations (55), they united in action, involving acceptance of the central aims controlling the earlier Conference&#8212;care for the well-being of the native people, and protection for just rights in trade (56).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>51 See words of Lord Vivian at Brussels, Supplement, ¶'s 32, 33, cf. 34.</note>

<note>52 "These territories are almost exclusively situated in the interior, within the boundaries of the Congo State."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Congo Representative at Brussels.</hi> See also Supplement, ¶ 35.</note>

<note>53 For significant statement at Brussels Conference, see Supplt., ¶ 36.</note>

<note>54 See Act of Brussels, Supplement, ¶ 42, cf., e.g., language of Article IV:&#8212;"The States exercising sovereign powers or protectorates in Africa may delegate to companies provided with charters all or a portion of the engagements which they assume. * * * <hi rend="italics">They remain, nevertheless, directly responsible for the engagements which they contract</hi> by the present act and guarantee the execution thereof."</note>

<note>55 See, e.g., Supplement, ¶ 37.</note>

<note>56 See Supplt., ¶ 38. Cf. ¶ 40.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p24"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The United States Government, by formal ratification of the General Act of Brussels, would appear to have acknowledged participation with the other Powers in the relation of concern and guardianship respecting these two administrative interests in the Congo State (57).</p>

<p>The reservation in the formal ratification given by our Government to the action at Brussels apparently does not pertain to or affect the two points in which concern and obligation were acknowledged (58).</p>

<p>That the attitude thus indicated is not inconsistently held by our Government is shown in our State papers which, while uniformly guarding against acceptance of obligation to  enforce neutrality or to sustain the territorial claims of other Powers in the Congo Valley, have with marked uniformity affirmed an interest on the part of the United States respecting the well-being of the native people of the Congo basin and protection of our rights in trade (59).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>57 If ratification of this Act had any significance it could not have involved less than this. Compare in "Civilization in Congo Land." "Claiming, as at Berlin, to speak in the name of Almighty God, the signatories declared themselves to be equally animated by the firm intention of putting an end to the crimes and devastations engendered by the traffic in African slaves, of protecting effectually the aboriginal populations and of ensuring the benefits of peace and civilization."</note>

<note>For citations from Act of Brussels, see Supplement, ¶ 41.</note>

<note>Compare also provisions of Treaty of United States with Congo State, in Supplement, ¶ 52, cf. ¶ 45.</note>

<note>In relation to the issue as a whole, compare statement and resolution of House Committee on Foreign Affairs, cited in Supplement, ¶ 39.</note>

<note>58 "That the United States of America, having no possessions or protectorates in Africa, hereby disclaims any intention in ratifying the treaty to indicate any interests whatsoever in the possessions or protectorates established or claimed on that continent by the other powers, or in approval of the wisdom, expediency, or lawfulness thereof, and does not join in any expressions of the general act which might be construed as such declaration or acknowledgment."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Protocol introduced by United States in Act of Brussels.</hi></note>

<note>For statement of cause of delay in ratification of the Act of Brussels and for interpretation of the reservation made in foregoing protocol, see in Appleton's Annual, 1893, cited in Supplement, ¶ 43.</note>

<note>59 See citations from State papers, Supplement, ¶ 44.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p25"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The current reports concerning conditions in the Congo State imply disloyalty on the part of its government to the central aims and the definite declarations of the Conference at Brussels as truly as they involve disloyalty to the Conference at Berlin (60).</p>

<p>Having, with the full consent, and in accordance with the strongly expressed desire, of the Congo State and of European Powers entered into formal participation in a relation of concern and guardianship toward the people of the Congo territory, our Government is plainly entitled, and may reasonably regard itself as under honorable engagement, to inquire as to the King's fidelity to the trust committed to him.</p>

<p>Action by our Government at the present juncture will not involve concession of obligation in enforcement of neutrality as between European Powers in the territory of the Congo. It will imply only interest in the well-being of the native people and concern for the protection of rights of trade, and may appropriately be based upon either or both of these grounds (61).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>60 See specification of obligations in Act of Brussels, Supplement, ¶ 42.</note>

<note>Compare E. J. Glave, in <hi rend="italics">Century Magazine,</hi> volume 54, page 709: "Everywhere I hear the same news of the doings from the Congo Free State&#8212;rubber and murder&#8212;slavery in its worst form." See also Supplement, ¶ 46. Cf. Supplement, ¶ 61.</note>

<note>Compare, "Leopold's Rule in Africa," pp. 247-251 for forms of slavery and slave-raiding perpetrated and developed by the rule of the king.</note>

<note>61 "We attach the highest value to the coöperation of the United States in our work. We know that their traditional policy is to stand aloof from the treaties and political arrangements of European nations, but the work which we are carrying on is purely humanitarian; it has no connection with politics; its only object is the extinction of the slave trade and the improvement of the negro's lot, an object for which the United States have so often poured out blood and treasure. For these reasons we hope and trust that they will consent to associate themselves with our work."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of Lord Vivian, Brussels Conference.</hi> Compare letter of Mr. Frelinghuysen, Supplement, ¶ 47. Compare also ¶ 48.</note>

<note>For significant recognition at Brussels of commercial interests as belonging also to governments without territorial possessions in the Congo basin, see Supplement, ¶ 49.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p26"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>IT IS NOTEWORTHY THAT OUR GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ADDRESSED RECENTLY BY A SISTER STATE IN PROPOSALS LOOKING TOWARD AN INTERNATIONAL INQUIRY CONCERNING THE CONGO ADMINISTRATION (62).</p>

<p>Recognition by the king and the European Powers of the appropriateness of favorable response to these overtures is involved in their action respecting our participation in the Conference of Brussels. (Cf. Supplement ¶'s 30, 31, 38.)</p>

<p>IT MAY BE NOTED ALSO THAT OUR GOVERNMENT IS PARTY TO A TREATY PLEDGING TO IT UNRESTRICTED FREEDOM IN TRADE IN THE CONGO TERRITORY (63) AND PROVIDING FOR ARBITRATION IN CASE DIFFERENCE OF VIEW SHALL ARISE RESPECTING THE MAINTENANCE, APPLICATION, <hi rend="italics">or interpretation</hi> OF ANY PROVISION OF THE ENGAGEMENT (64).</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="notes">

<note>62 See action in House of Commons, Supplement, ¶ 50. Cf. ¶ 51.</note>

<note>63 Treaty of U.S. and Congo State. ARTICLE I. There shall be full, entire, and reciprocal liberty of commerce, establishment, and navigation between the citizens and inhabitants of the two contracting parties.</note>

<note>The citizens and inhabitants of the United States of America in the Independent State of the Congo and those of the Independent State of the Congo in the United States of America shall have reciprocally the right, on conforming to the laws of the country, to enter, travel, and reside in all parts of their respective territories; to carry on business there. * They can freely exercise their industry or their business, as well wholesale as retail, in the whole extent of the territories.</note>

<note>For assurance of all rights of the signatories at Berlin, see Suppl't, ¶ 53.</note>

<note>64 "In case a difference should arise between the two high contracting parties as to the validity, <hi rend="italics">interpretation, application, or enforcement</hi> of any of the provisions contained in the present treaty, and it could not be arranged amicably by diplomatic correspondence between the two governments, these last agree to submit to the judgment of an arbitration tribunal, the decision of which they bind themselves to respect and execute loyally."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Treaty of United States with Congo State, Article XIII.</hi></note>

<note>65 If unwittingly, we have lent a powerful influence for the creation of a government, by which an innocent people are subjected to inhuman wrongs, our responsibility for effort for correction of these is apparent.</note>

<note>66 Compare introductory words of Baron Lambermont, Belgian Representative and President of Brussels Conference, at opening session, November, 1889: "The (slave) trade annually sacrifices from 300,000 to 400,000 human beings. Feelings of humanity and pity are naturally aroused when we deliberate with our feet in blood."</note>

<note>67 The two issues cannot be separated. A just policy toward the world's trade will bring to the native contact with the world and relief from the system by which he is enslaved.</note>

</div2>

<pb n="p27"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p><hi rend="italics">In view of these several forms of relations sustained by our Government to the issue, it would seem impossible to believe that we are without power of action with respect to it.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Whatever we may most wisely do, recognition of our influence in securing to the Congo State its international standing (65), our engagement to seek to promote the well-being of the native population, considerations of humanity (66) and regard for the commercial interests and rights of our people (67) will constrain us to do.</hi></p>

<p>THE MEMORIAL PRESENTED TO CONGRESS DOES NOT ATTEMPT TO PRESCRIBE THE FORM OF ACTION TO BE TAKEN BY THAT BODY. IT ASKS ONLY THAT OUR GOVERNMENT, BY SUCH ACTION AS IT SHALL DEEM MOST FITTING, SHALL PROMOTE AN INQUIRY FROM WITHOUT INTO CONDITIONS IN THE CONGO STATE.</p>

<p>Signed on behalf of the Conference,<lb/>
THOMAS S. BARBOUR, <hi rend="italics">Chairman.</hi><lb/>
W. M. MORRISON, <hi rend="italics">Secretary.</hi></p>

<p>Issued by Congo Reform Association,<lb/>
No. 721 Tremont Temple, Boston.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p28"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY REFERENCES.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Profession of Philanthropic Purpose continued at Brussels Conference&#8212;Cited p. 6 (Ref. 3).</p>

<p>1 "The idea of liberating and civilizing the tribes of Central Africa by which the founder (of the Congo State) was inspired * * * is now in a fair way to be realized."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of Baron Lambermont, Belgian Representative and President of Brussels Conference, Session of June 28, 1890.</hi></p>

<p>2 "You know how many lives are daily sacrificed in Africa by the slave trade. Our conscience will not allow us to let such crimes go unpunished even for a time."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Van Maldeghen, Congo Representative at Brussels, June 16, 1890.</hi></p>

<p>Inadequacy of Investigations controlled by King&#8212;Cited p. 11 (Ref. 21).</p>

<p>3 "We do not pretend to be able to determine that the charges are all true, or that they are all untrue, but we are clearly persuaded that they are presented in such form and from such sources as to make them worthy of careful investigation. This fact, indeed, is recognized by the King of Belgium himself in the appointment of a special commission as long ago as last July to conduct the investigation. But it is ridiculous to regard this commission as impartial. It is made up from the very men who are or ought to be investigated. Moreover, its scope of inquiry is limited, and its methods necessarily are such as to deprive it of general confidence. Its creation by the King of Belgium is at once a confession of the need of a thorough inquiry and an effort to prevent it."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Editorial, N. Y. Times, October 1, 1904.</hi></p>

<p>Relation of Congo State to Powers participating in the Conferences&#8212;Cited p. 12 (Ref. 22-24).</p>

<p>4 "The representatives of the Congo State maintained that article IV of the act of Berlin imposes only <hi rend="italics">one limitation</hi> "to the powers that by virtue of our sovereign rights qualify us to establish in our territories such taxes as we see fit."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">From Report of Conference of Brussels.</hi></p>

<p>5 "All the powers exercising rights of influence in the aforesaid territories bind themselves <hi rend="italics">to watch over</hi> the preservation of the native tribes, which in the present state of affairs are scarcely of themselves able to defend their own interests, and to care for the improvement of the conditions of their moral and material well-being. * * * The local powers <hi rend="italics">will be held responsible.</hi>"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">From Protocol of Act of Berlin.</hi></p>

<p>6 "At the Berlin Conference in 1885 the powers took mutual engagements <hi rend="italics">to watch over the preservation of the native population</hi> of Africa and the improvement of their moral and material conditions of life."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Lord Vivian, Brussels Conference, March 14, 1890.</hi></p>

<p>7 "The signatory powers * * * reserve the right of introducing into the present general act, hereafter and by common consent, such modifications or improvements as experience may prove to be useful."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Act of Brussels, Article 97.</hi></p>

<pb n="p29"/>

<p>Status of Congo State defined&#8212;Cited p. 12 (Ref. 24).</p>

<p>8 A Belgian jurist, M. G. Rolin-Jacquemyns, defines the status of the Association at the end of the Berlin Conference as follows: "It is an International Colony, <hi rend="italics">sui generis,</hi> the generous promoter of which has been invested by the recognition and confidence of all the civilized States with the power and mission of governing, in the interest of civilization and of generous commerce, African territories comprised within certain limits which have been conventionally determined."</p>

<p>Trade in the Congo State, Its Importance recognized&#8212;Cited pp. 13, 14 (Ref. 25, 26).</p>

<p>9 "More than twenty years ago, before European occupation of the Congo basin, large commercial houses were established in the territories now belonging to the Congo State. * * * They possessed factories along the whole coast and the course of the rivers."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Representative of the Netherlands, Brussels Conference, June 14, 1890.</hi></p>

<p>10 "This Government, in its anxiety to obtain its proper share of the commerce of the Congo, deemed it proper to trust the preliminary work to your keeping."&#8212;Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Tisdel, Senate Documents, vol. 8, page 347, 48th Congress.</p>

<p>11 "The attitude of the United States in this question has for many years been clear, and in this particular case of the Congo this Government was among the first to proclaim <hi rend="italics">the policy of unrestricted freedom of trade in that vast and productive region.</hi> This Government could, consequently, not be expected to countenance * * * any result falling short of the broad principle it had enunciated."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Kasson, at Berlin, October 17, 1884.</hi></p>

<p>12 "In my opinion, the reported wealth of the Upper Congo valley has not been exaggerated."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Report to Navy Department by Lieut. E. A. Taunt, U. S. N., after six months' journey on the Congo river.</hi></p>

<p>Trade in the Congo State, a large Development promised&#8212;Cited p. 14 (Ref. 27, 28).</p>

<p>13 "I was interested the other day in making a curious calculation. * * * Supposing that all the inhabitants of the Congo basin were simply to have one Sunday dress each, how many yards of cotton cloth would be required? * * * I have said nothing about other cloths. Your own imagination will no doubt carry you to immeasurable and incalculable millions."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Mr. Stanley, address, Chamber of Commerce, Manchester, England, 1884.</hi></p>

<p>14 "The European merchant will go hand in hand with the dark African trader, and justice and law and order shall prevail, and murder and lawlessness and the cruel barter of slaves shall forever cease."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Stanley in "The Congo,"</hi> vol. 1, p. 59.</p>

<p>15 "The Berlin Conference wished to open up Central Africa to trade. Now trade is rushing to it in a ceaselessly increasing tide. On every side commercial establishments are being started. * * * Business follows the agents of the different States step by step in their forward movements. These commercial establishments whose number is ever on the increase, which we found established five years ago at the mouth of the Congo, and which today spread over more than three hundred leagues of the coast, what do they need above all? We do not hesitate to answer * * * that they must before all things have security."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">M. Van Maldeghen, Representative of the Congo State, Brussels Conference, June 2, 1890.</hi></p>

<pb n="p30"/>



</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>