<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0199">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from G.W. Gibson to Secretary of State February 2, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="CAA">Chelsea A. Akyeampong</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0199</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Letter from G.W. Gibson to Secretary of State February 2, 1882</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1882-02-2"></date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PEOPLE NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PLACES NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<!-- IF THIS IS NOT A LETTER, DISPATCH, OR CORRESPONDENCE OF SOME KIND, DELETE <correspDesc> -->

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>G.W. Gibson</persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia</placeName>
<date when="1882-02-02"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName></persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-06-21" who="#CAA">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0199.001"/>

<p>Department of State
    Monrovia February 2, 1882</p>

<p>Sir
      I am directed by the President after careful and anxious
   deliberation in the Cabinet to request you lay before your govern-
   ment the following:</p>

<p>   The Republic of Liberia whose origin and history are well
   known to the govenrment of the United States has now reached
   a period in her history when she surely needs and is fully able to
   bear a large influx of civilized descendants of Africa from the
   United States. An important addition to her civilized population
   is imperatively demanded if she is to go extending her influence
   and pushing her free insitutions against the encroachment of
   foreigners.</p>

<p>    The natives in the interior of the Republic are anxious for
   the planting of civilized settlements on the beautiful hills and in
   the futile valleys which diversify their interesting country. We are 
   pushing on as fact as we can get the emmigrants from the United
   States and our new settlements of civilized industry
    as they advance.</p>

<p>     Arthington and Bremerville foundecd about two years ago in
   dense forests by freed men from North Carolina, Mississipi, Alabama</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0199.002"/>

<p>Lousiana and Arkansas are now beautiful coffee groves with their
   computable fame buildings Christian Churches, School houses and
   workshops, and as the Represetatives of teh Christian religion and
   of American life are attracting the Aborigines drawing them both
   within and around the settlments. But in view of the most work
   to be done, it is comparatively little that can be prosecuted or accom
   plished by the few emigrants sent out at irregular intervals by a
   private association depending for its means upon voluntary contri-
   butions.</p>

<p>     For the last ten or fiften years the operations of the American
   Colonization Society have been confined to one section of the
   Republic for the most of means to send immigrants tas formerly
   to different points along the Coast. The consequence is that the
   civilized population in the three forward coutnries is rapidly dimin
   ishing and leaving the Aborigines to the money of the intrigues
   of designing foreigners who are anxious to see the prestige of Liberia
   not only lowered but destroyed among the natives on the Coast,
   hoping that eventually the six hundred miles of much coveted
   coast with its accessible and desirable interior to the commercial
   possibilities of Liberia, and the dangers to which she is exposed from
   external agencies I beg to refer you to the dispatch of the Hon.
   John H. Smyth the late Minister Resident here published in the
   Foreign Relations of teh United States for 1880. pp 694-707
                                                              The</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0199.003"/>

<p>The native wars which seem periodically among the Aborigines
   and whicha re the result in part of olod feuds leaving their <unclear/>
   in the days of the horrible slave trade, can never be permanently
   suppressed on the Coast and in the adjacent interior the
   presence in these territories of civilized settlements. Even in the
   immediate pressure a neighborhood of so powerful a government
   as that of Sierra Leone it is impossible to present the <unclear/> of
   desoltaing wars in the purely native districts to the detriment of
   trade and against the progress of the people.</p>

<p>     The Shebro and Sierra Leone rivers within British jurisdiction
   and having no settlements of civilized people are frequently the secure
   ruinous tribal wars, while the St Paul's, the Jank, the St. John's,
  and the SImoe Rivers within Liberian jurisdiction and settled by
  Colonists are entirely free from such disturbances. It is in the
  Northwestern and South eastern frontiers of the Republic and 
  in localities within our boundaries distant from the civilized 
  settlements where periodical wars now occur, and where trade
  is interrupted.</p>

<p>    The long pending question relating to the Northwestern boun-
   dary of the Republic is a source of continual annoyance and
   imitation; and the arrangement of it appears to be beyond the
  scope of ordinary diplomacy. The country must be settled by
  civilized immigrants</p>

<p>    During the negotiations of 1850 with aboriginal author-
                                                            ities</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0199.004"/>


</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
