<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1304">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, March 15, 1901</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1304</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, March 15, 1901</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 6</biblScope>
<date when="1901-03-15">March 15,1901</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Weeks, Charles P.</term>
<term>King, C. D. B.</term>
<term>Howard, Jr., T. W.</term>
<term>Cassell, N. H. B.</term>
<term>Houston, J. W. N.</term>
<term>Gant, W. B.</term>
<term>Moore, Wallace F.</term>
<term>Wesley, H. T.</term>
<term>Watson, J. B.</term>
<term>Summerville, J. D.</term>
<term>Roberts, Z. B.</term>
<term>Thomson, J. W. N.</term>
<term>Ashley, W. J.</term>
<term>Leigh, Samuel</term>
<term>Edwards, Ellis</term>
<term>Minick, A. W.</term>
<term>Haag, Hans</term>
<term>Humplmayr, August</term>
<term>Ring, W. A.</term>
<term>Rider, H. T.</term>
<term>Pinnock, F.</term>
<term>Hook, F. J.</term>
<term>Vieweg, J.</term>
<term>Woermann, A.</term>
<term>Bertram, Paul</term>
<term>Biehl, August</term>
<term>Dossen</term>
<term>Rowe, Samuel</term>
<term>Moort, Isaac</term>
<term>Tyler</term>
<term>Blvden</term>
<term>Hartzell, J. C.</term>
<term>Church, M. E.</term>
<term>Howard, Thomas W.</term>
<term>Johnson, H. R. W.</term>
<term>Camphor, A. P.</term>
<term>Bacon, Daniel</term>
<term>Dennis</term>
<term>Edwin, B. G.</term>
<term>Hook, F. J.</term>
<term>Payne, F. J.</term>
<term>Payne, E. C.</term>
<term>McGill, E. U.</term>
<term>Moore, C. R.</term>
<term>Stamer, Rudolf</term>
<term>Gloede, P.</term>
<term>Schultze, Carl</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Grand Bassa County, Liberia</term>
<term>Boston, Massachusetts</term>
<term>New York City, New York</term>
<term>Liverpool, England</term>
<term>Sierra-Leone</term>
<term>Cape Palmas</term>
<term>Sinoe</term>
<term>Cape Mount</term>
<term>Lagos</term>
<term>White Plains</term>
<term>Arthington</term>
<term>Brewerville</term>
<term>Munchen, Bavaria, Germany</term>
<term>Johnsonville, Montserrado County, Liberia</term>
<term>Bristol</term>
<term>Ivory Coast</term>
<term>Manoh River</term>
<term>Freetown, Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Ngaringa</term>
<term>Clay-Ashland</term>
<term>Hamburg, Germany</term>
<term>Netherlands</term>
<term>Sweden</term>
<term>Norway</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Owen L. W.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1901-03-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5692608">Hill, David Jayne, 1850-1932</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1901-04-25"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-11-15" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-3196.jpg"/>

<p><add>Con &amp; <unclear></unclear></add></p>

<p><add>INDEX BUREAU
REC'D
APR 25 '01
DEPT OF STATE.</add></p>

<p><add>ACKNOWLEDGED
MAY 7 1901
Bureau Foreign Commerce</add></p>

<p><add>3rd. ASST. SECRETARY.
APR 27 1901</add></p>

<p>No. 66. Consular.
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia,
March 15, 1901.</p>

<p><add>PRINTED IN ADVANCE SHEETS NO. 1040</add></p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill
Assistant Secretary of State
Washington.</p>

<p>Subject.
A Concession granted to the
Afro-American Steamship
and Mining Company of
Boston.</p>

<p>Synopsis.
The Liberian Government
grants a Concession to a
company of colored men
of Boston to establish a
Steamship, Mining and
Railway Company in Grand
Bassa County Liberia.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3197.jpg"/>

<p>3</p>

<p>No. 66. Consular.
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia;
March 15, 1901.</p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Secretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Sir:
I have the honor to
transit herewith, the
intelligence, that the Liberian
Government, has recently
granted a Concession, to a
Boston company of colored
men; represented here by the
recent arrival of our Charles
P. Weeks, as agent; known
as The Afro-American Steamship
and Mining Company,
of Boston, conceding to said
Company the night to
established a Steamship Company to
operate between Boston
and</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3198.jpg"/>

<p>4</p>

<p>and Liberia, to erect whereas,
and build <unclear></unclear>; rail and tram
ways; and to carry on a system
of Mining opperations, for
a period of Fifty gear. The
Company, however, is to
pay the Liberian Government, a consideration of
Ten Thousand Dollars, for
there special privileges.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be
your obedient servant;
Owen L. W. Smith,
Consul General.</p>

<p>Inclosure.
Liberia Recorder Feb'y 28, 1901.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3199.jpg"/>

<p><add>Hon. O. L. W. Smith</add></p>

<p><add><gap reason="missing"/> page 3.</add></p>

<p>The
Liberia Recorder</p>

<p>"VIVAT RESPUBLICA."</p>

<p>Vol. III. No. 24. <gap/> MONROVIA, Thursday, February 28, 1901. <gap/> Price 8c.</p>

<p>"The Liberia Recorder"
IS PUBLISHED IN MONROVIA. LIBERIA, WEST
COAST OF AFRICA,
On the 2nd and 4th Thursdays of each month.</p>

<p>At One Dollar and Seventy-five
cents per annum, payable in advance,
and is sent to any part of the world on
the payment of 25c extra for postage.</p>

<p>ALL COMMUNICATIONS for publication
or otherwise must be addressed to the Editor
"The Liberia Recorder."</p>

<p>C. D. B. KING, . . . . . . Editor.</p>

<p>ASSISTING EDITORS:
T. W. HOWARD, Jr., and THE REV. N. H. B.
CASSELL.</p>

<p>BUSINESS MANAGER:
J. W. N. HOUSTON.</p>

<p>AGENTS:
Brewerville--W. B. Gant, Esq.
Arthington--W. F. Moore, Esq.
White Plains--H. T. Wesley, Esq.
Cape Mount--J. B. Watson, Esq.
Grand Bassa--Hon. J. D. Summerville.
Sinoe--Hon. Z. B. Roberts, C. J.
Cape Palmas--J. W. N. Thomson, Esq.
Sierra-Leone--W. J. Ashley, Esq.
Lagos--Hon. Sam'l Leigh, Liberian Consul.
Liverpool--Hon. Ellis Edwards, Liberian
Consul.
New York--Hon. A. W. Minick, Liberian Consul.</p>

<p>THE LIBERIA RECORDER is the cheapest and most
effective advertising medium in the Republic having a
very wide commercial circulation both at home and
abroad.</p>

<p>Press of the New Africa, Monrovia, Liberia.</p>

<p>NOTICE! NOTICE!!
The public is hereby notified that Mr.
Hans Haag, of the city of Munchen,
Bavaria, Germany, and formerly of the
firm of "Humplmayr &amp; Haag," carrying
on farming operations at Johnsonville,
in the County of Montserrado, and
the Republic of Liberia, has dissolved
his connection with said firm, and that
the business of the said firm will be
carried on as heretofore, by Agust
Humplmayr alone under the name and style of
the "Liberian Coffee Plantation."
AUGUST HUMPLMAYR.
Monrovia, Liberia,
January 22nd, 1901.</p>

<p>AFRICAN STEAMSHIP CO.,
(Incorporated in 1852 by Royal Charter.)
ROYAL MAIL STEAMERS FROM LIVERPOOL
TO WEST COAST
OF AFRICA.
W. A. RING, Agent.</p>

<p>BRITISH AND AFRICAN STEAM NAVIGATION CO., LTD.
Royal Mail Steamers
FROM
Liverpool to West Coast of Africa.
W. A. RING, Agent.</p>

<p>RIDER &amp; PINNOCK,
H. T. RIDER, from Rider, Son &amp; Andrew, of Bristol and the Ivory Coast,
F. PINNOCK, from James Pinnock, of Liverpool and the Oil Rivers. 
West African Commission Agents and Merchants.
I Rumford Court,
LIVERPOOL.</p>

<p>We supply ALL CLASSES OF GOODS suitable for the WEST AFRICAN
MARKET at LOWEST POSSIBLE PRICES.
The enormous opportunities at our command give us a splendid field from
which to draw our supplies in this line. SUPERIOR QUALITY above everything.
PRODUCE consigned to us for sale will be realised at highest market prices obtainable.
INDENTS should be accompanied by either CASHH or PRODUCE.</p>

<p>We are the Sole Liverpool Agents
for Messsrs. J. R. PHILLIPS &amp;
Co.'s Wines and Spirits.
GINGER WINE a specialty.</p>

<p>Write us! No trouble to correspond with you! We
defy CONTRADICTION! We court INVESTIGATION!
WE CHALLENGE any EQUALITY!
Do you want samples? We'll send them.</p>

<p>SEND US your produce.
Agent for Monrovia, F. J. HOOK, Water Street, Monrovia.</p>

<p>NOTICE!
The undersigned having returned to
this country begs to inform his friends,
that he has taken charge again of the
business of the Oost Afrikaansche
Compagnie in Liberia.
J. VIEWEG,
Head Agent
Monrovia, 28th Dec., 1900.</p>

<p>NOTICE!
The undersigned begs to inform the
public that he has been appointed Agent
for A. Woermann at Monrovia, in the
place of Paul Bertram who a few days
ago, left for Germany owing to illness.
Customers will please take notice.
AUGUST BIEHL.
Monrovia, December 13th, 1900.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3200.jpg"/>

<p>2 <gap/> THE LIBERIA RECORDER.</p>

<p>Associate Justice Dossen's
speech delivered before His
Excellency the President in
behalf of the Supreme Court
of this Republic at the opening
of its Annual Sessions.</p>

<p>Mr. President:--The mighty wheel of time
has moved steadily onward and in its revolution,
has brought around again the time fixed
by the laws of this Republic, for the Annual
session of the Supreme Court of Liberia, which
we have the distinguished honor to represent.</p>

<p>It is to us a cause for unfeigned thanks to the
great Disposer of all things, that this ARM of
State, which is the highest expounder of the
laws under which we live; the guardian of the
civil and religious rights and liberties of this
people and the source from whence flows a
pure, unpolluted stream of Justice and Equity,
has been preserved through all the vicissitudes
of the past year, and that  we are today sound
in limb and mind and able to enter upon the
discharge of those grave and solemn duties
imposed upon us by law.</p>

<p>It is also a source of gratification to us, that
we find Your Excellency in the enjoyment of
health and surrounded by the most cheering
prospects, of a grand and prosperous future, in
the new position, which by operation of law,
you are called upon to fill.</p>

<p>In keeping with a time-honored custom of
this Tribunal, we are here, sir, to pay you officially,
our respects and to pledge you the warm,
unflinching support and earnest co-opperation
of this branch of the Government, in every
wise and legitimate measure of Your Excellency's
administration.</p>

<p>We wish here to assure Your Excellency, that
we highly appreciate the patriotism which
influenced you to accept the high office you now
fill, as the first citizen of your country, under
circumstances so unique in the history of this
Republic-Circumstances, which have
convulsed and revolutionized nations far greater
than this, and with centuries of growth and
civilization behind them. We take it as indicative
of the political genius, skill, patriotism and
predisposition of the people of Liberia to good
order,--(which, we would remark, is a cogent
reputation of the unfounded theory touching
the Negro's unfitness for self-government) that
the dangerous chasm which lately happened in
our national life, was safely bridged, without
producing any of those civil catastrophes,
which have in the past, over taken other countries,
passing through a similar ordeal.</p>

<p>To be the President of the Republic of Liberia;
to direct the destinies of the people, whom
ROBERTS, BENSON, and others ruled and
covered with renown; to see that no evil befall
this sacred heritage bequeathed unto us by the
immortal fathers--a heritage made dear to us
by their toils and their blood,--this is no light
task. He must study the welfare of the whole
common-wealth without respect to rank or
condition. He must thoroughly recognize his
responsibility to the people whom he would
successfully serve and seek to discharge that
responsibility in every wise and legitimate way.
He must place himself in touch of leading and
popular thoughts and march to the music of a
brilliant future.</p>

<p>The people in their majesty, through the
operation of laws made by their lawful
representatives, having selected you to be the standard-bearer
of this nation, we believe, that the
act has the approval of God; and that relying
upon the wisdom and power of Him who rules</p>

<p>the unverse, you shall not only succeed in
keeping in tact all that has been committed to
your trust, but that you will be instrumental
in leading forth this Republic to greater glory
and brighter renown.</p>

<p>We believe, sir, that the country can rely
with safety and composure, upon your broad
wisdom, sound, statesmanlike judgment and
unflinching devotion to duty;--already demonstrated
by a long and brilliant career in the
service of your country, to guard with vigil
watchfulness the rights and liberties of this
people; to represent their claims before the
cabinets of the civilized world; to promote the
happiness,.peace and prosperity of both citizen
and foreigner and to maintain for us, that civil
recognition and relgious freedom, which the
sleeping SIres of this rising Republic, laboured,
bled and died to secure to us and to our posterity.</p>

<p>On behalf of the JUDICIARY of the Republic
of Liberia, we congratulate Your Excellency,
and we wish you a long and a useful life, good
health and signal prosperity. We trust, sir,
that the happy relatious which have always
existed between the Executive and Judiciary
Branches of the Government may continue
uninterrupted for all future.</p>

<p>The Liberia Recorder,
Monrovia, Thursday, Feb. 28, 1901.</p>

<p>The Close of our third Year.</p>

<p>To-day marks the completion of our third
year in the field of Liberian journalism, which
after all said and done, is a most trying and
difficult one.</p>

<p>Many of our readers, no doubt will be anxious
to know whether this issue may not be regarded
as the last toll of our death knell declaring
the curtain dropt over us, and placing them
under the painful necessity of tracing our
vestiges along a beaten track, where their last
traces may have been obliterated, and their final
sounds long hushed in the distant air. To
this we answer, no. This issue leaves us a living
entity in the field of journalism.</p>

<p>The duty of a public journalist especially in
a community like ours is quite a thankless one.</p>

<p>During this short period of our existence
we have been called upon to steer into and
encounter fruitful sources of temptation and
alluring tendencies,-shoals and sand banks to
which a journal managed and controled by
young and in experienced men must be
exposed, and upon which many older and more
experienced journalists have too often become
stranded and floundered, thereby failing to be
any longer a faithful exponent of public opinion
or a true fidei defensor of the constitutional
rights and privileges of the people.</p>

<p>Whether we have avoided these shoals and
sand banks is a question which we leave entirely
with our readers to decide.</p>

<p>As journalists we are aware that we have not
pleased all parties, nor aided out all nations,
whether they be political, social, religious, racial
or otherwise, and that amidst well defined
policies many to whose personal wishes we did
not pander found room to impute base and
unworthy motives.</p>

<p>During this our journalistic year which is
now at its close, our working expenses have
been a little increased and our returns though</p>

<p>far from being as we should have wished them,
have on the whole been satisfactory.</p>

<p>In a Leader of our issue of Oct. 12, 1899, we
said, "There are a good many readers of the
RECORDER who have got into the shameful
habit of going about borrowing the paper from
those who had t satisfy the Editor before they
could get them to read."</p>

<p>This practice if discouraged by our subscribers
would materially assist us, because by such
discouragement we shall have the opportunity
of adding many more names to our list of our
subscribers at the commencement of our fourth
volume from the ranks of those who read but do not subscribe.</p>

<p>In closing this our third volume we have to
express to our subscribers, literary contributors,
both at home and abroad, and to all who
have directly or indirectly aided us heartfelt
thanks and gratitude and humbly request their
continued support and encouragement during
the ensuing year.</p>

<p>We also record our appreciations of the good
feelings and amicable relations which have
existed between our local contemporaries, the
Baptist Monitor, the Cape Palmas Reporter, the
New Africa and ourselves--feelings and relations
which cannot but have a salutary effect up
on journalism in Liberia. Each journal furnishing
materials, in its own way, and instilling
principles on which to build up a strong
national fabric with a healthy public opinion which
till now may be considered as in its embryo.</p>

<p>As our next volume will be opened by a
new Editor we cannot outline a policy which
will be pursued during the ensuing year, but
we are sure, however, that schemes will be
developed which will encourage a greater interest
in the LIBERIA RECORDER to such an extent
that in every house where there is an intelligent
reader a copy of this paper will find and
enterance.</p>

<p>Our collector will wait on our local subscribers
for the renewal of their subscriptions and
we trust that he will be pleasantly received and
his requests be attended to.</p>

<p>Not easy for a President.</p>

<p>In the space of a short article it would be
impossible to enumerate the many grave
responsibilities resting upon the President, all of
which require extraordinary ability. Consider
his legislative functions only. He is required
to approve every law passed by the Legislature,
or to return it without his signature--but that
seldom occurs.</p>

<p>The President, generally, has fixed and intelligent
ideas on all subjects of legislation, and
either approves or vetoes. As an executive
officer, he has to administer every department of
the Government; to conduct our foreign relations;
to carry on war and to conserve peace;
to collect and discharge the revenues; to supervise
the administration of Justice; to carry on
the mail service, both domestic and foreign;
to execute the laws relating to the Aboriginees,
public lands, mines patents, and an infinite
variety of other subjects; to govern the Interior;
and to make treaties. In the performance of
the last named duty, he is guided by the advice
and consent of the Senate.</p>

<p>Waiving all the thoughts of these numerous
and onerous executive functions, which, in
themselves call for superior ability, he must,
as above stated, devote much time and ability
to legislation.</p>

<p>The veto power was placed in his hand as
a great perogative to insure the independence
of the Executive. By it alone can the executive</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3201.jpg"/>

<p><gap/>THE LIBERIA RECORDER. <gap/>3</p>

<p>office itself and the rights of the people be
protected from encroachments upon the part of
the legislature and judicial branches of the
government. It is a very great power, and,
by most of the PResidents, has been very sparingly
used; yet, without its sagacious and
intelligent exercise form of government would be
a sad failure. This signal prerogative on the
part of the PResident calls for very great ability
and discretion. The power of the veto cannot
be entrusted to an inferior, ignorant or capricious
man, nor to one who has not carefully
studied the history and government of the
country at large.</p>

<p>Therefore in our selections of candidates for
the Presidency and Vice our leaders should
have an eyesingle in these directions.</p>

<p><add>x</add>The Manoah River Question.<add>x</add></p>

<p>There is a matter of vital importance in
connection with our relations with Great Britain,
which we would like to call the Executive
Government's immediate attention to, with the
view of their opening correspondence with His
Majesty's Government relative to the settlement
thereof; provided if such steps have not
already been taken. We refer to the propriety
of allowing the citizens of the Republic equal
right to the free navigation of the Manoh River;
which right is at present denied, based upon
the second article of the Convention concluded
between Great Britain and Liberia at Freetown,
Sierra Leone, on the eleventh day of November
A. D. 1885, by Sir Samuel Rowe, K.C.M.G.,
Governor and Commander-in-chief of Sierra
Leone and H. B. M.'s Consul for Liberia, representing
Great Britain, and the Honorables
Henry W. Grimes and Benjamin Anderson in
behalf of the PResident of the Republic of Liberia,
which article reads as follows:</p>

<p>"The line marking the North Western boundary
of the Republic of Liberia shall commence
at the point on the sea coast at which at low
water, the line of the South Western or left
bank of the Manoh River intersects the general
line of the sea coast and shall be continued
along the line marked by low water on the
South Western or left bank of the Manoh River
until such line or such line prolonged in a
North Easterly direction intersects the line or
the prolongation of the line marking the north
eastern or inland boundary of the territories of
the Republic, within Liberian Territory the
Town or Bopora and such other towns as shall
be hereafter acknowledged to have belonged to
the Republic at the time of signing of this
Convention."</p>

<p>From the above article it is easily seen that
instead of the Manoh River itself marking the
North Western boundary of this Republic it is
the left bank of said River at low water which
intersects the general line of the sea coast.</p>

<p>Now, article third which describes Great
Britain's boundary reads also as follows.</p>

<p>"The President of the Republic of Liberia
hereby recognizes the recent acquisition by Her
Majesty's Government of certain portions of
territory which makes the South Eastern boundary
of Her Majesty's possessions in this portion
of the line of the north western boundary of
the Republic of Liberia as described in article
II, which commences at the point on the sea
coast at which at low water the line of the South
Western or left bank of the Mannoh River
intersects the general line of the sea coast and
which terminates at the point on the line of the
said North Western boundary line nearest to the
town of Ngaringa situated on the right bank of
the Manoh River."</p>

<p>It is quite obvious that this article concedes
to Great Britain the entire river, which if had
been wonded thus, "The President of the
Republic of Liberia hereby recognizes the recent
acquisition by Her Majesty's Government of
certain portions of territory which mark the
South Eastern boundary of Her Majesty's
posessions in this portion of West Africa the
boundary of which commences at the point on the
sea coast at which at low water the line of the
South Eastern or right bank of the Manoh
River intersects the general line of the sea
coast" etc. etc., the River, then not being included
within the territorial limits of either government
its navigation would have unquestionably
been free and opened to the subjects and citizens
of both governments, as it is a well settled
principle of International Law, that the boundary
which divides two seperate states is neutral
ground and is accessable as a common highway
between the citizens of both states.</p>

<p>There is no concealing of the fact that the
failure on the part of the Special Commissioners
of the Government to obtain from the British
Government reciprocal rights for the use of the
Manoh River was a serious oversight and omission;
the effects of which largely hamper and
retard the commercial intersts of the Republic.</p>

<p>The greater portion of the trade in that
particular section of the country is on our side of
the river a great distance up, and our merchants
at Cape Mount not being allowed the
right of navigation on said river can only get
their goods and produce to and fro over-land
with the assistance of carriers; which means to
them an enormous outlay of money and a most
unprofitable business, besides a great waste of
time; whereas the English merchant who has
the free use of the river can easily convey to
and from said point 10 and 20 tons of cargo in
a less time and at less expense, by means of
a boat or vessel, than the Liberian merchant,
who would have to employ not less than 500 to
1000 carriers to convey the same quantity of
goods to said point.</p>

<p>Just a month ago a Liberian trader by the
name of Hoff was seized by the English authorities
on the other side of the River for attempting
to navigate said River for the purpose of
trade, but has since been released, as we are
informe,d under a strong reprimand. We are
however of the opinion that it si not the intention
of Great Britain to knowlingly take any
undrue advantage of this Republic directly or
indirectly, and the attitude assumed by the British
Government towards Liberia in all matters
pertaining to her interests and welfare, heretofore,
points in this direction.</p>

<p>In view therefore of the present harmonious
relations existing between the Governments of
Great Pritain anad this Republic, governments,
too, whose interests on this coast are so closely
identified and whose boundaries are conterminous
we think that the British Government would
unhesitingly come to a fair and equitable
arrangement with the Government of this Republic,
allowing its citizens equal rights to the free
navigation of the Manoh River for the purpose
of trade provided the proper steps be taken
by this government towards effecting such an
arrangement with the "Home Authorities."</p>

<p>NOTES.</p>

<p>APPOINTMENTS.</p>

<p>The President has appointed Mr. Wallace F.
Moore of the firm of Hill &amp; Moore, to fill the</p>

<p>position of Treasurer of the Republic made
vacant by the death of the Hon. Thos. W. Howard.</p>

<p>The President has also appointed Mr. Isaac
Morrt, ex-Auditor, Secretary of the General
Post Office in consequence of the resignation
of Mr. E. C. Johnson.</p>

<p>Judge Tyler of the Monthly and Probate
Court of Grand Bassa has also been appointed
Judge of the Court of Quarter Session and
Common Pleas of said County.</p>

<p>DR. BLVDEN.</p>

<p>Doctor Blyden who has recently been elected
President of Liberia College left here by the
steamship Benguea for the leeward for the
benefit of his health. The Doctor's health of
late has not been in the best condition.</p>

<p><add>x</add>BISHOP HARTZELL. <add>x</add></p>

<p>Bishop J. C. Hartzell of the M. E. Church
arrived in this city on the 25 ult. per S. S.
Alexandra Woermann.</p>

<p>The Bishop will open and preside over the
Liberia Annual Conference which is to convene
at Clay-Ashland on the 5th inst.</p>

<p>AN IRREGULARITY IN THE COURT OF GRAND
BASSA.</p>

<p>The following has been brought to our notice:
That there are at present two prosecuting
officers in the Courts of Bassa County known as
the "County Attorney" and the "Assistant
County Attorney" and that these officers
receive an annual salary of $400 each.</p>

<p>This is quite irregular and illegal. Whilst
there is a law providing for a prosecuting officer
in each county to be designated as the "County
Attorney," yet there is none extant in our statute
book providing for a permanent Assistant
County Attorney. If the present encbumbent is
incapable to fill the position, why, another
should be appointed, or if he is fully capable to
fill the position, do away with the assistant and
thereby curtail this unnecessary expense, and
put this portion of the revenue of that county
to better use.</p>

<p>We earnestly call the attention of the Executive
to this irregularity with the view of having
matters immediately looked into.</p>

<p>Montserrado County which has the largest
legal business in the Republic has not yet seen
the necessity of having two prosecuting officers.</p>

<p><add>x</add>DEATH OF EX-PRESIDENT JOHNSON.</p>

<p>As we are going to press information has just
reached us of the death of the Honorable H. R.
W. Johnson, Ex-President of this Republic
which has just occurred at his residence in this
city at 8.30 p.m. Full particulars will appear
in our next issue.</p>

<p>OUR NEW EDITOR.</p>

<p>Mr. Thomas W. Howard, Post Master of the
Port of Monrovia, has been elected Managing
Editor of this paper by its proprietors at their
last annual meeting held in this city.</p>

<p>The paper, under the management of Mr.
Howard, who has for a long time been its
Assistant Editor, will, we are sure, have a bright
future before it and will given general satisfaction
to its readers.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3202.jpg"/>

<p>4 <gap/> THE LIBERIA RECORDER.</p>

<p>ABLERT W. MINICK,
56 Hudson St., New York City.
Export and Import Merchant, Receiver of all
kinds of African Products, COFFEE A SPECIALTY,
and special facilities and connections
for selling same.
Orders executed for every kind of
goods against shipments of Coffee.</p>

<p>No Commission Charged
For selling Coffee or executing orders when Coffee is shipped to cover
same, otherwise a commission of one per cent will be charged for
selling.</p>

<p>CORRESPONDENCE INVITED.
References:
Bishop J. C. Hartzell, D. D., LL. D.,
Prof. A. P. Camphor, A. M., D.D.,
Daniel Bacon, Esq., of the British &amp; African Steam Navigation Co., Ltd., and African Steamship Co.</p>

<p>HOUSTON BROTHERS AND COMPANY,
WATER STREET, MONROVIA.
GENERAL MERCHANTS.</p>

<p>RECEIVE CONSIGNMENTS, BY EVERY STEAMER, OF LADIES' AND
GENTLEMEN'S REQUISITES, LATEST STYLES IN HATS, BOOTS, FANCY
TWEED STUFFS SUITABLE FOR LADIES' COSTUMES AND
MILLINERY REQUISITES; ALSO LADIES' AND GENTLEMEN'S SHOES
AND BOOTS, RIBBONS, TIES, SHIRTS AND COLLARS, COTTONS,
PRINTS OF EVERY DESCRIPTION TO MEET THE PRODUCE MAKET.</p>

<p>WINES, BEER, SPIRITS, AND VARIOUS LIQUORS, POWDER IN KEGS,
TOBACCO, GUNS, CARTRIDGES, BRASS KETTLES, PAINTS, PAINT
OIL, ETC.</p>

<p>INVITED INSPECTION, TRIAL SOLICITED.
Lowest prices quoted for cash.
Orders taken for English and Continental Monufactured Goods.
For further particulars, call at our office.</p>

<p>7 Alexandra Buildings,
Ormond Street,
LIVERPOOL.
September 1st, 1900.</p>

<p>The LIBERIAN CONSULATE has been removed
from Batavia Buildings, Hackins Hey, to the
above address. <gap/> ELLIS EDWARDS,
Liberian Consul.</p>

<p>JANTZEN &amp; THORMAHLEN, Hamburg.</p>

<p>This well known firm of Commission
Merchants are prepared to execute any Order sent
to them by their Liberian friends for all classes
of goods.</p>

<p>In order to assist our farmers and others
who have suffered from the great fall in price
of coffee, they will execute any Order sent them,
upon payment of one-fourth the probable value
of same to us, the balance to be paid on delivery
of the goods here in Monrovia, within in specified
time to be agreed upon by the sender and
ourselves when making the Order.</p>

<p>For further particulars of address, etc., apply
to the undersigned.</p>

<p>DENNIS BROS.
Water and Centre Streets, Monrovia.</p>

<p>American Lumber
OF ALL DESCRIPTIONS.
FOR SALE
CARL SCHULTZE,
Monrovia.</p>

<p>NOTICE!
CONSULATE OF THE NETHERLANDS,
SWEDEN AND NORWAY.
Having returned to this country, I have taken
charge again of the above named consulates.
J. VIEWEG,
Consul.
Monrovia, 28th Dec., 1900.</p>

<p>Edwards Brothers,
LIVERPOOL.
SHIPPERS FOR
30 YEARS to Liberia.
GOODS of kind shipped promptly
and at lowest possible prices.
Special attention given to the sale of
PRODUCE.</p>

<p>CARL SCHULTZE,
MONROVIA.
ORDERS TAKEN FOR ABROAD
SHIPPING &amp; FORWARDING
OF PRODUCTS.</p>

<p>AFRICA'S GIFT TO THE BRITISH NATION!!
A Boon to all that suffer from
RHEUMATISM, GOUT LUMBAGO,
PAINS IN THE CHEST BRONCHITIS, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>

<p>EDWIN'S CELEBRATED
AFRICAN OINTMENT
The PRODUCT of a well-known AFRICAN
TREE prepared with great skill and care
by
B. G. EDWIN,
68, Great George St.,
LIVERPOOL.
Price IS. 1 1/2d per box.
Agent for Monrovia, F. J. HOOK,
Water St., Monrovia.</p>

<p>NOTICE!
All persons having claims against the
Estates of F. J. and E. C. Payne, will
present them properly authenticated--
and all persons indebted to said Estates,
will come forward for settlement within
(90) ninety days from date.
E. U. M'GILL, Administrator.
C. R. MOORE, Administrtrix.
Monrovia,
January 29th, 1901.</p>

<p>NOTICE!
I hereby beg to inform the public generally,
that Mr. Rudlof Stamer has succeeded Mr. P.
Gloede as agent of my business,
Carl Schultze.
1st January, 1901.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>