<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0083">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Washington Bee, "A Queer People" (1883)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0083</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">A Queer People</title>
<title level="j">The Washington Bee</title>
<pubPlace>Washington (D.C.)</pubPlace>
<date when="1883-03-17">March 17, 1883</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-19" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0083.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>A Queer People.</p>

<p>They Believe the White Man To Be the Evil One&#8212;A Country Where Scandal is Unknown&#8212;Feeding the King of Terror.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>The Rev. William A. Fair, who recently returned from his missionary labors on the western coast of Africa, gives an interesting account of the religion and customs of the heathen natives. He says the country on the western coast of Africa is very fertile. As a good illustration of this I will give the native mode of cultivating sweet potatoes. The potatoes are dug out of the ground, and the tops, which have been cut off, inserted in the hole. In a few months a new crop is found at the roots of the old vines. A kind of cotton is found growing wild, and from it the native women weave cloth. The people are very careful to keep their teeth clean, and those of them who own tooth brushes carry them over their ears, as a clerk does his pencil. Provide 1 with a beaver hat, a tooth brush, a leather purse and a number of ivory and brass rings for his limbs, the native requires little else to make him a man of fashion. Each man has as many wives as he can support, and as the latter do all the work, those who are well provided for have but little labor to perform. They believe in a God who created all things; also in a devil, and as the latter is powerful and disposed to do them harm, they try by all means to propitiate him. Contrary to our supposition, they regard him as being white instead of black, and when the white men appeared on the coast with their great ships filled with rooms, and propelled by some mysterious means, they thought the devils had come to visit them. Even now that supposition is not entirely eradicated, and more by habit than anything else they call us devils. Among the majority of them the belief still lingers that we are related to the king of terrors, and as they regard him with a certain amount of awe and reverence, we are allowed many privileges which they do not accord to one another. They have what is called "devil men," who propitiate the evil spirits and prevent them from doing harm by means of charms. Little leather bags, supposed to possess mystic power, are sold by them at high prices, and the natives pay them well for sticking little pieces of wood in a triangular loan in front of their huts. The same charms are frequently seen on the sea shore to guard against the evil spirits of the deep. The devil is supposed to reside on the highest rock near to a village, and he is daily furnished with food and drink placed there by those who fear his power. Little sacred fires are kept burning before the doors of the huts for the comfort of the guardian spirit who is supposed to watch over each individual habitation. When a woman throws water out of the door, she says words equivalent to "excuse me," fearing that the spirit will depart, if he is splashed and not given warning to get out of the way. They believe that the spirits of the dead inhabit the earth, watching over their former friends and tormenting their former enemies. This fact, as well as their belief in witchcraft, has much to do with the extreme peacefulness of their society and their reticence to pick a quarrel. Witchcraft they believe in implicitly. If a man dies of consumption, smallpox, or at any other disease or accident, and any person can be remembered to have spoken ill of or quarreled with him, that person is said to have caused his death by witchcraft. If the witch be a woman, she is given three bowls filled with a deadly poison, and if a man, he is given four bowls of the same mixture. If the unfortunate being accused of witchcraft has a weak stomach which rejects the poison, he is supposed to be innocent, but if his stomach is strong and retains the deadly infusion, he is guilty. When the body of the victim begins to swell and death is seen to be drawing near, the people seize him, and dragging him out into the open air, pelt him with stones and clubs and injure him in every possible manner until he dies. If a person accused of being a witch refuses to drink the poison he is placed in the loft of a hut and a hot fire built under him. Pepper is thrown into the flames and the tortured, being in the loft, soon consents to risk the trial of the powerful drug. The manner of finding the person who caused the death of any one is as follows: The corpse is sometimes placed on the shoulders of the relatives, who pretend to be moved by the spirit of the departed, and passing from hut to hut stop at the witch's door. One of the offices performed by the devil men is to watch sharply for any controversy that may take place tween any two people, and when one of them dies the other is accused of causing his death. I have seen mothers killed for the death of their babes, having chastised them at some former time for a misdemeanor. A high priest lives in each town, and his person and premises are peculiarly sacred. If a man is pursued by a crowd of his fellows for having committed some deed, and he steps across the threshold of the priest's house, he is safe from injury, and if the high priest places his hand on his head he is exempt from all further violence.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
