<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0167">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies, "Memorandum on Christian Missions in Africa at the Peace Conference" (1919)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0167</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Memorandum on Christian Missions in Africa at the Peace Conference</title>
<date when="1919">1919</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>The National Archives, Kew, UK</repository>
<collection>Foreign Office</collection>
<idno>608/219</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>   

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39370745">Bourne, Cardinal, 1861-1935</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27094651">Curzon of Kedleston, George Nathaniel Curzon, Marquess, 1859-1925</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>London (England)</term>
<term>India</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Ireland</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Catholic</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref=" http://viaf.org/viaf/8182769">Oldham, J. H. (Joseph Houldsworth), 1874-1969</persName>
<placeName>London (England)</placeName>
<date when="1898-05-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29574721">Balfour, Arthur James, 1848-1930</persName>
<roleName>British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</roleName>
<placeName>London (England)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-05" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.001.jpg"/>

<p>No. 240<lb/>
(5976 / W50)</p>

<p>Earl Curzon of Kedleston presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit herewith copy of the undermentioned paper for disposal. No action with regard to it has been taken in the Foreign Office except that receipt has been acknowledged, and copies transmitted to Colonial Office</p>

<p>Foreign Office,<lb/>
30th Janry, 1919.</p>

<p>Description of Enclosure.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Name and Date.</cell>
<cell>Subject.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>From Conference of Missionary Societies in Great Britain &amp; Ireland</cell>
<cell>Christian Missions in Africa</cell>
</row>
</table>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.002.jpg"/>

<p>Conference of Missionary Societies,<lb/> 
in Great <sic>Britan</sic> and Ireland,<lb/>
117 Victoria Street, S.W.1.<lb/>
10th January, 1919.</p>

<p>Sir:-</p>

<p>I am directed by the Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies, in which the missionary organizations of all the Christian bodies in Great Britain and Ireland other than the Roman Catholics are officially represented, to transmit the accompanying Memorandum on the subject of Christian missions in Africa at the Peace Conference and to ask for its favourable consideration by His Majesty's Government.</p> 

<p>I am. &amp;c.,<lb/>
(Signed) J.H. Oldham.</p>

<fw type="address">The Right Honourable,<lb/>
Arthur J. Balfour, F.R.S., O.M., M.P.,<lb/>
H.M. Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs<lb/>
Foreign Office,<lb/>
London. S.W.1.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.003.jpg"/>

<p>Memorandum on Christian Missions in Africa at the Peace Conference.</p>

<p>(1) This Memorandum is submitted by the Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies in which the missionary organizations of all the Christian bodies in Great Britain and Ireland other than the Roman Catholics are officially represented.</p>

<p>(2) The General Act of the Conference of Berlin in 1885 contains an article providing in explicit terms for freedom of conscience and religious toleration and for liberty for Christian missions to carry on their work in the parts of Africa covered by the Act. The full text of the article is quoted in an appendix. The Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies desire to represent to His Majesty's Government that in the event of any international agreement with reference to the future government of tropical Africa being reached at the Peace Conference the rights and liberties secured to Christian missions under the Berlin Act should be conserved. The Committee are confident that Christian public opinion in Great Britain and America will expect that in the endeavours of the Peace Conference to lay the foundations of a new order based on justice and right the disinterested and beneficent work of Christian missions on behalf of the native races of Africa will not be <catchwords>placed/</catchwords> 

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.004.jpg"/>

placed in a less favourable position than that accorded to it by the Berlin Act.</p>

<p>3. The Committee are aware of the practical difficulties arising out of the war in reaffirming the Article of the Berlin Act in its present form. <unclear>They</unclear> do not regard all the provisions of the Article as essential. Having given careful thought to the subject they desire to submit a statement of their views of the course that might reasonably be adopted in conformity with the declared policy of His Majesty's Government and of other governments with reference to Christian missions. While other Powers have at different times entered into treaties guaranteeing religious toleration and freedom for the work of Christian missions, reference is made here, for the sake of brevity, only to the policy of the American and British Governments.</p> 

<p>Policy of the American Government.</p>

<p>(4) The general policy of the Government of the United States in regard to missionaries and missionary questions is set forth in a statement from the <unclear>Solicitor</unclear> for the Department of State in Washington <unclear>communicates</unclear> to the World Missionary Conference held in Edinburgh in 1910, and printed in Volume VII of the Report of that Conference (pp.123-34). A summary of the policy as expressed in treaties and correspondence between the United States and other Powers is given in the following quotation:</p>

<p>"The policy of the United States is that missionaries and merchants stand upon an equality in the eye of 
the law; that every man, whether he be preacher <catchwords>or</catchwords> 

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.005.jpg"/>

or man of affairs, is first of all a citizen of the United States, and, as such, entitled to protection to his person and property so far as international law permits, and the right, whether he be tradesman or churchman, to follow his calling. Just as the United States has entered into innumerable commercial treaties in order to secure for American industry and commerce in foreign parts equal rights and privileges with the native, so the United States has entered into treaties with various countries by the terms of which American missionaries are specifically granted the right to reside within the territory, to acquire property necessary for their mission, and to preach the Gospel to natives, provided that this be done without seeking to disturb the political organisation of the country in which they reside."</p>

<p>Policy of His Majesty's Government.</p>
 
<p>(5) The policy of His Majesty's Government in regard to Christian missions has recently been the subject of discussion between the Government and the Conference of Missionary Societies in Great Britain and Ireland. As the result of these discussions the Government has drawn up memoranda embodying its policy. The memoranda in their present form deal only with India, but it is understood that the same policy will be applied to other parts of the Empire. This statement of policy <unclear>has</unclear> received the approval of the Conference of Missionary Societies. The main features of this policy are the following:</p>

<p><catchwords>(a) The/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.006.jpg"/>

(a) The services of Christian missions in protect the material and moral welfare of <sic>polulations</sic> under British rule are recognised and their co-operatives in the future welcomed in the opening paragraph of the memoranda in the following terms:</p>
 
<p>"Appreciating to the full the value of the work done in the past by missionary and other philanthropic societies and organisations, His Majesty's Government and the Government of India cordially welcome their co-operation in the future in furthering the <unclear>moral</unclear> and material well-being of the peoples of India."</p>

<p>(b) So far as Great Britain and America are <unclear>concerned</unclear> the policy rests upon the voluntary co-operation of the Conference of Missionary Societies in Great Britain and Ireland and of the Foreign Missions Conference of North America with His Majesty's Government. The Conference <unclear>will</unclear> submit to the Government lists of "recognised" societies which they believe to be prepared to assume, and to be capable of exercising, responsibility for the control of their missionaries. No restrictions will be imposed on missionaries of these societies. Missionaries of societies that are not "recognised" must obtain a permit from the Government authorising them to carry on their work. In any question that may arise between His Majesty's Government and any recognised society or member of such society the Government will address the Conference, who will use their good offices to regulate the affair.</p>

<p>In regard to Roman Catholic missions, His Majesty's Government will <unclear/> Cardinal Archbishop <catchwords>of/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.007.jpg"/>

of Westminster who will in the same way recommend to His Majesty's Government a list of "recognised" societies.</p>
 
<p>(c) In the interests of public security missionaries of alien enemy nationality are excluded for a period to be defined hereafter and missionaries of other nationalities than British or American must obtain a permit authorising them to carry on their work. These restrictions, however, are based on the abnormal conditions created by the war and the way is left open for their removal and for the extension of the principle of freedom and of the voluntary co-operation of missionary bodies with His Majesty's Government when political conditions justify it.</p> 

<p>Proposals in regard to Africa.</p>

<p>(6) It is in the view of the Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies essential that any new international agreement that may be reached in regard to the future of tropical Africa should contain provisions guaranteeing freedom of conscience and religious toleration and securing to both natives and foreigners freedom from interference in the <sic>exercies</sic> of their religion and from any political or civil disability on the ground of their religious beliefs or in consequence of a change of faith.</p>

<p>(7) The Committee are further of opinion that Christian missions are entitled to claim that the services which they have rendered in the past to the <catchwords>cause/</catchwords> 

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.008.jpg"/>

cause of education and civilisation should be recognised by the Powers and their co-operation in the future in promoting the material and moral well-being of the natives of Africa should be explicitly welcomed. This claim they believe to be justified on the following grounds:</p>

<p>(a) The position already secured to Christian missions under the Berlin Act:</p>

<p>(b) the fact that the education of the natives of Africa has up to the present been mainly the work of Christian missions and the further services rendered by them in the exploration and opening up of the continent, in linguistic science, in the study of the customs and habits of the people and in the advancement of civilisation generally; and</p>

<p>(c) because the disinterested work of Christian missions on behalf of the natives of Africa is a valuable support to the principle of trusteeship which is the acknowledged basis of British policy in the government of subject races and which it is hoped will be embodied in the constitution of the League of Nations to be established at the Peace Conference.</p>

<p>(8) The Committee recognise that it may be necessary in consequence of the war to impose temporary restrictions upon missions of certain nationalities. So long as such restrictions are imposed as temporary and exceptional measures rendered necessary by abnormal conditions, they are not in conflict with the principle of freedom for missionary work which must be the basis <catchwords>of/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.009.jpg"/>

of any policy that will satisfy Christian public opinion in Great Britain and America.</p> 

<p>(9) Governments may justly claim that missionaries of foreign nationality admitted to work in their territories should abstain from all interference in the political organization of the country. The missionary societies represented in the British and American Conferences are willing to give voluntarily to any foreign government in whose territory they may be working a declaration recognising that all the obedient and respect should be given to the lawfully constituted government and that while carefully abstaining from political affairs it is their desire and purpose that their influence, so far as it may be properly exerted in such matters, should be so exerted in loyal co-operation with the government of the country concerned and that they will only employ agents who will work in this spirit. It is believed that missionary societies in other countries would be equally willing to give such an undertaking.</p>

<p>(10) It is recognised that it may sometimes be right and necessary for governments to impose temporary restrictions on missionary work in the interests of public order and security: and, further, that the necessity may occasionally arise of restraining the activities of indiscreet individuals, more particularly of those who are not the agents of some responsible missionary organization. It is submitted that if difficulties should arise in connection with these or other matters involving the relations of <catchwords>missons/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.010.jpg"/>

missions with governments any differences that may exist can best be adjusted by friendly discussion between responsible missionary bodies and the government concerned.</p>

<p>The settlement of such differences has been made easier by the growth in recent years of a missionary organization adapted to the purpose. There are now in Great Britain and America conferences in which all the important missionary organizations in each country, other than Roman Catholic, are represented. Similar organizations exist in some of the countries on the continent of Europe and there are links, which may be expected to become closer in the future, between Protestant missions on the continent and the conferences in Great Britain and America. There are further, in the principal mission fields, local conferences representing all the missions working in each area. These bodies which in the mission fields are composed of the most experienced missionaries and at home include responsible leaders in the different churches and <unclear>men</unclear> experienced in public affairs, may be relied upon not to put forward or support unreasonable claims. A more detailed statement of this missionary organization is given in an appendix.</p>

<p>It is respectfully submitted that the voluntary co-operation of these responsible missionary bodies with governments furnishes and adequate and sufficient means of dealing with any difficulties which may arise and may be expected to result in an increasing <catchwords>understanding/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.011.jpg"/>

understanding between missions and governments and in their more effective co-operation, each in their own proper sphere, in promoting the welfare of the native races of Africa.</p>

<p>(11) The Standing Committee of the Conference of Missionary Societies have not sufficient information regarding the probable action of the Peace Conference with reference to tropical Africa to justify them in making definite proposals. But for the sake of clearness and to indicate the practical bearing of the views expressed in this memorandum they suggest that, in the event of a new international agreement being substituted for the Berlin Act, it should include an article to the following effect:</p>

<p>"Freedom of conscience and religious toleration are guaranteed both to natives and foreigners. The followers of all religions shall be free from interference in the exercise of their religion and from any political or civil disability on the ground of their religious beliefs or in consequence of a change of faith.</p>

<p>"The Powers appreciate the value of the work done in the past by Christian missions and cordially welcome their co-operation in the future in promoting the moral and material well-being of the peoples of Africa. Subject to such restrictions as they may find it necessary in consequence of the war to impose for a period on missions of certain nationalities, the right of missions to teach the Christian religion, to acquire and hold property <catchwords>and/</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0167.012.jpg"/>

and to erect buildings for missionary purposes is recognised."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
