<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0060">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>L.A. Maynard, "The Congo Question"</title>

<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="CAA">CAA</name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0060</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Congo Question</title>
<author n="Maynard, L.A.">L.A. Maynard</author>
<title level="j">African Repository, The New York Observer></title>
<biblScope unit="volume"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1884-10">October 1884</date>
<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>

<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-04-26" who="#CAA">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="2" facs="African Repository 1884.10.1-The Congo Question.pdf"/>

<div2 type="titles">
<p>From the New York Observer.
  The Congo Question.
    By L.A. Maynard.
  It will be remembered that President Arthur, in his last Message
to Congress, suggested that measures be taken to protect our interests
in the Congo region in Africa, in common with those of other nations,</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>and that recognition be accorded to Stanley and the Association he
   represents, in their work of suppressing the slave trade in that country.
   In accordance with this suggestion, the Senate has recently passed a 
   resolution concurring in the views expressed by the President, and
   formally recognizing the flag of the African International Association.
   The justice and the importance of this action will be apparent when
   the aims and character of the organization referred to are understood.

        Among the various societies that have been formed in years past
   for the promotion of civilization in ther interior of Africa, few have 
   been more broadly and practically philanthropic, and none have
   achieved such wide spread and beneficent results in a brief time as the
   African International Association, organized at Brussels, Belgium, in
   September, 1876, and confirmed in its action by a Congress at the
   same place in the following year, at which representatives from the
   United States, England and other leading nations were present. King
   Leopold, of Belgium, was made its President, in his private, not 
   in his sovereign capacity. The stated objects of the Association are
   of a purely international and philanthropic character. It proposes to 
   form stations throughout the central portion of the African Continent
   as centres of civilizing influence and as the nuclei of future free States,
   which shall ultimately be left to elect their own rulers and provide for
   their own maintenance. In the meantime the work of education, Chris-
   tianization and material development will go on under the auspices
   of the Association. The traders as well as the missionaries and trav-
   elers of all nations, having legitimate objects in view, are welcomed
   by the Association and afforded equal rights, advantages and pro-
   tection.

        The work already accomplished by the Association has been very
   great. It has acquired possession, by treaty or purchase from the
   native chiefs, of a large tract of territory in the Congo valley and its
   branches, extending over two thousand miles of river bank, containing
   many hundreds of thousands of people, and has established twenty-
   five stations under the flag of the Association-a banner with a blue
   field and a golden star in the center. The authority of the Association
   is generally recognized by the natives and its rights respected. Un-
   der its auspices commerce has greatly revived, the slave trade has 
   sensibly diminished, and numerous missionary organizations have
   been established with success.

        But now that under the wise and efficient methods of the Asso-
   ciation this portion of Africa is assuming a commercial and general
   importance, the jealousies and conflicting interests of certain civilized
   nations seems likely to embarrass further progress, and to partially, if
   not wholly, defeat the ulterior objects of the movement itself.</p>

<p>     Portugal asserts her claim to the region around the mouth of the
   Congo and commanding the entrance to the interior. This claim is
   based on a discovery made by Diego Cam, a Portuguese, about the
   year 1484. The discovery was followed by a nominal possession, and
   Christianity was established by the Jesuits as the national religion. But
   through the duplicity, ignorance and cruelty of the Portuguese settlers
   no substantial benefits followed, either to the natives or to the na-
   tion claiming possession. The Portuguese gradually withdrew south-
   ward into Angola and Benguela, and it was not until recent years
   that they asserted any authority over the region north of the Ambriz
   river. But a treaty has just been concluded between England and
   Portugal which recognizes the sovereignty of the latter over that part
   of the West Coast of Africa situated between 8 deg. and 5 deg, 11 min.
   of south latitude, including the region around the mouth of the Congo.
   The terms of the treaty seem fair enough on their face. Freedom of
   trade, navigation, settlement and religion are guaranteed to citizens
   of all nations, within the limits mentioned, and solemn pledges are 
   given to suppress the slave trade not only in the Congo country, but
   in all other Portuguese possessions in Africa.

        This compact, however, seems to create great dissatisfaction in
   all quarters. A vigorous protest has been made against it by various
   commercial bodies in Great Britain, which claims that the rule of the
   Portuguese is corrupt and inefficient, that their pledges will not be
   kept, and that their control will greatly retard if not entirely defeat the
   movement for the development of the interior. It is asserted on good 
   authority that domestic slavery exists in the African colonies of Por-
   tugal, and that slaves are shipped every month at her port of Catum-
   bella to labor and to die at St. Thomas on the line. Opposition to 
   the treaty has also arisen in Holland on account of the interests which
   the Dutch have on the South African coast; and France comes for-
   ward with her claims and insists that there shall be a tripartite treaty,
   and that France shall be represented in the Congo commission with
   Portugal and England. On the other hand, a certain faction at Lis-
   bon is dissatisfied, asserting that Portugal has conceded too much,
   and that she has placed herself in a ruinous and humiliating position
   before England. The formal recognition by our Government of the
   International Association may also be constructed as a protest against
   the action of England in assuming to herself the protectorate of a
   territory over which she has no stronger claims than any other civili-
   zed country.

        It is difficult to see how any material advantages to the region
   in question can result from this coalition. The great object of every</p>

<p>movement in that country at present is or ought to be, to suppress
   the slave traffic, to elevate the native tribes, and promote the general
   interests of civilization. This is precisely the work being done by the
   International Assocation, and in a far more vigorous manner than 
   ever before. The question is, why not allow it to pursue this grand
   work unembarrassed by the selfish interests of any nation?</p>


</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
