<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0260">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from Henry Rider to William H. Seward, March 21, 1863</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0260</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from Henry Rider to William H. Seward, March 21, 1863</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1863-03-21">March 21, 1863</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Rider, Henry</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consular Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<date when="1863-03-21"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-05-28"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-03" who="#kln">Edits and review</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw">Encoding</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls">Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="62"/>

<note>Recd 28 May</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States of America at Sierra Leone<lb/>
March 21st 1863</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge 
the receipt of a communication 
from you dated the 21st 
day of May 1862 which arrived 
at this consulate office during my 
absence on leave.</p>

<p>I beg leave to say that in 
writing to the Department for 
promotion, I was under the impression 
that having been in 
the service some three years as 
consular agent, it was in the 
power of the Department of State 
to give me a Consul's commission 
without regard to outside influence.</p>

<p>I have the honor to enclose 
copies of late <sic>treaty's</sic> between 
<catchwords>this</catchwords>

<fw>Hon William H. Seward
Secretary of State
Washington D.C.</fw>


<pb n="63"/>

this Colonial Government and 
the native Chiefs occupying 
the territory around the Colony.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your most ob'd't servant<lb/>
Henry Rider<lb/>
U.S. Consular Agent</p>

<pb n="64"/>

<p>TREATY</p>

<p>BETWEEN his Excellency Colonel Stephen John Hill, C.B., 
Captain General and Governor-in-Chief in and over the Colony 
of Sierra Leone and its Dependencies, and Vice Admiral thereof, 
for and on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United 
Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland of the one part, and 
Alexander Bey Cantah, King of Quia Country, Nain Bannah, 
Bocarry Silly, Pa Mangee Ropee, Tom Needle, Pa Booboo, 
Soorie Coochie, Pa Savage, Dick London, John Mingo, Boom 
Warrah, Mangee Calemney, Cessey Queah, Pa Buenda, Rhuniah 
Booley, and Pa Sinney, Chiefs and Headmen of the Quiah Country 
of the other part.</p> 

<p>WHEREAS disputes have arisen between the Governor of Sierra 
Leone, and Alexander Bey Cantah and the Chiefs and Headmen 
above mentioned in consequence of attacks made by their War-men 
upon British Subjects, and upon the Island of Tombo, a Dependency 
of this Colony, and to punish which outrages the Governor of Sierra 
Leone had organized an Expedition, but Alexander Bey Cantah and 
the Chiefs and Headmen above mentioned having sued for peace, the 
contracting parties ave agreed upon the following Articles.</p>

<p>ARTICLE I.</p>

<p>King Alexander Bey Cantah and the Chiefs and Headmen above 
mentioned do hereby cede, surrender, give over and transfer from 
henceforth for ever unto Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain 
and Ireland, Her Heirs and Successors, the full, entire, free and 
unlimited right, possession, dominion and sovereignty in and over 
all that piece or portion of the Quia Country measuring Ten miles 
in width from Waterloo and Calmunt Creeks to the Quia River or 
Creek, and Sixteen miles in length from the River Sierra Leone to 
the Ribbie River or thereabouts, and bounded on the West by Waterloo 
Creek and Calmunt Creek; on the East by Quiah River or Creek, 
(which empties itself into the Rokelle River at Ro Benkeah) by the 
Creek known as Ma Sungoh Creek, and by a direct line running from 
the head of the said Ma Sungoh Creek; on the North by the 
Sierra Leone River; and on the South by the River Ribbie or Dibbie 
round to the entrance of Calmunt Creek, together with all and every 
right and title to the Navigation, Anchorage, Waterage, Bays, Waters, 
Rivers, Sea Coasts, Shores, Creeks and Inlets, Fishing and other 
Revenues and Maritime Claims, and all privileges appertaining to the 
same, which portion of the Quia land hereby ceded shall henceforth 
be annexed to, and be a Dependency of this Colony, and be subject 
to the Laws now in force and hereafter to be in force in this Colony.</p>

<p>ARTICLE II.</p>

<p>Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, in consideration 
of the cession hereby made of the above portion of the Quia country, 
agrees to pay unto Alexander Bey Cantah, King of Quia, his Successor 
and Successors, the sum of 2000 Bars, or £100 yearly and every year.</p>

<p>ARTICLE III.</p>

<p>Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland hereby 
guarantees to the Native Inhabitants of the portion of the Quia 
country hereby ceded, the full, entire, and free possession of the 
lands they now hold, in the same manner as the other Inhabitants 
of the Colony.</p> 

<pb n="65"/>

<fw type="page">2.</fw>

<p>ARTICLE IV.</p>

<p>The Towns of Ro Bagah, and Ro Baney, in their present dimensions, 
are expected from the cession of the portion of the Quia 
land hereby made.</p>

<p>ARTICLE V.</p>

<p>This Treaty shall be proclaimed immediately on its being concluded 
and signed, and be made Law throughout the Territories of Alexander 
Bey Cantah, and the Chiefs and Headmen above-mentioned. In witness 
whereof the contracting parties have signed the same, and have 
affixed their seals thereto.</p> 

<p>Done at Sierra Leone, the Second day of April, in the year 
of our Lord One thousand eight hundred, and sixty-one.</p>

<ab>Stephen J. Hill, (L.S.)<lb/>
Governor-in-Chief.</ab>

<ab>Alexander Bey Cantah (L.S.)<lb/>
his X mark<lb/>
King of the Quia Country</ab>

<ab>Nain Bannah. (L.S.)<lb/>
(Signed in Arabic.)</ab>

<ab>Bocarry Silly. (L.S.)<lb/>
Pa Mangee Ropee. (L.S.)<lb/>
Tom Needle. (L.S.)<lb/>
Pa Booboo. (L.S.)<lb/>
Coorie Coochee. (L.S.)<lb/>
Pa Savage. (L.S.)<lb/>
Dic London. (L.S.)<lb/>
John Mingo. (L.S.)<lb/>
their X marks.</ab>

<ab>Boom Warrah. (L.S.)<lb/>
her X mark.</ab>

<ab>Mangee Calemney. (L.S.)<lb/>
Cessey Queah. (L.S.)<lb/>
Pa Buenda. (L.S.)<lb/>
Rhuniah Booley. (L.S.)<lb/>
Pa Sinney. (L.S.)<lb/>
their X marks.</ab>

<ab>Witnesses to the Signatures</ab>

<ab>John Carr,<lb/>
Chief Justice.<lb/>
E. H., Sierra Leone.<lb/>
A. Fitzjames,<lb/>
Queen's Advocate.<lb/>
Geo. W. Nicol,<lb/>
Colonial Secretary.<lb/>
Chas. Heddle<lb/>
Robt. Bradshaw. Members of Council.<lb/>
John M'Cormack.</ab>

<pb n="66"/>

<ab>U.S. Consulate<lb/>
Sierra Leone<lb/>
March 21, 1863<lb/>
Inclosed copy of 
Treaty<lb/>
Henry Rider</ab>

<ab>Received at Statistical
Office May 29, 1863</ab>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>



