<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0133">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Correspondence to Florent Guillain</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie Brown</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Niendorf, Nicholas" xml:id="nn">Nicholas Niendorf</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">fr.letter.0133</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Correspondence to Florent Guillain</title>
<date when="1899-06-30">June 30, 1899</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Centre des Archives d'Outre-Mer</repository>
<collection>Généralités</collection>
<idno>Carton 91, Dossier 869</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Baker, Frazier</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46070870">Brawley, William H., 1841-1916</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64049097">Cambon, Jules, 1845-1935</term>
<term>Hose, Sam</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/814506">Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Fayetteville (Georgia)</term>
<term>Griffin (Georgia)</term>
<term>Guadeloupe (French West Indies)</term>
<term>Houston (Texas)</term>
<term>Lake City (South Carolina)</term>
<term>Martinique (French West Indies)</term>
<term>Mississippi</term>
<term>Silver City (Mississippi)</term>
<term>Texarkana (Arkansas)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Methodist</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Paris (France)</placeName>
<date when="1899-06-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/205135948">Guillain, Florent 1844-1915</persName>
<roleName>Minister of the Colonies</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-02" who="kln">reviewed, encoded.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">Edited encoding.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">Translated and encoded header information.</change>
<change when="2017" who="nn">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="20160615_103256.jpg"/>

<ab type="letterhead">
Ministère
des
Affaires étrangères
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
Direction
des
Affaires Politiques
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
Sous-Direction
du Nord
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
Au sujet de la situation
des nègres aux Etats-Unis.
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
RÈPUBLIQUE FRANÇAISE
</ab>

<p>Paris, le 30 Juin 1899</p>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre et cher Collègue,</p>

<p>L'Ambassadeur de France à Washington vient de
m'adresser, au sujet de la situation actuelle des
nègres aux Etats-Unis et du mouvement qui commence
à se dessiner parmi la population de couleur, à la
suite des mauvais traitements dont elle est victime
un rapport dont les indications me paraissent de nature 
à intéresser votre Département.</p>

<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous communiquer, ci-joint,
à toutes fins utiles, copie de la dépêche de M. Cambon.</p>

<p>Agréez, Monsieur le Ministre et cher Collègue,
les assurances de ma haute considération.</p>

<p>Pour le Ministre et par autorisation<lb/>
LE CONSEILLER D'ETAT DIRECTEUR<lb/>
<unclear extent="one signature"/></p>

<fw type="address">
Monsieur Guillain,<lb/>
Ministre des Colonies.
</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="20160615_103045.jpg"/>

<p>L'Ambassadeur de France à Washington,<lb/>
à Monsieur le Ministre des Affaires Etrangères.</p>

<p>Washington, le 30 Mai 1899.</p>

<p>Le peuple nègre des Etats-Unis vient de
lancer un appel aux Nations étrangères pour leur
demander protection.</p>

<p>Ce document est l'expression de la terreur 
qui pèse sur une partie de la population de
ce pays.</p>

<p>A la suite de la guerre de Sécession, les
nègres furent déclarés citoyens et le Gouvernement
dans les Etats du Sud passa entre leurs mains. Ils
le gardèrent jusqu'en 1877, époque à laquelle les
blancs les expulsèrent du pouvoir, quelquefois de
vive force et soit par la fraude soit par l'intimidation, 
les empêchèrent de voter. Depuis lors,
cette situation a duré: les nègres en fait ne votent 
point. L'Etat du <sic>Mississipi</sic> vient d'essayer
de régulariser cette situation en soumettant l'exercice 
du droit de vote à des examens sur la connaissance 
de la Constitution Fédérale, qui n'auront
aucune valeur pour les blancs et qui suffiront à

<pb n="20160615_103059.jpg"/>

annuler les droits des noirs. La Cour Suprême a 
décidé que cette clause de la Constitution du 
<sic>Mississipi</sic>, ne s'appliquant pas à la race nègre en
tant que race, était constitutionnelle. On peut
donc prévoir qu'elle aura généralisée.</p>

<p>En réalité, toute garantie juridique est
refusée aux nègres. Il n'est pas besoin d'autre
exemple que celui du Jury de Charleston ne condamnant 
pas les individus qui, à Lake City l'année
dernière, assassinèrent le Directeur de la Poste
et sa famille parce qu'il était nègre, et il est
remarquable que le Juge Brawley qui présidait les
assises tout en blâmant sévèrement les auteurs du
crime déclara que les autorités qui avaient nommé
ce Directeur de la Poste étaient également responsables.</p>

<p>Le 23 Avril dernier, un certain Samuel
Hose a assassiné un cultivateur et violé sa femme.
Les blancs se sont emparés de lui, l'ont brulé vif,
ont dépécé son cadavre et en ont vendu les morceaux
aux enchères au milieu de 2000 personnes. Il s'est
trouvé des journalistes pour excuser la fureur
populaire et le même jour deux autres nègres dont
un pasteur, furent pendus dans la même région, sans
qu'ils eussent commis aucun crime.</p>

<p>Depuis lors, il ne s'est pas passé un
jour sans que nous ayons appris qu'un ou plusieurs
nègres avaient été assassinés. Je vous donnerai à

<pb n="20160615_103109.jpg"/>

titre d'exemple la mort du nègre Pevug et de sa
femme à Atlanta, les assassinats commis à la fin
de Mars dans l'Arkansas à Texarkana: le nombre en
est inconnu, le triple lynchage dans le Texas à
Houston qui vient d'avoir lieu ces jours derniers,
les meurtres commis à Griffin (Georgie): là, il
s'est formé une association pour obliger les industriels  
à renoncer au travail des noirs. Dans
le <sic>Mississipi</sic> à Sylver City, trois noirs sans
défense sont noyés. Enfin ces jours derniers, à Fayetteville 
(Ga) un nègre inoffensif a été pris chez 
lui et tué sans raison.</p>

<p>Il n'est pas surprenant que les nègres
s'arment et songent à se venger. C'est ainsi qu'on
a vu la pasteur Rausom de l'Eglise Méthodiste oser
parler en chaire d'employer la dynamite contre les
blancs. Mais ces excès de paroles ne peuvent qu'amener
de nouveaux crimes. D'autres remèdes sont mis
en avant pour conjurer cette situation. Le premier
et le plus naturel a été que l'influence politique
des noirs s'étant toujours portée du côté des
Républicains, peut être il serait sage de la porter 
du côté des démocrates, les Etats du Sud appartenant 
à ce parti.</p>

<p>D'autres comme l'Evêque H. M. Turner ont
proclamé que l'unique remède était la séparation
complète des blancs et des noirs et que ceux-ci
devraient émigrer en Afrique et y fonder une République, 
l'Afrique aux Africains.</p>

<pb n="20160615_103120.jpg"/>

<p>D'autres enfin ont proposé de construire
des villes industrielles dans le Nord où l'on n'emploierait 
aucun ouvrier blanc. J'ai peur que ce
projet humanitaire ne cache un moyen pour certains
industriels de se procurer de la main d'oeuvre à
bon marché.</p>

<p>Quoiqu'il en soit, de nombreuses familles
nègres dans le Sud quittent le pays et comme il
y a de 8 à 10 millions de noirs aux Etats-Unis,
que la natalité dans cette race est considérable
on peut prévoir que d'ici à peu d'années un problème 
redoutable se posera devant le pays, qui
verra peut être une nouvelle guerre servile.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="20160615_103024.jpg"/>

<note>A.S. de la situation des nègres aux Etats Unis.</note>

<note>Confidentielle</note>

<p>Paris le <lb/> 
Monsieur le Gouverneur de la
Martinique<lb/>
Guadeloupe</p>

<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous
adresser ci-joint un rapport adressé par
l'ambassedeur de France à Washington à
M. le Ministre des Aff. Etr. au sujet de la
situation des nègres aux Etats-Unis.</p>

<p>Bien que ce rapport ait en <unclear extent="one word"/>
confidentiel, <unclear extent="one word"/> au
<unclear extent="one word"/> à faire état des renseignements
qu'il contient, par voie officieuse 
si des <unclear extent="one word"/> d'attention vers les
Etats-Unis venaient à se manifester
dans la population de <unclear>couleur</unclear> <unclear>habitant</unclear> la colonie
que vous <unclear>administrez</unclear>.</p>

<p><unclear>R.c.l.p.l.</unclear></p>

</div1>

<div1  xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb n="20160615_103256.jpg"/>

<ab type="letterhead">
Minister
of
Foreign Affairs
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
Direction
of
Political Affairs
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
Under-Direction
of the North
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
On the subject of the situation
of the Negroes in the United States.
</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">
FRENCH REPUBLIC
</ab>

<p>Paris, June 30, 1899</p>

<p>Mister Minister and dear colleague,</p>

<p>The French Ambassador in Washington has just
addressed to me, on the subject of the current situation of the
Negroes in the United States and of the movement that is starting
to materialize among the population of color,
following the poor treatment of which it is the victim
a report of which the indications seem to me to be of interest to your Department.</p>

<p>I have the honor to communicate to you, enclosed,
for all practical purposes, a copy of the dispatch of Mr. Cambon.</p>

<p>Accept, Mr. Minister and dear colleague,
the assurances of my highest consideration.</p>

<p>For the Minister and by authorization<lb/>
THE ADVISOR DIRECTOR OF STATE<lb/>
<unclear extent="one signature"/></p>

<fw type="address">
Mr. Guillain,<lb/>
Minister of the Colonies.
</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb n="20160615_103045.jpg"/>

<p>The Ambassador of France in Washington,<lb/>
to Mr. Minister of Foreign Affairs.</p>

<p>Washington, May 30, 1899.</p>

<p>The Negro people of the United States have just
launched a call to foreign nations to ask them
for protection.</p>

<p>This document is the expression of the terror 
that weighs on a part of the population of
this country.</p>

<p>Following the war of Secession, the
Negroes were declared citizens and the Government
in the Southern States passed between their hands. They
kept it until 1877, time in which the
whites removed power from them, sometimes with
lively force and either by fraud or by intimidation,
hindering them from voting. Ever since then,
this situation lasted: the Negroes in fact did not vote 
at all. The State of Mississippi has just
adjusted this situation in submitting the exercise 
of the right to vote to exams on the knowledge 
of the Federal Constitution, that has
no worth for the whites and that will suffer to

<pb n="20160615_103059.jpg"/>

remove the rights of the blacks. The Supreme Court decided
that this clause of the Constitution of Mississippi, 
not applying to the Negro race in the
capacity of race, was constitutional. One can
thus predict that it will be generalized.</p>

<p>In reality, any legal guarantee is
refused to the Negroes. There is not need of another
example than that of the Charleston Jury not condemning 
the individuals that, in Lake City last
year, assassinated the Director of the Post
and his family because he was Negro, and it is
remarkable that Judge Brawley who presided over the
seats while severely blaming the perpetrators of the
crime declared that the authorities who had named
this Director of the Post were equally responsible.</p>

<p>Last April 23rd, a certain Samuel
Hose assassinated a farmer and raped his wife.
The whites seized him, burned him alive,
cut up his body and sold the pieces
at auction in the middle of 2,000 people. Journalists were found
to excuse the popular
violence and on the same day, two other Negroes, including 
a pastor, were hung in the same region, without
committing any crime.</p>

<p>Since then, there has not been one
day without us having learned that one or more
Negroes were assassinated. I will give to you

<pb n="20160615_103109.jpg"/>

an example of the death of the Negro Pevug and his
wife in Atlanta, the assassinations committed at the end
of March in Arkansas in Texarkana: the number is
unknown, the triple lynching in Houston, Texas,
that just took place in these last few days,
the murders committed in Griffin (Georgia): there, 
an association was formed to oblige the industrialists
to refuse to employ blacks. In  
Sylver City, Mississippi, three helpless blacks are drowned. Finally, these past few days, in Fayetteville
(Ga) a harmless Negro was taken from his own 
house and killed without reason.</p>

<p>It is not surprising that the Negroes
are arming themselves and dream of vengeance. It is just as one
saw pastor Rausom of the Methodist Church dare
to speak in the pulpit about using dynamite against the
whites. But this excess of speech can only bring 
new crimes. Other remedies are put 
forward to ward off this situation. The first
and the most natural thing was the political influence 
of Blacks always being brought to the side of the
Republicans, maybe it would be good to bring it
to the side of the Democrats, the Southern States belonging
to this party.</p>

<p>Others like the Bishop H. M. Turner 
proclaimed that the unique remedy was the complete
separation of whites and blacks and that those who
would have to emigrate to Africa and found a Republic there,
Africa to the Africans.</p>

<pb n="20160615_103120.jpg"/>

<p>Others, finally, proposed building
industrial towns in the North where no white workers
would be employed. I have fear that this
humanitarian project only hides a way for certain
industrialists to obtain cheap labor.</p>

<p>Be that as it may, numerous Negro
families in the South are leaving the country and as there
are 8 to 10 million Blacks in the United States, 
the birth rate in this race is considerable,
one can predict that from here in a few years a formidable 
problem will be posed to the country, that
may see a new servile war.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb n="20160615_103024.jpg"/>

<note>A.S. of the situation of the Negroes in the United States.</note>

<note>Confidential</note>

<p>Paris, <lb/> 
Mr. Governor of
Martinique<lb/>
Guadeloupe</p>

<p>I have the honor to address
to you enclosed a report addressed by
the ambassador of France in Washington to
Mr. Minister of Foreign Affairs on the subject of the
situation of the Negroes in the United States.</p>

<p>Although this report has <unclear extent="one word"/>
confidential, <unclear extent="one word"/> to the
<unclear extent="one word"/> to mention the information
that it contains, unofficially
if the <unclear extent="one word"/> of attention towards the
United States would come to manifest itself
in the population of <unclear>color</unclear> 
inhabiting the colony
that you <unclear>administer</unclear>.</p>

<p><unclear>R.c.l.p.l.</unclear></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
