<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1267">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, May 18, 1899</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1267</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, May 18, 1899</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 6</biblScope>
<date when="1899-05-18">May 18, 1899</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Morris, W. R.</term>
<term>Todd, Julius C.</term>
<term>Gale, Edward C.</term>
<term>C., W. J.</term>
<term>Johnson</term>
<term>Gale, Samuel C.</term>
<term>Rust, George H.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Minneapolis, Minnesota</term>
<term>Hennepin County, Minnesota</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Owen L. W.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1899-05-18"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Hill, David J.</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1899-06-26"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-10-31" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-3036.jpg"/>

<p>No. 29, Consular Series.
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia,
May 18, 1899.</p>

<p><add>INDEX BUREAU
REC'D
JUN 26 '99
DEPT OF STATE</add></p>

<p><add>3rd ASST. SECRETARY.
JUN 28 1899</add></p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Secretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Sir:
I have to say, that
upon receipt of your No. 15,
"Consular," of Feb'y 8, 1899,
through the third Assistant
Secretary; with the inclosure
of a letter from Wm.
R. Morris, Esq., the guardian
of the indigent Todd
children here, I had decided
to say nothing further,
relative to the matter; but as
the Secretary of the Legation,
here, in overhawling the
papers and files, in his
office, has just came
across, what seems to me,
to</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3037.jpg"/>

<p>to be, a very important letter,
relative to the Todd estate,
which upon its face, seems
to contradict, in part, the
statement of Mr. Morris,
relative to the sustenance of the
children, if at home; and
would probably have
the appearance that he
does not desire the presence
of the children in Minneappolis,
in order, that the
property may be otherwise
disposed of. For this reason, I
thought it my duty to
inclose the said letter of
Gale &amp; co. of June 12, 1894,
with one from Wm. R. Morris
Esq., of Nov. 1, 1895, which
I found in my office, on
taking charge, for your
information. I have the
honor to be your obedient
servant: Owen L. W. Smith
C. General</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3038.jpg"/>

<p>No. 29, Consular Series
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia,
May 18, 1899.</p>

<p>Owen L. W. Smith
To
Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Secretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Subject.
Todd Children.</p>

<p>Synopsis.
The letter of Gale &amp;Co., of
June 12, 1894, placing the
value of the Todd estate to
$3000.00 to $4000.00, just discovered.
See letter of Nov. 1, 1895, from W. R. Morris.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3039.jpg"/>

<p>Consular Bureau
MEMORANDUM.</p>

<p>Consular Bureau
JUL 29 1899</p>

<p>Mr. Cridler:
On February 3, 1899, William R.
Morris informed the Department that there were
no funds available to bring the Todd children to
this country and that an effort to raise the
money had resulted in failure. Morris is the
guardian of the children's property. We sent
the letter to the Consul General who replied
under dat of May 18, 1899, enclosing a letter
from messss Gale &amp; Co., dated June 12, 1894,
who state that the father of the children had
died and left them a home valued at $3,000 to
$4,000. A letter from William R. Morris,
dated November 1, 1895, was also enclosed.
Morris had at that time been appointed guardian
of the children. He stated that they were trying
to raise money to bring the children to the
United States; that the personal property left</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3040.jpg"/>

<p>Consular Bureau.
MEMORANDUM.</p>

<p>by their father amounted to but few dollars;
and that the real estate could not be sold until
the youngest child became of age; that it
might with the consent of the court be mortgaged
for $600 or $700, but there would be no
way of paying the mortgage off when due, etc.
We sent a copy of this correspondence to
Gale and Company on June 29, 1899, and Mr.
Edward C. Gale now replies that Morris is still
guardian of the children; that on account of a
shrinkage of value the property is worth little
more than $2,000; that the only way to raise
money would be by mortgage; that the children
if here would have to be supported by charity
after the money raised by the mortgage was
exhausted; and that there is now $124 in cash
in the hands of the guardian over and above the</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3041.jpg"/>

<p>Consular Bureau.
MEMORANDUM.</p>

<p>taxes, etc., which have all been paid.</p>

<p>I fail to see what we can do in the matter
except to copy Mr. Gale's letter to the Consul
General. The property is in the hands of
a state court, and will be disposed of in
such manner as that court may direct; and
we have no funds at our disposal with which
to bring the children to this country.</p>

<p>W. J. C.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3042.jpg"/>

<p>Inclosures.
1. Letter from Gale &amp; Co.
Minneappolis, June 12, 1894.
2. 1 Letter from Wm. R. Morris,
Minneappolis, Nov. 1, 1895.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3043.jpg"/>

<p>GALE &amp; CO.,
Real Estate, Mortgage Loans
and Insurance.
New York Life Building,
Minneapolis, Minnesota.</p>

<p>LAND AND LOAN DEPARTMENT.
SAMUEL G. GALE, ATTORNEY AT LAW
GEO. H. RUST.
Minneapolis, June 12, 1894.</p>

<p>United States Consul,
Monrovia, Liberia,
West Africa;</p>

<p>Dear Sir:-
Some time in the autumn of '93, Mr. Julius C. Todd, a worthy colored
mon long a resident of this city, left here with his family with the
avowed purpose of joining some Christian mission in Africa. We do not
understand that he went out under the auspices of any society, but at his
own expense. A Philadeplphia paper published by the colored Methodists on April
19 published a letter from a missionary stating that word had been received
from Brother Johnson of Monrovia that Mr. Todd and wife had both
died in or near Monrovia soon after reaching that country. If true, their
deaths must have taken place some time in February or March of this year.
When they left here they had five children. All sorts of rumors are
afloat among their acquaintances as to their condition, but no direct
word has been received from any one. Mr. Todd left a comfortable home
here valued at $3000. to $4000, and before leaving leased it for five
years at $15. per month, and left it in our care to collect rents, pay
taxes, etc. We have heard nothing directly from him, and nothing
indirectly, except as above, since he left New York. In order that we
may protect the interests of his children, look after his estate, etc.,
will you kindly make diligent inquiry as to the facts in this case? If
you find that both are dead, it will be necessary to have an affidavit
as to the time and place of death of both Mr. and Mrs. Todd; also, any
information as to the present condition and whereabouts of the children
will be very important for us to have. Awaiting your early reply,
Very truly yours,
Gale &amp; Co.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3044.jpg"/>

<p>Attorney and Consular at Law,
927 GUARANTY LOAN BUILDING.</p>

<p>In re Estate of J. C.
Todd, deceased</p>

<p>Minneapolis, Minn., U.S. <unclear>Ad No.</unclear> 1st 1895.</p>

<p>Mr. A. <unclear></unclear>Williams, Guardian Todd children,
Monrovia, Liberia, Africa.</p>

<p>Sir:-
Your communication of Sept. 16th 1895 to Edward
C. Gale Esq. is before me, and the contents have been carefully noted.
It is the desire of the acquaintances of Mr. Todd that his children should
be brought to this city reared and educated. Here they here homes could be
provided for them and they be suitably educated. The estate has been
settled; there is no money left and nothing that can be turned
into money that could be used for their nurture. We are now doing
our returns to raise money enough to pay the passage of the children
to this land; there are several out with subscription lists for this
purpose. At present I am unable to say whether or not we will be
successful. No compensation can be given any one for the care of the
children as there is none to be derived from the estate that can be used
for this purpose. The final report of the administrator shows in
personal property the sum of $15 56/100 giving the sum of $3 89.100 to each
child, but ten dollars of this ammount is in the shape of a worthless
promissory note, this leaving the sum of $5 56/100 to be divided among
the children. There is a house and lot left to them each having</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3045.jpg"/>

<p>an undivided one fourth interest in the same. This cannot
as the matter now stands be corrected into money nor could it
be until the youngest child becomes of age. The property was leased
by Mr. Todd for a period of five years at a rental of twelve
dollars per month making a yearly rental of $144 00/100 deducting commission
we have a balance of $129.60 out of this. The sum of $75 00/100 more
or less must be deducted for taxes and there is left the sum
of fifty or sixty dollars to be divided yearly amount the children.
If the property were mortgaged, if the court permitted this, not prove
than the sum of six or seven hundred dollars could be obtained
on it and as there would be no money to pay off the mortgage when
due and no certainty of keeping the interest paid up it would result
in the loss of the property and the children would derive very little benefit
therefore. There are friends of Mr. Todd here who would take the
children and rear them without charge if they were her, Mrs Sykes
is not a guardian for the children. I am the guardian appointed
by the Probate court of this Hennepin County, Minnesota. When Mr.
Todd left here he took with him considerable personal property
and guite a sum of money. Here there, any any personal effects
left by either Mr. or Mrs. Todd? If so in whose possession are
for the payment of the passage of the children to this country that
they be sent here and that whatever personal effects there are left in
your country go toward compensating those who have so kindly
cared for the children since the death of their parents.</p>

<p>The youngest child is how old now?</p>

<p>Trusting the children are in good health I am
most respectfully yours,
Wm. R. Morris,
Guardian of the Todd children,</p>

<p>I would be pleased to hear from you at your
earliest connvenience.
Wm R. Mo.</p>
    
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>