<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Conditions in the Congo State: Grounds for Action by the United States Government (1904)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0020</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Conditions in the Congo State: Grounds for Action by the United States Government</title>
<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>Judd &amp; Detwiler</publisher>
<date when="1901">1904</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-13" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Conditions in the Congo State</p>

<p>Grounds for Action by the United States Government</p>

<p>Synopsis of Case</p>

<p>With Citations from State Papers and Other Sources</p>

<p>Washington, D.C.<lb/>
Judd &amp; Detweiler, Printers<lb/>
1904</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p2"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Important Dates in the Development of the Congo State.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The founding of the Congo State resulted from the opening of Central Africa through the explorations of Mr. Henry M. Stanley. An association was quickly formed, under the leadership of King Leopold of Belgium, for further exploration, with a view to occupation of the country. The association, having received recognition by the Powers, became the Congo State.</p>

<p>Mr. Stanley arrives at the mouth of the Congo, completing his journey across Africa, August 12, 1877.</p>

<p>Comité d'Etudes du Haut-Congo, formed by King Leopold for study of conditions in the Congo territory, November 20, 1878.</p>

<p>Stanley revisits central Africa, under the auspices of the Comité, August, 1879, to June, 1882; December, 1882, to January, 1884.</p>

<p>The Comité becomes Interenational Association of the Congo, January, 1883.</p>

<p>Tentative treaty of England with Portugal, recognizing Portuguese claims in West Africa as opposed to those of International Association, February 26, 1884.</p>

<p>Recognition of International Association of the Congo by the United States Government, April 22, 1884.</p>

<p>The Association promises to France a reversionary interest in its territories, April 23, 1884.</p>

<p>International Association recognized by Germany, November 8, 1884.</p>

<p>International Conference of fourteen Powers convenes at Berlin for consideration of problems in Congo territory, November 15, 1884, to January 26, 1885.</p>

<p>International Association recognized by Great Britain, December 16, 1884; by Italy, December 19, 1884; by Austro-Hungary, December 24, 1884; by other Powers, December 27, 1884, to February 23, 1885.</p>

<p>The king bequeaths to Belgium the succession to his interests in the Congo State, August 2, 1889.</p>

<p>International Conference convenes at Brussels to devise measures for suppression of slave trade, November 22, 1889, to July 2, 1890.<lb/>
At this Conference the Congo State seeks and gains permission for imposition of import duties.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

</div2>

<pb n="p5"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>Conditions in the Congo State.</p>

<p>Grounds for Action by the United States Government.</p>

<p>A Synopsis of Case as viewed by the Conference by which Memorial of April, 1904, was addressed to Congress. *</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Societies composing the conference appear in the case not primarily as complainants, but as transmitters of testimony received by them which their moral responsibility requires them to make known (1).</p>

<p>The Defendant in the case is King Leopold, not Belgium (2).</p>

<p>THE CASE UNIQUE.</p>

<p>A single man claims unlimited sovereign power and proprietorship in a territory embracing one million square miles.</p>

<note>* For Memorial see <hi rend="italics">Senate Documeent No. 282, 58th Congress, 2d session.</hi></note>

<note>1 For relation of missionaries to the issue, see in general pp. 16, 17 of Memorial. Cf. Rev. J. H. Weeks in letter to Congo officials: "I deeply regret having to write this letter to you but I cannot sit quietly and see these unfortunate folk crushed out of existence by oppression and cruelty without making a protest in the name of religion and humanity."</note>

<note>Compare also: "A white officer unacquainted with the missionary whom he was addressing, after a cruel raid, jokingly remarked that he had killed many people and secured a fine lot of curios. He said that while his soldiers were firing upon the villages the people ran wildly about, crying, 'Sheppite, Sheppite.' It was their name for Rev. W. H. Sheppard, whom they were beseeching to come to their aid."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Cited in Memorial to Congress, p. 17.</hi></note>

<note>2 "The union between Belgium and the new State shall be exclusively personal."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Action of Belgian Parliament, April, 1885.</hi></note>

<note>Belgium holds treaty relations with the Congo State substantially identical with those sustained by other Powers.</note>

<pb n="p6"/>

<p>THE ORIGINAL RECOGNITION OF THE CONGO STATE.</p>

<p>This recognition secured through professions of philanthropy and interest in the promotion of unrestricted commerce for all nations (3).</p>

<p>THE REQUEST MADE IN MEMORIAL.</p>

<p>Congress is asked to take action in promotion of an impartial investigation of present conditions in the Congo State.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Grounds upon which the request is made:</hi></p>

<p>I. An impartial inquiry is demanded in view of prevalent reports of grave abuses in the administration of the Congo State.</p>

<p>The reports are sufficient in volume and definiteness to justify and require impartial investigation.</p>

<p>They present a dreadful catalogue of alleged wrongs, involving accusation of excessive cruelties, massacres, mutilations, cannibalism, and the threatened extermination of tribes and depopulation of large territories.</p>

<p>They imply not exceptional instances of inhumanity but its prevalence throughout the vast rubber district, as the result of the system maintained by the State.</p>

<note>3 "Our only program, I am anxious to repeat, is the work of moral and material regeneration."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">King Leopold, 1885.</hi></note>

<note>"The objects of this Society are philanthropic. It does not aim at permanent political control but seeeks the neutrality of the valley."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Message of President Arthur, December, 1883.</hi></note>

<note>"The fundamental idea of this program is to facilitate the access of all commercial nations to the interior of Africa."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Prince Bismarck's opening address as President of Berlin Conference</hi></note>

<note>Compare also represeentatations made at Brussels:&#8212;</note>

<note>"When we have made sufficient progress in all directions to allow of the natives asking for our protection, and when we are strong enough to grant it, no one will venture any longer to capture or transport slaves."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Report Congo Administration, read at Brussels Conference.</hi></note>

<note>"For Belgian trade, as for that of traders of every nationality established in our territories, we have an equal solicitude. All appreciate the security they enjoy under the Congo Government."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Remarks of Representative of Congo State in Conference at Brussels.</hi></note>

<note>Compare also Supplement, ¶'s 1, 2.</note>

<pb n="p7"/>

<p>The witnesses represented in the reports include:</p>

<p>(1.) Missionaries of all American and English Societies having work in the Congo and of all stations of these Societies which are in the vicinity of the rubber-producing district (4).</p>

<p>The missionary a reluctant witness. It is his desire and it is for his interest to seek the favor of government. The peril of charge of disloyalty (5).</p>

<p>The silence of Belgian missionaries not unnatural, in view of their two-fold relation with the king (6). Their testimony, if favorable to the Government, should not fail of consideration in the impartial inquiry sought.</p>

<note>4 See Memorial to Congress, pages 7, 23-52.</note>

<note>See, also, "King Leopold's Rule in Africa," by E. D. Morel, and "Civilization in Congo Land," by H. R. Fox Bourne.</note>

<note>5 "The Governor made inquiry concerning the atrocities which he had reported and finally said to him: 'If you continue to demand investigation in these matters, we will make a charge against you. The natives say you have told them not to being India rubber to the State.' He denied this, but was again threatened by the Governor, who said: 'That means five years' imprisonment.'"&#8212;<hi rend="italics">From interview with Rev. E. V. Sjoblom, Ikoko, Africa.</hi></note>

<note>Compare report of Governor General of the Congo State in recent issue of <sic>Officiel</sic> Bulletin: "Certain officers have complained of the arrogant attitude the native population assumes when it has been subjected to certain influences. Once cannot escape the fact that this situation reveals itself in the neighborhood of certain * * * missionary posts. * * * I have already called the attention of the Government to this grave situation and to the measures it is likely to entail if it continues. Already our local officers have found it necessary to act in order to safeguard the authority of the State, and if it is necessary the Governor General will consider the advisability of making use of the means that the decree of September 15, 1889, puts at his disposal in the case of strangers who use their influence over the natives against the State."</note>

<note>Compare letter of Rev. Mr. Harris, written at Baringa, July 2, 1904,&#8212;printed in London <hi rend="italics">News</hi>:</note>

<note>"I called the judge's attention to the imprisonment of women and children who would not be released until their husbands and fathers satisfied the rubber demand. * * * In June sentries were sent into the towns with instructions to forbid any individuals going to the mission schools and services. Thus instead of two hundred or three hundred we had not a soul."</note>

<note>6 "The Belgian missionaries are subjects of their king, which at once makes their position very difficult. Then again, all these Belgian establishments on the Congo receive grants from the Congo Government, and it would be a very serious matter, indeed, for them if they were to say publicly what they know to be the case and what some of them privately write to their friends."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">E. D. Morel in "New York Evening Post," Octo., 1904.</hi> C. f. Debate in Belgian Parliament. Supplement, ¶s 54-67.</note>

<pb n="p8"/>

<p>(2.) Witnesses of many callings&#8212;travelers, explorers, consular residents, and men formerly agents of the State (7).</p>

<p>The testimony of Mr. Glave, an honored companion of Mr. Stanley (8).</p>

<p>The detailed report of Roger Casement, British Consul, after a journey made through interior districts (9).</p>

<p>Testimony of M. Pickard, a Belgian Senator (10).*</p>

<note>7 See, e.g., testimony of Mr. Ewart S. Grogan in "From the Cape to Cairo;" Mr. Pickersgill, British Consul, in "Official Report, 1898;" Col. Williams, an ex-officer in King Leopold's army, "Affairs of West Africa," page 320; Major Parminter, "Civilization in Congo Land," pages 132-'4; M. Moray, ex-agent of Concessionaire Co., "Civilization in Congo Land," page 52; M. Pickard, Belgian Senator, "En Congolie," pages 95-97; Mr. Joseph Conrad, novelist, quoted in London <hi rend="italics">Morning Post,</hi> October, 1904, etc. See, also, "King Leopold's Rule in Africa," by E. D. Morel, and "Civilization in Kongo Land," by H. R. Fox Bourne.</note>

<note>8 Mr. E. J. Glave, having been associated with Mr. Stanley in the earlier days in Africa, revisited the Congo after an absence of six years. His record of his experiences as he made his way over the route followed previously with Mr. Stanley is given in articles "New Conditions in Central Africa," in the <hi rend="italics">Century Magazine,</hi> volumes 53, 54. At first he is perplexed and incredulous. Successive entries in his journal show the growth of his deep indignation and abhorrence. For citations, see Memorial to Congress, pages 7 and 9, and pamphlet "Treatment of Women and Children in the Congo State," pp. 3, 5-10.</note>

<note>For warm commendation of Mr. Glave by Stanley, see "Introduction" to Glave's volume, "Six Years in the Congo."</note>

<note>9 "Meanwhile Mr. Roger Casement, permanent British Consul in the Congo State, an official 'of wide African experience,' had been conducting a personal investigation in the Upper Congo. The appalling account of his experience is now before the world."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">"King Leopold's Rule in Africa," p. xiv.</hi></note>

<note>"Mr. Casement has never forgotten, in the course of his report, that he was a machine sent to record in a spirit of calm judicial impartiality the sights he witnessed, and he preformed his task with marvelous self-restraint."</note>

<note>"The British Government has placed in the hands of all the Powers the report of Mr. Casement. The British premier declared publicly that the proof of the existence of grave abuses was overwhelming."</note>

<note>"We submit herewith his painstaking and comprehensive testimony, the straightforward, regretful fidelity of which, we think, cannot fail to be apparent to every fair-minded reader."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">Memorial to Congress, p. 9.</hi> For document, see Memorial, pp. 72-136.</note>

<note>10 After a journey in the Congo State in 1896, M. Pickard writes of the "mutilated forests where until lately villages had nestled; great heaps of cinders amid desolated palm groves and trampled-down banana fields." He adds: "The terror caused by the memory of inhuman floggings and massacres haunts their brains, and they go as fugitives to the hospitable bush or across the frontiers."&#8212;<hi rend="italics">"En Congolie," p. 95.</hi></note>

<note><hi rend="italics">* For remarkable debate in Belgium Parliament, see Supplement, ¶'s 54-67.</hi></note>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>