<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1382">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter, March 28, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1382</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1882-03-28">March 28, 1882</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43915538">Havelock, Arthur Elibank, Sir, 1844-1908</term>
<term>Harris</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/78527251">Kennedy, Arthur Edward, Sir, 1809-1883</term>
<term>Prince Manna</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Mount (Liberia)</term>
<term>Half Garraway (Liberia)</term>
<term>Manna River</term>
<term>Marfa River</term>
<term>Robertsport (Liberia)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Solymah (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Vice Consul</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1882-03-28"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3981158369766001460009">Hunter, William, 1805-1886</persName>
<roleName>Second Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1882-05-23"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-02" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3012.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received May 23 1882</note>

<note>No 4</note>

<p>United States Consulate General<lb/>
Monrovia March 28th 1882.</p>

<p>M. A Aenmey to the Second Assist Secy of State</p>

<p>Subject</p>

<p>Arrival of Governor Havelock. Claims of English Subjects. Northwest Boundary Question. Reception of Governor A. E. Havelock as English Consul near the Government of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-3013.jpg"/>

<note>No 4</note>

<p>United States Consulate General<lb/>
Monrovia, March 28, 1882</p>

<p>M. A Aenmey to the Second Assist. Secretary of State</p>
<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to inform you that, during the last three weeks, several British war vessels have touched at Monrovia. Their visit were caused by the expected arrival here of Captain A. E. Havelock, Governor in Chief of Her <sic>Brittanic</sic> Majesty's West African Settlements, who has been recently appointed to discharge the duties of British Consul near the Government of Liberia, to receive his exequatur and to conduct certain negotiations between the two governments.</p>

<p>The British vessels called either for orders or to received dispatches.</p>

<p>Governor Havelock announced that he would arrive here on the 11th inst. On receipt of this notification the Liberian Consul at Sierra Leone was directed to request the Governor to defer his visit until the 28th instant. H.M.S. Briton which arrived here on the 11th inst. brought a dispatch from Governor Havelock in which he regretted that <catchwords>he</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3014.jpg"/>

he could not defer his visit later than the 17th inst. In that despatch occasion was taken to indicate the subjects upon which negotiations were desired on the part of the <sic>Brittish</sic> Government. These subjects were, I understand, the following–viz</p>

<p>1. The Manna River Claims. (2) The Claims of Mr Harris, a British subject, residing at Sulymah, a place claimed to be within the jurisdiction of Liberia and (3) the Northwest Boundary Question.– The Manna River claims are certain sums claimed by a few British traders, who were doing in the Manna Country in 1871, at the time the Liberian Government sent an expedition into the territory, to punish a refracting chief, known as Prince Manna, who at that time raided in the neighborhood of the settlement of Robertsport, burning native Hamlets, killing the inmates and carrying both Americo Liberians and native citizens of the Republic into captivity; Mr Roye's Government informed Sir A. E. Kennedy, then Governor of Sierra Leone, that a military expedition would be sent against Prince Manna; Sir A. E. Kennedy issued a notification to the <sic>Brittish</sic> traders in the territory acquainting them of the proposed movement and requiring them to remove their persons and <catchwords>property</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3015.jpg"/>

property within British territory. Although more than twenty day's elapsed, before the Liberian force reached the neighborhood of their factories, they seem to have neglected to remove. A Resident of the town, in which the factories were, stated at the time of the Expedition that there was an understanding in the town that one the <sic>approch</sic> of the Liberian forces the injury should be all attributed to them. The factory were plundered and destroyed, English subjects and native residents, declare that it was done by the Liberians; Liberian citizens and residents of the town declare, that <sic>is</sic> was done by the retreating natives. The traders claim to have lost £8838. and there is every indication that pressure will be put on the Liberian Government in order that this money way be regained.</p>

<p>Mr Harris of Sulymah claims something over £9000 for losses alleged to have been suffered at the hands of the Liberian authorities for a period extending over twenty years commencing with the seizure of the Phoebe and Emily by the Liberian Government in 1860 and concluding with the capture of the <sic>Crooboy</sic> by the local authorities of Maryland County at half <sic>Garroway</sic> in 1880. <catchwords>This</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3016.jpg"/>

This claim was entirely unexpected and took the Liberian Government by surprise. It will <sic>verry</sic> possibly not be pressed should the Liberian authorities be able to make certain facts apparent.</p>

<p>For the settlement of the north-west Boundary question, the <sic>folowing</sic> were the basis laid down. Her Majesty's Government is of opinion (1) that the territories of Liberia and Sierra Leone should be conterminous, and (2) that the jurisdiction of Liberia ought not to extend over the any territory Westward of Cape Mount, the natives of which are indisposed to accept the control of the Government of the Republic, or in which Liberia has not established and well settled rights.</p>

<p>Governor Havelock <sic>arived</sic> here on Monday the 19th inst, in the Colonial <sic>yatch</sic> Prince of Wales escorted by H.B.M. ship Algerine He was received by the President of the Republic at 4. p.m. in presence of the Cabinet, the foreign Consuls and the prominent citizens of the town, I had the honor of being present.</p>

<p>The Government appointed Edw. W. Blyden Esq. and Ex Attorney General W. Davis to confer with Governor Havelock and to conduct the negotiations on the part of Liberia; a <catchwords>kind</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3017.jpg"/>

kind of mined commission has been organized. The first session of the commission took place on Tuesday the 20th of March. The Mannah River claims were discussed. The British dispositions were read. The Liberian Commissioners then put in their counter-case. Copies of their statement and evidence were asked for and the commission adjourned until the 21st in the afternoon in order that Governor Havelock might present his views thereon. On the 22d of March Governor Havelock proposed to the Liberian Commissioners, that, if the Government of Liberia would abandon all the territories westward from Cape Mount down to the <sic>Marpha</sic> River, and now claimed by the Liberia Government, that the British Government would settle all the claims of their Subjects, and the negotiations could be regarded as concluded. The Liberian Citizens have expressed such unmistakable evidence of their dissatisfaction with the proposals of the British Commissioner that the President of Liberia has <sic>deem</sic> it necessary to call an extra session of the Senate to discuss the matter.</p>

<p>Governor Havelock returned in the Prince of Wales escorted by the <sic>Algerin</sic> to Sierra Leone without having <sic>succeded</sic> in getting the British claim <catchwords>settled</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-3018.jpg"/>

settled; that general opinion is that in short the British Government will use force to recover their claim.</p>

<p>With consideration of the highest esteem<lb/>
I remain Sir<lb/>
Your obedt servant<lb/>
M. A Aenmey<lb/>
U.S. Vice Consul Genl</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>