<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


Consulate of the United States
of America at Sierra Leone
31st December 1861

Sierra Leone yearly report

I have the honor to forward the following report in acordance with the consular instructions as contained in the 153rd and 154th sections of the consular regulations.

The colony of sierra Leone <unclear> ceded </unclear> to the English in the year 1787 by the native <unclear extent= two words/> embraces an extent of aout 5 or square miles, its southern point- <unclear extent=three words/> in about 8 <degree sign/>  10' in latitude and its southern point <unclear> freelines</unclear> lies in about 8 <degree sign/> 30' it is mostly mountainous land having an elevation of from <unclear/> to 25 ou feet above thee level of the sea, it was first <unclear> nettlect by a fiarty of </unclear> few blacks from Nova Scotia in the year 1792 and their descedents are to this day called letters, in the Colony. 

The colony is divided into four districts the 1st and 2nd Eastern comprisig the vilages of Kessy, Welington, Hastings, Newlands, Allentown, Rokelle, Frasertown, Denham, and Waterlou, the mountain district comprising Wilberforce, Merrytown, Aberdeen Gloucester, Bathurst, Request and Charlotte, the Banana islands, dependencies of the Colony are also included in this district and included in this district and have the small vilages of Dublin and Ricketts on them, the Western district includes the vilages of Hamilton, York, Goodrich and Heut, each district is under the charge of officer styled manager who is accountable to the colonial government in Freetown the sea-pert and capitol of the colony. 

The government of the colony is <unclear> vestel</unclear> in the Goverbot, and a council of fewer members, all of whom hold colonial appointments under the Leone government wit the exception of one, a merchant of the colony, the following are the gentlemen of the council, John Carr Chief Justice E.H. Beccler, Bishop, A. ityjames Queens advocate Gov. N. Nicel Colonial secretary, T Commissing Collector, R. Bradshaw Colonial Surgeon, and Cader Hedder merchant, all of whom are styled <unclear> favorable </unclear> , they are only responsible to the home governemnt, and the laws they pass and submitted to the Queen and confirmed by the before the colonists are aware of their entrance, people of the colony have no <unclear> choice </unclear> whatever in their government, neither in the election of the members of council above mentioned. 

The commerce of the colony has fallen off considerably the past year in consequence of the American difficulties, and a failure of the ground-nut crop.

For a <unclear/> of the imports and exports of this colony I would refer you to the snnul report from this consulate for this yer 1860.

The imports from the United States for the present year show a fair average with those of past-years of the general state of commerce is taken int considertion, the colony being to a great extent dependent on the United States for several of the staple articles of its trade our difficulties have naturally interfer with the general facilities of trade, the following table given . correct <unclear> eden </unclear> of the imports for the present year.

Table of Imports 
Article Quantity Value 
Tobacco 609 <unclear/> $182,700 00
N.E. Rum 2267 Barrels 30,000 00
Flour 1030 do 8,240 00
Bread 510 do 3,100 00
Shingles 450,000 2,250 00
Boards 482,000 fest 12,320 00
Cotton Cards 113 Cases 226 bag 904 00
Tabacco 200 Bales 3,000 00
Cotton Goods 160 Packages 17,600 00
Beef 60 Barrels 900 00
Smoke Herring 1287 Boyes 643 50
Soap 250 do 1500 00
Candles 115 do 575 00
Total of Value $263,742 50

With the above imports we have <unclear> undry small consequments</unclear> of Quincy bays, Corn meal Alewives, Mackerel. Sactfish, Herring in barrels, Gunpowder, Bulten, Cheese, <unclear>Lord; Biscuit, Herouni Vil, Heroo Lamer Pamilo, Maucula hemp cpldage, Quince, Potatoes, Pork, Hames Oars, Chaves, Bedstend, Plat-form Seales, Jruvall Boats, Brown, and Nleite Bitters, Ceder Medicines, Coal-tor, For, Pitch, Nails, Trunks Cigards se, se, se. community  in the aggregate to about $50,000.00 giving a ground total of $313,742.50. </unclear>

The exports to the United States for the same year show the following, requires; vig-

Table of Exports
Article Quantities Value 
Hides 104,605 wight 1,043,450 ths $153900 00
Palm Vil 583 Casks 68940 gals 34,470 00
Ginger 201 Tons 19807 00
Ground0nuts 15000 Beerfeels 7500 00
$215,677 00

Bender there the following articles are chipped in small quanitities Camwood, Aloe Copper, Old competition Ivory, Coffee, Hove, Leopard skins shelled, Pepprs, Arrowort, Old fro se, se, se valued about 30,000 00

Grand total of exports $245,677 00                           