<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0304">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Secretary of State, November 4, 1907</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0304</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Vice Governor General to the Secretary of State</title>
<date when="1907-11-04">November 4, 1907</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 239, Liasse 205</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bertrand</term>
<term>Gilchrist</term>
<term>Memminger</term>
<term>Reed, Henry</term>
<term>Smith</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bangala</term>
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Coquilhatville</term>
<term>Kasai</term>
<term>Leopoldville</term>
<term>Lulonga</term>
<term>Maringa-Lopori zone</term>
<term>Sonabata</term>
<term>Stanley-Pool</term>
<term>Upoto</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Vice Governor General</roleName>
<placeName>Boma</placeName>
<date when="1907-11-04"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-11" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2018" who="pr">Translated.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.001.jpg"/>

<p>Etat Independant
Du 
Congo<lb/>
Gouvernement Local<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 2132<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse la date et le numéro<lb/>
2 Annexes.<lb/>
Objet:
Voyage Consul Général Etats-
Unis d'Amerique.</p>

<p>Boma, le 4 Novembre 1907.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Secrétaire d'Etat,</p>

<p>Comme suite à dépêche no 1643, du 29 août dernier,
relative au voyage du Consul des Etats-Unis d'Amerique,
j'ai l'honneur de vous faire parvenir, sous ce pli, en copie,
la lettre no 115 G.L., du 15 octobre, que le Commissaire
de district de l'Equateur m'a adressée.</p>

<p>Cette lettre m'a été envoyée en réponse à un télégramme
que, sous la date du 14 octobre, j'avais envoyé à
M. Bertrand et dans lequel je m'étonnais de n'avoir pas
été avisé du passage du Consul Général des Etats-Unis
d'Amérique, à Coquilhatville.</p>

<p>MM. Smith et Memminger sont rentrés à Boma il y a
quelques jours.</p>

<p>D'après le télégramme ci-joint en copie du Commissaire
de district du Stanley-Pool, datée du 24 octobre, M.
Smith se serait rendu la veille de sa descente à Boma à
Sonabata.</p>

<p>M. Smith aurait l'intention d'entreprendre prochainement
un voyage dans le district du Kasai.</p>

<p>J'aurai soin de vous tenir au courant de tous les
renseignements qui me parviendraient au sujet des déplacements
de cet agent consulaire.</p>

<p>Le Vice Gouveneur Général,<lb/>
<unclear extent="one signature"/></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.002.jpg"/>

<p>No 115-G.IL.</p>

<p>Coquilhatville, le 15 octobre 1907.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Gouverneur Général,</p>

<p>En réponse à votre télégramme rappelé ci-contre,
j'ai l'honneur de porter à votre connaissance qu'ayant
été avisé par Lépoldville du passage du Consul Général
des Etats-Unis, je croyais le Gouvernement averti de ce
déplacement. Comme au surplus M. Smith, en passant la première
fois, n'a fait que mettre pied à terre, disant regretter
de ne pas rencontrer le Commissaire de district
absent, comme aucun incident d'aucune espèce ne s'est produit,
je n'ai attaché à cette visete aucun caractère 
d'importance valant une communication au Gouvernement. Avant
de partir, M. Smith ayat dit qu'il comptait me recontrer
en cours de voyage, on en avait conclu qu'il se rendait
dans la zone de la Maringa-Lopori où il n'a d'ailleurs
pas pénétré.</p>

<p>Ce n'est que le 12 octobre, lors de son retour, que
j'ai appris qu'il avait été dans le district des Bangala.
Cette fois il est resté à Coquilhatville environ une
heure et demie. Il s'est informé du montant des prestations
dans le district. Les roles de prestations n'ayant pas
un caractère confidentiel, j'ai cru devoir lui donner les
renseignements demandés.</p>

<p>Le Consul Général m'a dit, en s'informant de la véracité
de la plainte, que les indigènes de Lulonga lui avaient
signalé l'exagération des prestations en poisson
exigées d'eux. Or, ces indigènes ne sont imposés que pour 
900 grammes de poisson boucané par mois. Ils avaient affirmé
que l'imposition était hebdomadaire. J'ai démenti
la chose simplement en m'en rapportant aux feuilles d'avertissement
signées pour acquit par l'agent percepteur.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.003.jpg"/>

<p>M. Smith n'avait pas songé à examiner les dates de paiement.
Cette plainte n'a pu être faite qu'à l'instigation
du missionnaire Gilchrist de Lulonga.</p>

<p>Incidemment, dans le cours de la conversation très 
cordiale entre nous, il m'a fait savoir qu'aux environs
d'Upoto, je crois, il avait lui-même été faire une récolte
de caoutchouc. Mon impression est qu'il trouve exagérée
la quantité de 3 kilos exigée mensuellement des contribuables.</p>

<p>M. Smith, accompagné du Vice Consul, voyageait à bord
du "Henry Reed" de la A.B.M.U."</p>

<p>Je ne vois rien d'autre à signaler concernant le passage
de ces agents diplomatiques.</p>

<p>Le Commissaire de district,<lb/>
(s) Bertrand.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.004.jpg"/>

<p>De Léopoldville, le 24 octobre 1907.</p>
    
<p>Consul Général Etats-Unis partir aujourd'hui pour
Sonabata (mission américaine Baptist missionary Society)
descendre demain Boma. Vice Consul anglais partira probablement
lundi pour Boma.</p>
    
<p>(s) Heer.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.001.jpg"/>
        
<p>Independent State
of the
Congo<lb/>
Local Government<lb/>
Direction<lb/>
No 2132<lb/>
Remember the date and number in the response<lb/> 
2 Annexes.<lb/>
Subject:<lb/>
Consulate General of the United States 
of America's Trip.</p>
        
<p>Boma, Novembre 4, 1907.</p>

<p>Mr. Secretary of State,</p>
        
<p>Following the dispatch no 1643, from last August 29, 
regarding the voyage of the United States of America Consulate,
I have the honor to transmit herewith, in copy, 
letter no 115 G.L., from October 15, that the Commissioner 
from the Equator district addressed to me.</p>
        
<p>This letter was sent to me in response to a telegram
that, under the date of October 14, I had sent to 
M. Bertrand and in which I was astonished to not have 
been informed about the passage of the Consulate General of the United States
of America, in Coquilhatville.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Smith and Memminger came back to Boma a couple 
days ago.</p>
        
<p>After the telegram copy attached here from the Commissioner 
of district of Stanley-Pool, dated October 24, Mr. 
Smith would have been the day before his descent to Boma by 
Sonabata.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Smith had the intention to begin next with 
a trip in the Kasai district.</p>
        
<p>I will take care to keep you updated on all the 
information that reach me about the movement 
of this consulate agent.</p>
        
<p>The Vice Governor General,<lb/>
<unclear extent="one signature"/></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.002.jpg"/>

<p>No 115-G.I.</p>

<p>Coquilhatville, October 15, 1907.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Governor General,</p>
        
<p>In response to your telegram recalled here,  
I have the honor to carry to your knowledge that having 
been informed by Lépoldville of the passage of the Consulate General 
of the United States, I believe the Government was told of this 
movement. What is more, while passing the first 
time, Mr. Smith did not land, expressed regrets in
not meeting the Commissioner of the absent 
district, as no incident of any type had risen,
I attached no importance of character to this
visit worth communication to the Government. Before
leaving, Mr. Smith had said that he counts my return 
during the voyage, we had concluded that he rose 
in the Maringa-Lopori zone where he had not further 
penetrated.</p>
        
<p>It was only October 12, during your journey home, that
I learned that he had been in the Bangala district. 
This time he had rested in Coquilhatville about one 
and a half hours. He was informed of the rising performances
in the district. The roles of the performances had no
confidential character, I believed the necessity in giving him the 
details asked for.</p>
        
<p>The Consul General told me, by informing of the truthfulness
of the complaint, that the Lulonga natives had signaled to
him the exaggeration of the performance in the fish benefits
required of them. Yet, the natives were not commanded that for
900 grams of smoked fish a month. They had confirmed
that the imposition was weekly. I denied 
this simply by reporting to the sheets of warning
signed for receipt by the tax collector.

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.003.jpg"/>
        
Mr. Smith had not dreamed of examining the dates of payment.
This complaint cannot be made from missionary Gilchrist of Lulonga's 
instigation.</p>
        
<p>Incidentally, in the course of the very cordial  
conversation between us, he informed me that in the vicinity 
of Upoto, I believe, he had himself been doing rubber
harvests. My impression is that he finds exaggerated 
quantity of 3 kilos demanded every month from  
taxpayers.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Smith, accompanied by Vice Consul, traveling aboard 
the "Henry Reed" from the  A.B.M.U."</p>
        
<p>I see nothing else to signal regarding the passage 
of these diplomatic agents.</p>
        
<p>District Commissioner,<lb/>
(s) Bertrand.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0304.004.jpg"/>

<p>From Léopoldville, October 24, 1907.</p>
        
<p>Consul General of the United States leaves today for  
Sonabata (American mission Baptist missionary Society)
comes down tomorrow Boma. English Vice Consul will leave probably 
Monday for Boma.</p>
        
<p>(s) Heer.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
