<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>
George W. Williams, "The Negro as a Political Problem" (1884)
</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0013</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">1862&#8212;Emancipation Day&#8212;1884; The Negro as a Political Problem</title>
<author n="Williams, George W.">George W. Williams</author>
<editor/>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<publisher>Alfred Mudge &amp; Son, Printers</publisher>
<date when="1884">1884</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-08-12" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p000" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.000"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>1862&#8212;Emancipation Day&#8212;1884</p>

<p>The Negro as a Political Problem.</p>

<p>Oration
by the
Hon. George W. Williams,
of Massachusettes,
at the
Asbury Church, Washington, D.C.,
April 16, 1884.</p>

<p>"From every hill instinct with life is sent<lb/>
Gratitude&#8212;a mental sacrament,<lb/>
That from their neck they loosen'd felt the yoke&#8212;<lb/>
That the first link in slavery's chain was broke."</p>

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.001"/>

<p>Oration.</p>

<p>The Negro as a Political Problem.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Mr. President, Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>

<p>From the waters of the Potomac to the liberty-crowned 
dome of the Capitol of the nation the bells of
liberty have been ringing. The prayer of gratitude has
been said, and the dirge has been sung at the tomb of
slavery. The stirring strains of martial music, the
swinging battalions of troops, the citizens in holiday attire, 
the bright faces and glad voices of the day, proclaim
this an occasion of more than ordinary interest. And
now, at the close of this anniversary day, while the
pride, pomp, and circumstance of the occasion pass to
their place in history, let us turn to the muse of meditation. 
Under this sacred shelter, whose platform has
been the fortress of every honest and humane interest,
we may find all the conditions friendly to reflection and
instruction. Experience holds in lifted hand the flaming 
torch of knowledge, while our hearts know full
well the serious lessons this day would teach us. There
are but two rational reasons for going back into the
past: one is where we can gather the fadeless flowers

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.002"/>

of memory whose aroma may yet cheer the present;
the other is where the bitter herbs of experience may
act as a tonic upon a debilitated moral effort amid the
living issues of the present.</p>

<p>Few, indeed, and odorless and colorless, are the flowers 
of memory that we as a race care to turn back and
pluck. Passion flowers innumerable we might find.
But were we to turn and touch them, every stamen and
petal would instantly become vocal with a thousand
tongues. They would tell the story of tribes cheated,
villages burned, and murder perpetrated by the remorseless 
hand of gain. They would relate the story
of the middle passage, of young men and innocent
maidens, of old men and helpless women, forced into
the horrible middle passage; how that the ocean
became a voracious sepulchre for hundreds of thousands 
of the hapless victims of the slave-trade, and will
forever chant a ceaseless requiem over their watery
grave; they would voice the deep plaint of innocent
womanhood led into captivity, of broken hearts and
sundered families; they would tell the long and mournful 
story of a race's wrongs and sufferings,&#8212;of hope
and piety, love and fear; we should hear how the race
was mobbed in the North and sold at the South; how
malice and vengeance, lash, knife, gun, dungeon, fire,
water, and insanity, performed their hateful work. God
forbid that we should undertake so dreadful a task!
For were we thus to review the past we would find little 
else save a cemetery. And as we walked abroad we
should find naught but graves of buried rights, hopes,

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.003"/>

and loves; of manly aspirations foully murdered, and 
pious protests cruelly strangled. Over such terrible 
things we must let the pall drop. We must turn only 
to those facts of history that may act as a tonic and 
inspiration for the discharge of duties present and 
future.</p> 

<p>SLAVERY IN THIS DISTRICT<lb/> 
was always an anomaly. The District was ceded to 
the United States government by Maryland and Virginia; 
but the portion belonging to Virginia was subsequently 
ceded back to that State. Thus the District 
was ceded entirely by Maryland. This was consummated 
in 1790, and comprised sixty-four square miles. 
In 1634 the Colony of Maryland was formed out of a 
portion of the territory belonging to Virginia. And 
Maryland, as the other Southern Colonies, held slaves 
until the war for the Union destroyed the institution. 
When Congress appointed a committee to secure a permanent 
seat for the government, instructions were also 
given to provide a place where it should have authority 
also. This was done; and in December, 1800, the Congress 
of the United States moved into the District.</p>
 
<p>In the articles of concession, the people then living 
in the District of Columbia did not reserve any vested 
rights. They had no indefeasible possessory right to 
slave property. There was nothing in the Constitution 
justifying the existence of the evil at the very seat of 
the American government. So, then, the crime was 
permitted for more than sixty years.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.004"/>

<p>The following table exhibits the number of free and bond persons of color in the District for the space of six decades:&#8212;</p>
 
<table>
<row>
<cell>Year.</cell>
<cell>Free Negroes.</cell>
<cell>Slave Negroes.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1800</cell>
<cell>490</cell>
<cell>3,244</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1810</cell>
<cell>1,527</cell>
<cell>5,395</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1820</cell>
<cell>2,758</cell>
<cell>6,377</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1830</cell>
<cell>4,604</cell>
<cell>6,119</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1840</cell>
<cell>6,499</cell>
<cell>4,694</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1850</cell>
<cell>10,059</cell>
<cell>3,687</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>1860</cell>
<cell>11,131</cell>
<cell>3,181</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>In 1870 there were 43,404 Negroes in the District; 
and in 1880, 59,596.</p>
 
<p>That it was clearly within the power of Congress to 
abolish it no clear-headed statesman ever doubted. It 
was tolerated in the States because the people had the 
right to support it by State Constitution, or abolish it 
by amendment. But all government territory was 
under the immediate and absolute control of Congress.
If it were claimed by Northern apologists that the 
Union could not have been formed except slavery were 
allowed in the Southern States, there was certainly no 
good excuse for tolerating the crime in the District of 
Columbia. And yet for more than two generations 
slavery built its altars under the aegis of the American 
Capitol; the slave-hound bayed his human victims, and 
the black shadow of the accursed institution sent a chill 
of death through thousands of hearts.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p005" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.005"/>

<p>In 1800, as we have shown, there were 3,244 slaves in 
the District of Columbia. Ten years later the slave 
population had increased to 5,3^)5, in 1820 it was 6,877, 
in 1830 it was 6,119, in 1840 it was 4,694, in 1850 it 
was 3,687, and in 1860 there were only 3,186. By these 
figures we see that at the end of six decades there were 
less slaves in the District than there were at the beginning 
of the century. The largest number was in 1820, 
6,377. This was the year in which the Missouri Compromise 
occasioned so much excitement. From that 
year down to the breaking out of the Rebellion, the 
slave population was on a steady decrease. Slavery, 
existing within the District without sanction of law, 
attracted the attention of anti-slavery men from the beginning. 
In 1827 William Lloyd Garrison began his career 
as an anti-slavery agitator by addressing a petition 
to Congress for the abolition of slavery in the District 
of Columbia. The friends of freedom saw the glaring 
inconsistency of allowing the slave-trade to go on at 
the capital of a free republic, and thus they felt it to be 
a patriotic duty to labor for the abolition of the evil in 
the District. But the influence of the South was overwhelming. 
Avarice and cotton were more than a match 
for humanity, and the clank of the slaves' chains was 
heard in your streets. Justice tarried; the nation 
halted at its plain, constitutional duty, and failed to use 
its authority. The years flew apace, until at last even-handed 
justice lifted the bitter chalice of war to the 
nation's lips.</p>
 
<p>The shock of embattled arms, that had been the nation's

<pb xml:id="p006" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.006"/>

lullaby, was heard in dreadful reverberations 
throughout the land. A year of an unbroken series 
of Union disasters humbled the national pride. While 
the nation was struggling and gasping for life, while 
all the powers of Congress were invoked to tear, one 
by one, the steel fingers of armed rebellion from the 
nation's throat, in the slave marts of the capital bonds-men, 
with brows beaded with the sweat of unrequited 
toil, lifted their pinioned hands to yon goddess of liberty 
in vain. The heart of the nation was as hard as 
the brazen images on the Capitol that had witnessed for 
years that the Constitution of this great Republic was a 
tissue of lies. The national treasury was depleted; the 
bonds were depreciated; the commerce that had 
whitened all seas had largely disappeared; the workshops 
were deserted; treason lurked in the high places; 
the rebel forces were closing in upon the capital, and 
the red fields of inglorious conflict admonished the 
Congress to wipe the foul stain of slavery from the 
District of Columbia.</p>

<p>THE MORAL EFFECT<lb/>
of emancipation in the District of Columbia was marked. 
Anti-slavery men regarded this as the entering wedge. 
It was the thermometer of Congressional patriotism; it 
was the glorious reward of patient and consistent labor; 
it was the answer to agonizing prayers,&#8212;a prophecy of 
victory, long delayed, for the cause of the Union. It 
became the theme of the pulpit, the topic of editorial

<pb xml:id="p007" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.007"/>

discussion, the inspiration of our army, the bright star
of a nation's hope, suddenly breaking into a long night
of distress and perplexity.</p> 

<p>From field and mountain, from cabin and cot, from 
hamlet and village, the long, dark stream of eager freedmen
poured into the capital of the Republic. In the 
more evil days they shrank from the name of Washington
as from some deadly reptile. Washington was the 
place where legal chains were forged for their unwilling 
limbs. Under the goddess of liberty laws had been 
enacted that charged every power of the government to 
hunt down, at all hazards, and regardless of cost, the 
fugitive flying for life, and hurry him back to the hell 
of slavery. Under the dome of that Capitol a Chief 
Justice had declared that "a Negro had no rights that a 
white is bound to respect." No Negro had been allowed 
to walk under the shadow of the Capitol or darken its 
door, except as nurse or servant to some Southern 
slaveholder.</p>
 
<p>Horrible indeed were the thoughts of Washington to 
the poor slaves beyond its borders. But the news of 
emancipation had come to them in their dark Isle of 
Patmos, and was heard above the mad storm of civil 
war. Washington was transformed from a prison to a 
castle. To the poor fugitive and bondman it seemed 
now to be the only secure place in all the land. It 
stood as a lone island in the midst of an angry sea, and 
every wave of rebellion seemed anxious to devour it. 
But there it stood, amid the boom of cannon, the 
glare of the lightnings of war, safe even amidst the

<pb xml:id="p008" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.008"/>

machinations and plottings of treason. And here the 
curious Negro found rest and security. Under the 
ample folds of "the stars and stripes," the poetry of all 
loyal hearts, thousands of homeless, nameless, and penniless
freedmen went and came through these streets 
without let or hindrance.</p> 

<p>EDUCATED NEGROES<lb/> 
came into Washington also. They felt some security 
now, and were willing to serve the race and nation as 
opportunity offered; and history should not fail to record 
the fact that such Colored men as Douglass, 
Langston, Walls, Cook, Yashon, Garnet, Downing, and 
others exerted a good influence over the President and 
the Congress in the interest of the race. The Freedmen's 
Bureau, Bank, and barracks, the founding of 
night schools and hospitals, were brought about and 
managed not without the aid of intelligent and patriotic 
men of the Negro race. Industrious, sober, and educated 
leaders of the race in the District have wrought 
mightily for good; and since the close of the war 
Washington has contained a larger number of educated 
men and women of the Negro race than any other city 
in the United States, according to its population. The 
District of Columbia is the home of Frederick Douglass, 
and he will always remain the great historic Negro. 
Hon. John Mercer Langston, United States Minister to 
Hayti, Wm. E. Matthews, the broker, Capt. O. B. S. 
Walls, are among the foremost men of Washington; 

<pb xml:id="p009" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.009"/>

and the professions contain noble representatives of the 
race. Howard University and Wayland Seminary, 
Sumner High School and the seventy-five public schools 
for Colored pupils alone, are equal to the educational 
work to be accomplished in the District.</p>
 
<p>THE OFFICE-HOLDERS<lb/> 
in Washington are not all white persons; there are 
six hundred and twenty persons of color in the departments. 
The collector of taxes, the register of 
deeds, and the register of the United States treasury 
are able men of the Negro race. But, notwithstanding
this showing, we must see through the lenses 
of experience that office-seeking or office-holding 
is not a healthy employment for young men. It is 
true that there must be trained men for these 
positions of government trust and emolument, but there are 
always more horses than stalls. The evil is in making 
a government position a profession. This idea once 
espoused, a young man is unfitted for any other position 
in civil life. When an office-holder has saved some 
money&#8212;but few ever do&#8212;he should resign, and go 
into some business for which he is especially fitted. 
We know that few officials die, and none resign. But 
two resignations gave the Negro race a successful 
broker and an historian. Let others follow these examples.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p010" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.010"/>

<p>SUFFRAGE IN THE DISTRICT<lb/> 
would do much good to all classes of people. It was 
tried once, but purblind prejudice sought its destruction 
before the results were reached.</p>
 
<p>Nevertheless, Alexander Shepard sowed wisely, and 
to-day all of the people of the District are enjoying 
the fruit of his wise labors. If suffrage for the people of 
this District is objected to because it would grant a 
power to a large number of ignorant people, we would 
say that such an objection but begs the question. To 
advance such an objection is to confess universal manhood 
suffrage a failure. And, furthermore, if suffrage 
is withheld on account of ignorance in the District of 
Columbia, it should be withdrawn in New York City 
for the same reason. Ignorance in the majority cannot 
dominate an intelligent and patriotic minority: one of 
the latter can chase a thousand of the former, and two 
can put ten thousand to flight. With a competent man 
as governor of the territory, with a careful House of 
Delegates and a Council, reforms could be inaugurated, 
abuses corrected, and such public improvements made 
as to make Washington the best regulated and most 
beautiful city in all the wide world.</p>
 
<p>RACE PREJUDICE<lb/> 
should be driven from Washington, suffrage or no suffrage. 
It is a national disgrace that nearly every hotel 
in Washington closes its doors against the Negro. He 

<pb xml:id="p011" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.011"/>

comes, if he come at all, amply prepared to pay his 
way; and the fact that he goes to a first-class hotel 
should be regarded as prima facie evidence of decent 
personal appearance, good manners, and good sense. 
Circumstances govern these cases, or ought to. Hotel 
proprietors are more to be blamed than the public. 
They are in a position to educate the travelling public; 
and, to cater to this absolute and wicked prejudice, is to 
retard the moral growth and intellectual expansion of 
the public. Hotels are licensed and protected by law. 
The law-makers are the servants of the people. They 
intend, in serving and representing the people, that 
public inns shall provide for the wants of travellers 
without regard to race, color, or previous condition of 
servitude.</p> 

<p>A prejudice so pronounced and hurtful should be 
abolished here at the capital of the nation. In this good 
work Colored men themselves can accomplish a great 
deal. Visitors to the capital of the nation are very observing.
They form their judgments from what they 
see. And whom do they see first, last, and all the time 
they are here? The idle, shiftless, unkempt Negroes 
who lounge at the corners of the streets, doze on the 
City Hall steps, and whose deportment and idle colloquy 
make every decent person blush for very shame. 
Every clergyman in the District ought to make it a part 
of his ministry to teach these poor people the use of 
water and soap, of comb and brush. Cleanliness is 
next to godliness. And the most distressing part of 
this public exhibition of rags, ignorance, and idleness 
is, 

<pb xml:id="p012" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.012"/>

our respectable, industrious citizens are not seen. Here, 
then, a great injustice is done to all the Colored citizens 
of the District. Let us remove the beam from our own 
eye, then we shall see clearly the mote in the eye of a 
prejudiced and misguided public.</p>
 
<p>THE NEGRO PROBLEM<lb/>
is older than our government, Not that the Negro has 
thrust himself upon the attention of the world, but the 
world has been interested in him for various and conflicting
reasons. Strangely enough, the Negro has appeared 
at the central points in the history of the world. 
Simon, of Cyrene, appeared in time to bear the cross of the Saviour to Calvary.</p> 

<p>In North Africa, in the second century of the Christian 
era, the Negro bore the brunt of Saracen persecution, 
and clung to the Christian faith. In fact Africa was the 
battle-ground upon which the organic life of the Christian 
church was tested; and from that point of history 
and victory it went forth to civilize Northern Europe.</p> 

<p>The trend of the great forces of the world's best civilization, 
arms, commerce, letters, religion, and science 
has been around Africa. Touched but gently on the 
outer edge, the heart of the great continent is yet a 
stranger to the noblest impulses of the world's best life. 
For the most part only the defiling hand of slavery has 
been lain upon her. For nearly five centuries the slavetrade, 
domestic and foreign, shut out the light of 
knowledge as storm-clouds veil the brightness of the 
sun. In 1562 Sir John Hawkins, Sir Lionel Duchet, 

<pb xml:id="p013" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.013"/>

Sir Thomas Lodge, and Sir William Winter laid the 
foundation of the slave-trade during the reign of Elizabeth. 
At first the queen expressed herself as horrified; 
but later on encouraged the most pestiferous crime that 
ever cursed the seas. In 1702 her "most gracious 
Majesty," Queen Anne, in her elaborate instructions to 
the royal governors of the British Colonies in North 
America, urged that the people "take especial care 
that God Almighty be devoutly and duly served," and 
that the " Koyal African Company, of England," "take 
especial care that the said Province may have a constant 
and sufficient supply of merchantable Negroes at 
moderate rates." "The British Board of Trade" never
lost sight of the slave-trade; while Parliament never
thought the question of trafficking in human beings beneath 
its notice.</p> 

<p>SLAVERY IN THE COLONIES<lb/> 
was as early as anything connected with them. Alongside 
of the church and schoolhouse the colonists built 
the slave-pen. And with their prayers for religious 
and political liberty they supplicated both the earthly 
and heavenly throne for "merchantable Negroes." The 
evil grew, as evils do, until it was no less a serious 
question than the Stamp Act or the writs of assistance.</p>
 
<p>THE REVOLUTION ART WAR<lb/> 
<sic>demonstated</sic> how difficult a problem the Negro was.
On the 24th of October, 1774, the Continental Congress 

<pb xml:id="p014" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.014"/>

passed the Non-Importation Covenant. All the delegates 
from the twelve Colonies signed this covenant, 
that "We will neither import nor purchase any slave 
imported after the first day of December next; after 
which time we will wholly discontinue the slave-trade, 
and will neither be concerned in it ourselves, nor will 
we hire our vessels, nor sell our commodities or manufactures 
to those who are concerned in it." This magnificent
article, one of the two passed by the Congress 
then in session at Philadelphia, gives us a fair idea of 
the magnitude of the Negro problem. And it shows 
also, in the light of subsequent history, how false governments 
can be to themselves and how cruel to their subjects.</p>
 
<p>GEORGE WASHINGTON<lb/> 
was chairman of a meeting held at Fairfax Court 
House, Va., on the 18th of July, 1774, to protest against 
the slave-trade. Twenty-four resolutions were presented 
and unanimously adopted; three of the resolutions 
were directly against the slave-trade.</p>
 
<p>"17. Resolved, That it is the opinion of this meeting, 
that, during our present difficulties and distress, no 
slaves ought to be imported into any of the British 
Colonies on this continent; and we take this opportunity 
of declaring our most earnest Welshes to see an entire 
stop forever put to such a wicked, cruel, and unnatural 
trade."</p> 

<p>Coming from Virginia, the mother of slavery before 
she was the mother of Presidents, meant a great deal; 

<pb xml:id="p015" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.015"/>

but the feeling of concern about the slave-trade was 
not confined to any one Colony; all of them took action 
of some kind, and the interest was deep and genuine. 
The Colonies heard the low reverberations of the thunders 
of war; the clouds were gathering; they wanted to get 
into line with the anti-slavery sentiment of the provinces, 
to be in harmony with the increasing humanity of Europe,
to break the favorite hobby of the Crown, and to 
secure the sympathy of the slave population at home.</p> 

<p>On the 29th of May, 1775, the Committee of Safety 
for the Province of Massachusetts discussed the question 
of the military employment of Negroes. The 
question again made its appearance in the deliberations 
of this committee on the 6th of June, and once more on 
the 10th of July. On the 29th of September, 1775, the 
Negro question was warmly discussed in the Continental 
Congress, and on the 8th of October it entered the military 
conference at Cambridge. On the 18th and 23d 
of October, 1775, it was discussed, and on the 12th of 
November, 1775, Gen. George Washington made it the 
subject of a general order. On the 30th of December, 
Gen. "Washington again made it the subject of another 
general order, and on the next day, 31st December, 
wrote the President of the Continental Congress; 
and on the 16th of January, 1776, Negroes were 
admitted to serve as soldiers in the Continental Army.</p> 

<p>THE MINISTERIAL ARMY<lb/>
craved the services of the Negro, and its leaders were 
not idle. On the 16th of November, 1775, Lord Dunmore 

<pb xml:id="p016" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.016"/>

issued a proclamation, offering protection, freedom, 
the British uniform, and bounty to all Negroes 
who should join his standards; and for a time this proclamation 
had a disastrous effect upon the Negroes of 
Virginia in particular, and upon those of other Colonies 
in general. The struggle to secure the valuable services 
of the Negro went on until after the proclamation 
of Sir Henry Clinton, June 30, 1799. This 
proclamation appeared again in the Royal Gazette of 
New York, on the 3d of July, but the Negro had cast 
his lot with the colonial army. He heard the warning 
shots at Lexington, and the victorious guns of Rochambeau, 
Lafayette, and Washington at Yorktown; 
and when the war was over he heard the order of 
Washington read to the victorious troops that the 
British General, Sir Guy Carleton, in evacuating New 
York, was "not to carry away Negroes and other 
property."</p>

<p>THE CONSTITUTION<lb/> 
could not be made without a long, bitter discussion on 
the Negro question. This question overshadowed all 
others. It puzzled, perplexed, and annoyed the convention of distinguished gentlemen who had met to make 
a Constitution for the new government, born of the 
struggle between despotism and liberty. There were 
generals and statesmen, orators and authors, philanthropists 
and lawyers; there were soldiers, with the halo of 
battle still upon their brows, fresh from victorious fields, 
where they had witnessed the valor, efficiency, and 

<pb xml:id="p017" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.017"/>

humanity of Negro troops. The famous declaration of 
Jefferson, "that all men were created equal, that they 
are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable 
rights; that among these are life, liberty, and the pursuit 
of happiness," had become the shibboleth of all 
true Americans. Every memory and incident of the 
glorious Revolutionary struggle, every garland of victory, 
every impulse of humanity, the dictum of reason, 
the groans and tears of the slaves, and the voice of conscience 
cried aloud for consistency and justice. But the 
South wanted unpaid slaves, and the North wanted free 
ships. Slaves and ships were the paramount question.</p> 

<p>The Southern delegates shrewdly sought to restrict 
all navigation laws to a two-thirds vote, and by relieving 
the Southern States from duties on exports, and upon 
the importation of slaves, New England had to take 
what she could get. By denying Congress the authority 
of giving preference to American over foreign shipping, 
it was designed to secure cheap transportation for 
Southern exports; but, as the shipping was largely 
owned in the Eastern States, their delegates were zealous 
in their efforts to prevent any restriction of the 
power of Congress to enact navigation laws. The prohibition 
of duties on the importation of slaves was 
demanded by the delegates from South Carolina and 
Georgia. They assured the convention that without 
such a provision they could never give their assent to 
the Constitution. The Northern delegates gave their 
support to the restriction, and the Negro became a fixed 
quality in this great political equation.</p> 

<pb xml:id="p018" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.018"/>

<p>WITH SLAVERY CONCEDED<lb/> 
to the Southern States, maintainable by constitutional 
authority, an element in the basil condition of Congressional
representation, there was no way out of this conspiracy 
against human liberty. Ichabod, the glory had 
departed from the Constitution. It had conceived sin 
and was to bring forth death. "What would be the 
logic of this constitutional position? Legislation in 
harmony with constitutional recognition of slavery. 
On the 6th of April, 1789, the first day of the first session 
of the first Congress under the present Constitution, 
the Negro question made its appearance in the 
tariff bill presented by Mr. Parker, of Virginia. In 
every session of Congress, until the year 1800, the 
Negro question appeared in one form or another. It 
could not be said to have subsided for any considerable 
time.</p> 

<p>Pained by the past, expecting ills to come,<lb/> 
In some dread moment by the fates assign'd,</p> 

<p>the Congress knew not the hour or character in which 
the insoluble question might come.</p> 

<p>THE NINETEENTH CENTURY<lb/> 
opened with an earnest struggle for the extinction 
of the slave-trade to the coast of Guinea. On the 2d 
of January, 1800, a committee of intelligent citizens of 
color, from Philadelphia, presented a petition to Congress 
protesting against the continuance of the slavetrade 

<pb xml:id="p019" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.019"/>

on the seas. It was presented by the member 
from the county of Philadelphia, and provoked immediate 
and sharp discussion. The tone and manner of 
the Southern members clearly indicated that they were 
committed to the policy of non-interference with slavery 
on the part of the Northern members.</p> 

<p>On the 2d of April, 1802, Georgia ceded the territory
lying west of her present limits, now embracing the 
States of Alabama and Mississippi. By the ordinance 
of 1787, passed on the 13th of July that same year, 
slavery was excluded from the western territory. In the Georgia articles of concession, slavery was allowed; 
and the demand of Georgia for the spread of the evil 
was acceded to. When the Territory of Indiana desired 
to be formed into a State and admitted into the 
Union, an attempt was made to repeal the ordinance 
of 1787. Accordingly, on the 2d of March, 1803, the 
select committee, to whom the prayer of the inhabitants 
of Indiana Territory had been referred, took the matter 
under consideration. It dragged its lazy lengths 
through the entire session of this Congress, and 
slept only during the recess. On the 17th of February, 
1804, it was again under discussion. The committee 
reported that the sixth article of the ordinance of 1787, 
excluding slavery from the western territory, should 
"be suspended in a qualified manner for ten years." 
The Congress did not reach the matter, but the friends 
of slavery did not lose sight of it. So again, in the 
Congress of 1805-G, another attempt was made in the 
interest of the measure. On the 14th of February, 

<pb xml:id="p020" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.020"/>

1806, the committee having the memorial in charge 
made a favorable report. The report was made the 
special order for a day certain, but was crowded out by 
other business. Nothing daunted. Gen. Harrison, governor 
of the Indiana Territory, with resolves from his 
territorial legislature, addressed a letter urging a suspension 
of the ordinance of 1787. On the Hist of January, 
1807, his letter, with enclosures, was received, and 
sent to a special committee. On the 12th of February, 
1807, the committee made a favorable report. Again 
the matter was made the special order, but was never 
called up. Two other attempts were made, when the 
matter subsided.</p>
 
<p>THE SLAVE POPULATION<lb/> 
increased thirty-three per cent during these years of excitement, 
and slavery as an institution was sending its 
dark death-roots into the organic life of the nation. In 
1817, Dec. 10, Mississippi applied for admission into the 
Union. The trial of slaves by grand juries was dispensed 
with, and the regulations for the system were 
exacting and cruel.</p> 

<p>OUR NAVY<lb/> 
policed the seaboard for several years to prevent the 
slave-trade from foreign parts. Congress had attempted 
to make the old fugitive slave law more efficient 
by amendment. In the session of 1817-18, it 
passed the House by a vote of eighty-four to sixty-nine. 
Amended in the Senate, it passed by a vote of seventeen 

<pb xml:id="p021" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.021"/>

to thirteen, but was tabled in the House. Anti-slavery 
sentiment began to take shape, and many stammering 
tongues were cut loose. Men who had only thought, 
now began to speak and act. But the activity and zeal 
were not all on one side.</p> 

<p>In the month of March, 1818, the delegate from Missouri 
presented a petition from the people praying to be 
admitted into the Union as a State. It went to the appropriate 
committee, where it remained till the next session. 
Then followed a fierce and prolonged struggle. 
The admission of Missouri with a slave Constitution, 
after denying the prayer of Indiana, was a bold move. 
But the violation of the sacred ordinance of 1787, that 
aimed to preserve the western territory from the defiling
touch of slavery, was nothing less than a gigantic political 
crime.</p> 

<p>RESTRICTION OR EXTENSION<lb/> 
of slavery was now the battle-cry. Missouri was the 
storm-line; and the political sky was filled with portentous 
clouds. The struggle between the friends and 
enemies of slavery was long and bitter; but the end 
came at last, and Mr. Clay's famous compromise was 
adopted. The Missouri Legislature made a solemn 
agreement not to pass any act "by which any other
citizens of either of the States should be excluded from 
the enjoyment of the privileges and immunities to which 
they were entitled under the Constitution of the United 
States." Thus on the 27th of February, 1821, Missouri 
was admitted into the Union.</p>

<pb xml:id="p022" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.022"/>

<p>ANTI-SLAYERY SENTIMENT<lb/>
began to be felt; local societies were forming throughout 
the Northern States, and anti-slavery became a topic 
of discussion in colleges and lyceums. All this work 
was a preparation for a grand organization. The lonely 
voice of Benjamin Lundy had already been heard as
one crying in the wilderness. He had organized the 
press and platform for the cause of the slave; had enlisted 
woman in the work, and had put his worldly fortune 
upon the altar of the righteous cause.</p> 

<p>In the fulness of time came "William Lloyd Garrison. 
From obscurity, poverty, down from the wind-swept 
and snow-capped mountains of Vermont, he came into 
the great moral conflict. He threw down the gage of 
battle at the feet of the haughty Goliath of slavery. He organized a party; he founded a great journal; he 
converted the conservatism of New England; he 
attacked the Constitution and the pulpit, and brought not " peace, but a sword." His clarion call to battle 
startled the slave power from its security; and by his 
iron will, steady purpose, and unflagging zeal aroused 
the country as no one man had ever done before.</p>
 
<p>DIVERSIFIED METHODS<lb/> 
there were, but all of them aimed at the common enemy, 
led to the same end. Anti-slavery societies multiplied. 
The Garrisonian, Heterodox, Political Abolition, Economic, 
Aggressive, Colonization, Under-ground and

<pb xml:id="p023" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.023"/>

Free Soil parties enlisted in the cause of the slave. The 
slave power was correspondingly industrious. Southern 
legislatures enacted severer laws, and subjected their 
victims to a most rigorous state of bondage. Suspicion 
fell with merciless fury upon every Northern person 
who went into the slave States. An embargo was laid 
against Northern anti-slavery publications of every 
description; and Southern executive and legislative 
dignity was not lowered by offering rewards for antislavery 
books and heads. Books were written from 
both points of view; the pew became as deeply concerned 
as the change, and the pulpit began to imitate 
the platform.</p> 

<p>THE DRED SCOTT DECISION<lb/> 
added more fuel to the flame. Then the Burns rescue 
case, the struggle in Kansas, and last, but more than 
all else, the bold stroke of grand old John Brown at 
Harper's Ferry carried the Negroes' case on appeal from 
the court of reason to the court of war.</p>
 
<p>THE SLAVERY REBELLION<lb/> 
was begun by the South at Charleston, and ended by 
the North at Appomattox. You know the story of the 
Negroes' wrongs and trials in that memorable struggle.
I need not tell you how he was first counted on the 
outside, hunted down by Union troops, clubbed, shot, 
and burned in the North; first given a spade, then intrusted 
with a musket. He had to conquer the prejudice 
of the Union army; and then, upon $7.00 a month,&#8212; 

<pb xml:id="p024" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.024"/>

half pay,&#8212;defeat the skilled soldiery of the Southern 
Confederacy. He did this, and more; and history, not 
grudgingly but cheerfully, records, "The Colored Troops fought nobly."</p> 

<p>RECONSTRUCTION<lb/> 
followed the destruction wrought by the great military 
struggle. Homeless and nameless, penniless and friendless, 
four million freedmen stood alone under the open 
sky. No Egyptians were there from whom to borrow 
finger-rings and jewelry; no sandals, no staff in hand, 
no wise leadership, no pillar of cloud by day and fire 
by night. There they stood; and their faith in God 
and the government of the United States flickered 
through the dark mists of uncertainty; and they did 
not faint. Upon this inexperienced people grave 
responsibilities were placed; and, taking all their disadvantages 
under consideration, they did better than might
have been expected. We will not subject their work 
to a critical test, but after twenty-two years of freedom 
let us recount the progress they have made.</p> 

<p>There were 271,421 Negroes in the United States 
army during the war for the Union, and they participated 
in 249 battles. In the Freedmen's Savings Bank 
and in other banks, from 1866 to 1873, the Negroes of the 
country deposited $53,000,000. There have been seven lieutenant-governors, four secretaries of state, three 
State auditors, two State treasurers, two United States 
senators, fifteen members of the United States House 
of Representatives, one register of the United States

<pb xml:id="p025" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.025"/>

treasury, and one collector of taxes, one United States 
marshal, one recorder of deeds in the District of 
Columbia; nine Negroes have served in the diplomatic 
service, and there are at present 620 in the departments at 
Washington. There are 14,889 schools for Negroes,
with 720,853 pupils in them. This was the result in 
1880, and now, in 1884, we may safely add a quarter 
of a million more pupils. There are also 188 Colored 
students in the junior and senior classes of colleges in 
the Northern States, and thousands of Colored children 
in the common schools of the North.</p> 

<p>THE CIVIL RIGHTS<lb/> 
of the Colored people have been overthrown by a recent 
decision of the United States Supreme Court, followed by 
a disastrous moral eifect at the South. The Civil Rights 
Bill was the crowning act in the life of our devoted 
friend, the late Charles Sumner. It was the offspring 
of a rare scholarship, broad statesmanship, and peerless 
philanthropy. The bill was subjected to the severest 
scrutiny and criticism by its friends and enemies; and, 
after passing through the fires of debate, it became 
the law of the land. After remaining in force for 
nearly a decade, the United States Supreme Court was 
called to pass upon its constitutionality. The Court, 
with but one noble exception,&#8212;Justice Harlan,&#8212;decided
that the bill was unconstitutional. In the Dred 
Scott case, Judge Taney gave the decision of the 
Court, Justice McLean dissenting, upon the question 
of the citizenship of a Negro under the Constitution. 

<pb xml:id="p026" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.026"/>

He admitted that the words negro, slave, 
and colored person did not appear in the Constitution; 
but maintained that it was the duty of the 
Court to consider the intention of the framers of 
the Constitution; that the word person was intended to 
be construed as meaning slave, and, that, therefore, 
Dred Scott being a Negro, was not a citizen, but a 
slave. If Judge Taney, as Chief Justice, under a Democratic
administration, could interpret the Constitution 
liberally in the interest of slavery, it ought not to have 
been a difficult matter for Judge Waite, Chief Justice 
under a Republican administration, to interpret the Constitution
liberally in the interest of freedom. We had 
fought four years and one half to destroy slavery; we 
had made 500,000 graves; we had <sic>mained</sic> 300,000 men; 
we had expended $3,000,000,000; we had emancipated
4,500,000 human beings. In the light of these facts it 
was clear to be seen that civil rights were but the incidents 
of freedom, and followed as naturally as heat 
does light or the rising of the sun. A liberal interpretation 
of this law would have been in line and in harmony 
with the great civilization of the nineteenth 
century. Kot only the Supreme Court, but political 
parties have turned to abstractions rather than to the 
great questions of humanity. Materialism reigns everywhere.</p> 

<p>THE NEGROES' PAST<lb/>
political action was the irresistible logic of gratitude. 
He entered the ranks of his political friends. He voted 

<pb xml:id="p027" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.027"/>

as he had fought, for the Union. Any other political 
action would have earned the execrations of God and 
man. Moreover, the Negro's ballot was as indispensable 
to the successful work of reconstruction as the 
Negro's bullet was to the successful prosecution of the 
war. The ex-rebels were sullen and intractable during 
the entire period of reconstruction. Some of them went 
off to Mexico, Brazil, England, and Egypt; others remained 
in a state of inertia; while a very small minority 
accepted the situation like men, and put their energies 
into the work of reconstruction. The carpet-bagger, 
scallawag, and Negro had control of the Southern 
States. These were not the most desirable forces to 
effect so great a work; but they were to be preferred to 
traitors. The failure of reconstruction must be charged 
to Congress, and to the educated native white men of 
the South. Congress could have enacted wiser laws, 
and the white men of the South could have secured 
better government there, by methods of prudence and humanity.</p>

<p>THE POLITICAL FIDELITY<lb/> 
of the Negro is the marvel of all political history. He 
stood by his friends through evil and through good 
report. And when the white Republicans had been 
reduced to a mere corporal's guard, the Negro remained 
loyal to his party. In fact he was more faithful than his 
friends. For his fidelity he was rewarded by being 
deserted by his friends and by being shot by his enemies. 
Thousands upon thousands of brave black Republicans 

<pb xml:id="p028" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.028"/>

were murdered for political opinion's sake; and political 
suffrage in the South has had a name to live, but is dead.</p>
 
<p>GEN. GRANT<lb/> 
owed his election in 1868 and in 1872 to the patriotic 
fidelity of the Negro voters of the South. And when 
the destiny of the Republican party and nation was in 
the hands of the Negro members of the returning boards 
of Mississippi, Louisiana, and Florida, in 1876, it was 
secure beyond all temptation. Rather than betray their 
friends those Negroes chose to go to prison on bread and 
water. Several fortunes were at their disposal if they 
would only consent to alter the returns, but they indignantly 
declined the bribe. They could neither be bought 
nor bullied. They were good men and true. And, 
opposite their fidelity, a bargain was consummated between 
their friends and enemies by which, when the 
President the Negroes had made should be inaugurated,
the three doubtful States should pass to the control of 
red-shirt and white-line leagues. The conspiracy 
triumphed, and the Negroes who saved the Republican 
party in 1876 were disfranchised, and are exiles in this 
free Republic until this day.</p> 

<p>RUTHERFORD B. HAYES<lb/> 
is not alone to blame for this crime against truth, virtue, 
and fidelity. The Northern press, and a one-eyed, narrow, 
prejudiced public sentiment made the crime possible. 
The liberal movement of 1872 broke the confidence 

<pb xml:id="p029" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.029"/>

of the North in the Southern Negro, and the great 
financial panic of 1873 stifled the voice of compassion, 
and palsied the helping hand that was extended to aid 
the persecuted blacks. A deaf ear was turned to all 
stories of Southern outi'age, and materialism congealed 
the feelings of humanity, and the poor Negro went down 
to inhospitable and bloody political graves before the 
white-line banners, upon which was inscribed the 
motto, "We must carry these States: peaceably, if we 
can; forcibly, if we must."</p>
 
<p>JAMES A. GARFIELD<lb/> 
owed his election to the Presidency to the clannishness 
of the Negro vote of the North. The Negro vote in the 
following Northern States in 1880 was as follows:&#8212;</p>
 
<table>
<row>
<cell>Connecticut</cell>
<cell>11,547</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Illinois</cell>
<cell>46,368</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Indiana</cell>
<cell>39,228</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Kansas</cell>
<cell>43,107</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Massachusetts</cell>
<cell>18,697</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Michigan</cell>
<cell>15,100</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>New Jersey</cell>
<cell>65,104</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>New York</cell>
<cell>531,277</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ohio</cell>
<cell>79,900</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Pennsylvania</cell>
<cell>85,535</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell>
<cell>935,843</cell>
</row>
</table>  
    
<pb xml:id="p030" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.030"/>    
   
<p>We have only taken the Northern States where the 
Colored people are in largest numbers. So we have 
nearly one million of them in ten States. We have at 
least three hundred thousand Negro votes in these 
States. Had the Negro vote of Ohio been thrown for 
Gen. Hancock, Garfield would have lost his own State; 
and the Negro vote of Indiana and New York could 
have given Gen. Hancock an overwhelming majority 
in the Electoral College. The loyal Negro elected the 
last President.</p> 

<p>A SOLID SOUTH<lb/> 
is a fact. It will stand in the face of Northern sentiment 
and refuse to be broken. The next Presidential 
candidate of the Republican party must carry a 
solid North, or suffer defeat. But it is said by 
some that the Negro question is settled; that the 
North is weary of it; that the Negro goes from 
the South to the national convention, insists upon 
the nomination of a candidate, towards whose selection 
by the Electoral College he can contribute no aid; 
that we must have other issues than the Negro question, 
tariff, civil service, internal improvements, etc. 
If this be true, and if this is to be the policy of the Republican
party, the Negro says, Amen! If civil-service 
reform is of more importance than human liberty, let 
the party abandon the Negro. Then what has the party 
to say of the Negro's abandonment of Republicanism? 
It is a poor rule that does not work both ways. 
The Republican party voluntarily assumed the task of emancipating 

<pb xml:id="p031" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.031"/> 

the Negro; it followed up this great and good 
work by making him a soldier, a citizen, a voter, and 
an office-holder. Is the work of the party ended? Is 
its mission completed? Oh, no. fellow-citizens! not 
until the humblest, blackest citizen in all the land shall 
be amply protected in the constitutional exercise of the 
political rights conferred upon him by the Constitution 
of these United States! To stop short of this would 
be cowardice; to close its otherwise glorious career
without making free citizenship as broad as the continent, 
would be to go down to history as an inglorious
failure. The Republican party cannot afford to surrender 
its magnificent history and splendid possibilities to 
the shot-gun policy of the South. It cannot afford to 
say to civilized Europe, "We made the Negro a freeman 
and a citizen; he helped us win glorious victories in war 
and in politics, but now we cannot defend our defenders!"</p>

<p>THE NATION POWERLESS<lb/>
to protect its citizens? It is a libel upon our free 
government to offer such a miserable apology for its 
stolid indifference to murder and arson. Under the 
internal revenue laws the government requires a tax 
on every gallon of distilled spirits. If any manufacturer 
refuses to pay the tax, or attempts to evade the 
law, he is taken in hand. If he resists, he is shot. 
Nobody complains, and the government goes on. A 
loyal human life ought to be equal in value to a 
gallon of whiskey! The men who formed the Constitution

<pb xml:id="p032" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.032"/>

reserved the right to the people to change
it whenever their interests required it. The creator
is greater than the creature; the people are more 
important than the Constitution! If there is no 
power in the Constitution by which the people at the 
South can be protected, then let the Republican party
recast the Constitution; and let it be made a shield of 
burnished steel, large enough, strong enough, to protect 
every citizen, East and West, North and South, black 
and white, Democrat and Republican, from the golden 
shores of the Pacific to the pearly coast of the Atlantic. 
This can be done; this must be done.</p>

<p>PUBLIC SENTIMENT<lb/>
annoys many of our statesmen. They would be perfectly 
willing to do more for the Negro if it were not for 
public sentiment. When the statesmen in Athens 
were asked why they desired to banish Aristides, 
they replied that they were weary hearing of Aristides
the Just, and desired to get rid of him. 
A shell was handed to Aristides in the streets of 
Athens by a citizen who did not know him. He
was asked to cast his vote to banish Aristides. He
wrote his own name on the shell without asking a question,
and passed on. Is the Republican party weary 
hearing about the Negro? and would it have him consent 
to be abandoned, and pass on as a political exile 
and orphan? The party must speak at Chicago, and
the North must answer our question at the November

<pb xml:id="p033" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.033"/>

ballot-box. Do we ask too much? Verily not. All 
we ask is that party platforms, promises, and resolves 
may be translated into honest action and hearty fulfilment. 
We ask that our persons, property, families, and 
lives may be defended from assassins and bulldozers; 
that our labor may have its just compensation; that 
justice may not tip the scales in favor of our enemies; 
that public inns, common-carrier companies, workshops, 
and schools may be open to us, as they are to 
the white race; and that we may be permitted to cast 
an honest ballot, have it fairly counted, and receive a 
truthful declaration of the count. Could we ask 
less? Would the country have us ask less? By our 
adherence to the Republican party we have drawn the 
fire and intensified the malice of our enemies. And 
now if we cannot be protected by the party we have 
served, self-preservation, the first law of nature, 
demands us to save ourselves at all hazards. For this 
salvation we must organize, remembering that eternal 
vigilance is the price of liberty.</p>

<p>REVENGE<lb/>
has been suggested by some madcaps. God forbid!
We are but a handful in this country, and we must not 
destroy our reputation for gentleness. The Negro has 
taught the world the gospel of forgiveness. Seven million 
Negroes may not hope to strike at forty-three million 
whites. Copiah and Danville first sicken the heart; 
then horrify, then madden us. They will be thoroughly 
investigated. Republican orators will ring the changes

<pb xml:id="p034" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.034"/>

on them until after election, and the government will 
do&#8212;nothing, simply nothing.</p>

<p>"Not mine sedition's trumpet blast<lb/>
And threatening word;<lb/>
I read the lesson of the past,<lb/>
That firm endurance wins at last<lb/>
More than the sword.</p>

<p>"O clear-eyed Faith and Patience, thou<lb/>
So calm and strong,<lb/>
Lend strength to weakness; teach us how<lb/>
The sleepless eyes of God look through<lb/>
This night of wrong."</p>

<p>EMIGRATION
has virtue in the judgment of some of our discouraged 
and gloomy brethren. This is an error of judgment. 
America is the theatre of the Negro's noblest acts. 
The graves of his ancestry are here. He was married 
and was given in marriage here. His children were born 
here; and, while undergoing the crucial test of manhood 
and citizenship, he can not afford to withdraw.</p>

<p>This is our own, our native land,<lb/>
and under American institutions we are to demonstrate 
our claims to manhood, and our fitness for the duties 
of citizenship.</p>

<p>THE MORAL PHASE<lb/>
of the Negro question is worthy of profound study.
We have not the time to examine the ethics of the antislavery 

<pb xml:id="p035" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.035"/>

slavery movement, but venture the statement that the 
American people owe much of their moral breadth to 
the Negro question. The Negro problem was the other 
side of American materialism. The leading men of 
the last century obtained their greatness in the struggle
the Colonies passed through. The constant dwelling 
upon the questions of personal rights made them moral 
giants; and all the marked men of the present century 
owe their greatness to the Negro problem. It was 
natural that a young nation in a new country would be 
given over to materialism. The obstructions across the 
path of its physical advancement were numerous and 
stubborn. The bread-winner in such a country and 
nation would not be humane as a rule. <sic>Invironment</sic> 
is a profound factor in the problem of civilization. 
Constant contact with the rougher phases of nature 
makes men correspondingly rough. The humanity 
and social life of young colonies in new countries 
are scarcely ever of a high order. But some injured 
right of humanity crying aloud for redress keeps 
the moral senses of society from slumbering, and holds 
the affections in healthful tension. Fortunate, indeed, 
for the permanent fame of the American nation, that 
the Negro problem has been ever before them. The 
poor Negro saved America from the grossest materialism,
and furnished the condition for the production of 
her ablest men. The great French preacher, Fénelon 
began his eulogy over the body of the dead king of 
France by exclaiming, "God only is great!" And there 
is, certainly, no earthly greatness but goodness. The

<pb xml:id="p036" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.036"/>

greatness of the foremost Americans of the nineteenth 
century was distilled through the tears and bloody 
sweat of the Negro slave; and every ray of lasting 
glory that rests upon the brow of the Republic was
born in the deepest vale of the slave's degradation. 
The republic of letters owes the Negro a debt of 
gratitude. Poetry and prose, history and biography,
have gleaned in this field; and fiction, approaching
with tardy step, will yet be blessed with a rich store of 
fact and fancy unequalled in the world's history.</p>

<p>If there had been no Negro slavery there would
have been no anti-slavery agitation; and having no
anti-slavery agitation, we could have had no Lundy, no
Garrison, no Phillips no Sumner, no Stevens, no Lincoln. 
And there being no contest between slavery and 
freedom, there would have been no rebellion; and, 
hence, Grant and Thomas, Sheridan and McPherson, 
would have been as obscure as South Sea Islanders. 
The fame of Lincoln rests upon the Emancipation edict; 
the fame of Sumner rests upon his two great speeches, 
The Barbarism of Slavery, The Crime against Kansas, 
and his Civil Rights Bill. The only Americans 
immortal in history are those who emptied themselves 
for humanity. Other men have striven to make a place 
in history, but as in the zoölogical classification of animals,
so they will find their proper group. By their 
works ye shall know them.</p>

<pb xml:id="p037" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.037"/>

<p>THE BLAIR EDUCATIONAL BILL<lb/>
is the grandest measure of our times. It is broad, comprehensive,
and beneficent. It is a prophecy of better 
things to come; and a pledge that this country is not to 
be Europeanized or turned over to native ignorance, 
and the nihilism of Russia, the communism of France, 
the socialism of Germany. What we want is more 
light in America. The electric light in the streets of
Washington is more than your police force. Light in 
this country is more than our army, stretching from 
Lake Itasca to where the Mississippi mingles his golden 
thread in the deep blue of the Gulf of Mexico; more 
than our navy, overshadowing the ocean.</p>

<p>"THE NEW SOUTH,"<lb/>
as Gen. James B. Gordon puts it, must aid this work. 
A happy solution of the Negro problem can be speedily 
reached the white people of the South will take an 
interest in this question. Three things must be done by 
the white people there, viz., the chain-gang system 
should be abolished; the iniquitous, cheating plantation 
credit system should be abandoned; and every 
child, white and black, should be sent to school for at
least seven months in every year.</p>

<p>The Negro thirsting for knowledge, and should be
Some years before the war, an artist of Philadelphia
was secured by the State of South Carolina to 
paint some national emblematic picture for her State

<pb xml:id="p038" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.038"/>

House. Jefferson Davis was invited to act with 
the South Carolina committee at Washington, in criticising 
the studies of this work. The most creditable sketch 
presented was a design representing the North by 
various mechanical implements; the West by a prairie 
and plough; while the South was represented by various 
things, the centre-piece, however, being a cotton-bale 
with a Negro upon it fast asleep. When Mr. Davis 
saw he said, "Gentlemen, this will never do; what 
will become of the South when the Negro wakes up?"</p>

<p>THE SOUTHERN REBELLION<lb/>
startled the Negro; the reconstruction struggle brought
him to his feet; he has yawned, and, to-day, with open 
eyes, he manfully looking the serious questions of
life squarely in the face. He learning the practical 
lessons of life with ease and thoroughness; and all he
requires is kind treatment and fair dealing from the 
whites, and no people in the country will more heartily 
rejoice that he was aroused from his slumbers than the
Southern people themselves.</p>

<p>THE VALLEY OF THE CONGO,<lb/>
in Africa, attracting intelligent attention. Every
in the United States should have an honest 
pride in the African question. Africa yet going to 
pay this nation dollar for dollar of the three billions 
spent in prosecuting the war; and America going to 
compensate Africa for stealing her children by placing

<pb xml:id="p039" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.039"/>

the means of civilization in her waiting and willing 
hands. Thanks to his Excellency President Arthur 
for his message on the Congo, and loud huzzas for the 
United States Senate for recognizing the International 
African Association. Africa is sure to be the scene of 
the world's greatest civilization. She will be quickened
in every nerve and fibre by the power of commerce; 
and Christian civilization will give tone to her sluggish
moral pulse. Africa will be regenerated; tribes will 
be converted; states will be founded; arts and letters 
will flourish ; peace will reign in her mountains and smile 
in her valleys; ships and cables, journals and literature, 
science and discovery, will bind her to the civilized 
world in bonds of eternal friendship.</p>

<p>NEW LEADERS<lb/>
for the Negro race are needed. Not the time-serving
lickspittle, not the self-seeking parasite, not the obsequious, 
cringing go-between, not swaggering insolence 
or skulking cowardice in leadership, nor any man who 
is either ashamed of being, or mean enough to deny that 
he is, a Negro. We want, we demand leaders, first of 
all, who are not ashamed of the race; who are possessed 
of brains, character, courage, zeal, and tact. We want 
leaders who know the history of the race's trials, struggles, 
and achievements; and who can, from that history, 
draw inspiration for the great work to be accomplished. 
We demand leaders who are the friends of mechanical 
education for the rising young men; and who are pledged

<pb xml:id="p040" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.040"/>

to a system of thorough education for our young women. 
We demand leaders who will neither touch, taste, nor 
handle, nor put to their neighbors' lips, in private 
or public, at home or abroad, on land or sea, the accursed 
cup of drink. Men they must be of noble instincts and 
generous impulses; who have a genius for hard, self-sacrificing 
labor to build up the race. Such leaders will 
have the skill to detect the condition of our people, and 
the genius and heroism to lead the way to the heart of 
the race's moral need. God grant that such men may 
be forthcoming.</p>

<p>MORAL EMANCIPATION<lb/>
is what we most need now. Many salutary lessons are 
taught us by the bitter past. Let us lay them to 
heart, and, taking fresh courage, turn to the great 
work that awaits us on every hand. All that remains 
of this tempestuous state of things is but the rocking of 
a troubled sea to rest. For He whose chariot the winds 
are, and the clouds, the dust that waits upon His sultry 
march shall visit us in mercy; shall descend propitious 
in His chariot, paved with love.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>