<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0281">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Henry May to William H. Seward, September 31, 1863</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0281</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Henry May to William H. Seward, September 31, 1863</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gaboon, 1856-1888 T-466</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-466, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1863-09-31">September 31, 1863</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>



<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>May, Henry</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul</roleName>
<placeName>Gaboon</placeName>
<date when="1863-09-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Seward, William H.</persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>
<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">
    
<pb facs="20170615_111239"/>

<p>United States Comml Agency<lb/>
at Gaboon River Sept 30th 1863</p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I would beg to offer you the following 
information. The trade in this river is free 
to all vessels of every country. No tonnage
duties or other port dues. No vessel however is 
allowed to proceed more than fifteen miles up the 
river without a special permit from the authorities.
This permit has not been granted to any vessels
visiting the river since my arrival. The 
Captain of every vessel must deposit his ships
papers. With the commandant of the "Guard Ship"
immediately upon his arrival and report himself 
to the Commandant on shore presenting a manifest 
of the ships cargo and passenger list. No passenger
is <sic>permited</sic> to land without permission. The 
Captain must give twenty four hours notice in 
order to obtain his discharge and receive no papers.</p>

<p>The trade upon this part of the African
coast is increasing. The amount of 
rubber shipped from the Gaboon, Mooney and 
Moondah river for the present year greatly 
<catchwords>exceeds</catchwords>

<pb facs="20170615_111245"/>

that of any former year. The rubber mostly goes 
to England costing here about six cents per pound.
The amount of Ivory exported from 
this place and sicenety is about the same as it
was twenty years ago. The price is much higher 
Ivory coasts here from fifty to one hundred and 
fifty its her prunel according to the quality 
most of this reduction give through England
to the Continents. 

<p></p>The amount of Bai Wood id equal
to the demand though it is becoming scared 
upon the banks of the River. The principal supply 
being percured some distance up the River and 
into the interior. Most of this eventually reaches 
France through a great proposition is shipped 
in Engish vessels. Bai-Wood cost here about 
four hundred and fifty to per ton.

<p></p>It is exceeding difficult, to obtain any reliable
information in regard to the recources of the interior
jealousies which exist between different duties. From
the best information which I can gather in *ordu to secure 
the milk from which it is made destroy the vine.
The French aree extending this possessions upon 
this Coast having recently purchased the River

river

<pb facs="20170615_111251"

<p></p>and country of Bonny Payeng a large drum 
to the native "King" (Peppell"). They have 
latern possession of the Congo at least the 
north bank of it and also of Cape Lopey,
the latter is a few miles to the South of this 
river. They have to the Rivero money and 
Mondah. Which aew situatue about fifty 
miles to the birth of this place emptying theur 
maters into Cousco bay.

<ab></ab>I have no arrivals or 
olehartures of American vessels to report 
during the last six months.

With the highest consideration I 
have the honor to be your most 
humble and obedient servant 
Henry May U.S. Comml. Agt
at Gaboon W. Africa 

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
