<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0279">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- DOCUMENT TITLE + DATE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Etienne to Under Secretary of State, August 14, 1889 --></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0278</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Roncière Lenour to Mister Director of the Colonies--></title>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 226, Liasse 167</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PEOPLE NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PLACES NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT FROM --></placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT TO --></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-30" who="kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0279.001.jpg"/>

<p>Consulat Général
de 
L’État Indépendant Du Congo,
Baltimore.</p>
    
<p>le 7 septembre 1908.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Chevalier,</p>
 
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous faire parvenir sous ce pli le
rapport du Consul Général Américain à Boma sur la possibilité de fonder
une société anonyme pour le développement du commerce entre le Congo et
les Etats-Unis.</p>
    
<p>S'il y a une disposition parmi les industriels americains à donner suite
à cette idée du Consul Général Américain je ne manquerai pas à vous en
donner des nouvelles. Le cas echéant je tâcherai à mettre à la
tête de l'entreprise des individus compétents et amicales qui pourraient
être utiles au Congo au lieu d'être nuisibles.</p>
 
<p>Il est intéressant à remarquer que le Consul Général Américain n'est 
point d'avis des conglophobes anglais au sujet de l'introduction de la
monnaie au Congo. Il dit (page 11) que la plupart des indigenes ignorent
la valeur et l'utilité de la monnaie et qu'on ne peut pas l'introduire
incessamment.</p>
    
<p>Veuillez agréer, Monsieur le Chevalier, l'assurance de ma consideration
la plus distinguée.</p>
    
<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>

<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Chevalier de Cuvelier
Bruxelles.</fw>
    
</div1>  

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">  

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0279.002.jpg"/>

<p>Daily Consular and Trade Reports.</p>

<p>Kongo Commercial Opportunities.</p>
    
<p>Future of the Heart of Africa&#8212;How Americans May Participate.</p>
 
<p>In view of the fact that the status of the Kongo Free State is now
more definitely arranged and that its development is commencing,
Consul-General James A. Smith, of Boma, has prepared the following
review of the commercial aspects, and how Americans may best
secure business in that vast region of mid-Africa with 900,000 square
miles of undeveloped territory:</p>
    
<p>The Kongo may soon offer an opportunity for every independent
trader to traffic freely with the natives in the rich commercial products 
of the country, consisting mainly at present of rubber, ivory,
gum copal, palm kernels, and palm oil, the two latter being principally
products of the lower Kongo. Under such circumstances it 
appears important that the American manufacturer should be informed,
so far as is possible at present, of the opportunities which
will be found here to dispose of his goods and the best manner in 
which he can obtain a foothold, and to have clearly pointed out some 
of the difficulties he must encounter and overcome if American trade
in the Kongo is to increase.</p>

<p>Class of Goods At Present Imported.</p>
    
<p>Importations into the Kongo average at present, in round numbers,
$4,000,000 annually. Of these principal items, comprising, as
will be noted, about 88 per cent of the total, are as follows:</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Arms and ammunition</cell>
<cell>$178,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Clothing</cell>
<cell>251,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Food products, mostly canned meats, vegetables, etc</cell>
<cell>782,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Hardware, enameled iron ware, etc.</cell>
<cell>156,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Liquors, including beer</cell>
<cell>336,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Machinery</cell>
<cell>208,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Metals</cell>
<cell>212,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Steamers, boats, and material for</cell>
<cell>278,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tissues, mostly cotton piece goods</cell>
<cell>1,146,000</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell>
<cell>3,547,000</cell>
</row>
</table>    
    
<p>So far as the natives are concerned, who are the most important
to consider because the bulk of the furniture trade will be carried on
with them, the items of the greatest interest to the American manufacturer
in the foregoing list are, in the order of their value, cotton
piece goods, bleached and unbleached, prints and dyes; food products,
consisting for the greater part of canned meats and vegetables,
largely consumed, it is true, by the white population at present, but
for which a demand can be created among the natives; clothing; the
bulk of which is cheap underclothing, shirts, shoes, hats, and caps;
hardware, of which an important part is enameled iron ware, plates,
basins, various kitchen utensils, etc.</p>
    
<p>The remainder of the articles are for the larger part imported for
use in building and opening up the country for the whites, construction 
and maintenance of railways, steamer lines, etc. The sale of alcoholic
liquors to natives in the upper Kongo is forbidden by law.</p>
    
<p>Practical Method to Secure Trade.</p>
    
<p>The question of methods to secure trade must be regarded from the
standpoint of the interest of the American manufacturer and not of
the individual small trader. There is but one practical way for the 
American manufacturer to secure and retain a foothold in this market,
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0279.003.jpg"/>

which promises results materially increasing American foreign trade
here and which will eventually make the venture worth while. It is
not likely that American goods will ever reach this market to any
large extent except directly through an American company located
here. Every trading house already established in the lower Kongo&#8212;
English, French, German, Dutch, Portuguese, or Belgian&#8212;is interested,
primarily, in pushing the sale of the goods of its own nation.
The large concessionary companies are all Belgian, they purchase the
greater part of their supplies in Belgium, and their barter goods are
mostly Belgian. As a Belgian colony, the future administration will
be interested first of all in encouraging and broadening the market
for Belgian manufactures.</p>

<p>Geographical position and direct lines of steamers from almost all
the countries named are other important factors favorable to their
trade development here. For these reasons, I believe, there is but one
practical and efficient way by which we can succeed in gaining a firm 
foothold here&#8212;namely, through the organization of an American
trading house composed preferably of a combination of various 
American manufacturers of or dealers in the different lines of merchandise
it is found profitable to handle, and interested therefore
before all in introducing and pushing exclusively American goods.
A number of general stores should be established in favorable localities,
with a central distributing warehouse and store at Leopoldville.</p>

<p>Distribution of Supplies&#8212;Competent Salesmen.</p>

<p>The company should own and operate its own steamer of steamers
on the upper river for the transport of its goods and distribution to
the various stores established, as well as the carrying to Leopoldville
of the merchandise received in exchange-rubber, ivory, etc. The
network of navigable waterways furnishes the most convenient
means of communication at present, but freight rates on the steamers
belonging to the State are high and porterage "a dos d'homme" is
slow and uncertain and must eventually be done away with entirely.</p>

<p>A thoroughly efficient and practical business man should be sent
out to study the general situation, the wants of the natives, manner 
of packing goods for tropical countries, etc., and decide as to the 
most favorable localities for the establishment of the stores. The
preliminary work would doubtless require fully a year's time. Cotton 
piece goods will form the principal article of commerce at first, but
it would be unwise for the company to confine itself to any one line.
Through contact with the whites the material wants of the natives 
will gradually increase, and the company must be prepared to supply
these wants in every direction.</p>

<p>Difficulties To Overcome.</p>

<p>In the absence of money as a circulation medium of trade, and the
entire ignorance of the greater part of the natives in the upper
Kongo as to its value of use, the trade in the beginning will be simply
a question of barter. For this reason, perhaps, the greatest difficulty 
which a trading house will meet with at first will be to persuade the
native to bring in his produce in exchange for goods offered. Some
time must necessarily elapse and a constantly humane, just, and gen-

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0279.004.jpg"/>

erous treatment invariably accorded to the native before he will begin
to realize the material advantages to be gained by himself in trading
with the white man. Once he is certain of this the most difficult
obstacle to trade will have been overcome.</p>

<p>An American house without experience in Africa will have to compete
with English, French, German, Dutch, Portuguese, and Belgian
companies and in the eastern districts with Indian and Arab traders,
many of them long standing in the lower Kongo, familiar with 
the country and the ways of the natives, speaking og the commercial
language, etc. Many of these traders will doubtless enlarge the field
of their operations in the upper Kongo. The Germans are already
preparing for the opening up on the country to trade, as I learn that
a German house at Matadi, backed by official encouragement, is to
place a steamer at once on the upper river and commence operations
by selling goods along the river direct from the steamer in exchange
for ivory.</p>

<p>Another difficulty is the absence of direct lines of transportation.
American sailing ships already, I believe, come to the Sierra Leone and 
the West Coast with cotton good and petroleum, and their itinerary
might, it would seem, be extended to the lower Kongo. </p>

<p>General Observation.</p>

<p>In the development of the country the native must necessarily play
an important part. His labor is absolutely essential to the future
welfare of the colony, and he will be the principal purchaser of 
foreign goods. In a colony of at least 20,000,000 blacks, who will be
brought, as the country is opened up, more and more into constant
contact with white civilization, and whose material wants will in
consequence continually increase, the future market will be one of 
constant growth and practically unlimited extent. If the United
States is to share in this market in any appreciable measure the
present is the time to make a beginning. It is the man who is the 
first on the ground who will have the advantage in an experience
gained in dealing with the native, and who will consequently secure
the larger and more profitable share in the trade. The difficulties
do not appear by any means insurmountable. Enterprise directed
intelligently, patience, and tenacity are required here as everywhere
else to secure and hold a market against active competition.</p>

<p>The opportunity is a grand one and should not be neglected. A
consular officer can do no more than point this out. It remains for
American manufacturers to take advantage of the situation and
make a beginning here at the earliest possible moment. Details as
to prices of cotton piece goods, etc., can not be given because, 
dependent as they are upon the cost of transport, they vary widely in 
different sections and have been, up to the present time,  more of less
arbitrary.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0279.001.jpg"/>
        
<p>Consulate General 
of 
The Independent State of the Congo,
Baltimore.</p>
        
<p>7 September 1908.</p>
        
<p>Monsieur le Chevalier,</p>
        
<p>I have the honor to transmit, herewith, the
report from the American Consul General in Boma on the possibility of founding 
an anonymous society for the development of commerce between the Congo and the 
United States.</p>
        
<p>If there is a arrangement amongst the American manufacturers to follow
this idea from the American Consul General I will not miss 
giving you the news. If need be I will try to put at the 
head of the company the competent and amicable individuals who could 
be useful in the Congo in stead of being harmful.</p>
        
<p>It's interesting to see that the American Consul General is of no 
opinion of the English Conglophobes about the introduction of the 
currency in the Congo. He says (page 11) that the majority of the natives ignore 
the value and the usefulness of the currency and that one cannot introduce it
shortly.</p>
        
<p>Please accept, Mr. le Chevalier, the assurance of my most 
distinguished consideration.</p>
        
<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>
        
<p>Mr. Chevalier de Cuvelier 
Brussels.</p>
            
</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
