<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0238">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from Horace Tufts, et al, September 1857</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0238</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to "To Enter Africa from America", made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from Horace Tufts, et al, September 1857</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1857-09">September 1857</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>



<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Tufts, Horace</persName>
<roleName>Master of the Bark Ida</roleName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date when="1857-09"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName></persName>
<roleName></roleName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw"> Encoding</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls"> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="30"/>

<opener>West Coast of Africa, Sierra Leone<lb/>
September 1854</opener>

<p>The Humble Memorial of the undersigned the commander of vesels belonging to citizens of the United States of America; Merchants: super cargoes traders and others citizens of America trading or residing on the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<ab>Humbly Sheweth, </ab>
<p>1 That we your memorialists have after much consideration on the subject matter of this petition come to the unanimous conclusion that it is our duty to the Government of which we are citizens to report the very unsatisfactory position in which the representation of the American Governement stands in the Colony of Sierra Leone.</p>

<p>2 That notwith standing the very important an extensive commerce between the United States and West Coast of Africa, and particularly with this Colony it is a singular fact that there has never been a Consul not event Consulate Agent appointed by the United States Government as its representation here.</p>

<p><catchwords>That</catchwords>

<pb facs="31"/>

3 That on the 11th of August 1853 Commander J Mayo of the United States Flag Ship "Constitution" having due regard to the interests of his Government was pleased to appoint Captain John Etting Taylor an American citizen and Merchant residing in ths Colony as acting Consul on the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>4 That such acting appointment has never been confirmed by the Government of the United States not legally recognized by the English Government.</p>

<p>5 That although the American Government has at at all times sanctioned those acts pertaining to the consulship, which have been performed by the acting Consul and bearing in mind the fact that the local authorities in the Sierra Leone have hitherto recognized Captain Taylor as acting Consul , yet we regard it as unsafe to permit matters to remain as they now are, inasmuch as it is in the power of the English Government whenever it may think proper to decline any further recognition of the authority of the preset acting Consul.</p>

<p>6 That your memorialists desire to bear testimony to the strict attention which the acting Consul has at all times paid to the requirements of the commanders of american vessels and American citzens generally on this

<pb facs="32"/>

 part of the Coast and to his sensitive regard for the dignity and honor of the Union.</p>

<p>Your memorialists therefore pray that the United States Government will be pleased to confer this appointment of Consul of the United States Government on this Coast on the present acting Consul. And your memorialists will ever pray so. </p>

<closer>Horace Tufts<lb/>
Master of the Bark Ida<lb/>

James Gains<lb/>
Master Brig. "Calvert"<lb/>
George Willar <lb/>
Master Barque Aaron T. Harvey<lb/>
John <unclear/> Master of the<lb/>
Honor Mitchell<lb/>
W.B.Wett M.D. of. Cincinnatti Ohio<lb/>
John H. Lanscomb Mass<lb/>
Charles H. Nelson Scho H N Gambill<lb/>
William E. Cousins Ship Tho Watson<lb/>
A.B Grindle<lb/>
Brig Enterprise of New York<lb/>
James Lord<lb/>
Master of Scho Jane P. Glover<lb/>
H P West, Master of Brig "Zorro"<lb/>
N. York</closer>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>




