<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Pauline E. Hopkins - Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self. (1902-1903)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0095</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>

<bibl n="1" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.001">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1902-11">November 1902</date>
<biblScope unit="page">29-40</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="2" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.002">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1902-11">December 1902</date>
<biblScope unit="page">102-113</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl n="3" corresp="teaa.en.periodical.0095.003">
<title level="a" type="main">Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self.</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482" n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1903-01">January 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">191-200</biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Fiction</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-12" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.001">

<pb facs="p29"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Chapter I.</p>

<p>The recitations were over for the day.
It was the first week in November and it
had rained about every day the entire
week; now freezing temperature added
to the discomforture of the dismal season.
The lingering equinoctial whirled the
last clinging yellow leaves from the trees
on the campus and strewed them over the

deserted paths, while from the leaden sky
fluttering snow-white flakes gave an unexpected 
touch of winter to the scene.</p>

<p>The east wind for which Boston and
vicinity is celebrated, drove the sleet
against the window panes of the room in
which Reuel Briggs sat among his books
and the apparatus for experiments. The
room served for both living and sleeping.
Briggs could have told you that the bare-

<pb facs="p30"/>

ness and desolateness of the apartment
were like his life, but he was a reticent
man who knew how to suffer in silence.
The dreary wet afternoon, the cheerless
walk over West Boston bridge through
the soaking streets had but served to
emphasize the loneliness of his position,
and morbid thoughts had haunted him all
day: To what use all this persistent hard
work for a place in the world&#8212;clothes,
food, a roof? Is suicide wrong? he asked
himself with tormenting persistency.
From out the storm, voices and hands
seemed beckoning him all day to cut the
Gordian knot and solve the riddle of
whence and whither for all time.</p>

<p>His place in the world would soon be
filled; no vacuum remained empty; the
eternal movement of all things onward
closed up the gaps, and the wail of the
newly-born augmented the great army of
mortals pressing the vitals of mother
Earth with hurrying tread. So he had
tormented himself for months, but the
courage was yet wanting for strength to
rend the veil. It had grown dark early.
Reuel had not stirred from his room since
coming from the hospital&#8212;had not eaten
nor drank, and was in full possession of
the solitude he craved. It was now five
o'clock. He sat sideways by the bare
table, one leg crossed over the other. His
fingers kept the book open at the page
where he was reading, but his attention
wandered beyond the leaden sky, the
dripping panes, and the sounds of the
driving storm outside.</p>

<p>He was thinking deeply of the words he
had just read, and which the darkness had
shut from his gaze. The book was called
"The Unclassified Residuum," just published 
and eagerly sought by students of
mysticism, and dealing with the great
field of new discoveries in psychology.
Briggs was a close student of what might
be termed "absurdities" of supernatural
phenomena or mysticism, best known to
the every-day world as "effects of the

imagination," a phrase of mere dismissal,
and which it is impossible to make precise; 
the book suited the man's mood.
These were the words of haunting significance:</p>

<p>"All the while, however, the phenomena 
are there, lying broadcast over the
surface of history. No matter where
you open its pages, you find things recorded 
under the name of divinations,
inspirations, demoniacal possessions, apparitions,
trances, ecstasies, miraculous
healing and productions of disease, and
occult powers possessed by peculiar individuals 
over persons and things in their
neighborhood.</p>

<p>"The mind-curers and Christian scientists, 
who are beginning to lift up their
heads in our communities, unquestionably
get remarkable results in certain cases.
The ordinary medical man dismisses
them from his attention with the
cut-and-dried remark that they are
'only the effects of the imagination.' But
there is a meaning in this vaguest of
phrases.</p>

<p>"We know a non-hysterical woman
who in her trances knows facts which
altogether transcend her <hi rend="italics">possible</hi> normal
consciousness, facts about the lives of
people whom she never saw or heard of
before. I am well aware of all the
liabilities to which this statement exposes
me, and I make it deliberately, having
practically no doubt whatever of its
truth."</p>

<p>Presently Briggs threw the book down,
and, rising from his chair, began pacing
up and down the bare room.</p>

<p>"That is it," at length he said aloud.
"I have the power, I know the truth of
every word&#8212;of all M. Binet asserts, and
could I but complete the necessary experiments, 
I would astonish the world.
O Poverty, Ostracism! have I not
drained the bitter cup to the dregs!" he
apostrophized, with a harsh, ironical
laugh.</p>

<pb facs="p31"/>

<p>Mother Nature had blessed Reuel
Briggs with superior physical endowments, 
but as yet he had never had reason 
to count them blessings. No one
could fail to notice the vast breadth of
shoulder, the strong throat that upheld
a plain face, the long limbs, the sinewy
hands. His head was that of an athlete,
with close-set ears, and covered with an
abundance of black hair, straight and
closely cut, thick and smooth; the nose
was the aristocratic feature, although
nearly spoiled by broad nostrils, of this
remarkable young man; his skin was
white, but of a tint suggesting olive, an
almost sallow color which is a mark of
strong, melancholic temperaments. His
large mouth concealed powerful long
white teeth which gleamed through lips
even and narrow, parting generally in a
smile at once grave, genial and singularly
sweet; indeed Briggs' smile changed
the plain face at once into one that interested 
and fascinated men and women.
True there were lines about the mouth
which betrayed a passionate, nervous
temperament, but they accorded well
with the rest of his strong personality.
His eyes were a very bright and piercing
gray, courageous, keen and shrewd.
Briggs was not a man to be despised
physically or mentally.</p>

<p>None of the students associated together 
in the hive of men under the fostering 
care of the benign mother knew
aught of Reuel Briggs's origin. It was
rumored at first that he was of Italian
birth, then they guessed he was a Japanese, 
but whatever land claimed him as
a son, all voted him a genius in his scientific
studies, and much was expected
of him at graduation. He had no money,
for he was unsocial and shabby to the
point of seediness, and apparently no relatives, 
for his correspondence was limited
to the letters of editors of well known local 
papers and magazines. Somehow he

lived and paid his way in a third-rate
lodging-house near Harvard square, at
the expense of the dull intellects or the
idle rich, with which a great university
always teems, to whom Briggs acted as
"coach," and by contributing scientific
articles to magazines on the absorbing
subject of spiritualistic phenomena. A
few of his articles had produced a pro
found impression. The monotonous
pacing continued for a time, finally ending 
at the mantel, from whence he abstracted 
a disreputable looking pipe and
filled it.</p>

<p>"Well," he soliloquized, as he reseated
himself in his chair, "Fate has done her
worst, but she mockingly beckons me on
and I accept her challenge. I shall not
yet attempt the bourne. If I conquer, it
will be by strength of brain and will-power. 
I shall conquer; I must and
will."</p>

<p>The storm had increased in violence;
the early dusk came swiftly down, and
at this point in his revery the rattling
window panes, as well as the whistle and
shriek of gusts of moaning wind, caught
his attention. "Phew! a beastly night."
With a shiver, he drew his chair closer to
the cylinder stove, whose glowing body
was the only cheerful object in the bare
room.</p>

<p>As he sat with his back half-turned to
catch the grateful warmth, he looked out
into the dim twilight across the square
and into the broad paths of the campus,
watching the skeleton arms of giant trees
tossing in the wind, and the dancing
snow-flakes that fluttered to earth in their
fairy gowns to be quickly transformed into 
running streams that fairly overflowed
the gutters. He fell into a dreamy state
as he gazed, for which he could not account. 
As he sent his earnest, penetrating 
gaze into the night, gradually the
darkness and storm faded into tints of
cream and rose and soft moist lips. 

<pb facs="p32"/>

Silhouetted against the background of lowering 
sky and waving branches, he saw
distinctly outlined a fair face framed in
golden hair, with soft brown eyes, deep
and earnest&#8212;terribly earnest they
seemed just then&#8212;rose-tinged baby lips,
and an expression of wistful entreaty. O
how real, how very real did the passing
shadow appear to the gazer!</p>

<p>He tried to move, uneasily conscious
that this strange experience was but "the
effect of the imagination," but he was
powerless. The unknown countenance
grew dimmer and farther off, floating
gradually out of sight, while a sense of
sadness and foreboding wrapped him
about as with a pall.</p>

<p>A wilder gust of wind shook the window 
sashes. Reuel stared about him in
a bewildered way like a man awakening
from a heavy sleep. He listened to the
wail of the blast and glanced at the fire
and rubbed his eyes. The vision was
gone; he was alone in the room; all was
silence and darkness. The ticking of the
cheap clock on the mantel kept time
with his heart-beats. The light of his
own life seemed suddenly eclipsed with
the passing of the lovely vision of Venus.
Conscious of an odd murmur in his
head, which seemed to control his movements, 
he rose and went toward the window 
to open it; there came a loud knock
at the door.</p>

<p>Briggs did not answer at once. He
wanted no company. Perhaps. the
knocker would go away. But he was
persistent. Again came the knock ending 
in a double rat-tat accompanied by
the words:</p>

<p>"I know you are there; open, open,
you son of Erebus! You inhospitable
Turk!"</p>

<p>Thus admonished Briggs turned the
key and threw wide open the door.</p>

<p>"It's you, is it? Confound you, you're
always here when you're not wanted,"
he growled.</p>

<p>The visitor entered and closed the
door behind him. With a laugh he stood
his dripping umbrella back of the stove
against the chimney-piece, and immediately 
a small stream began trickling
over the uncarpeted floor; he then relieved 
himself of his damp outer garments.</p>

<p>"Son of Erebus, indeed, you ungrateful 
man. It's as black as Hades in this
room; a light, a light! Why did you
keep me waiting out there like a
drowned rat?"</p>

<p>The voice was soft and musical.
Briggs lighted the student lamp. The
light revealed a tall man with the beautiful 
face of a Greek God; but the sculptured 
features did not inspire confidence.
There was that in the countenance of
Aubrey Livingston that engendered
doubt. But he had been kind to Briggs,
was, in fact, his only friend in the college,
or, indeed, in the world for that matter.</p>

<p>By an act of generosity he had helped
the forlorn youth, then in his freshman
year, over obstacles which bade fair to
end his college days. Although the
pecuniary obligation was long since paid,
the affection and worship Reuel had conceived 
for his deliverer was dog-like in
its devotion.</p>

<p>"Beastly night," he continued, as he
stretched his full length luxuriously in
the only easy chair the room afforded.
"What are you mooning about all alone
in the darkness?"</p>

<p>"Same old thing," replied Briggs
briefly.</p>

<p>"No wonder the men say that vou
have a twist, Reuel."</p>

<p>"Ah, man! but the problem of whence
and whither! To solve it is my life; I
live for that alone; let'm talk."</p>

<p>"You ought to be re-named the
'Science of Trance-States,' Reuel. How
a man can grind day and night beats
me." Livingston handed him a cigar
and for a time they smoked in silence.

<pb facs="p33"/>

At length Reuel said:</p>

<p>"Shake hands with Poverty once,
Aubrey, and you will solve the secret of
many a student's success in life."</p>

<p>"Doubtless it would do me good," replied
Livingston with a laugh, "but just
at present, it's the ladies, bless their
sweet faces who disturb me, and not
delving in books nor weeping over ways
and means. Shades of my fathers, forbid
that I should ever have to work!</p>

<p>"Lucky dog!" growled Reuel, enviously, 
as he gazed admiringly at the handsome 
face turned up to the ceiling and
gazing with soft caressing eyes at the
ugly whitewashed wall through rings of
curling smoke. "Yet you have a greater
gift of duality than I," he <sic>addded</sic> dreamily. 
"Say what you will; ridicule me, torment 
me, but you know as well as I that
the wonders of a material world cannot
approach those of the undiscovered
country within ourselves&#8212;the hidden self
lying quiescent in every human soul."</p>

<p>"True, Reuel, and I often wonder what
becomes of the mind and morals, distinctive 
entities grouped in the republic
known as man, when death comes. Good
and evil in me contend; which will gain
the mastery? Which will accompany me
into the silent land?"</p>

<p>"Good and evil, God and the devil,"
suggested Reuel. "Yes, sinner or saint,
body or soul, which wins in the life
struggle? I am not sure that it matters
which," he concluded with a shrug of his
handsome shoulders. "I should know if
I never saw you again until the struggle
was over. Your face will tell its own tale
in another five years. Now listen to
this:" He caught up the book he had
been reading and rapidly turning the
leaves read over the various passages
that had impressed him.</p>

<p>"A curious accumulation of data; the
writer evidently takes himself seriously,"
Livingston commented.</p>

<p>"And why not?" demanded Reuel.

"You and I know enough to credit the
author with honest intentions.</p>

<p>"Yes; but are we prepared to go so
far?"</p>

<p>"This man is himself a mystic.
gives his evidence clearly enough."</p>

<p>"And do you credit it?"</p>

<p>"Every word! Could I but get the
necessary subject, I would convince you;
I would go farther than M. Binet in unveiling 
the vast scheme of compensation
and retribution carried about in the vast
recesses of the human soul."</p>

<p>"Find the subject and I will find the
money," laughed Aubrey.</p>

<p>"Do you mean it, Aubrey? Will you
join me in carrying forward a search for
more light on the mysteries of
existence?"</p>

<p>"I mean it. And now, Reuel, come
down from the clouds, and come with me
to a concert."</p>

<p>"Tonight?"</p>

<p>"Yes, 'tonight,'" mimicked the other.
"The blacker the night, the greater the
need of amusement. You go out too
little."</p>

<p>"Who gives the concert?"</p>

<p>Well, it's a new departure in the
musical world; something Northerners
know nothing of; but I who am a
Southerner, born and bred, or as the vulgar 
have it, 'dyed in the wool,' know and
understand Negro music. It is a jubilee
concert given by a party of Southern
colored people at Tremont Temple. I
have the tickets. Redpath has them in 
charge."</p>

<p>"Well, if you say so, I suppose I must."
Briggs did not seem greatly impressed.</p>

<p>"Coming down to the practical, Reuel,
what do you think of the Negro problem? 
Come to think of it, I have never
heard you express an opinion about it.
I believe it is the only burning question
in the whole category of live issues and
ologies about which you are silent."</p>

<pb facs="p34"/>

<p>"I have a horror of discussing the woes
of unfortunates, tramps, stray dogs and
cats and Negroes&#8212;probably because I
am an unfortunate myself."</p>

<p>They smoked in silence.</p>

<p>Chapter II.</p>

<p>The passing of slavery from the land
marked a new era in the life of the nation.
The war, too, had passed like a dream of
horrors, and over the resumption of normal 
conditions in business and living, the
whole country, as one man, rejoiced and
heaved a deep sigh of absolute content.</p>

<p>Under the spur of the excitement occasioned 
by the Proclamation of Freedom, 
and the great need of schools for
the blacks, thousands of dollars were
contributed at the North, and agents
were sent to Great Britain, where
generosity towards the Negroes was
boundless. Money came from all directions, 
pouring into the hands of philanthropists, 
who were anxious to prove that
the country was able, not only to free the
slave, but to pay the great debt it owed
him,&#8212;protection as he embraced freedom, 
and a share in the great Government 
he had aided to found by sweat and
toil and blood. It was soon discovered
that the Negro possessed a phenomenal
gift of music, and it was determined to
utilize this gift in helping to support
educational institutions of color in the
Southland.</p>

<p>A band of students from Fisk University 
were touring the country, and those
who had been fortunate enough to listen
once to their matchless untrained voices
singing their heartbreaking minor music
with its grand and impossible intervals
and sound combinations, were eager to
listen again and yet again.</p>

<p>Wealthy and exclusive society women
everywhere vied in showering benefits
and patronage upon the new prodigies
who had suddenly become the pets of

the musical world. The Temple was a
blaze of light, and crowded from pit to
dome. It was the first appearance of the
troupe in New England, therefore it
was a gala night, and Boston culture was
out in force.</p>

<p>The two friends easily found their
seats in the first balcony, and from that
position idly scanned the vast audience
to beguile the tedious waiting. Reuel's
thoughts were disturbed; he read over
the program, but it carried no meaning
to his pre-occupied mind; he was uneasy;
the face he had seen outlined in the
twilight haunted him. A great nervous
dread of he knew not what possessed
him, and he actually suffered as he sat
there answering at random the running
fire of comments made by Livingston on
the audience, and replying none too
cordially to the greetings of fellow-students, 
drawn to the affair, like himself, by
curiosity.</p>

<p>"Great crowd for such a night," observed 
one. "The weather matches your
face, Briggs; why didn't you leave it outside? 
Why do you look so down?"</p>

<p>Reuel shrugged his shoulders.</p>

<p>"They say there are some pretty girls
in the troupe; one or two as white as
we, continued the speaker unabashed by
Reuel's surliness.</p>

<p>"They range at home from alabaster
to ebony," replied Livingston. "The results
of amalgamation are worthy the
careful attention of all medical experts.</p>

<p>"Don't talk shop, Livingston," said
Briggs peevishly.</p>

<p>"You are really more disagreeable
than usual," replied Livingston, pleasantly. 
"Do try to be like the other fellows,
for once, Reuel."</p>

<p>Silence ensued for a time, and then
the irrepressible one of the party remarked: 
"The soprano soloist is great;
heard her in New York." At this
there was a general laugh among the
men. Good natured Charlie Vance was

<pb facs="p35"/>

generally "stuck" once a month with the
"'loveliest girl, by jove, you know."</p>

<p>"That explains your presence here,
Vance; what's her name?"</p>

<p>"Dianthe Lusk."</p>

<p>"Great name. I hope she comes up to
it,&#8212;the flower of Jove."</p>

<p>"Flower of Jove, indeed! You'll say
so when you see her," cried Charlie with
his usual enthusiasm.</p>

<p>"What! again, my son? 'Like Dian's
kiss, unmasked, unsought, Love gives itself'" 
quoted Livingston, with a smile on
his handsome face.</p>

<p>"Oh, stow it! Aubrey, even your cold
blood will be stirred at sight of her exquisite 
face; of her voice I will not speak;
I cannot do it justice."</p>

<p>"If this is to be the result of emancipation, 
I for one vote that we ask Congress 
to annul the Proclamation," said
Reuel, drily.</p>

<p>Now conversation ceased; a famous
local organist began a concert on the
organ to occupy the moments of waiting.
The music soothed Reuel's restlessness.
He noticed that the platform usually occupied 
by the speaker's desk, now held a
number of chairs and a piano. Certainly,
the assiduous advertising had brought
large patronage for the new venture, he
thought as he idly calculated the financial 
result from the number in the
audience.</p>

<p>Soon the hot air, the glare of lights,
the mingling of choice perfumes emanating 
from the dainty forms of elegantly attired women, 
acted upon him as an intoxicant. 
He began to feel the pervading 
excitement&#8212;the flutter of expectation, 
and presently the haunting face left
him.</p>

<p>The prelude drew to a close; the last
chord fell from the fingers of the artist: a
line of figures&#8212;men and women&#8212;dark in
hue, and neatly dressed in quiet evening
clothes, filed noiselessly from the anterooms 
and filled the chairs upon the

platform. The silence in the house was
painful. These were representatives of
the people for whom God had sent the
terrible scourge of blood upon the land
to free from bondage. The old abolitionists 
in the vast audience felt the blood
leave their faces beneath the stress of
emotion.</p>

<p>The opening number was "The Lord's
Prayer." Stealing, rising, swelling,
gathering, as it thrilled the ear, all the
delights of harmony in a grand minor cadence 
that told of deliverance from bondage 
and homage to God for his wonderful
aid, sweeping the awed heart with an ecstasy 
that was almost pain; breathing,
hovering, soaring, they held the vast multitude 
in speechless wonder.</p>

<p>Thunders of applause greeted the
close of the hymn. Scarcely waiting for
a silence, a female figure rose and came
slowly to the edge of the platform and
stood in the blaze of lights with hands
modestly clasped before her. She was
not in any way the preconceived idea of
a Negro. Fair as the fairest woman in
the hall, with wavy bands of chestnut
hair, and great, melting eyes of brown,
soft as those of childhood; a willowy
figure of exquisite mould, clad in a
sombre gown of black. There fell a
voice upon the listening ear, in celestial
showers of silver that passed all conceptions, 
all comparisons, all dreams ; a voice
beyond belief&#8212;a great soprano of unimaginable 
beauty, soaring heavenward
in mighty intervals.</p>

<p>"Go down, Moses, way down in Egypt's
land,<lb/>
Tell ol' Pharaoh, let my people go."<lb/>
sang the woman in tones that awakened
ringing harmonies in the heart of every
listener.</p>

<p>"By Jove!" Reuel heard Livingston
exclaim. For himself he was dazed,
thrilled; never save among the great
artists of the earth, was such a voice
heard alive with the divine fire.</p>

<pb facs="p36"/>

<p>Some of the women in the audience
wept; there was the distinct echo of a
sob in the deathly quiet which gave
tribute to the power of genius. Spellbound 
they sat beneath the outpoured
anguish of a suffering soul. All the
horror, the degredation from which a
race had been delivered were in the
pleading strains of the singer's voice.
It strained the senses almost beyond endurance. 
It pictured to that self-possessed, 
highly-cultured New England
assemblage as nothing else ever had, the
awfulness of the hell from which a people
had been happily plucked.</p>

<p>Reuel was carried out of himself; he
leaned forward in eager contemplation of
the artist; he grew cold with terror and
fear. Surely it could not be&#8212; he must be
dreaming! It was incredible! Even as
he whispered the words to himself the
hall seemed to grow dim and shadowy;
the sea of faces melted away; there be
fore him in the blaze of light&#8212;like a
lovely phantom&#8212;stood a woman wearing
the face of his vision of the afternoon!</p>

<p>Chapter III.</p>

<p>It was Hallow-eve.</p>

<p>The north wind blew a cutting blast
over the stately Charles, and broke the
waves into a miniature flood; it swept the
streets of the University city, and danced
on into the outlying suburbs tossing the
last leaves about in gay disorder, not
even sparing the quiet precincts of
Mount Auburn cemetery. A deep, clear,
moonless sky stretched overhead, from
which hung myriads of sparkling stars.</p>

<p>It Mount Auburn, where the residences 
of the rich lay far apart, darkness
and quietness had early settled down.
The main street seemed given over to
the duskiness of the evening, and with
one exception, there seemed no light on
earth or in heaven save the cold gleam of
the stars.</p>

<p>The one exception was in the home
of Charlie Vance, or "Adonis," as he was
called by his familiars. The Vance
estate was a spacious house with rambling 
ells, tortuous chimney-stacks, and
corners, eaves and ledges; the grounds
were extensive and well kept telling
silently of the opulence of its owner. Its
windows sent forth a cheering light. Dinner 
was just over.</p>

<p>Within, on an old-fashioned hearth,
blazed a glorious wood fire, which gave
a rich coloring to the oak-panelled walls,
and fell warmly on a group of young
people seated and standing, chatting
about the fire. At one side of it, in a
chair of the Elizabethan period, sat the
hostess, Molly Vance, only daughter of
James Vance, Esq., and sister of
"Adonis," a beautiful girl of eighteen.</p>

<p>At the opposite side, leaning with
folded arms against the high carved mantel, 
stood Aubrey Livingston; the beauty
of his fair hair and blue eyes was never
more marked as he stood there in the
gleam of the fire and the soft candle
light. He was talking vivaciously, his
eyes turning from speaker to speaker, as
he ran on, but resting chiefly with pride
on his beautiful betrothed, Molly Vance.</p>

<p>The group was completed by two or
three other men, among them Reuel
Briggs, and three pretty girls. Suddenly
a clock struck the hour.</p>

<p>"Only nine," exclaimed Molly. "Good
people, what shall we do to wile the
tedium of waiting for the witching hour?
Have any one of you enough wisdom to
make a suggestion?"</p>

<p>"Music," said Livingston.</p>

<p>"We don't want anything so commonplace."</p>

<p>"Blind Man's Buff," suggested
"Adonis."</p>

<p>"Oh! please not that, the men are so
rough!"</p>

<p>"Let us," broke in Cora Scott, "tell
ghost stories."</p>

<pb facs="p37"/>

<p>"Good, Cora! yes, yes, yes."</p>

<p>"No, no!" exclaimed a chorus of
voices.</p>

<p>"Yes, yes," laughed Molly, gaily, clapping 
her hands. "It is the very thing.
Cora, you are the wise woman of the
party. It is the very time, tonight is the
new moon, and we can try our projects
in the Hyde house."</p>

<p>"The moon should be full to account
for such madness," said Livingston.</p>

<p>"Don't be disagreeable, Aubrey," replied 
Molly. "The 'ayes' have it.
You're with me, Mr. Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Of course, Miss Vance," answered
Reuel, "to go to the North Pole or
Hades&#8212;only please tell us where is
'Hyde house.'"</p>

<p>"Have you never heard? Why it's the
adjoining estate. It is reputed to be
haunted, and a lady in white haunts the
avenue in the most approved ghostly
style."</p>

<p>"Bosh!" said Livingston.</p>

<p>"Possibly," remarked the laughing
Molly, "but it is the 'bosh' of a century."</p>

<p>"Go on, Miss Vance; don't mind
Aubrey. Who has seen the lady?"</p>

<p>"She is not easily seen," proceeded
Molly, "she only appears on Hallow-eve,
when the moon is new, as it will be tonight. 
I had forgotten that fact when I
invited you here. If anyone stands, to-
night, in the avenue leading to the house,
he will surely see the tall veiled figure
gliding among the old hemlock trees."</p>

<p>One or two shivered.</p>

<p>"If, however, the watcher remain, the
lady will pause, and utter some sentence
of prophecy of his future."</p>

<p>"Has any one done this?" queried
Reuel.</p>

<p>"My old nurse says she remembers
that the lady was seen once."</p>

<p>"Then, we'll test it again tonight!" exclaimed 
Reuel, greatly excited over the
chance to prove his pet theories.</p>

<p>"Well, Molly, you've started Reuel off

on his greatest hobby; I wash my hands
of both of you."</p>

<p>"Let us go any way!" chorused the
venturesome party.</p>

<p>"But there are conditions," exclaimed
Molly. "Only one person must go at a
time."</p>

<p>Aubrey laughed as he noticed the consternation 
in one or two faces.</p>

<p>"So," continued Molly, "as we cannot
go together, I propose that each shall
stay a quarter of an hour, then whether
successful or not, return and let another
take his or her place. I will go first."</p>

<p>"No&#8212;" it was Charlie who spoke&#8212;"I
put my veto on that, Molly. If you are
mad enough to risk colds in this mad
freak, it shall be done fairly. We will
draw lots."</p>

<p>"And I add to that, not a girl leave
the house; we men will try the charm
for the sake of your curiosity, but not a
girl goes. You can try the ordinary
Hallow-eve projects while we are away."</p>

<p>With many protests, but concealed relief, 
this plan was reluctantly adopted by
the female element. The lots were prepared 
and placed in a hat, and amid much
merriment, drawn.</p>

<p>"You are third, Mr. Briggs," exclaimed 
Molly who held the hat and
watched the checks.</p>

<p>"I'm first," said Livingston, "and
Charlie second."</p>

<p>"While we wait for twelve, tell us the
story of the house, Molly," cried Cora.</p>

<p>Thus adjured, Molly settled herself
comfortably in her chair and began:
"Hyde House is nearly opposite the cemetery,
and its land joins that of this house;
it is indebted for its ill-repute to one of
its owners, John Hyde. It has been
known for years as a haunted house, and
avoided as such by the superstitious. It
is low-roofed, rambling, and almost entirely 
concealed by hemlocks, having an
air of desolation and decay in keeping
with its ill-repute. In its dozen rooms

<pb facs="p38"/>

were enacted the dark deeds which gave
the place the name of the 'haunted
house.'</p>

<p>"The story is told of an unfaithful husband, 
a wronged wife and a beautiful
governess forming a combination which
led to the murder of a guest for his
money. The master of the house died
from remorse, under peculiar circumstances. 
These materials give us the
plot for a thrilling ghost story."</p>

<p>"Well, where does the lady come in?"
interrupted "Adonis."</p>

<p>There was a general laugh.</p>

<p>"This world is all a blank without the
ladies for Charlie," remarked Aubrey.
"Molly, go on with your story, my
child."</p>

<p>"You may all laugh as much as you
please, but what I am telling you is be-
lieved in this section by every one. aA
local magazine speaks of it as follows, as
near as I can remember:</p>

<p>"'A most interesting story is told by
a woman who occupied the house for a
short time. She relates that she had no
sooner crossed the threshold than she
was met by a beautiful woman in flowing
robes of black, who begged permission
to speak through her to her friends. The
friends were thereupon bidden to be present 
at a certain time. When all were assembled 
they were directed by invisible
powers to kneel. Then the spirit told the
tale of the tragedy through the woman.
The spirit was the niece of the murderer,
and she was in the house when the
crime was committed. She discovered 
blood stains on the door of
the woodshed, and told her uncle
that she suspected him of murdering 
the guest, who had mysteriously
disappeared. He secured her promise
not to betray him. She had always kept
the secret. Although both had been
dead for many years, they were chained
to the scene of the crime, as was the

governess, Who was the man's partner in
guilt. The final release of the niece from
the place was conditional on her making
a public confession. This done she
would never be heard from again. And
she never was, except on Hallow-eve,
when the moon is new.'"</p>

<p>"Bring your science and philosophy to
bear on this, Reuel. Come, come, man,
give us your opinion," exclaimed Aubrey.</p>

<p>"Reuel doesn't believe such stuff; he's
too sensible," added Charlie.</p>

<p>"If these are facts, they are only for
those who have a mental affinity with
them. I believe that if we could but
strengthen our mental sight, we could
discover the broad highway between this
and the other world on which both good
and evil travel to earth," replied Reuel.</p>

<p>"And that 'irst highway was beaten
out of choas by Satan, as Milton has it,
eh, Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Have it as you like, Smith. No matter. 
For my own part, I have never believed 
that the whole mental world is
governed by the faculties we understand,
and can reduce to reason or definite feeling. 
But I will keep my ideas to myself: 
one does not care to be laughed at."</p>

<p>The conversation was kept up for an-
other hour about indifferent subjects, but
all felt the excitement underlying the
frivolous chatter. At quarter before
twelve, Aubrey put on his ulster with the
words: "Well, here goes for my lady."
The great doors were thrown open, and
the company grouped about him to see
him depart.</p>

<p>"Mind, honor bright, you go," laughed
Charlie.</p>

<p>"Honor bright," he called back.</p>

<p>Then he went on beyond the flood of
light into the gloom of the night. Muffled 
in wraps and ulsters they lingered
on the piazzas waiting his return.</p>

<p>"Would he see anything?"</p>

<pb facs="p39"/>

<p>"Of course not!" laughed Charlie and
Bert Smith. 'Still, we bet he'll be sharp
to his time."</p>

<p>They were right. Aubrey returned at
five minutes past twelve, a failure.</p>

<p>Charlie ran down the steps briskly, but
in ten minutes came hastening back.</p>

<p>"Well," was the chorus, "did you see
it?"</p>

<p>"I saw something&#8212;a figure in the
trees!"</p>

<p>"And you did not wait?" said Molly,
scornfully.</p>

<p>"No, I dared not; I own it."</p>

<p>"It's my turn; I'm third," said Reuel.</p>

<p>"Luck to you, old man," they called as
he disappeared in the darkness.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs was a brave man. He
knew his own great physical strength and
felt no fear as he traversed the patch
of woods lying between the two estates.
As he reached the avenue of hemlocks
he was not thinking of his mission, but
of the bright home scene he had just left
&#8212;of love and home and rest&#8212;such a life
as was unfolding before Aubrey Livingston 
and sweet Molly Vance.</p>

<p>"I suppose there are plenty of men in
the world as lonely as I am," he mused;
"but I suppose it is my own fault. A
man though plain and poor can generally 
manage to marry; and I am both. But
I don't regard a wife as one regards
bread&#8212;better sour bread than starvation; 
better an uncongenial life-companion 
than none! What a frightful mistake! 
No! The woman I marry must
be to me a necessity, because I love her;
because so loving her, 'all the current of
my being flows to her,' and I feel she is
my supreme need."</p>

<p>Just now he felt strangely happy as
he moved in the gloom of the hemlocks,
and he wondered many times after that
whether the spirit is sometimes mysteriously 
conscious of the nearness of its
kindred spirit; and feels, in anticipation,

the "sweet unrest" of the master-passion
that rules the world.</p>

<p>The mental restlessness of three weeks
before seemed to have possession of him
again. Suddenly the "restless, unsatisfied 
longing," rose again in his heart.
He turned his head and saw a female
figure just ahead of him in the path, coming 
toward him. He could not see her
features distinctly, only the eyes&#8212;large,
bright and dark. But their expression!
Sorrowful, wistful—almost imploring&#8212;
gazing straightforward, as if they saw
nothing&#8212;like the eyes of a person entirely 
absorbed and not distinguishing one
object from another.</p>

<p>She was close to him now, and there
was a perceptible pause in her step. Suddenly 
she covered her face with her
clasped hands, as if in uncontrollable
grief. Moved by a mighty emotion,
Briggs addressed the lonely figure:</p>

<p>"You are in trouble, madam; may I
help you?"</p>

<p>Briggs never knew how he survived
the next shock. Slowly the hands were
removed from the face and the moon
gave a distinct view of the lovely features 
of the jubilee singer&#8212;Dianthe
Lusk.</p>

<p>She did not seem to look at Briggs,
but straight before her, as she said in a
low, clear, passionless voice:</p>

<p>"You can help me, but not now; tomorrow."</p>

<p>Reuel's most prominent feeling was
one of delight. The way was open to
become fully acquainted with the woman
who had haunted him sleeping and waking, 
for weeks past.</p>

<p>"Not now! Yet you are suffering.
Shall I see you soon? Forgive me&#8212;but
oh! tell me&#8212;"</p>

<p>He was interrupted. The lady moved
or floated away from him, with her face
toward him and gazing steadily at him.</p>

<p>He felt that his whole heart was in his

<pb facs="p40"/>

eyes, yet hers did not drop, nor did her
cheek color.</p>

<p>"The time is not yet," she said in the
same, clear, calm, measured tones, in
which she had spoken before. Reuel
made a quick movement toward her, but
she raised her hand, and the gesture forbade 
him to follow her. He paused involuntarily, 
and she turned away, and
disappeared among the gloomy hemlock
trees.</p>

<p>He parried the questions of the merry
crowd when he returned to the house,
with indifferent replies. How they
would have laughed at him&#8212;slave of a
passion as sudden and romantic as that
of Romeo for Juliet; with no more
foundation than the "presentments" in
books which treat of the "occult." He
dropped asleep at last, in the early morning 
hours, and lived over his experience
in his dreams.</p>

<p>Chapter IV.</p>

<p>Although not yet a practitioner, Reuel
Briggs was a recognized power in the
medical profession. In brain diseases he
was an authority.</p>

<p>Early the next morning he was
aroused from sleep by imperative knocking 
at his door. It was a messenger

from the hospital. There had been a
train accident on the Old Colony road,
would he come immediately?</p>

<p>Scarcely giving himself time for a cup
of coffee, he arrived at the hospital almost
as soon as the messenger.</p>

<p>The usual silence of the hospital was
broken; all was bustle and movement,
without confusion. It was a great call
upon the resources of the officials, but
they were equal to it. The doctors
passed from sufferer to sufferer, dressing
their injuries; then they were borne to
beds from which some would never rise
again.</p>

<p>"Come with me to the women's ward,
Doctor Briggs," said a nurse. "There is
a woman there who was taken from the
wreck. She shows no sign of injury, but
the doctors cannot restore her to consciousness. 
Doctor Livingston pronounces 
her dead, but it doesn't seem
possible. So young, so beautiful. Do
something for her, Doctor."</p>

<p>The men about a cot made way for
Reuel, as he entered the ward. "It's no
use Briggs," said Livingston to him in
reply to his question. "Your science
won't save her. The poor girl is already
cold and stiff."</p>

<p>He moved aside disclosing to Reuel's
gaze the lovely face of Dianthe Lusk!</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.002">

<pb facs="p102"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Chapter IV. (Concluded.)</p>

<p>The most marvellous thing to watch is
the death of a person. At that moment
the opposite takes place to that which
took place when life entered the first unit,
after nature had prepared it for the inception 
of life. How the vigorous life
watches the passage of the liberated life
out of its earthly environment! What a
change is this! How important the
knowledge of whither life tends! Here is
shown the setting free of a disciplined
spirit giving up its mortality for immortality,
&#8212;the condition necessary to know
God. Death! There is no death. Life
is everlasting, and from its reality can
have no end. Life is real and never
changes, but preserves its identity eternally 
as the angels, and the immortal
spirit of man, which are the only realities 
and continuities in the universe, God
being over all, Supreme Ruler and Divine 
Essence from whom comes all life.
Somewhat in this train ran Reuel's
thoughts as he stood beside the seeming
dead girl, the cynosure of all the medical
faculty there assembled.</p>

<p>To the majority of those men, the case
was an ordinary death, and that was all
there was to it. What did this young upstart 
expect to make of it? Of his skill
and wonderful theories they had heard
strange tales. but they viewed him coldly
as we are apt to view those who dare to
leave the beaten track of conventionality.</p>

<p>Outwardly cool and stolid, showing no
sign of recognition, he stood for some
seconds gazing down on Dianthe; every
nerve quivered, every pulse of his body
throbbed. Her face held for him a wonderful 
charm. an extraordinary fascination. 
As he gazed he knew that once
more he beheld what he had vaguely

sought and yearned for all his forlorn
lite. His whole heart went out to her;
destiny, not chance, had brought him to
her. He saw, too, that no one knew her,
none had a clue to her identity; he determined 
to remain silent for the present,
and immediately he sought to impress
Livingston to do likewise.</p>

<p>His keen glance swept the faces of the
surrounding physicians. "No, not one,"
he told himself, "holds the key to unlock
this seeming sleep of death." He alone
could do it. Advancing far afield in the
mysterious regions of science, he had
stumbled upon the solution of one of
life's problems: <hi rend="italics">the reanimation of the
body after seeming death</hi>.</p>

<p>He had hesitated to tell of his discovery 
to any one; not even to Livingston
had he hinted of the daring possibility,
fearing ridicule in case of a miscarriage
in his calculations. But for the sake of
this girl he would make what he felt to be
a premature disclosure of the results of
his experiments. Meantime, Livingston,
from his place at the foot of the cot,
watched his friend with fascinated eyes.
He, too, had resolved. contrary to his first
intention, not to speak of his knowledge
of the beautiful patient's identity. Curiosity 
was on tiptoe; expectancy was in
the air. All felt that something unusual
was about to happen.</p>

<p>Now Reuel, with gentle fingers,
touched rapidly the clammy brow, the icy,
livid hands. the region of the pulseless
heart. No breath came from between
the parted lips; the life-giving organ was
motionless. As he concluded his examination, 
he turned to the assembled doctors:</p>

<p>"As I diagnose this case, it is one of
suspended animation. This woman has
been long and persistently subjected to

<pb facs="p103"/>

mesmeric influences, and the nervous
shock induced by the excitement of the
accident has thrown her into a cataleptic
sleep."</p>

<p>"But, man!" broke from the head physician 
in tones of exasperation, "rigor
mortis in unmistakable form is here. The
woman is dead!"</p>

<p>At these words there was a perceptible
smile on the faces of some of the students
&#8212;associates who resented his genius
as a personal affront, and who considered
these words as good as a reprimand for
the daring student, and a settler of his
pretensions. Malice and envy, from Adam's 
time until today, have loved a shining 
mark.</p>

<p>But the reproof was unheeded. Reuel
was not listening. Absorbed in thoughts
of the combat before him, he was oblivious 
to all else as he bent over the lifeless
figure on the cot. He was full of an earnest 
purpose. He was strung up to a
high tension of force and energy. As he
looked down upon the unconscious girl
whom none but he could save from the
awful fate of a death by post-mortem,
and who by some mysterious mesmeric
affinity existing between them, had drawn
him to her rescue, he felt no fear that he
should fail.</p>

<p>Suddenly he bent down and took both
cold hands into his left and passed his
right hand firmly over her arms from
shoulder to wrist. He repeated the movements 
several times; there was no response 
to the passes. He straightened
up, and again stood silently gazing upon
the patient. Then, like a man just
aroused from sleep, he looked across the
bed at Livingston and said abruptly:</p>

<p>"Dr. Livingston, will you go over to
my room and bring me the case of vials
in my medicine cabinet? I cannot leave
the patient at this point."</p>

<p>Livingston started in surprise as he replied: 
"Certainly, Briggs, if it will help
you any."</p>

<p>"The patient does not respond to anv
of the ordinary methods of awakening.

She would probably lie in this sleep for
months, and death ensue from exhaustion, 
if stronger remedies are not used to
restore the vital force to a normal condition."</p>

<p>Livingston left the hospital; he could
not return under an hour; Reuel took up
his station by the bed whereon was
stretched an apparently lifeless body, and
the other doctors went the rounds of the
wards attending to their regular routine
of duty. The nurses gazed at him curiously; 
the head doctor, upon whom the
young student's earnestness and sincerity 
had evidently made an impression,
came a number of times to the bare little
room to gaze upon its silent occupants,
but there was nothing new. When Livingston
returned, the group again gathered 
about the iron cot where lay the patient.</p>

<p>"Gentlemen," said Reuel, with quiet
dignity, when they were once more assembled, 
"will you individually examine
the patient once more and give your verdicts ?"</p>

<p>Once more doctors and students carefully 
examined the inanimate figure in
which the characteristics of death were
still more pronounced. On the outskirts
of the group hovered the house-surgeon's
assistants ready to transport the body to
the operating room for the post-mortem.
Again the head physician spoke, this time
impatiently.</p>

<p>"We are wasting our time, Dr. Briggs;
I pronounce the woman dead. She was
past medical aid when brought here."</p>

<p>"There is no physical damage, apparent 
or hidden, that you can see, Doctor?"
questioned Reuel, respectfully.</p>

<p>"No; it is a perfectly healthful organism, 
though delicate. I agree entirely
with your assertion that death was induced 
by the shock."</p>

<p>"Not <hi rend="italics">death</hi>, Doctor," protested Briggs.</p>

<p>"Well, well, call it what you like&#8212;call
it what you like, it amounts to the same
in the end," replied the doctor testily.</p>

<pb facs="p104"/>

<p>"Do you all concur in Doctor Hamilton's 
diagnosis?" Briggs included all
the physicians in his sweeping glance.
There was a general assent.</p>

<p>"I am prepared to show you that in
some cases of seeming death&#8212;or even
death in reality&#8212;consciousness may be
restored or the dead brought back to life.
I have numberless times in the past six
months restored consciousness to dogs
and cats after rigor mortis had set in, he
declared calmly.</p>

<p>"Bosh!" broke from a leading surgeon.
In this manner the astounding statement,
made in all seriousness, was received by
the group of scientists mingled with an
astonishment that resembled stupidity.
But in spite of their scoffs, the young student's 
confident manner made a decided
impression upon his listeners, unwilling
as they were to be convinced.</p>

<p>Reuel went on rapidly; his eyes kindled; 
his whole person took on the majesty 
of conscious power, and pride in the
knowledge he possessed. "I have found
by research that life is not dependent upon 
organic function as a principle. It
may be infused into organized bodies
even after the organs have ceased to perform 
their legitimate offices. Where
death has been due to causes which have
not impaired or injured or destroyed tissue 
formation or torn down the structure
of vital organs, life may be recalled when
it has become entirely extinct, which is
not so in the present case. This I have
discovered by my experiments in animal
magnetism."</p>

<p>The medical staff was fairly bewildered. 
Again Dr. Hamilton spoke:</p>

<p>"You make the assertion that the dead
can be brought to life, if I understand
your drift, Dr. Briggs, and you expect
us to believe such utter nonsense." He
added significantly, "My colleagues and
I are here to be convinced."</p>

<p>"If you will be patient for a short time
longer, Doctor, I will support my assertion 
by action. The secret of life lies in

what we call volatile magnetism&#8212;it exists 
in the free atmosphere. You, Dr.
Livingston, understand my meaning; do
you see the possibility in my words?" he
questioned, appealing to Aubrey for the
first time.</p>

<p>I have a faint conception of your
meaning, certainly, replied his friend.</p>

<p>"This <sic>subtile</sic> magnetic agent is constantly 
drawn into the body through the
lungs, absorbed and held in bounds until
chemical combination has occurred
through the medium of mineral agents
always present in normal animal tissue
When respiration ceases this magnetism
cannot be drawn into the lungs. It must
be artificially supplied. This, gentlemen,
is my discovery. I supply this magnetism. 
I have it here in the case Dr. Livingston 
has kindly brought me." He
held up to their gaze a small phial
wherein reposed a powder. Physicians
and students, now eager listeners, gazed
spell-bound upon him, straining their ears
to catch every tone of the low voice and
every change of the luminous eyes; they
pressed forward to examine the contents
of the bottle. It passed from eager hand
to eager hand, then back to the owner.</p>

<p>"This compound, gentlemen, is an exact 
reproduction of the conditions existing 
in the human body. It has common
salt for its basis. This salt is saturated
with oleo resin and then exposed for several 
hours in an atmosphere of free ammonia. 
The product becomes a powder,
and <hi rend="italics">that</hi> brings back the seeming dead to
life."</p>

<p>"Establish your theory by practical
demonstration, Dr. Briggs, and the
dreams of many eminent practitioners
will be realized," said Dr. Hamilton,
greatly agitated by his words.</p>

<p>"Your theory smacks of the supernatural, 
Dr. Briggs, charlatanism, or dreams
of lunacy," said the surgeon. "We leave
such assertions to quacks, generally, for
the time of miracles is past."</p>

<p>"The supernatural presides over man's

<pb facs="p105"/>

formation always," returned Reuel, quietly. 
"Life is that evidence of supernatural 
endowment which originally entered
nature during the formation of the units
for the evolution of man. Perhaps the
superstitious masses came nearer to solving 
the mysteries of creation than the favored 
elect will ever come. Be that as it
may, I will not contend. I will proceed
with the demonstration."</p>

<p>There radiated from the speaker the
potent <sic>pressence</sic> of a truthful mind, a
pure, unselfish nature, and that inborn
dignity which repels the shafts of lower
minds as ocean's waves absorb the drops
of rain. Something like respect mingled
with awe hushed the sneers, changing
them into admiration as he calmly proceeded 
to administer the so-called life-giving 
powder. Each man's wat.h was
in his hand; one minute passed&#8212;another
&#8212;and still another. The body remained
inanimate.</p>

<p>A cold smile of triumph began to
dawn on the faces of the older members
of the profession, but it vanished in its
incipiency, for a tremor plainly passed
over the rigid form before them. Another 
second&#8212;another convulsive movement
of the chest!</p>

<p>"She moves!" cried Aubrey at last,
carried out of himself by the strain on his
nerves. "Look, gentlemen, she breathes!
<hi rend="italics">She is alive</hi>; Briggs is right! Wonderful!
Wonderful!"</p>

<p>"We said there could not be another
miracle, and here it is!" exclaimed Dr.
Hamilton with strong emotion.</p>

<p>Five minutes more and the startled
doctors fell back from the bedside at a
motion of Reuel's hand. A wondering
nurse, with dilated eyes, unfolded a
screen, placed it in position and came and
stood beside the bed opposite Reuel.
Holding Dianthe's hands, he said in a
low voice: "Are you awake?" Her eyes
unclosed in a cold, indifferent stare which
gradually changed to one of recognition.
She looked at him&#8212;she smiled, and said

in a weak voice, "Oh, it is you; I dreamed
of you while I slept."</p>

<p>She was like a child&#8212;so trusting that
it went straight to the young man's heart.
and for an instant a great lump seemed
to rise in his throat and choke him. He
held her hands and chafed them, but
spoke with his eyes only. The nurse said
in a low voice: "Dr. Briggs, a few spoonfuls 
of broth will help her?"</p>

<p>"Yes, thank you, nurse; that will be
just right." He drew a chair close beside
the bed, bathed her face with water
and pushed back the tangle of bright
hair. He felt a great relief and quiet joy
that his experiment had been successful.</p>

<p>"Have I been ill? Where am I?" she
asked after a pause, as her face grew
troubled and puzzled.</p>

<p>"No, but you have been asleep a long
time; we grew anxious about you. You
must not talk until you are stronger."</p>

<p>The muse returned with the broth;
Dianthe drank it eagerly and called for
water, then with her hand still clasped
in Reuel's she sank into a deep sleep,
breathing softly like a tired child.
It was plain to the man of science that
hope for the complete restoration of her
faculties would depend upon time, nature
and constitution. Her effort to collect
her thoughts was unmistakable. In her
sleep, presently, from her lips fell incoherent 
words and phrases; but through it
all she clung to Reuel's hand, seeming to
recognize in him a friend.</p>

<p>A little later the doctors filed in noiselessly 
and stood about the bed gazing
down upon the sleeper with awe, listening 
to her breathing, feeling lightly the
fluttering pulse. Then they left the quiet
house of suffering, marvelling at the miracle 
just accomplished in their presence.
Livingston lingered with Briggs after
the other physicians were gone.</p>

<p>"This is a great day for you, Reuel,"
he said, as he laid a light caressing hand
upon the other's shoulder.</p>

<p>Reuel seized the hand in a quick convulsive

<pb facs="p106"/>

clasp. "True and tried friend, do
not credit me more than I deserve. No
praise is due me. I am an instrument&#8212;
how I know not&#8212;a child of circumstances. 
Do you not perceive something
strange in this case? Can you not deduce
conclusions from your own intimate
knowledge of this science?"</p>

<p>"What can you mean, Reuel?"</p>

<p>"I mean&#8212;it is a <hi rend="italics">dual</hi> mesmeric trance!
The girl is only partly normal now. Binet
speaks at length of this possibility in his
treatise. We have stumbled upon an
extraordinary case. It will take a year to
restore her to perfect health."</p>

<p>"In the meantime we ought to search
out her friends."</p>

<p>"Is there any hurry, Aubrey?" pleaded
Reuel, anxiously.</p>

<p>"Why not wait until her memory returns; 
it will not be long, I believe, although 
she may still be liable to the
trances."</p>

<p>"We'll put off the evil day to any date
you may name, Briggs; for my part, I
would preserve her incognito indefinitely."</p>

<p>Reuel made no reply. Livingston was
not sure that he heard him.</p>

<p>Chapter V.</p>

<p>The world scarcely estimates the service 
rendered by those who have unlocked 
the gates of sensation by the revelations 
of science: and yet it is to the
clear perception of things which we obtain 
by the study of nature's laws that
we are enabled to appreciate her varied
gifts. The scientific journals of the next
month contained wonderful and <hi rend="italics">wondering</hi> (?) accounts of the now celebrated
case,&#8212;re-animation after seeming death.
Reuel's lucky star was in the ascendant;
fame and fortune awaited him; he had
but to grasp them. Classmates who had
once <sic>ingored</sic> him now sought familiar association, 
or else gazed upon him with
awe and reverence. "How did he do it?"

was the query in each man's mind, and
then came a stampede for all scientific
matter bearing upon animal magnetism.</p>

<p>How often do we look in wonder at the
course of other men's lives, whose paths
have diverged so widely from the beaten
track of our own, that, unable to comprehend 
the one spring upon which, perhaps,
the whole secret of the diversity hinged,
we have been fain to content ourselves
with summing up our judgment in the
common phrase, "Well, it's very strange;
what odd people there are in the world.
to be sure!"</p>

<p>Many times this trite sentence was uttered 
during the next few months, generally 
terminating every debate among
medical students in various colleges.</p>

<p>Unmindful of his growing popularity,
Reuel devoted every moment of his spare
time to close study of his patient. Although 
but a youth, the scientist might
have passed for any age under fifty, and
life for him seemed to have taken on a
purely mechanical aspect since he had become 
first in this great cause. Under pretended 
indifference to public criticism.
throbbed a heart of gold, sensitive to a
fault; desiring above all else the well-being 
of all humanity: his faithfulness to
those who suffered amounted to complete
self-sacrifice. Absolutely free from the
vices which beset most young men of his
age and profession, his daily life was a
white, unsullied page to the friend admitted 
to unrestricted intercourse, and
gave an irresistible impetus to that friendship, 
for Livingston could not but admire
the newly developed depths of nobility
which he now saw unfolding day by day
in Reuel's character. Nor was Livingston 
far behind the latter in his interest
in all that affected Dianthe. Enthused by
its scientific aspect, he vied with Reuel in
close attention to the medical side of the
case, and being more worldly did not neglect 
the material side.</p>

<p>He secretly sought out and obtained
the address of the manager of the jubilee

<pb facs="p107"/>

singers and to his surprise received
the information that Miss Lusk had left
the troupe to enter the service of a traveling 
magnetic physician&#8212;a woman&#8212;for
a large salary. They (the troupe) were
now in Europe and had heard nothing
of Miss Lusk since.</p>

<p>After receiving this information by
cable, Livingston sat a long time smoking 
and thinking: people often disappeared 
in a great city, and the police
would undoubtedly find the magnetic
physician if he applied to them. Of
course that was the sensible thing to do,
but then the publicity, and he hated that
for the girl's sake. Finally he decided to
compromise the matter by employing a
detective. With him to decide that it was
expedient to do a certain thing was the
same as to act; before night the case was
in the hands of an expert detective who
received a goodly retainer. Two weeks
from that day&#8212;it was December twenty-fourth
&#8212;before he left his boarding place,
the detective was announced. He had
found the woman in a small town near
Chicago. She said that she had no knowledge 
of Miss Lusk's whereabouts. Dianthe 
had remained with her three weeks,
and at the end of that time had mysteriously 
disappeared; she had not heard of
her since.</p>

<p>Livingston secured the woman's name
and address, gave the man a second check
together with an admonition to keep silence 
concerning Miss Lusk. That closed
the episode. But of his observations and
discoveries, Aubrey said nothing, noting
every phase of this strange happening in
silence.</p>

<p>Strangely enough, none of the men
that had admired the colored artist who
had enthralled their senses by her wonderful 
singing a few weeks before, rec-
ognized her in the hospital waif consecrated 
to the service of science. Her incognito 
was complete.</p>

<p>The patient was now allowed the freedom 
of the corridors for exercise, and

was about her room during the day. The
returns of the trance-state were growing
less regular, although she frequently fell
into convulsions, thereby enduring much
suffering, sometimes lying for hours in a
torpid state. Livingston had never happened 
to be present on these occasions,
but he had heard of them from eye-witnesses. 
One day he entered the room
while one was occurring. His entrance
was unnoticed as he approached lightly
over the uncarpeted floor, and stood
transfixed by the scene before him.</p>

<p>Dianthe stood upright, with closed
eyes, in the middle of the room. Only the
movement of her bosom betrayed breath.
The other occupants of the room preserved 
a solemn silence. She addressed
Reuel, whose outstretched arms were extended 
as if in blessing over her head.</p>

<p>"Oh! Dearest friend! hasten to cure
me of my sufferings. Did you not promise 
at that last meeting? You said to me,
'You are in trouble and I can help you.'
And I answered, 'The time is not yet.' Is
it not so?"</p>

<p>"Yes," replied Reuel. "Patience a
while longer; all will be well with you."</p>

<p>"Give me the benefit of your powerful
will," she continued. "I know much but
as yet have not the power to express it;
I see much clearly, much dimly, of the
powers and influences behind the Veil,
and yet I cannot name them. Some time
the full power will be mine; and mine
shall be thine. In seven months the sick
will be restored&#8212;she will awake to
worldly cares once more." Her voice
ceased; she sank upon the cot in a recumbent 
position. Her face was pale;
she appeared to sleep. Fifteen minutes
passed in death-like stillness, then she
extended her arms, stretched, yawned,
rubbed her eyves&#8212;awoke.</p>

<p>Livingston listened and looked in a
trance of delight, his keen artistic sense
fully aroused and appreciative, feeling
the glamour of her presence and ethereal
beauty like a man poring over a poem

<pb facs="p108"/>

that he has unexpectedly stumbled upon,
losing himself in it, until it becomes, as
it were, a part of himself. He felt as he
watched her that he was doing a foolish
thing in thus exposing himself to temptation 
while his honor and faith were
pledged to another. But then, foolishness 
is so much better than wisdom, particularly 
to a man in certain stages of life.
And then he fell to questioning if there
could be temptation for him through this
girl&#8212;he laughed at the thought and the
next instant dismay covered him with
confusion, for like a flash he realized that
the mischief was already done.</p>

<p>As we have already hinted, Aubrey
was no saint; he knew that fickleness was
in his blood; he had never denied himself 
anything that he wanted very much
in his whole life. Would he grow to want
this beautiful woman very much? Time
would tell.</p>

<p>* * * *</p>

<p>It was Christmas-time&#8212;a good, sensible
seasonable day before Christmas, with frost
and ice in abundance, and a clear, bright,
wintry sky above. Boston was very full
of people&#8212;mostly suburban visitors&#8212;
who were rushing here and there bent on
emptying their purses on the least provocation. 
Good-nature prevailed among
the pedestrians; one poor wretch stood
shivering, with blue, wan face, on the
edge of the sidewalk, his sightless eyes
staring straight before him, trying to
draw a tune from a consumptive violin
&#8212;the embodiment of despair. He was,
after all, in the minority, to judge by the
hundreds of comfortably-clad forms that
hurried past him, breathing an atmosphere 
of peace and prosperity.</p>

<p>Tomorrow the church bells would ring
out tidings that another Christmas was
born, bidding all rejoice.</p>

<p>This evening, at six o'clock, the two
friends went to dine in a hotel in a fashionable 
quarter. They were due to spend
the night and Christmas day at the Vance
house. As they walked swiftly along

with the elastic tread of youth, they
simultaneously halted before the blind
musician and pressed into his trembling
hand a bountiful gift; then they hurried
away to escape his thanks.</p>

<p>At the hotel Livingston called for a private 
dining room, and after the coffee
was served, he said:</p>

<p>"Tell me, Briggs, what is the link between 
you and your patient. There is a
link, I am sure. Her words while in the
trance made a great impression upon
me."</p>

<p>There was a pause before Reuel replied 
in a low tone, as he rested his arm
on the opposite side of the table and
propped his head up on his hand:</p>

<p>"Forgive me, Aubrey!"</p>

<p>"For what?"</p>

<p>"This playing with your confidence. I
have not been entirely frank with you."</p>

<p>"Oh, well! you are not bound to tell
me everything you know. You surely
have the right to silence about your affairs, 
if you think best."</p>

<p>"Listen, Aubrey. I should like to tell
you all about it. I would feel better.
What you say is true; there is a link; but
I never saw her in the flesh before that
night at the Temple. With all our
knowledge, Aubrey, we are but barbarians 
in our ideas of the beginning, interim
and end of our creation. Why were we
created? for whose benefit? can anyone
answer that satisfactorily?</p>

<p>"'Few things are hidden from the man
who devotes himself earnestly and seriously 
to the solution of a mystery,' Hawthorne 
tells us," replied Aubrey. "Have
not you proved this, Reuel?"</p>

<p>"Well, yes&#8212;or, we prove rather, that
our solution but deepens the mystery or
mysteries. I have surely proved the last.
Aubrey, I look natural, don't I? There is
nothing about me that seems wrong?"</p>

<p>"Wrong! No."</p>

<p>"Well, if I tell you the truth you will
call me a lunatic. You have heard of
people being haunted by hallucinations?"

<pb facs="p109"/>

Aubrey nodded. 'I am one of those persons. 
Seven weeks ago I saw Dianthe
first, but not in the flesh. Hallow-eve I
spoke to her in the garden of the haunted
house, but not in the flesh. I thought 't
strange to be sure, that this face should
lurk in my mind so much of the time;
but I never dreamed what a crisis it was
leading up to. The French and German
schools of philosophy have taught us
that going to places and familiar passages
in books, of which we have had no previous 
knowledge, is but a proof of
Plato's doctrine&#8212;the soul's transmigration, 
and reflections from the invisible
world surrounding us.</p>

<p>"Finally a mad desire seized me to find
that face a living reality that I might
love and worship it. Then I saw her at
the Temple&#8212;I found her at the hospital
&#8212;<hi rend="italics">in the flesh!</hi> My desire was realized."</p>

<p>"And having found her, what then?"
He waited breathlessly for the reply.</p>

<p>"I am mightily pleased and satisfied. I
will cure her. She is charming; and if it
is insanity to be in love with her, I don't
care to be sane."</p>

<p>Livingston did not reply at once. His
face was like marble in its impassiveness.
The other's soft tremulous tones, fearless
yet moist eyes and broken sentences, appeared 
to awaken no response in his
breast. Instead, a far-off gleam came into 
his blue eyes. At last he broke the silence 
with the words:</p>

<p>"You name it well; it is insanity indeed, 
for you to love this woman."</p>

<p>"Why?" asked his friend, constrainedly.</p>

<p>"Because it is not for the best."</p>

<p>"For her or me?"</p>

<p>"Oh, for <hi rend="italics">her</hi> &#8212;!" he finished the
sentence with an expressive gesture.</p>

<p>"I understand you, Aubrey. I should
not have believed it of you. If it were
one of the other fellows; but you are
generally so charitable."</p>

<p>"You forget your own words: 'Tramps,
stray dogs and Negroes &#8212;.'" he

quoted significantly. "Then there 1s your
professional career to be considered,&#8212;you
mean honorable, do you not? &#8212; How
can you succeed if it be hinted abroad that
you are married to a Negress?"</p>

<p>"I have thougnt of all that. I am determined. 
I will marry her in spite of hell
itself! Marry her before she awakens to
consciousness of her identity. I'm not
unselfish; I don't pretend to be. There
is no sin in taking her out of the sphere
where she was born. God and science
helping me, I will give her life and love
and wifehood and maternity and perfect
health. God, Aubrey! you, with all you
have had of life's sweetness, petted idol
of a beautiful world, you who will soon
feel the heart-beats of your wife against
your breast when lovely Molly is eternally
bound to you, what do you know of a
<sic>lonelly</sic>, darkened life like mine? I have
not the manner nor the charm which
wins women. Men like me get love from
them which is half akin to pity, when
they get anything at all. It is but the
shadow. This is my opportunity for happiness; 
I seize it. Fate has linked us together 
and no man and no man's laws
shall part us."</p>

<p>Livingston sipped his wine quietly, intently 
watching Reuel's face. Now he
leaned across the table and stretched out
his hand to Briggs; his eyes looked full
into his. As their hands met in a close
clasp, he whispered a sentence across the
board. Reuel started, uttered an exclamation 
and flushed slowly a dark, dull red.</p>

<p>"How&#8212;where&#8212;how did you know
it?" he stammered.</p>

<p>"I have known it since first we met; but
the secret is safe with me."</p>

<p>Chapter VI.</p>

<p>The scene which met the gaze when an
hour later the young men were ushered
into the long drawing-room of the Vance
house was one well-calculated to remove
all gloomy, pessimistic reasoning.

<pb facs="p110"/>

Warmth, gaiety, pretty women, luxury,&#8212;
all sent the blood leaping through the
veins in delightful anticipation.</p>

<p>Their entrance was greeted by a shout
of welcome.</p>

<p>"Oh, Aubrey! I am so glad you are
come," cried Molly from the far end of
the room. "Fancy tomorrow being
Christmas! Shall we be ready for all that
company tomorrow night and the ballroom, 
dining room and hall yet to be
trimmed? Is it possible to be ready?"</p>

<p>"Not if we stand dwadling in idle talk."
This from "Adonis," who was stretched
full length on the sitting-room sofa, with
a cigarette between his lips, his hands
under his handsome head, surrounded by
a bevy of pretty, chattering girls, prominent 
among whom was Cora Scott, who
aided and <sic>abbetted</sic> Charlie in every piece
of mischief.</p>

<p>Molly curled her lip but deigned no
reply.</p>

<p>Bert Smith, from a corner of the room
where he was about ascending a step-ladder, 
flung a book heavily at Adonis's lazy
figure.</p>

<p>"Don't confuse your verbs," exclaimed
Aubrey. "How can you stand when you
are lying down, and were you ever known
to do anything else but dwadle, Adonis&#8212;
eh?"</p>

<p>"I give it up," said Charlie, sleepily,
kicking the book off the sofa.</p>

<p>"Is this an amateur grocery shop, may
I ask, Miss Vance?" continued Aubrey as
he and Briggs made their way to their
hostess through an avalanche of parcels
and baskets strewn on the tables and the
floor.</p>

<p>Molly laughed as she greeted them.
"No wonder you are surprised. I am
superintending the arrangement of my
poor people's gifts," she explained. "They
must all be sent out tonight. I don't
know what I should have done without all
these good people to help me. But there
are <hi rend="italics">piles</hi> to be done yet. There is the

tree, the charades, etc., etc.," she continued, 
in a plaintive little voice.</p>

<p>"More particularly cetra, cetra," said
Aubrey from Bert's corner where he had
gone to help along the good works of
placing holly wreaths.</p>

<p>"Oh, you, Aubey&#8212;stop being a mag.
pie." Aubrey and Molly were very matter 
of fact lovers.</p>

<p>"Molly," again broke in Charlie, "suppose 
the box from Pierson's has never
come, won't you be up a tree?" and the
speaker opened his handsome eyes wide,
and shook off his cigarette-ash.</p>

<p>Molly maintained a dignified silence toward 
her brother. The firelight danced
and dwelt upon her lovingly. She was so
pretty, so fair, so slender, so graceful.
Now in her gray plush tea-gown, with her
hair piled picturesquely on the top of her
small head, and fixed there with a big
tortoise-shell pin, it would have been difficult 
to find a more delightful object for
the gaze to rest upon.</p>

<p>"We shall have to fall back upon the
wardrobes," she said at length. "You
are a horrid wet-blanket, Charlie! I am
sure I&#8212;"</p>

<p>Her remarks were cut short as the door
opened, and with laughter and shouting
a bevy of young people who had been at
work in another part of the house rushed
in. "It is come; it's all right; don't
worry, Molly!" they sang in chorus.</p>

<p>"Do be quiet all of vou; one can hardly
hear oneself speak!"</p>

<p>The box from the costumer's had arrived; 
the great costume party was saved;
in short, excitement and bustle were in
full swing at Vance Hall as it had been at
Christmas-time since the young people
could remember.</p>

<p>Adonis lifted himself from the sofa
and proposed to open the box of dresses
at once, and trv them on.</p>

<p>"Charlie, you are a brick!&#8212;the very
thing!"</p>

<p>"Oh! yes, yes; let us try them on!"</p>

<p>Molly broke through the eager voices:

<pb facs="p111"/>

"And we have not done the ball-room
yet!" she said reproachfully.</p>

<p>"Oh! bother the ball-room!" declared
Adonis, now thoroughly aroused. "We
have all night. We can't do better than
to don our finery."</p>

<p>Molly sat down with an air of resigned
patience. "I promised Mr. Pierson," she
observed quietly, "that the box should not
be touched until he was here to superintend 
matters."</p>

<p>"Oh, Pierson be blowed!" elegantly observed 
her brother. But Reuel Briggs
suddenly dropped his work, walked over,
and sided with Molly.</p>

<p>"You are quite right, Miss Molly; and
you Charlie and Aubrey and the rest of
you men, if you want to open the box tonight
you must first decorate the ballroom.
Business before pleasure."</p>

<p>"Saved!&#8212;saved! See my brave, true
Knight defends his lady fair." Molly
danced, practising the step she was about
to astonish the company with on Christmas-night. 
"I think I am what the Scotch
call 'fev' she laughed. "I don't know
why I feel so awfully jolly tonight. I
could positively fly from sheer excitement
and delight."</p>

<p>"Don't you know why?" observed Cora.
"I will tell you. It is because this is
your last Christmas as Molly Vance; next
year&#8212;"</p>

<p>"Ah, do not!" interrupted Molly, quickly. 
"Who knows what a year may bring
forth. Is it net so, Dr. Briggs?" she
turned appealingly to Reuel.</p>

<p>"Grief follows joy as clouds the sunlight. 
'Woe! woe! each heart must bleed,
must break,'" was his secret thought as
he bowed gravely. But on his face was a
look of startled perplexity, for suddenly
as she spoke to him it appeared that a
dark veil settled like a pall over the laughing 
face at his side. He shivered.</p>

<p>"What's the matter, Briggs?" called
out Adonis. They had reached the ballroom 
and were standing over the piles
of holly and evergreen, ready for an onslaught
on the walls.</p>

<p>"Don't be surprised if Briggs acts
strangely," continued Charlie. "It is in
order for him to whoop it up in the spirit
line."</p>

<p>"Why, Charlie! What do you mean?"
questioned Molly with an anxious glance
ut Reuel.</p>

<p>"Anything interesting, Charlie?" called
out a jolly girl across the room.</p>

<p>"Briggs is our 'show' man. Haven't
you heard, girls, what a celebrity is with
you tonight? Briggs is a philosopher&#8212;
mesmerism is his specialty. Say, old
man, give the company a specimen of
your infernal art, can't you? He goes the
whole hog, girls; can even raise the
dead."</p>

<p>"Let up, Charlie," said Aubrey in a
low tone. It's no joking matter."</p>

<p>There were screams and exclamations
from the girls. With reckless gaiety
Adonis continued,</p>

<p>"What is to be the outcome of the
great furore you have created, Briggs?"</p>

<p>"Nothing of moment, I hope," smiled
Reuel, good-naturedly. I have been
simply an instrument; I leave results to
the good angels who direct events. What
does Longfellow say about the arrow
and the song?

<q>'Long, lone afterwards, in an oak<lb/>
I found the arrow still unbroke;<lb/>
And the song, from beginning to end,
I found in the heart of a friend.'</q>

May it be so with my feeble efforts."</p>

<p>"But circumstances alter cases. In this
case, the 'arrow' is a girl and a devilish
handsome one, too; and the 'air' is the
whole scientific world. Your philosophy
and mysticism gave way before Beauty.
Argument is a stubborn man's castle, but
the heart is still unconvinced."</p>

<p>"'I mixed those children up, and not
a creature knew it,'" hummed Bert
Smith. "Your ideas are mixed, Don;
stick to the ladies, you understand girls
and horseflesh: philosophy isn't in your
line."</p>

<pb facs="p112"/>

<p>"Oh, sure!" said Adonis unruffled by
his friend's words.</p>

<p>"Charlie Vance," said Molly severely,
"if we have any more <hi rend="italics">swearing</hi> from you
to night, you leave the room until you
learn to practice good manners. I'm surprised 
at your language!"</p>

<p>"Just the same, Briggs is a fraud. I
shall keep my eye on him. It's a case of
beauty and the beast. Oh," he continued
in malicious glee, "wouldn't you girls
turn green with envy, every man jack of
you, if you could see the beauty!"</p>

<p>Thereupon the girls fell to pelting him
with holly wreaths and evergreen festoons, 
much to the enjoyment of Mr.
Vance, who had entered unperceived in
the general melee.</p>

<p>"What is it all about, Dr. Briggs?"
asked Molly in a low voice.</p>

<p>"It is the case of a patient who was in
a mesmeric sleep and I was fortunate
enough to awaken her. She is a waif;
and it will be months before she will be
well and strong, poor girl."</p>

<p>"Do you make a study of mesmerism,
Doctor?" asked Mr. Vance from his armchair 
by the glowing fire.</p>

<p>"Yes sir; and a wonderful science it is."
Before Mr. Vance could continue, Livingston 
said: "If you folks will be still for
about ten minutes, I'll tell you what
happened in my father's house when I
was a very small boy; I can just remember 
it."</p>

<p>"If it's a ghost story, make it strong,
Aubrey, so that not a girl will sleep tonight. 
Won't the dears look pretty blinking 
and yawning tomorrow night? We'll
hear 'em, fellows, in the small hours of
the morning, 'Molly, Molly! I'm so
frightened. I do believe someone is in my
room; may I come in with you, dear?'"</p>

<p>"Charlie, stop your <sic>nonsence</sic>," laughed
his father, and Adonis obediently subsided.</p>

<p>"My father was Dr. Aubrey Livingston
too," began Aubrey, "and he owned a
large plantation of slaves. My father was

deeply interested in the science of medicine, 
and I believe made some valuable
discoveries along the line of mesmeric
phenomena, for some two or three of his
books are referred to even at this advanced 
stage of discovery, as marvellous
in some of their data.</p>

<p>"Among the slaves was a girl who was
my mother's waiting maid, and I have
seen my father throw her into a trance-state 
many times when I was so small that
I had no conception of what he was doing.</p>

<p>"Many a time I have known him to call
her into the parlor to perform tricks of
mind-reading for the amusement of visitors, 
and many wonderful things were
done by her as the record given in his
books shows.</p>

<p>"One day there was a great dinner
party given at our place, and the êlite
of the county were bidden. It was about
two years before the civil war, and our
people were not expecting war; thinking
that all unpleasantness must end in their
favor, they gave little heed to the ominous 
rumble of public opinion that was
arising at the North, but went on their
way in all their pride of position and
wealth without a care for the future.</p>

<p>"Child as I was I was impressed by the
beauty and wit of the women and the
chivalric hearing of the men gathered
about my father's hospitable board on that
memorable day. When the feasting and
mirth began to lag, someone called for
Mira&#8212;the maid&#8212;and my father sent for
her to come and amuse the guests.</p>

<p>"My father made the necessary passes
and from a serious, rather sad Negress,
very mild with everyone, Mira changed to
a gay, noisy, restless woman, full of irony
and sharp jesting. In this case this
peculiar metamorphosis always occurred.
Nothing could be more curious than to
see her and hear her. 'Tell the company 
what you see, Mira,' commanded
my father.</p>

<p>"You will not like it, captain; but if I

<pb facs="p113"/>

must, I must. All the women will be
widows and the men shall sleep in early
graves. They come from the north, from
the east, from the west, they sweep to the
gulf through a trail of blood. Your
houses shall burn, your fields be laid
waste, and a down-trodden race shall rule
in your land. For you, captain, a prison
cell and a pauper's grave."</p>

<p>The dinner-party broke up in a panic.
and from that time my father could not
abide the girl. He finally sold her just
a few months before the secession of the
Confederate States, and that was the last
we ever knew of her."</p>

<p>"And did the prophecy come true about
your father? asked Mr. Vance.</p>

<p>"Too true, sir; my father died while
held as a prisoner of war, in Boston Harbor. 
And every woman at the table was
left a widow. There is only too much
truth in science of mesmeric phenomena.
The world ts a wonderful place."</p>

<p>"Wonderful!" declared his hearers.</p>

<p>"I am thinking of that poor, pretty
creature lying ill in that gloomy hospital
without a friend. Men are selfish! I tell
you what, folks, tomorrow after lunch
we'll make a Christmas visit to the
patients, and carry them fruit and flowers.
As for your beautiful patient, Dr. Briggs,
she shall not be friendless any longer, she

shall come to us at Vance Hall."</p>

<p>"Molly!" broke simultaneously from
Aubrey and Charlie.</p>

<p>"Oh, I mean it. There is plenty of
room in this great house, and here she
shall remain until she is restored to
health."</p>

<p>Expostulation was in vain. The petted
heiress was determined, and when Mr.
Vance was appealed to he laughed and
said, as he patted her hand:</p>

<p>"The queen must have her own."</p>

<p>At length the costumer's box was
opened amidst jest, song and laughter.
The characters were distributed by the
wilful Molly. Thus attired, to the music
of Tannhauser's march, played by one of
the girls on the piano, the gay crowd
marched and counter-marched about the
spacious room.</p>

<p>In the early morning hours, Aubrey
Livingston slept and dreamed of Dianthe
Lusk, and these words haunted his sleep
and lingered with him when he woke:</p>

<p>"She had the glory of heaven in her
voice, and in her face the fatal beauty of
man's terrible sins."</p>

<p>Aubrey Livingston knew that he was
as hopelessly lost as was Adam when he
sold his heavenly birthright for a
woman's smile.</p>

<p>(To be continued.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0095.003">

<pb facs="p191"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Of One Blood.<lb/>
Or, The Hidden Self.</p>

<p>Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="fiction">

<p>Synopsis of Chapters I to VI.</p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, a young medical student, interested in
mysticism, sees a face that haunts him. He attends a
concert with his friend Aubrey Livingston, and there
discovers in a negro concert-singer the owner of the
mysterious face. He sees this woman again on Hallow
Eve while playing at charms with a party of young
people at Vance Hall, the home of Livingston’s betrothed. 
Early the next morning he is called to attend
the victims of a railroad disaster at the hospital. He
finds among them the girl whose face haunts him, in a
cataleptic sleep which the doctors call death. He succeeds 
in restoring her to consciousness, but with a
complete loss of memory. She loses her identity as a
negress. Reuel falls deeply in love with her.</p>

<p>Chapter VII.</p>

<p>Through days and days, and again
through days and days, over and over
again, Reuel Briggs fought to restore his
patient to a normal condition of health.
Physically, he succeeded ; but mentally his
treatment was a failure. Memory remained 
a blank to the unhappy girl. Her
life virtually began with her awakening
at the hospital. A look of wonder and a
faint smile were the only replies that
questions as to the past elicited from her.
Old and tried specialists in brain diseases
and hypnotic states came from every part
of the Union on bootless errands. It was
decided that nothing could be done; rest,
freedom from every care and time might
eventually restore the poor, violated mind
to its original strength. Thus it was that
Dianthe became the dear adopted daughter 
of the medical profession. Strange to
say, Molly Vance secured her desire, and
wearing the name of Felice Adams.
Dianthe was domiciled under the roof of
palatial Vance hall, and the small annuity
provided by the generous contributions of
the physicians of the country was placed
in the hands of Mr. Vance, Sr., to be expended 
for their protege.</p>

<p>The astonishing nature of the startling
problems he had unearthed, the agitation

and indignation aroused in him by the
heartless usage to which his patient must
have been exposed, haunted Briggs day
and night. He believed that he had been
drawn into active service for Dianthe by
a series of strange <sic>coincidencies</sic>, and the
subtle forces of immortality; what future
acts this service might require he knew
not, he cared not; he registered a solemn
promise to perform all tasks allotted him
by Infinity, to the fullest extent of his
power.</p>

<p>The brilliant winter days merged themselves 
into spring. After one look into
Dianthe’s eves, so deep, clear and true,
Molly Vance had surrendered unconditionally 
to the charm of the beautiful
stranger, drawn by an irresistible bond of
sympathy. “Who would believe,” she observed 
to Livingston, “that at this stage
of the world’s progress one’s identity
could be so easily lost and one still be
living. It is like a page from an exciting 
novel.”</p>

<p>With the impulsiveness of youth, a
wonderful friendship sprang up between
the two; they rode, walked and shopped
together; in short, became inseparable
companions. The stranger received every
attention in the family that could be given
an honored guest. Livingston and Briggs
watched her with some anxiety; would
she be able to sustain the position of intimate 
friendship to which Molly had
elected her? But both breathed more
freely when they noted her perfect manners, 
the ease and good-breeding displayed 
in all her intercourse with those
socially above the level to which they
knew this girl was born. She accepted
the luxury of her new surroundings as
one to the manner born.</p>

<pb facs="p192"/>

<p>“We need not have feared for her; by
Jove, she's a thorough-bred!" exclaimed
Aubrey one day to Reuel. The latter
nodded as he locked up from his book.</p>

<p>“And why not? Probably the best
blood of the country flows in the poor
girl’s veins. Who can tell? Why should
she not be a thorough-bred.”</p> 

<p>“True,” replied Aubrey, as a slight
frown passed over his face.</p>

<p>“I am haunted by a possibility, Aubrey,” 
continued Reuel. “What if memory 
suddenly returns? Is it safe to risk
the unpleasantness of a public reawakening 
of her sleeping faculties? I have
read of such things.”</p>

<p>Aubrey shrugged his handsome shoulders. 
“We must risk something for the
sake of science; where no one is injured
by deception there is no harm done.”</p>

<p>“Now that question has presented itself
to me repeatedly lately: Is deception
justifiable for any reason? Somehow it
haunts me that trouble may come from
this. I wish we had told the exact truth
about her identity.”</p>

<p>"'If 'twere done when 'tis done, then
"twere well it were done quickly” murmured 
Aubrey with a sarcastic smile on
his face. “How you balk at nothing.
Reuel,” he drawled mockingly.</p>

<p>“Oh, call me a fool and done with it,
Aubrey: I <sic>supose</sic> I am; but one didn't
make one’s self.”</p>

<p>Drives about the snow-clad suburbs of
Cambridge with Briggs and Molly, at
first helped to brighten the invalid; then
came quiet social diversions at which
Dianthe was the great attraction.</p>

<p>It was at an afternoon function that
Reuel took courage to speak of his love.
A dozen men buzzed about “Miss Adams”
in the great bay window where Molly had
placed Dianthe, her superb beauty set off
by a simple toilet. People came and went
constantly. Musical girls, generally with
gold eyeglasses on esthetic noses, played
grim classical preparations, which have as
cheerful an effect on a gay crowd as the

perfect, irreproachable skeleton of a bygone 
beauty might have; or articulate,
with cultivation and no voices to speak of,
arias which would sap the life of a true
child of song to render as the maestro intended.</p>

<p>The grand, majestic voice that had
charmed the hearts from thousands of
bosoms, was pinioned in the girl’s throat
like an imprisoned song-bird. Dianthe’s
voice was completely gone along with her
memory. But music affected her strangely, 
and Reuel watched her anxiously.</p>

<p>Her face was a study in its delicate,
quickly changing tints, its sparkle of
smiles running from the sweet, pure
tremor of the lovely mouth to the switt
laughter of eyes and voice.</p>

<p>Mindful of her infirmity, Reuel led her
to the conservatory to escape the music.
She lifted her eyes to his with a curious
and angelic light in them. She was conscious 
that he loved her with his whole
most loving heart. She winced under the
knowledge, for while she believed in him,
depended upon him and gathered strength
from his love, what she gave in return
was but a slight, cold affection compared
with his adoration.</p>

<p>He brought her refreshments in the
conservatory, and then told his love and
asked his fate. She did not answer at
once, but looked at his plain face, at the
stalwart elegance of his figure, and again
gazed into the dark, true, clever eyes, and
with the sigh of a tired child crept into
his arms, and into his heart for all time
and eternity. Thus Aubrey Livingston
found them when the company had departed. 
So it was decided to have the
wedding in June. What need for these
two children of misfortune to wait?</p>

<p>Briggs, with his new interest in life,
felt that it was good just to be alive. The
winter passed rapidly, and as he threaded
the streets coming and going to his hospital 
duties, his heart sang. No work was
now too arduous; he delighted in the duty
most exacting in its nature. As the spring

<pb facs="p193"/>

came in it brought with it thoughts of the
future. He was almost penniless, and he
saw no way of obtaining the money he
needed. He had not been improvident,
but his lonely life had lived a reckless
disregard of the future, and the value of
money. He often lived a day on bread
and water, at the same time sitting without 
a fire in the coldest weather because
his pockets were empty and he was too
proud to ask a loan, or solicit credit from
storekeepers. He now found himself in
great difficulty. His literary work and
the extra cases which his recent triumph
had brought him, barely sufficed for his
own present needs. Alone in his bachelor
existence he would call this luxury, but it
was not enough to furnish a suitable establishment 
for Dianthe. As the weeks
rolled by and nothing presented itself, he
grew anxious, and finally resolved to consult 
Livingston.</p>

<p>All things had become new to him, and
in the light of his great happiness the very
face of old Cambridge was changed. Fate
had always been against him, and had
played him the shabbiest of tricks, but
now he felt that she might do her worst,
he held a talisman against misfortune
while his love remained to him. Thinking
thus he walked along briskly, and
the sharp wind brought a faint color into
his sallow face. He tried to think and
plan, but his ideas were whirled away <sic>befort</sic> 
they had taken form, and he felt a
giant’s power to overcome with each inspiring 
breath of the crisp, cool March
air. Aubrey should plan for him, but he
would accomplish.</p>

<p>Livingston had apartments on Dana
Hill, the most aristocratic portion of
Cambridge. There he would remain till
the autumn, when he would marry Molly
Vance, and remove to Virginia and renew 
the ancient splendor of his ancestral
home. He was just dressing for an evening 
at the theatre when Briggs entered
his rooms. He greeted him with his usual
genial warmth.</p>

<p>“What!” he said gaily, “the great scientist 
here, at this hour?”</p>

<p>Then noticing his visitor’s anxious
countenance he added:</p>

<p>“What’s the matter?”</p>

<p>“I am in difficulties and come to you
for help,” replied Reuel.</p>

<p>“How so? What is it? I am always
anxious to serve you, Briggs.”</p>

<p>“I certainly think so or I would not be
here now,” said Reuel. “But you are just
going out, an engagement perhaps with
Miss Molly. My business will take some
time&#8212;”</p>

<p>Aubrey interrupted him, shaking his
head negatively. “I was only going out
to wile away the time at the theatre. Sit
down and free your mind, old man.”</p>

<p>Thus admonished, Reuel flung himself
among the cushions of the divan, and began 
to state his reasons for desiring assistance; 
when he finished, Livingston
asked:</p>

<p>“Has nothing presented itself?”</p>

<p>“O yes; two or three really desirable
offers which I wrote to accept, but to my
surprise, in each case I received polite regrets 
that circumstances had arisen to prevent 
the acceptance of my valuable services. 
That is what puzzles me. What
the dickens did it mean?”</p>

<p>Aubrey said nothing but continued a
drum solo on the arm of his chair. Finally
he asked abruptly: “Briggs, do you
think anyone knows or suspects your
origin?”</p>

<p>Not a muscle of Reuel’s face moved as
he replied, calmly: “I have been wondering 
if such can be the case.”</p>

<p>“This infernal prejudice is something
horrible. It closes the door of hope and
opportunity in many a good man’s face.
I am a Southerner, but I am ashamed of
my section,” he added warmly.</p>

<p>Briggs said nothing, but a dark, dull
red spread slowly to the very roots of his
hair, Presently Aubrey broke the painful
silence.</p>

<p>“Briggs, I think I can help you."</p>

<pb facs="p194"/>

<p>“How ?”</p>

<p>“There’s an expedition just about starting 
from England for Africa; its final
destination is, I believe, the site of ancient
Ethiopian cities; its object to unearth
buried cities and treasure which the shifting 
sands of Sahara have buried for centuries. 
This expedition lacks just such a
medical man as you; the salary is large,
but you must sign for two years; that is
my reason for not mentioning it before.
It bids fair to be a wonderful venture and
there will be plenty of glory for those
who return, beside the good it will do to
the Negro race if it proves the success in
discovery that scholars predict. I don't
advise you to even consider this opportunity, 
but you asked for my help and this
is all I can offer at present.”</p>

<p>“But Dianthe!” exclaimed Reuel faintly.</p>

<p>“Yes,” smiled Aubrey. “Don’t I know
how I would feel if it were Molly and I
was in your place? You are like all other
men, Reuel. Passion does not calculate,
and therein lies its strength. As long as
common sense lasts we are not in love.
Now the answer to the question of ways
and means is with you; it is in your
hands. You will choose love and poverty 
I suppose; I should. There are people 
fools enough to tell a man in love to
keep cool. Bah! It is an impossible thing.”</p>

<p>“Does true love destroy our reasoning
faculties ?” Reuel asked himself as he sat
there in silence after his friend ceased
speaking. He felt then that he could not
accept this offer. Finally he got upon his
feet, still preserving his silence, and made
ready to leave his friend. When he
reached the door, he turned and said: “I
will see you in the morning.”</p>

<p>For a long time after Briggs had gone,
Aubrey sat smoking and gazing into the
glowing coals that filled the open grate.</p>

<p>All that night Reuel remained seated in
his chair or pacing the cheerless room,
conning ways and means to extricate himself 
from his dilemma without having recourse 

to the last extremity proposed by
Aubrey. It was a brilliant opening;
there was no doubt of that; a year&#8212;six
months ago&#8212;he would have hailed it with
delight, but if he accepted it, it would
raise a barrier between his love and him
which could not be overcome&#8212;the ocean
and thousands of miles.</p>

<p>“Oh, no!” he cried, “a thousand times
no! Rather give up my ambitions.”</p>

<p>Then growing more rational he gazed
mournfully around the poor room and
asked himself if he could remain and see
his wife amid such surroundings? That
would be impossible. The question then,
resolved itself into two parts: If he remained 
at home, they could not marry,
therefore separation; if he went abroad,
marriage and separation. He caught at
the last thought eagerly. If then they
were doomed to separate, of two evils
why not choose the least? The African
position would at least bind them irrevocably 
together. Instantly hope resumed 
its sway in Reuel’s breast so fertile
is the human mind in expedients to calm
the ruffled spirit; he began to estimate
the advantages he would gain by accepting 
the position: He could marry
Dianthe, settle a large portion of his
salary upon her thus rendering her independent 
of charity, leave her in the care
of the Vance family, and return in two
years a wealthy man no longer fearing
poverty. He had never before builded
golden castles, but now he speculated upon 
the possibility of unearthing gems and
gold from the mines of ancient Meroe
and the pyramids of Ethiopia. In the
midst of his fancies he fell asleep. In the
morning he felt a wonderful relief as he
contemplated his decision. Peace had returned 
to his mind. He determined to
see Aubrey at once and learn all the particulars 
concerning the expedition. Providentially, 
Aubrey was just sitting down
to breakfast and over a cup of steaming
coffee Reuel told his decision, ending with
these words: “Now, my dear Aubrey, it

<pb facs="p195"/>

may be the last request I may ever ask
of you, tor who can tell what strange adventures 
may await me in that dark and
unknown country to which Fate has
doomed me?”</p>

<p>Livingston tried to remonstrate with
him.</p>

<p>“I know what I am saying. The
climate is murderous, to begin with, and
there are many other dangers. It is better 
to be prepared. I have no friend but
you.”</p>

<p>“Between us, Reuel, oaths are useless;
you may count upon my loyalty to all your
interests,” said Aubrey with impressiveness.</p>

<p>“I shall ask you to watch over Dianthe.
I intrust her to you as I would intrust her
to my brother, had I one. This is all I
ask of you when I am in that far country.”</p>

<p>With open brow, clear eyes and grave
face, Aubrey Livingston replied in solemn
tones:</p>

<p>“Reuel, you may sail without a fear.
Molly and I will have her with us always
like a dear sister.”</p>

<p>Hand clasped in hand they stood a moment 
as if imploring heaven’s blessing on
the solemn compact. Then they turned
the conversation on the business of securing 
the position at once.</p>

<p>Chapter VIII.</p>

<p>Reuel was greatly touched during the
next three months by the devotion of his
friend Livingston, whose unselfishness in
his behalf he had before had cause to
notice. Nor was this all; he seemed
capable of any personal sacrifice that the
welfare of Briggs demanded.</p>

<p>Before many days had passed he had
placed the young man in direct communication 
with the English officials in charge
of the African expedition, The salary
was most generous; in fact, all the arrangements 
were highly satisfactory.
Whatever difficulties really existed
melted, as it were, before Aubrey’s influence, 

and Reuel would have approached
the time of departure over a bed of roses
but for the pain of parting with Dianthe.</p>

<p>At length the bustle of graduation was
over. The last article of the traveler's
outhit was bought. The morning of the
day of departure was to see the ceremony
performed that would unite the young
people for life. It was a great comfort to
Reuel that Charlie Vance. had decided to
join the party as a tourist for the sake of
the advantages of such a trip.</p>

<p>The night before their departure Aubrey 
Livingston entertained the young
men at dinner in his rooms along with a
number of college professors and other
learned <sic>savans</sic>. The most complimentary
things were said of Reuel in the after-dinner 
toasts, the best of wishes were
uttered together with congratulations on
the marriage of the morrow for they all
admired the young enthusiast. His superiority 
was so evident that none disputed 
it; they envied him, but were not
jealous. The object of their felicitations
smiled seldom.</p>

<p>“Come, for heaven sake shake off your
sadness; he the happy groom upon whom
Tortune, fickle jade, has at last consented
to smile,” cried Adonis. So, amid laughter 
and jest, the night passed and the morrow came.</p>

<p>After his guests had departed, Aubrey
Livingston went to the telegraph office
and sent a message:</p>

<p>“To Jim Titus,<lb/>
“Laurel Hill, Virginia:&#8212;<lb/>
“Be on hand at the New York dock,
Trans-Atlantic Steamship Co., on the
first. I will be there to make things right
for you. Ten thousand if you succeed the
first six months.</p>

<p>"A. L."</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>It was noon the next day and the newly 
wedded stood with clasped hands uttering 
their good-byes.</p>

<p>“You must not be unhappy, dear. The
time will run by before you know it, and

<pb facs="p196"/>

I shall be with you again. Meanwhile
there is plenty to occupy you. You have
Molly and Aubrey to take you about. But
pray remember my advice,&#8212;don't attempt 
too much; you're not strong by
any means.”</p>

<p>“No, I am not strong!” she interrupted
with a wild burst of tears. “Reuel, if you
knew how weak I am you would not leave
me.”</p>

<p>Her husband drew the fair head to his
bosom, pressing back the thick locks with
a lingering lover’s touch.</p>

<p>“I wish to God I could take you with
me," he said tenderly after a silence.
Dear girl, you know this grief of yours
would break my heart, only that it shows
how well you love me. I am proud of every 
tear.” She looked at him with
expression he could not read; it was full
of unutterable emotion&#8212;love, anguish,
compassion.</p>

<p>“Oh,” she said passionately, “nothing
remains long with us but sorrow and regret. 
Every good thing may be gone 
tomorrow&#8212;lost! Do you know, I sometimes 
dream or have waking visions of a
past time in my life? But when I try to
grasp the fleeting memories they leave me
groping in darkness. Can’t you help me
Reuel?”</p>

<p>With a laugh he kissed away her
anxieties, although he was dismayed to
know that at most any time full memory
might return. He must speak to Aubrey.
Then he closed her lips with warm lingering 
kisses.</p>

<p>"Be a good girl and pray for your husband’s 
safety, that God may let us meet
again and be happy! Don’t get excited.
That you <hi rend="italics">must</hi> guard against.”</p>

<p>And Reuel Briggs, though his eyes
were clouded with tears, was a happy man
at heart that day. Just that once he
tasted to the full all that there is of happiness 
in human life. Happy is he who is
blessed with even <hi rend="italics">one</hi> perfect day in a
lifetime of sorrow. His last memory of
her was a mute kiss and a low “God bless

you," broken by a sob. And so they
parted.</p>

<p>In the hall below Molly Vance met him
with a sisterly kiss for good-bye; outside
in the carriage sat Mr. Vance, Sr., Charlie
and Aubrey waiting to drive to the depot.</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>Reuel Briggs, Charlie Vance and their
servant, Jim Titus, sailed from New York
for Liverpool, England, on the first day
of July.</p>

<p> . . . . . . </p>

<p>The departure of the young men made
a perceptible break in the social circle at
Vance Hall. Mr. Vance buried himself
in the details of business and the two
girls wandered disconsolately about the
house and grounds attended by Livingston, 
who was at the Hall constantly
and pursued them with delicate attentions.</p>

<p>By common consent it was determined
that no summer exodus could be thought
of until after the travellers had reached
August, all being well, they would seek
the limit of civilized intercourse in Africa.
While waiting, to raise the spirits of the
family, it was decided to invite a house
party for the remainder of July, and in
the beauties of Bar Harbor. Soon gaiety
and laughter filled the grand old rooms;
the days went merrily by.</p>

<p>Two men were sitting in the billiard 
room lounging over iced punch. Light,
perfumed and golden, poured from the
rooms below upon the summer night, and
the music of a waltz made its way into
the darkness.</p>

<p>"What an odd fish Livingston has
grown to be,” said one, relighting a thin,
delicate-looking cigar. “I watched him
out of curiosity a while ago and was
struck at the change in him.”</p>

<p>“Ah!” drawled the other sipping the
cooling beverage. “Quite a Priuli on the
whole, eh?”</p>

<p>“Y-e-s! Precisely. And I have fancied
that the beautiful Mrs. Briggs is his
Clarisse. What do you think? She 

<pb facs="p197"/>

shudders every time he draws near, and sinks
to the ground under the steady gaze of
his ye. Odd, isn’t it?”</p>

<p>“Deucedly odd! About to marry Miss
Vance, isn’t he?”</p>

<p>“That don’t count. Love is not always
legitimate. If there’s anything in it, it is
only a flirtation probably; that’s the
style.”</p>

<p>“What you say is true, Skelton. Let’s
drink the rest of this stuff and go down
again. I know we're missed already.”</p>

<p>When they had swallowed the punch
and descended, the first person they saw
was Livingston leaning against the door
of the salon. His face was abstracted
and in dead repose, there lurked about the
corners of his full lips implacable resolution. 
The waltz was ended.</p>

Some interminable argument was go-
ing on, generally, about the room. Con-
versation progressed in sharp, brisk sen-
tences, which fell from the lips like the
dropping shots of sharpshooters. There
was a call for music. Molly mentally cal-
culated her available talent and was about
to give up the idea and propose something
else, when she was amazed to see Dianthe
rise hurriedly from her seat on an otto-
man, go to the piano unattended and sit
down. Unable to move with astonish-
ment she watched in fascination the slen-
der white fingers flash over the keys.
There was a strange rigid appearance
about the girl that was unearthly. Never
once did she raise her eves. At the first
sharp treble note the buzz in the room
was hushed at stillness. Livingston
moved forward and rested his arm upon
the piano fastening his gaze upon the
singer’s quivering lips.

Slowly. tremulously at first, pealed

forth the notes:

“Go down, Moses, way down in Egypt's
land,
Tell ol’ Pharaoh, let my people g x0,’
Scarcely was the verse begun when ev-
ery person in the room started suddenly

197

and listened with eager interest. As the
air proceeded, some grew visibly pale,
and not daring to breathe a syllable,
looked horrified into each other’s faces.
“Great heaven!” whispered Mr. Vance to
his daughter, “do you not hear another
voice beside Mrs. Briggs’ ?”

it was true, indeed. A weird contralto,
veiled as it were, rising and falling upon
every wave of the great soprano, and
reaching the ear as irom some strange
distance. The singer sang on, her voice
dropping sweet and low, the echo follow-
ing it, and at the closing word, she fei!
back i in a dead faint. Mr. Vance caught
her in his arms.

“Mrs. Briggs has the soul of an artiste.
She would make a perfect prima donna
for the Grand Opera,” remarked one man
to Molly.

“We are as surprised as anyone,’ re-
plied the young girl; “we never knew
that Mrs. Briggs was musical until this
evening. It is a delightful surprise.”

They carried her to the quiet, cool li-
brary away from the glaring hghts and
the excitement, and at her request left her
there alone. Her thoughts were painful.

Memory had returned in full save as to

her name. She knit her brow in painful
thought, finally leaning back among her
cushions wearily, too puzzled for further
thought. Presently a step paused besice
her chair. She looked up into Living-
ston’s face. |

“Are you feeling better?” he asked,
gently taking in his slender wrist and
counting the pulse-beats.

Instead of answering his question, she
began abruptly: “Mr. Livingston, Reuel
told me to trust you implicitly. Can you
and will you tell me what has happened

‘to me since last I sang the song I have

sung here tonight? I try to recall the
past, but all is confusion and mystery, It
makes my head ache so to think.”

Livingston suddenly drew closer to
her.

caw

</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
