<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0267">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from the Minister of the Colonies in Brussels to Minister, January 24, 1911</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0267</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from the Minister of the Colonies in Brussels to Minister</title>
<date when="1911-01-24">January 24, 1911</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 122</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Broeder</term>
<term>Clark</term>
<term>Count of Buisseret</term>
<term>King Albert</term>
<term>King Leopold II</term>
<term>Richards</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Banana</term>
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Brussels</term>
<term>Central Africa</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Coquilhatville</term>
<term>Eala</term>
<term>Leopoldville</term>
<term>Matadi</term>
<term>Washington</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>American</term>
<term>Belgian</term>
<term>English</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Protestant</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName/>
<roleName>Minister of the Colonies in Brussels</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels</placeName>
<date when="1911-01-24"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Minister</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-25" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information</change>
<change when="2018" who="sab">translated</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.001.jpg"/>

<p> Ministère 
des
Affaires Étrangères<lb/>
Direction P No. CI<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse les numéros
le litta de la Direction ainsi que la date.<lb/>
1 Annexe</p>
    
<p>Bruxelles, le 24 janvier 1911</p>
    
<p>Monsieur le Ministre,</p>

<p>Je vous si fait parvenir, le 23 Décembre dernier,
la copie d'un rapport du 22 Novembre précédent par lequel le
Ministre du Roi a Washington me faisait part de conversations
qu'il avait eues avec les missionnaires américains Clark et
Richards.</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous communiquer, sous ce pli, 
la traduction d'une lettre qu'a la date du 14 Décembre 1910
de Révérend M. Clark a adressée au Comte de Buisseret.</p>
    
<p>Ce dernier a été autorisé par une autre lettre
du même missionnaire a faire tel usage qu'il croirait
convenable du document ci-joint.</p>
    
<p>J'estime, Monsieur le Ministre, qu'il y aurait
avantage à donner le plus tôt possible une large publicité
aux déclarations de M. Clark. Si vous partagez cette manière
de voir, je communiquerai à la Presse le texte de sa lettre
au Comte de Buisseret.</p>
    
<p>Je vous prie de me fair connaître votre sentiment 
le plus tôt possible.</p>

<p><unclear></unclear></p>
    
<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Ministre des Colonies, 
Bruxelles</fw>    

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.002.jpg"/>

<p>Légation de Belgique
à Washington.</p>

<p>Traduction-COPIE.</p>
    
<p>Office of 
The Battle Creek Sanatorium<lb/>
Battle Creek, Michigan,<lb/>
14 décembre 1910.</p>
    
<p>Le Comte Conrad de Buisseret,
Envoyé Extraordinaire et Ministre Plénipotentiaire
de S.M. le Roi des Belges près les Etats-Unis d'Amérique.</p>

<p>Excellence,</p>
    
<p>Avant mon embarquement d'Amérique pour l'Afrique Centrale,
au printemps de cette année, vous m'avez demandé de vous faire savoir,
si possible, s'il existait encore les mêmes motifs de plainte
que j'avais, en ma qualité de missionnaire, allégués contre l'administration
de l'Etat Indépendant du Congo sous feu Sa Majesté le
Roi Léopold II.</p>
    
<p>J'ai maintenant grand plaisir à vous faire un bref
rapport.</p>
    
<p>Vous vous rappellerez que je devais voyager en compagnie
de quatre gentlemen américains qui devaient visiter, sur le
Congo, autant de stations de missions que possible pendant le court
laps de temps dont ils disposaient.</p>
    
<p>Nous avons passé huit semaines dans la Colonie belge
et visité 21 établissements de missionnaires, où nous avons rencontré
des hommes et des femmes de cinq nationalités et de sept sociétés 
religieuses protestantes différentes.</p>
    
<p>Trois des missions représentées étaient américaines.</p>

<p>Nous avons parcouru 800 milles en remontant la rivière
du Congo, et visité certains districts où, sous l'ancien régime, les
plaintes contre le Gouvernement étaient des incidents quotidiens. 
Nous avons fait de courts voyages à pied et visité des villages <fw type="catch">indigènes</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.003.jpg"/>

indigènes insolés, et certains d'entre eux étaient dans la région qui
était autrefois le théâtre de raids pour le caoutchouc, et d'où émanaient
beaucoup des récits de cruautés que j'ai racontés dans le 
passé.</p>

<p>Dans tout ce voyage, et dans mes rencontres avec tant de
missionnaires qui s'exprimaient franchement, et avec des containes
d'indigènes dont je connais bien les idiomes, je n'ai pas vu une
seule chose qui fît même penser à la continuation d'atrocités, d'agissements
cruels ou injustes de la part des fonctionnaires actuels
de l'Etat envers les indigènes.</p>

<p>Je n'ai entendu de la part, ni de blancs, ni de noirs,
aucune allusion à une continuation de l'ancien état de choses dans
la colonie.</p>
    
<p>Mais ce que j'ai entendu, c'est que de grands changements
avaient été apportés dans l'administration, et que ces changements
avaient introduit des conditions favorables pour les missionnaires
blancs et aussi pour le noir ignorant. (untutored).</p>

<p>Je ne puis parler que pour les districts visités par nous;
mais dans ceux-ci j'ai trouvé que la clameur contre le travail
forcé avait cessé, grâce aux changements déjà apportés à l'administration.</p>
    
<p>Même à l'égard du missionnaire, il semblait que la façon
d'agir et l'attitude des fonctionnaires se fussent modifiées. Je
crois que le missionnaire protestant n'est plus regardé comme un
ennemi et un espion, mais comme un ami honnête et franc.</p>
    
<p>En entrant dans des villages isolés, nous avons trouvé que 
les indigènes ne s'enfuyaient plus et ne se cachaient plus, comme
ils l'eussent fait il y a trois ans. La confiance dans le blanc et <fw type="catch">dans</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.004.jpg"/>

dans ses lois est maintenant en train d' être rétablie. Nous avons
trouvé l'indigène occupé près de sa maison. De nouvelles habitations
étaient en construction. Des jardins plus grands et plus beaux étaient
en culture. La paix règne maintenant, ainsi que la confiance, où la
guerre et le trouble régnaient autrefois. Ces changements sont dûs, sans
aucun doute, aux lois meilleures imposées au peuple par S.M. le Roi
Albert et le Parlement belge.</p>
    
<p>Je suis certain également, que ces changements sons permanents
et que les promesses d'une amélioration encore plus étendue
seront accomplies aussitôt que le "mécanisme de l'Etat" pourra entreprendre
sa tâche terriblement difficile. Lorsqu'on songe aux grandes
distances qui doivent être atteintes par l'administration, et à l'absence
de facilités par télégraphe et par chemin de fer dans la plus
grande partie de la colonie, on commence à comprendre comment il doit
y avoir un certain délai. Un ordre édicté par le Gouverneur Général
à Boma peut facilement prendre six semaines, et dans certaines saisons
de l'année, au moins deux mois, pour atteindre beaucoup des postes
isolés.</p>
    
<p>C'est avec très grand intérêt que nous avons visité l'établissement
agricole d’expériences à Eala, sur le Haut Congo. Nous avons
été enchantés de l'instruction donnée en jardinage pratique et scientifique
aux jeunes indigènes de la région.</p>
    
<p>Nous avons vu quelque chose de l'oeuvre en cours, en ce qui
concerne la bactériologie et l'étude générale de maladies tropicales
à Léopoldville, où l'admirable et patient docteur Broeder à pendant de
nombreuses années, rendu de splendides services à tous venants.</p>
    
<p>Nous avons visité les écoles du Gouvernement à Boma, et
avons trouvé que ce que nous avons vu là était un splendide commence- <fw type="catch">ment,</fw>

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.005.jpg"/>

commencement, plein de promesses pour le développement de l'indigène.</p>
    
<p>Nous avons passé quelque temps à examiner les stations
de l'Etat à Banana, Boma, Matadi, Léopoldville et Coquilhatville,
et dans aucune nous n'avons rien vu qui pût choquer, en ce qui
concerne le Gouvernement. Nous avons vu beaucoup de choses destinées
à relever l'indigène, principalement l'éducation industrielle
donnée dans ces centres à un grand nombre de jeunes gens.</p>
    
<p>Je viens d'apprendre cette semaine d'un de mes amis,
missionnaires anglais, qu'un nouvel emplacement pour une station
a été accordé à sa mission. Ceci détruit un des sujets de plainte 
sérieux élevés jusqu'à présent par les missionnaires protestants.</p>
    
<p>J'ai le grand plaisir à ajouter que des entrevues
très agréables nous ont été accordées par le Ministre des Colonies
à Bruxelles et par le Gouverneur Général du Congo à Boma.</p>
    
<p>Espérant que ce court récit de notre voyage et de ce
que nous avons vu et entendu intéressera Votre Excellence, je 
reste,</p>
    
<p>Votre humble serviteur,<lb/>
(signé/Joseph Clark.</p>

</div1>
   

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.001.jpg"/>
        
<p> Minister 
of
Foreign Affairs<lb/>
Direction P No. CI<lb/>
Reminding int he response the numbers
in the Direction and the date.<lb/>
1 Annex</p>
        
<p>Brussels, January 24, 1911</p>
        
<p>Mr. Minister,</p>
        
<p>I asked that you be sent, on the 23rd of last December,
the copy of a report from the 22nd of that previous November by which the 
Minister of the King in Washington had me report on the conversations
that he had had with the American missionaries Clark and 
Richards.</p>
        
<p>I have the honor to communicate herewith, 
the translation of a letter from December 14, 1910 
from the Reverend Mr. Clark addressed to the Comte de Buisseret.</p>
        
<p>The latter has been authorized by another letter 
from the same missionary to make such use that he believes
acceptable from the enclosed document.</p>
        
<p>I estimate, Mr. Minister, that it would be
advantageous to give publicity as soon as possible 
about the declarations from Mr. Clark. If you share this 
view, I will communicate to the Press the text of your letter 
from the Comte de Buisseret.</p>
        
<p>I would as you to let me know your thoughts  
as soon as possible.</p>

<p><unclear></unclear></p>
        
<fw type="footer">Mr. Minister of Colonies,
Brussels</fw>       

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.002.jpg"/>

<p> Belgian Legation 
in Washington</p>

<p>Translation-COPY.</p>
    
<p>Office of 
The Battle Creek Sanatorium
Battle Creek, Michigan,
the 14th of December 1910.</p>
    
<p>Count Conrad of Buisseret,
Extraordinary Envoy and Minister Plenipotentiary
of S.M. the Belgian King near the United States of America.</p>

<p>Your Excellence,</p>
    
<p>Before my departure to America for Central Africa,
in the spring of this year, you asked me to let you know,
if possible, if the same grounds of complaint that I had 
still existed, in my capacity as a missionary, alleged against the administration
of the Independent State of the Congo during the reign of His Majesty the 
King Léopold II.</p>
    
<p>I now have the great pleasure to give you a brief 
report.</p>
    
<p>You recall that I had to travel in the company 
of four American gentlemen who had to visit, in the
Congo, just as many stations de missions as possible during the short lapse
of time in which they were available..</p>
    
<p>We spent eight weeks in the Belgian Colony 
and visited 21 missionary establishments, where we met 
men and women of five nationalities and seven different 
protestant religious societies.</p>
    
<p>Three of the representative missions were American.
We crossed 800 miles sailing back up the Congo
river, and visited certain districts where, under the ancient regime, the
complaints against the government were of incidents relating to daily life. 
We made the short voyage by foot and visited the villages
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.003.jpg"/>    
    
sunbathed natives, and certain amongst themselves were in the region that 
was formerly the theater of raids for the rubber, and where 
a lot of stories of cruelty come from that I have related in the 
pass.</p>

<p>Throughout this voyage, and in my encounters with many 
missionnairies who expressed frankly, and with des containes
of natives of which I know the idioms well, I haven't seen a 
single thing that makes me think the same of the continuation of atrocities, 
cruel or injust from the current government officers 
of State towards the natives.</p>

<p>I did not hear from, neither the whites, nor the blacks,
any illusion to a continuation of the ancient state of things in
the coloney.</p>
    
<p> But that which I heard, it's that these big changes 
have been brought in the administration, and that these changes
have introduced favorable conditions for the white 
missionaries and also for the untutored black. (untutored).</p>

<p>I cannot speak for the visited districts by us;
but in these I found that the clamor against the forced
work had ceased, thanks to the changes aready apporés to the administration.</p>
    
<p>Even the missionary's regard, it seems that the way
the governement officials act and their attitude was altered. I
believe that the Protestant missionary is no longer lookd at 
as an enemy, but more like an honest and frank friend. </p>
    
<p> By entering into these secluded villages, we found that
the natives no longer run away or hide, as if 
ils l'eussent fait il y a trois ans. La confiance dans le blanc

<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.004.jpg"/>
    
in these laws is now in the middle of being re-established. We 
found the native occupied near their house. The new dwellings 
were in construction. The biggest and most beautiful gardens were
in the process of growing. Peace reigns now, along with confidence, where the
war and the trouble once reigned. These changes sons dûs, without
any doubt, these better laws imposed on the people by S.M. the King
Albert and the Belgian Parliament.</p>
    
<p>I am also certain, that these changes are permanent
and that the promises of another improvement which is more extensive
will be accomplished as soon as the mechanism of State can begin 
the terribly difficult task. When one dreams of these great
distances that must be reached by the administration, and in the absence
of ease by telegraph and by the iron track in the  
biggest part of the colony, one starts to comprehend how there 
must be some delay. A decreed order by the Governor General
of Boma can easily take six weeks, and in some seasons during the year, at least two months, to reach a lot of isolated postal services.</p>
    
<p> It's with great interest that we visited the agricultural 
establishment of experiments in Eala, on the Haut Congo. We were 
enchanted by the given instruction in the gardening practice and science 
to the native boys in the region.</p>
    
<p> We saw something of <unclear></unclear> in disarray, in regards 
to microbiology and the general study of tropical sicknesses 
in Léopoldville, where the <unclear>amirable</unclear> and patient doctor Broeden for 
numerous years, render splendid services to all coming.</p>
    
<p>We visited the Boma Government schools and 
found that that which we saw <unclear></unclear> was splendid
    
<pb n="teaa.fr.letter.0267.005.jpg"/>
    
beginning, full of promise for the development of the native. </p>
    
<p>We spent some time examining the stations 
of State in Banana, Boma, Matadi, Léopoldville, and Coquilhatville,
and in no way we have nothing seen that can shock, in that which 
concerns the Government. We saw a lot of things intended for
raising the natives, primarily industrial education 
given in these centers at a big number of young people.</p>
    
<p>I just learned this week from one of my friends, 
an English missionary, that a new place for a station 
was granted to his mission. That destroys one of the subjects of serious, 
high complaint so far by the protestant missionaries.</p>
    
<p>I have the great pleasure of adding that these very agreeable 
glimpses we were accorded by the Minister of Colonies 
in Brussels and by the Governor General of Congo in Boma. </p>
    
<p>Hoping that this short account of our voage and that 
what we saw and heard interested Your Excellence, I
remain,</p>
    
<p>Your humble servant,
(Signed/Joseph Clark.</p>
    
</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
