<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0933">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader, November 11, 1876</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0933</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1876-11-11">November 11, 1876</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Tarbell, J.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>New York</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>St. Louis (Missouri)</placeName>
<date when="1876-11-11"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66848474">Cadwalader, John L. (John Lambert), 1836-1914</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1876-11-16"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-08" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1086.jpg"/>

<note><sic>Seperate</sic></note>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Republic of Liberia<lb/>
J Milton Turner<lb/>
to the<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington U.S.A.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Referring to the instruction of the Department as communicated through a despatch dated October 16th 1876.; and referring to quarterly accounts.</p>

<p>Enclosures:</p>

<p>No. 1. Copy of letter from Comptroller's office relating to the adjustment of accounts</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1087.jpg"/>

<note><sic>Seperate</sic></note>

<p>St Louis Missouri 11. November 1876.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the Department's unnumbered despatch dated 16. October 1876; and, referring to the unsatisfactory stall in which my accounts for the quarter ended June 30th. 1876., appear to have been rendered, and returning to me for correction my accounts for the quarter mentioned. It is proper that I should inform the Department that that despatch was not received by me until the eighth instant; and, that this delay is to be accounted for through my absence from St. Louis, in the interior of Missouri, until my return hither on the morning of the seventh instant. I am directed, in the communication to which I am now
<catchwords>replying,</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable, John L. Cadwalader,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1088.jpg"/>

replying to prepare as soon as practicable, on a form sent to me in July last, a new account for salary and contingent expenses. Being at this time absent from my post, and therefore without the form alluded to, as well as without a copy of the Regulations from which I might otherwise <unclear extent="one word"/> a copy of said form. I have left to me only to express my regret for the delay which must ensue from my necessity to request the Department to furnish me through the mail with a few copies of that form, to the end that I may obey the instruction <sic>refered</sic> to. I have noticed with great care and concern the tenor and specialties of the instruction herein <sic>refered</sic> to; as well as the several portions thereof to which the Department has the more particularly directed my attention. And, after first expressing my sincere regret for the confused unpresentable condition in which the reports in 
<catchwords>question</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1089.jpg"/>

question reached the Department I hasten to offer my <sic>assurrances</sic> that no such untoward circumstance shall happen in the future during my incumbency of the office with which I am at present entrusted. Indeed, it would seem proper that I should explain, that on account of my protracted illness in Africa, (of which the Department is aware) I was sometimes necessitated to employ clerical assistance to the end that my reports and correspondence might be forwarded at the time designated by the requirements of the Regulations: and, that my report of the 30. June 1876., was, therefore, not made up by myself – as is <sic>apparrent</sic> from the hand writing employed thereupon. That report, as is true of a few others, was prepared and sent forward during the lucid intervals of delirium from which I was, at the time, suffering on account of the inhospitable effect of 
<catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1090.jpg"/>

the African climate upon my general health. With reference to my drafts for salary having been frequently drawn for a less time than one month as is expected by the Department will not be the case, I have, respectfully, to state: that the general currency in use in Liberia is composed almost altogether of foreign drafts and United States greenbacks; and, while it is true that under a provision of the Regulations I am instructed to draw on the Department for loss by exchange of drafts drawn by me on Government, the same instruction expresses the Department's desire that officers abroad should avoid paying unreasonable or <sic>exhorbitant</sic> rates for the exchange of their drafts. While the next preceeding statement is true, it is equally so, that by drawing my drafts for small sums as they fall due from me I am able, when in Liberia, both to avoid the <sic>exhorbitant</sic>
<catchwords>prices</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1091.jpg"/>

prices which I should otherwise be obliged to pay for loss by exchange on my drafts of larger denominational gold value, and to place my drafts in circulation, like other foreign gold drafts, as a kind of currency; thereby avoiding, as may have been noticed by the Department, in a great majority of cases all loss by exchange of my drafts. Indeed, in many instances when my drafts were for small sums, I have been able to find like sums of United States greenbacks at Monrovia, for which I have been able to sell my drafts at a premium of from seven to eight per cent to parties doing business with houses at New York. By careful management I have been able in that country where the financial system is crowded with inconveniences and uncertainties to bring my drafts to be more sought for than those of any other person; meanwhile
<catchwords>I</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1092.jpg"/>

I have had a care that my drafts should not be presented to the Department for sums in excess of the amount due to me. I have deemed this explanation necessary to the end that I may not be regarded as having behaved carelessly or indifferently in this matter of drawing my drafts. The remarks of the Department upon this point elicits from me expressions of regret for whatsoever inconvenience my course may have caused, and of assurance of my endeavor in the future to observe the instruction I have received with reference to this point. With reference to the trouble and doubt which has been experienced in the adjustment of my accounts, it is, perhaps, not amiss for me to enclose herewith, marked No. 1., a copy of a letter that was kindly granted to me from the officer of the comptroller, <del>and</del> which shows that all differences in my

<catchwords>accounts</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1093.jpg"/>

accounts for the last fiscal year are nominal, with the exception in favor of Government, of twenty dollars and eighty one cents; and, those differences I have no doubt, as remarked by Mr. Tarbell, will disappear when my accounts shall have reached the Comptroller's office. It only remains for me to disclaim all intention to be, or even to seem careless in reference to the above or other duties of my post, and to repeat my assurances of increased care and attention in future in the preparation of my accounts.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be/<lb/>
Sir:<lb/>
With high considerations and esteem/<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J Milton Turner</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1094.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Inclosure No. 1.</note>

<fw type="letterhead">Treasury Department,<lb/>
First Comptroller's Office.</fw>

<p>Washington, D.C., October 9, 1876.</p>

<p>Hon. J. Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Your account of Salary and Contingent Expenses, for the quarter ending September 30, 1875, has been adjusted per Report No. 79,647, and a balance found due from you to the United States of $3119.48<lb/>
Balance per your account, 0.00<lb/>
Difference, $3119.48.</p>

<p>Thus accounted for:</p>

<p>Balance admitted due to the United States in your Contingent Account, for 3d quarter, 1874, $29.21, not thereafter brought forward by you, less amount credited in your present account current ($20.50) as said balance; leaving still outstanding on account of said balance $8.71
<catchwords>Forward</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1095.jpg"/>

Brought Forward $8.71</p>

<p>Overcharge for Salary for the fractional quarter ending March 31, 1875, as advised October 5, 1875. 11.10</p>

<p>Short credit of draft of March 31, 1875, as $42.23 instead of $43.23, as advised October 5, 1875. 1.00</p>

<p>Total amount of outstanding difference to June 30, 1875. $20.81</p>

<p>The following drafts on the Secretary of State, paid and charged to you in this adjustment, but not yet credited in your account; since the same belong to your Accounts for Salary and Contingent Expenses subsequent to September 30, 1875, viz:</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Draft</unclear> dated October 11, 1875. For Contgt. Exps.</cell>
<cell>100.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 12 " " Salary</cell>
<cell>25.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 16 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>25.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 19 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>48.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 24 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>70.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " November 2 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>50.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 2 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>52.50</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 4 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>40.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>$412.38</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Forward</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$20.81</cell>
</row>

<pb n="Roll3-1096.jpg"/>

<row>
<cell>Brought forward</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$20.81</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" "</cell>
<cell>$412.38</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Draft dated November 25, 1875. For Salary</cell>
<cell>200.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 26, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>200.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " December 14, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>95.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>175.35</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31 " " Contgt. Exps.</cell>
<cell>37.50</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31 " " Do.</cell>
<cell>44.36</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " January 14, 1876. " Salary</cell>
<cell>50.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 28, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>71.93</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 28, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>100.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " February 15, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>175.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " March 1, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>50.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 2, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>150.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 12, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>95.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>125.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>159.55</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 31, " " Contgt. Exps.</cell>
<cell>58.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " April 20, " " Salary</cell>
<cell>93.50</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 21, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>90.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Forward</cell>
<cell>$2382.57</cell>
<cell>$20.81</cell>
</row>

<pb n="Roll3-1097.jpg"/>

<row>
<cell>Brought Forward</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$20.81</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" "</cell>
<cell>$2382.57</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Draft dated April 22, 1876. For Salary</cell>
<cell>50.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 22, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>33.60</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 30, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>27.50</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " May 6, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>60.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 20, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>175.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " June 8, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>40.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 15, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>30.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 27, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>100.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>" " " 30, " " Do.</cell>
<cell>200.00</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table>

<p><unclear>Total</unclear> amount of Drafts charged herein, but not credited, $3098.67</p>

<p>Difference Explained, $3119.48</p>

<p>The 1st. item ($8.71) of the above difference arises from your erroneously deducting said sum ($8.71) from the balance of $29.21, admitted as due from you to the United States on your Contingent Account for 3rd. quarter, 1874; and bringing forward in your present account $20.50 only, instead of $29.21. You claim that this difference of $8.71, is the Loss by Exchange

<pb n="Roll3-1098.jpg"/>

on your draft of September 30, 1874, for $87.16, on account of Contingent Expenses: Whereas said loss ($8.71) has already been charged by you in your Contingent Account for the 3rd. quarter of 1874, and allowed in the adjustment of the same per Report No. 75,093.</p>

<p>You will therefore credit said item of $8.71, to the United States in your next account of Salary and Contingent Expenses, also item No. 2, ($11.10), and item No. 3, ($1.00), as already directed in letter from this Office of October 5, 1875.</p>

<p>The 4th item ($3098.67) appears to be nominal, and will disappear when your accounts subsequent to September 30, 1875, shall have been received and adjusted, in which accounts the foregoing drafts now paid and charged to you, will, no doubt, be properly credited.</p>

<p>I am informed that said accounts, subsequent to September 30, 1875, have not

<pb n="Roll3-1099.jpg"/>

yet been received at this Department; and you are respectfully requested to render them promptly, in order that the existing difference may be removed.</p>

<p>I am,<lb/>
Very respectfully<lb/>
(signed) J. Tarbell<lb/>
Acting Comptroller.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>