<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0261">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Treaty, Sent from Henry Rider to William H. Seward, March 21, 1863</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0261</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to "To Enter Africa from America", made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Treaty, Sent from Henry Rider to William H. Seward, March 21, 1863</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1863-03-21">March 21, 1863</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>



<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Rider, Henry</persName>
<roleName>United States Consular Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<date when="1863-03-21"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Seward, William H.</persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washinton, D. C.</placeName>
<date when="1863-05-29"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw"> Encoding</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls"> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="64"/>

<ab>TREATY</ab>

<p>BETWEEN his Excellency Colonel Stephen John Hill C.B., Captain General and Governeor-in-Chief in and over the Colony of Sierra Leone and its Dependencies, and Vice Admiral thereof, for and on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland of the one part, and Alexander Bey Cantah, King of Quia Country, Nain Bannah, Bocarry Silly, Pa Mangee Ropee, Tom Needle, Pa Booboo, Soorie Coochie, Pa Savage, Diek London, John Mingo, Boom Warrah, Mangee Calemney, Cessey Queah, Pa Buenda, Rhuniah Booley, and Pa Sinney, Chiefs and Headmen of the Quiah Country of the other part.</p> 

<p>WHEREAS disputes have arisen between the Governer of Sierra Leone, and Alexander Bey Cantah and the Chiefs and Headmen above mentioned in consequence of attacks made by their War-men upon British Subjects, and upon the Island of Tombo, a Dependency of this Colony, and to punish which outrages the Governor of Sierra Leone had organized an Expedition, but Alexander Bey Cantah and the Chiefs and Headmen above mentioned having sued for peace, the contracting parties ave agreed upon the following Articles. </p>

<ab>ARTICLE I.</ab>

<p>King Alexander Bey Cantah and the Chiefs and Headmen above mentooned do hereby cede, surrender, give over and transfer from henceforth for ever unto Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, Her Heirs and Successors, the full entire, free and unlimited right, possession, dominion and sovereignty in and over all that piece or portion of the Quia Country measuring Ten miles in width from Waterloo and Calmunt Creeks to the Quia River or Creek, and Sixteen miles in length from the River Sierra Leone to the Ribbie River or thereabouts, and bounded on the West by Waterloo Creek and Calmunt Creek; on the East by Quiah River or Creek, (which empties itself into the Rokelle River at Ro Benkeah) by the Creek known as Ma Sungoh Creek, and by direct line running from the head of the said Ma Sungoh Creek; on the North by the Sierra Leone River; and on the South by the River Ribbie or Dibbie round to the entrance of Calmunt Creek, together with all and every right and title to the Navigation, Anchorage, Waterage, Bays, Waters, Rivers, Sea Coasts, Shores, Creeks and Inlets, Fishing and other Revenues and Maritime Claims, and all privileges appertaining to the same, which portion of the Quia land hereby ceded shall henceforth be annexed to, and be a Dependency of this Colony, and be subject to the Laws now in force and hereafter to be in force in this Colony. </p>

<ab>ARTICLE II.</ab>

<p>Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, in consideration of the cession hereby made of the above portion of the Quia country, agrees to pay unto Alexander Bey Cantah, King of Quia, his Successor and Sucessors, the sum of 2000 bars, or &#163; 100 yearly and every year.</p>

<ab>ARTICLE III.</ab>

<p>Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland hereby guarantees to the Native Inhabitants of the portion of the Quia country hereby ceded, the full, entire, and free possession of the lands they now hold, in the same manner as the other Inhabitants of the Colony.</p> 

<pb facs="65"/>
<fw>2</fw>
<ab>ARTICLE IV.</ab>

<p>The Towns of Ro Bagah, and Ro Baney, in their present dimensions, are expected from the cession of the portion of the Quia land hereby made. </p>

<ab>ARTICLE V. </ab>

<p>This Treaty shall be proclaimed immediately on its being concluded and signed, and be made Law throughout the Territories of Alexander Bey Cantah, and the Chiefs and Headmen above-mentioned. In witness whereof the contracting parties have signed the same, and have affixed their seals there to.</p> 

<p>Done at Sierra Leone, the Second day of April, in the year of our Lord One thousand eight hundred, and sixty-one.</p>

<ab>Stephen J. Hill (L.S.)<lb/>
Governor-in-Chief </ab>


<ab>Alexander Bey Cantah (L.S.)<lb/>
his X mark<lb/>
King of the Quia Country
</ab>
<ab>NAIN BANNAH. (L.S.)<lb/>
(Signed in Arabic.)</ab>


<ab>BOCARRY SILLY (L.S.)<lb/>
PA MAGEE ROPEE (L.S.)<lb/>
TOM NEEDLE (L.S.)<lb/>
PA BOO BOO (L.S.)<lb/>
SOORIE COOCHEE (L.S.)<lb/>
PA SAVAGE (L.S.)<lb/>
DICK LONDON (L.S.)<lb/>
JOHN MINGO (L.S.)<lb/>
their x marks</ab>


<ab>BOOM WARRAH (L.S.)<lb/>
her x mark</ab>


<ab>MANGEE CALEMNEY (L.S.)<lb/>
CESSEY QUEAH (L.S.)<lb/>
PA BUENDA (L.S.)<lb/>
RHUNIAH BOOLEY (L.S.)<lb/>
PA SINNEY (L.S.)<lb/>
their x marks</ab>

<ab>Witnesses to the Signatures<lb/>
JOHN CARR,<lb/>
Chief Justice.<lb/>
E.H., SIERRA LEONE<lb/>
A. FITZJAMES<lb/>
Queen's Advocate.<lb/>
GEO W. NICOL,<lb/>
Colonial Secretary.<lb/>
CHAS. HEDDLE ROBT. BRADSHAW Members of Council<lb/>
JOHN M'CORMACK</ab>

<pb facs="66"/>

<ab>U.S. Consulate
Sierra Leone
March 21, 1863
Enclosed copy of Treaty
Henry Rider
</ab>

<ab>Received at States <unclear>local</unclear> office May 29,1863</ab>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>