<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Civil Commandants Office
Balania, West Coast of Africa
6th March 1869

David C. Miller, late master of the American Barque Gem' stakes

On the morning of the 4th March I made the land coming from the soles-de-loss, which I afterwards found out to be that of the dolons of Orage bearing E.N.E. stare a bone of breakers and then altore any course and store to the south oare and Eastward at this timeI owes into fathoms Wates, after allowing and standing to the 5th and 6th I still found steal Water <unclear> unstol </unclear> the Vessel streak in 3 fathers after the had struck I saw at was hopeless to think of getting her off as the continued to be at into one fatherom I then (ordered) had the 2 beats codored and into whichI pick provisions and Water, the boat int which I got I had 3 mem, the ther boat under the Chief Officer had 25 sucars. The vessel struck about 9:30 a.m. and the weather was very thick after we left the vessel we all take that she was on fire. smoking coming out from about the Foremost and Kitchen afterward had placed about a 0/4 of a mile between the boats and the vessel, an explosion took place on board occasioned by the fire reaching the boarder infush was on board I had I think about 3 Tons of Powder onboard at the time of the fire, several explosions took place blowing the whole of the after part away, The main and Migenmasks going at the came hime. As at was out of all human power to do any good in staying, I gave the boats a course to steer by so that we could make the Soland of Bolania, which Incade about 3 o'clock on the afternoon of the 6th March 1869. The best under the charge of the Chief Officer has not yet come in, the last I saw of the Chief Officer's boat was about 6 p.m. on th 14th March 1869.

Signed and declared before th undersigned one of H.M. Justices of the Race and Civil Commandant of Bulamal.

Signed David C. Jultor
Lake Master of th Bargess "Gem"
"G.F. Linseath" AB
"E.J. Sones" AB
"John his Donald"
Mark

Signed "J. Craig Loggie"
S.P.

Ceorl Commandant Buloma

Witaeper

Signed "Alfred Walker Lewis"
Police Clark
"Abraham Edwards"
Polic Serpeant

"A True Copy"
Signed "J1869. Craig Loggie"
J.P.
Civil Commandant Buloma
