<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 
No. 8

U.S. Consulate at
Sierra Leone April 17th 1879

To
F.W. Seward 
Assistant Secretary of State

Sir
I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch No 10 with enclosures refering to the matter of Capt O'Brien of the American Brig "Annie and Lily" DC.

I am sorry to say that I cannot confirm Capt O'Brien statement throughout Ne did not come to my apothicny that and asked for his paper he, on his way to his cosignees, between 7 and 8 O'Cock A.M., in passing my ship, stoped and informed me that he would that day go <unclear/>.

I knowing that he could not clear from the Boston hives before 10 <unclear/> and that his object was that I should get his papers ready. I asked him what time would be ready to recieve the two seamen on board? He replied he would rather use the men at my office that I might give them orders that they were to work, as Consuls men were disposed to <unclear/> as spoil the crew, to when told to do any thing they would refuse". I accordingly sent for the men. Capt O'Brien returned about 1 OClock M, saw the men at my office, an "refused to take them, saying they were to sick to do anything on board of his ships." I admit they were a little sick, as they come to this Consulate under the effects of fever, but were able each day to walk to my office the distance of a quarter of a mile, when they wish to do so: my experience of nine years in the treatment of the African or Coast fever (4 years as Chief Physician in the American Colonization Hospital or <unclear/> in Liberia, and 5 years private practia on the coast) was sufficient for me to have concluded that a few days at sea would set-them right, as I have frequently sent patients suffering with African fever, to sea, with good results. 

Capt O'Brien after refusing to take then was asked for his papers, which I refused to give unless he consented to take them or give a written reason; this he also refused to do.

In his fit if exasperation he said that "the American laws governing American Merchant vessels were a swindle, and that it was a disgrace now a day to sail under that Flag; he would rather give one dollar and pay for each sailors offer than to be bothered with them." or words to this intent. This took place at the Consulate and not in my medical office.

Capt O'Brien left, and in a short time after the correspondence I sent in my dispatch No. 3 passed between us At 8 the next morning Capt O'Brien called at this Consulate and asked to be directed to the seamen boarding house on his wished to lake Dr. Smith to see the men for the purpos of getting a certificate  " I sent a boy to <unclear/> him their place, But did not take  Dr.Smith ashe  should have done, but but went to the house himself, and finding me of the men in bed with a chill insisted on their going to the doctor to beexamined. They refused sayingt hey were too sick to do so. Capt O'brin then informedme that the men had themselves admited that they were too sick to go to sea. I went to their room and asked them had they made such a statement as they said Yes." I then told the Capt that he could have his papers, to they were delivered to him that afternoon, as he had to <unclear/> his clearance from the Custom house first,which he didn't do until pm. As regards the statement made by Mrs. J Gray, I believe it to be true, and I am sorry she is too sick to enable me to obtain a written statement from her properly authenticated I do not believe Capt O'Brin wanted to take the men on board of his vessel, and after showing so much annoyance at being compelled to do so; I think the men were afraid to go with him particularly "Henry Miller, who said he kne him to be a bad man at sea" Capt O'Brin could have obtained (through his consigned) a certificate from Dr. Smith, <unclear/> as he wished it, I think most everyone  in town will admit this.

As regars to Capt remarks about my no being a regular Physician I am quite sue he can ge all the information  he desires on that subject by offering to the records of Harvard Medical School Boston Mass or Dartmouth

College of N.H.
Had these men be affected with contageoys disease,i would not have asked the Capt to take them but they were not this affected and in proof of this I inclose correspondence betweent he Colonial Surgeon, Dr.Smith and mysel on the subject. I beg to say in conclusion that the men are not too sick to go on board on the 21st Oct: for the distance fromtheir boarding place to the word is much shorter,than the distance to the Hospital, to which place they walked on the 23rd when they were admitted: the day Capt O'Briwn sailed. I havenot complaint to make of Capt O'Brin is private concluded; but as Capt of an American ship in this particular case his actions were very inhumane: and as I have adapted the polciy to inform the Department of all that occurs in this Consulate during my incumbeing, I felt it my duty to state the facts in this case just asthey occured

I have the honor to be
Sir
Your Obdt Servant
John A Parm U.S. Consul

Enclosure C Correspondence
between Collonia Surgeon, Dr.Smith and myself
