<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0264">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- DOCUMENT TITLE + DATE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Etienne to Under Secretary of State, August 14, 1889 --></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0264</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m"><!--DOCUMENT TITLE. EXAMPLE: Letter from Roncière Lenour to Mister Director of the Colonies--></title>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 122</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PEOPLE NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- ALPHABETIZED LIST OF ALL PLACES NAMED IN THE DOCUMENT. -->
<term><!-- EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT FROM --></placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName><!-- PLACE LETTER WAS SENT TO --></placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-11" who="kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">     

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0264.001.jpg"/>

<p>Ministère
des
Affaires Ètrangères<lb/>
Direction P No C I<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse les numéros
le litta de la Direction ainsi que la date<lb/>
Annexe</p>
    
<p>Bruxelles, le 10 Fevrier 1911</p>

<p>Monsieur Le Ministre,</p>
    
<p>Par une lettre du 31 janvier (E No. 1139) j'ai
eu l'honneur de vous faire savoir que la Légation des Etats-
Unis à Bruxelles m'avait fair parvenir la lettre de provision
de M. Charles C Broy, nommé Vice-Consul Général
suppléant de la République à Roma.</p>
    
<p>J'attire votre attention, Monsieur le Ministre, sur
le fait que la letter de provision de M. Broy, datée du mois
de septembre 1910, est identique à celle de M. Phelan, nommé
à Bruxelles en la même qualité en 1905. La demande de reconnaissance
qui n'a été adressé par le Ministre des Etats-Unis
a été rédigée dans des termes absolument semblales pour ces
deux agents.</p>
    
<p>Le Gouvernement américain n'a pas parlé d'exequatur.
Il ne réclame l'exequatur que lorsqu'il s'agit d'un Consul ou
d'un Consul-Général en titre. M. Broy, de même que M. Phelan,
n'est que Vice and Deputy Consul Général. Pour les agents de <fw type="catch">cette</fw>

<fw type="footer">M. le Ministre des Colonies à Bruxelles.</fw>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0264.002.jpg"/>

cette catégorie, le gouvernment américain demande la "reconnaissance"
et c'est ce qu'il a fait pour l'un comme pour l'autre.</p>

<p>On s'est donc adressé à nous pour M. Broy exactement
comme ont l'aurait fait s'il s'était agi de nommer cet
agent en Belgique même. C'est reconnaître que le Congo est une
dépendance de la Belgique.</p>

<p>Je me réserve éventuellement de souligner ce fait
lors de la discussion du budget des Affaires Etrangères par
les Chambres.</p>

<p>Le Comte de Buisseret m'a fait savois par un rapport
en date du 16 décembre dernier, d'après un conversation qu'il
a eue avec un sous secrétaire d'Etat américain, que le Gouvernement
des Etats-Unis ne fera pas de déclaration formelle
de reconnaissance de l'annexion, ce que nous ne l'avons du
reste jamais sollicité de faire. On estime à Washington que
cette reconnaissance est acquise à la Belgique par une série
d'actes accomplis par le gouvernement Américain. La demande
dont M. Broy vient d'être l'objet est la plus significatif de
ces actes.</p>

<p><unclear></unclear></p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0264.001.jpg"/>
        
<p>Minister
of
Foreign Affairs<lb/>
Direction P No C I<lb/>
Remember in the response the numbers 
of the Direction as well as the date<lb/> 
Annex</p>
        
<p>Brussels, the 10th of February 1911</p>
        
<p>Mr. Minister,</p>
        
<p>By a letter from the 31th of January (E No. 1139) I have 
had the honor to make it known to you that the Legation of the United 
States in Brussels made me send Mr. Charles C Broy's 
provisional letter, who was named Vice-Consul General 
deputy of the Republic in Roma.</p>
        
<p> I direct your attention, Mr. Minister, to 
that fact that the provisional letter of Mr. Broy, dated the month 
of September 1910, is identical to that of Mr. Phelan, who was named 
in Brussels in the same capacity in 1905. The request for recognition
that was not addressed by the Minister of the United States 
was written in terms absolutly similar for the 
two agents.</p>
        
<p>The American Government did not speak of an exequatur.
He only claims the exequatur that when he acts as a Consul or 
a Consul General officially. Mr. Broy, like Mr. Phelan,
is only the Vice and the Deputy Consul General. For the agents of <fw type="catch">this</fw>
        
<fw type="footer"> Mr. Minister of the Brussels Colonies</fw>
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0264.002.jpg"/>

this category, the American government asks the "recognition" 
and that what he did for one is similar to the other.</p>
        
<p>One is so addressed to us for Mr. Broy exactly
as it had been done if it had been a question of naming this 
agent in Belgium itself. This is to recognize that the Congo is a 
dependence of Belgium.</p>
        
<p>I reserve myself to eventually underline the fact 
during the budget discussion of Foreign Affairs by 
the Chambers.</p>
        
<p>The Count Busseret made it known to me by a report 
dated last 16 of December, after a conversation that he 
had had with an assistant secretary of the American State, that the United
States Government will not do a formal declaration 
of recognition of the annexation, which we have never 
asked him to do. It is estimated in Washington that 
this recognition bought by Belgium by a series 
of acts accomplished by the American Government. The demand
which Mr. Broy comes to be the object of more significance in
these acts.</p>

<p><unclear></unclear></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
    
</TEI>
