<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0951">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to Frederick W. Seward, October 16, 1877</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0951</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to Frederick W. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1877-10-16">October 16, 1877</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Blackledge, J. W.</term>
<term>Cheeseman, Joseph James</term>
<term>Crusoe, H. Lafayette</term>
<term>Williams, Henry Augustus</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Edina (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1877-10-16"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1877-12-03"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-10" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1177.jpg"/>

<p>No. 34.</p>

<p>Consulate General, United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia<lb/>
16th Octo. 1877</p>

<p>J. Milton Turner<lb/>
To the<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington</p>

<p>Subject: U.S. Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa.</p>

<p>Abstract of contents:</p>

<p>The attention of the Liberia Govt. was called to the appointment of the successor of Mr. Crusoe according to 7th Article of Treaty. Mr. Cheeseman's right to act as such, <sic>witheld</sic> by the Lib. Govt: and recommending the appointment of H. A. Williams to be successor to Mr. Crusoe.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1178.jpg"/>

<p>No. 34.</p>

<p>Consulate General, United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia<lb/>
16. Octo. 1877</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>The subject of my No. 31. which relates to the appointment of a gentleman to succeed Mr. Crusoe in the capacity of Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa, Liberia having recurred, I have the honor to state for the information of the Department, that in compliance with the provisions of the 7th Article of our Treaty with Liberia <catchwords>I</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable<lb/>
F. W. Seward<lb/>
Asst. Secty State,<lb/>
Washington</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1179.jpg"/>

I addressed to the Secretary of State a note, copy of which is transmitted herewith, and marked "enclosure No. 1" in which I requested the permission of this Government to be extended to Mr. J. J. Cheeseman to be Acting Commercial Agent of the United States, instead of Mr. Crusoe, resigned. It appears from the reply of Secretary Blacklidge, Copy of which is marked "enclosure No. 2," – that there are on the part of this Government, objections to Mr. Cheeseman's being permitted to act in that capacity. My recognition of those objections may be found by reference to enclosures 3. 5. of this despatch Enclosure No. 7. relates to my tender of the <catchwords>position</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1180.jpg"/>

position to H. A. Williams, Esqr. a citizen of Grand Bassa, engaged in mercantile business in that County. As soon as Mr. Williams can be heard from, I will, if he accepts the position, ask the permission of this Government to be extended to him to act in that capacity, and report the result to the Department.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1181.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 1.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34</note>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia<lb/>
28. Sept. 1877</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to inform your Government that Honorable <sic>J.</sic> L. Crusoe has resigned the position of United States Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa and to request, respectfully, the permission of your Government for Honorable J. J. Cheeseman to act in that position until such <catchwords>time</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable<lb/>
J. W. Blacklidge<lb/>
Secty of State<lb/>
Monrovia.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1182.jpg"/>

time as my Government may think proper to name Mr. Crusoe's successor</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
With expressions of highest esteem<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
(Sd) J. Milton Turner.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1183.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 2.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Department of State<lb/>
Monrovia, 6. Octo. 1877.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your favor of the 28 ultimo, conveying the intelligence to my government of your appointing J. J. Cheeseman of the County of Grand Bassa temporary vice U.S. Consul, vice <sic>J.</sic> L. Crusoe resigned.</p>

<p>Absence from the City several days is the cause of not replying sooner. I hasten now to do so, advising you that I have the <catchwords>direction</catchwords>

<fw type="address">His Excellency<lb/>
J. Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Minister Resident<lb/>
Monrovia.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1184.jpg"/>

direction of the President to inform you of a circumstance you may not have known or perhaps overlooked viz: the recent election of the Gentleman named for that appointment by you to the Honorable the House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia: and the recognition of whose appointment would at least, appear <sic>incongrous</sic> having him acting in a double capacity or in other words, in the interest of each nationality</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
(Sd) J. W. Blacklidge</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1185.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 3.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia 9 Octo. 1877</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Your despatch of the 6th instant is received. It relates to my application for the permission of your Government to be extended to Honorable J. J. Cheeseman to be Acting Commercial Agent of the United States at Grand Bassa, until such time as my Government can appoint a successor to Honorable H. L. Crusoe, resigned; and points <catchwords>to</catchwords> 

<fw type="address">Honorable,<lb/>
J. W. Blacklidge,<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
Monrovia</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1186.jpg"/>

to the reasons influencing the Government of Liberia to <sic>withold</sic> the permission referred to.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
(Sd) J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1187.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 4.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your favor dated October 9th. in answer to my note of the 6th. inst. with reference to the appointment of J. J. Cheeseman as Commercial Agent of the United States</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
(Sd) J. W. Blacklidge</p>

<fw type="address">Honorable<lb/>
J. Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Minister Resident<lb/>
Monrovia.</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1188.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 5<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Be pleased to find transmitted herewith a copy of my application to the Government of Liberia requesting permission, as required by a provision of the Treaty of the United States with Liberia, for you to act in the capacity of United States Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa; also a copy of the Secretary of States's reply thereto; in which is pointed <catchwords>out</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable<lb/>
J. Jas. Cheeseman,<lb/>
Edina,<lb/>
Grand Bassa.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1189.jpg"/>

out the reasons why the necessary permission is withheld from you by the Government of Liberia.</p>

<p>Should you consent to guard the safety of the Archives of the Agency until such time as Mr. Crusoe's successor is designated, I will esteem it an especial consideration.</p>

<p>I am,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Very Respectfully<lb/>
Your obedient servant,<lb/>
(Sd) J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1188.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 5.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, 9. Octo. 1877.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Be pleased to find transmitted herewith a copy of my application to the Government of Liberia requesting permission, as required by a provision of the Treaty of the United States with Liberia, for you to act in the capacity of United States Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa; also a copy of the Secretary of States's reply thereto; in which is pointed <catchwords>out</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable<lb/>
J. Jas. Cheeseman,<lb/>
Edina,<lb/>
Grand Bassa.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1189.jpg"/>

out the reasons why the necessary permission is withheld from you by the Government of Liberia.</p>

<p>Should you consent to guard the safety of the Archives of the Agency until such time as Mr. Crusoe's successor is designated, I will esteem it an especial consideration.</p>

<p>I am,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Very Respectfully<lb/>
Your obedient servant,<lb/>
(Sd) J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1190.jpg"/>

<note>Copy.</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 6.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency,<lb/>
Grand Bassa, Octo. 16. 1877.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your dispatches under Sept. 18. &amp; 9th. inst. both of which reached me to day. Copies of your correspondence with the Government of Liberia respecting my appointment as U.S. Com. Agent. I have perused, and the reply of the Honorable Secretary of State, directed to you in which he makes reference to the incongruity of serving in a two fold position I have especially noted. The honorable Secretary was <catchwords>pleased</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1191.jpg"/>

pleased to remark in his dispatch to you that "The recent election of the gentleman named by you for that appointment to the Honorable the House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia, would at least appear <sic>incongruious</sic> having him acting in a double capacity," permit me to remark that my being a member of the Legislature of Liberia lies peculiarly within the knowledge of the Government. And it is indeed very strange that no such notice has come to hand, and consequently I have no authority to say that I am a member of the House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia.</p> 

<p><catchwords>I</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1192.jpg"/>

I have the honor to remain<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your Obedient Servant,<lb/>
(Sd) J. Jas. Cheeseman</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2001.jpg"/>

<note>Copy.</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 7.<lb/>
Despatch No. 34.</note>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia<lb/>
16. Octo. 1877.</p>

<p>H. A. Williams<lb/>
Edina.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Should you be willing to accept the position of United States Commercial Agent, Grand Bassa County, hereby tendered to you, be pleased to apply to either Honorable H. L. Crusoe or Honorable J. J. Cheeseman for advices how to make up a Bond for ($2000) Two Thousand Dollars as specified by the United States Consular Regulations and directed by Law to be filed at Washington with <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2002.jpg"/>

the United States Treasurer for the safety of the Archives of the Agency &amp;c. and forward same to me by return mail whereupon this paper shall be your sufficient authority for receipting for the Seal and Archives of the United States Commercial Agency at Bassa to Honorable J. J. Cheeseman the Actg. Commercial Agent; and also your authority for entering upon the discharge of the duties of United States Commercial Agent at Bassa until such time as you shall receive Certificate of your appointment by the Government at Washington, or further advices from this Legation.</p>

<p><catchwords>I</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2003.jpg"/>

I am,<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
(Sd) J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>