<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>William Coppinger, "The Continent of the Future" (1881)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0015</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">1862--Emancipation Day--1884; The Negro as a Political Problem</title>
<author n="Coppinger, William, 1828-1892">William Coppinger</author>
<editor/>
<pubPlace>Hampton, VA</pubPlace>
<publisher>Normal School Steam Press</publisher>
<date when="1881">1881</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-27" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p524" facs="teaa.en.book.0015.001"/>

<div2 type="title">


</div2>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Slave Trade, African.</p>

<p>Revival of.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>In the annual message of Governor Adams, of South Carolina, for the year 1856, he proceeded to argue in favor of the reopening of the salve trade as follows:&#8212;</p>

<p>"It is apprehended that the opening of this trade will lessen the value of slaves, and ultimately destroy the institution. It is a sufficient answer to point to the fact that unrestricted immigration has not diminished the value of labor in the northwestern confederacy. The cry there is the want of labor, notwithstanding capital has the pauperism of the old world to press into the grinding service. If we cannot supply the demand for slave labor, then we must expect to be supplied with a species of labor we do not want, and which is, from the very nature of things, antagonistic to our institutions. It is much better that our drays should be driven by slaves, that our factories should be worked by slaves, that our hotels should be served by slaves, that our locomotives should be manned by slaves, than that we should be exposed to the introduction from any quarter of a population alien to us by birth, training, and education, and which in the process of time must lead to that conflict between capital and labor 'which makes it so difficult to maintain free institutions in all wealthy and highly civilized nations where such institutions as ours do not exist.' In all slaveholding states true policy dictates that the superior race should direct, and the inferior perform all menial service. Competition between the white and black man for this service may not disturb norther sensibility, but it does not exactly suit our latitude.</p>

<p>"Irrespective, however, of interest, the act of Congress declaring the slave trade piracy is a brand upon us which I think it important to remove. If the trade be piracy, the slave must be plunder, and no ingenuity can avoid the logical necessity of such a conclusion. My hopes and fortunes are indissolubly associated with this form of society. i feel that I would be wanting in duty if I did not urge you to withdraw your assent to an act which is itself a direct condemnation of your institutions. But we have interests to enforce a course of self-respect. I believe, as I have already stated, that more slaves are necessary to a continuance of our monopoly in plantation products. I believe that they are necessary to the full development of our whole round of agricultural and mechanical resources; that they are necessary to the restoration of the South to an equality of power in the general government, perhaps to the very integrity of the slave society, disturbed as it has been by causes which have induced an undue proportion of the ruling race. To us have been committed the fortunes of this peculiar form of society resulting from the union of unequal races. It has vindicated its claim to the approbation of an enlightened humanity; it has civilized and christianized the African; it has exalted the white race itself to higher hopes and purposes, and it is perhaps of the most sacred obligation that we should give it the means of expansion, and that we should press it forward to a perpetuity of progress."</p>

<p>In the House of Representatives of the United States, Monday, Dec. 15, 1856, Mr. Etheridge (Fillmore American), of Tenn., asked leave to introduce the following resolution:&#8212;</p>

<p>"Resolved, That this House of Representatives regard all suggestions and propositions of every kind, by whomsoever made, for a revival of the African slave trade, as shocking to the moral sentiment of the enlightened portion of mankind; and that any action on the part of Congress conniving at or legalizing that horrid and inhuman traffic, would justly subject the Government and citizens of the United States to the reproach and execration of all civilized and Christian people throughout the world."</p>

<p>Mr. Smith (Democrat), of Va., objected. Mr Etheridge moved a suspension of the rules, which was carried&#8212;yeas 140, nays 53.</p>

<p>During the pendency of these proceedings, the following remarks were made by members:&#8212;</p>

<p>Mr. Walker. I do not design to enter into debate, but only to ask the gentleman from Tennessee whether, if there is a suspension of the rules, and this resolution is received, it is his purpose to call the previous question with a view of cutting off debate upon the adoption of the resolution?</p>

<p>Mr. Etheridge. I will answer the gentleman. The resolution, to my mind, contains a self-evident proposition. I presume there is no gentleman here who has not an opinion upon the question, and I do not wish to discuss it. I shall move the previous question if I shall succeed in getting the floor.</p>

<p>Mr. Jones of Tenn. I would ask my colleague if he cannot modify his resolution so as to leave out all his reasons, his argument, and his speech? I say to my colleague that I am [loud cries of "Order!" "Order!"] as much opposed to opening the African slave trade as he is or any other man. [Cries of "Order!" "Order!"]</p>

<p>The Speaker. Debate is not in order.</p>

<p>Mr. Jones of Tenn. I do not intend to debate the matter, but I am not to be put down by my colleague.</p>

<p>The yeas and nays were ordered.</p>

<p>Mr. Orr. I give notice that, if the rules are suspended, I will offer the following resolution as a substitute for that proposed by the gentleman from Tennessee:&#8212;</p>

<p>"Resolved, That it is inexpedient to repeal the laws prohibiting the African slave trade."</p>

<p>Mr. Puryear. Before I vote upon this question, I desire to ask the indulgence of the House to state that I am as much opposed to the revival of the slave trade as any gentleman upon this floor; but I believe that this resolution

<pb xml:id="p525" facs="teaa.en.book.0015.002"/>

is introduced out of place, and that this is not the time for it. I shall therefore vote against it. If the time shall ever arrive when my vote can affect the question, I shall vote against the revival of the slave trade.</p>

<p>Mr. Smith of Va. In explanation of the vote which I shall give, I will say that I deem the revival of the slave trade as inexpedient; but I think I understand the object in introducing this resolution, and non concurring in that object, I shall vote "no."</p>

<p>Mr. Zollicoffer. I desire to say that I am decidedly opposed to the reopening of the slave trade; but as I do not perceive that any good can grow out of introducing that question here, I shall vote "no."</p>

<p>Mr. Phelps. I am opposed to re-establishing the slave trade, and should vote against a bill which proposes to repeal the laws now prohibiting it. But I am against abstractions; and as the message of Governor Adams of South Carolina is not before us, I record my vote in the negative.</p>

<p>Mr. Burnett. I am as much opposed to reopening the slave trade as any man upon this floor; but believing I fully understand the object of the gentleman who introduced the resolution, and that I can understand the inducements which have led him to present it at this time, I shall vote "no."</p>

<p>Mr. Washburne of Me. I shall object to any explanations hereafter.</p>

<p>Mr. Jewett. I would inquire of the Chair whether, if the rules are suspended, the first question will be upon the amendment of the gentleman from South Carolina [Mr. Orr], and then upon the resolution offered by the gentleman from Tennessee?</p>

<p>The Speaker. The amendment of the gentleman from South Carolina has not been received. If the rules are suspended, the question will be first upon the resolution offered by the gentleman from Tennessee.</p>

<p>Mr. Jewett. I vote "no."</p>

<p>Mr. Barksdale. I am not in favor of reopening the African slave trade.</p>

<p>Mr. Washburne of Me. I object to debate.</p>

<p>Mr. Barksdale. I do not believe that any gentleman upon this side of the House is. ["Order!" "Order!"] But I regard the resolution of the gentleman from Tennessee as ill-timed [renewed cries of "Order!"], out of place, thrown into the House as a firebrand [loud cries of "Order!" "Order!" and great confusion], and for the accomplishment of a party purpose. I therefore vote "no."</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>