<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0195">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley to Knight of Guvelier, August 13, 1908</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0195</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from James Gustavus Whiteley to Knight of Guvelier</title>
<date when="1908-08-13">August 13, 1908</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 241, Liasse 217</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Handley, William W.</term>
<term>Olcott</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Matanzas, Cuba</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Puerto Plata</term>
<term>Santo Domingo</term>
<term>Trinidad</term>
<term>Venezuela</term>
<term>Washinton</term>
</keywords>
    

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Whiteley, James Gustavus</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
<date when="1908-08-13"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName>Knight of Guvelier</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-09" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">Encoded header information and translated.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="fr"  >

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0195.001.jpg"/>
 
<p>Consulat Général De L'Etat Indépendant Du Congo, Baltimore.</p>    

<p>le 13 aout 1908.</p>
    
<p>Monsieur le Chevalier,</p>
    
<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous transmetter les
renseignments suivants à propos de Monsieur William W. Handley 
recemment nomme Consul Général des Etats Unis a Boma.</p>
    
<p>Monsieur Handley, originaire de Washington, a trente-six ans. Aprés
avoir fait ses études au Columbia College, il est entré au
service du Gouvernement Américain au Bureau d'Imprimerie où il est resté 
quatre ans. Quittant le service du Gouvernement il est entré dans des
affaires commerciales et il a formé des relations avec l'Orinoco
Steamship Company (ligne de navigation entre New  York et Venezuela_) qui
l'a envoyé à Trinidad pour y représennter la societé.</p> 
    
<p>En janvier 1904, il etatie nommé vice-consul des Etats-Unis a
Trinidad. En aout 1904 le Gourvernement Américain l'a nommé Agent
Américain a Matanzas, Cuba. En juin 1905 il est devenu consul a Puerto
Plata, Santo Domingo, et en novembre 1905 on l'a nommé consul a Trinidad
oú il est resté jusqu'à sa promotion au poste de consul général a Boma.</p>
   
<p> Il parait que ses chefs au Departement d'Etat on formé une
opinion trés favorable et de sa modeste et son bon sens. On dit qu'il
a fait une trés bonne impression sur le Gouverneur-Général de Trinidad.</p>
   
<p>Monsieur Handley est le beau-frére de Monsieur Olcott, le président 
de l'Orinoco Steamship Company. Cette light de navigation a fait une 
reclamation contre le Gouvernement de Venezuela pour une grosse summe
d'argent. Cette reclamation est une des cinq demandes qui on cause le
    
<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Chevalier de Guvelier.</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0195.002.jpg"/>
    
différend actuel entre le Venezuela et les Etats-Unis.</p>
  
<p>Veuillez agréer, Monsieur le Chevalier, l'assurance de ma consideration
la plus distinguée.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>  
       
</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation"  >

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0195.001.jpg"/>
 
<p>Consulate General Of The Independent State of the Congo, Baltimore.</p>    

<p>August 13, 1908.</p>
    
<p>Mister Knight,</p>
    
<p>I have the honor to transmit to you the
following information about Mister William W. Handley 
recently named Consul General of the United States in Boma.</p>
    
<p>Mister Handley, originally from Washington, is 36 years old. After
having studied at Columbia College, he entered in the
service of the American Government in the Bureau of Printing where he stayed 
four years. Leaving the service of the Government he entered in 
comercial affairs and he formed relations with the Orinoco
Steamship Company (line of navigation between New  York and Venezuela_) who
sent him to Trinidad to represent the society.</p> 
    
<p>In January 1904, he was named vice-consul of the United States in
Trinidad. In August 1904 the American Government named him American
Agent in Matanzas, Cuba. In June 1905 he became consul in Puerto
Plata, Santo Domingo, and in November 1905 they named him consul in Trinidad
where he stayed until his promotion to the post of consul general in Boma.</p>
   
<p> It seems that these chiefs in the State Department formed an
opinion very favorable and of his modesty and good sense. They say that he
made a very good impression on the General Governor of Trinidad.</p>
   
<p>Mister Handley is the brother in law of Mister Olcott, the president 
of the Orinoco Steamship Company. This light of navigation made a 
complaint against the Government of Venezuela for a large sum
of money. This demand is one of the five demands that they speak the
    
<fw type="footer">Monsieur le Chevalier de Guvelier.</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0195.002.jpg"/>
    
current differend between Venezuela and the United States.</p>
  
<p>Please accept, Mister Knight, the assurance of my most distinguished
consideration.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley</p>  
       
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
