<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<pb facs="p0"/>
THIS BOOK IS DEDICATED 
TO
MANUEL GONZALES,
MY COMPANION AND PHOTOGRAPHER
UPON MY CONGO EXPEDITION 
AND TO 
OUR BLACK BOYS, MANOELI AND TUMBA

<pb facs="vii"/>
<pWhen I returned to America, I had decided 
to express no opinion upon the public and 
political questions of the Congo Free
State. Having found conditions there quite different 
form what I had expected, it was impossible for me 
to state my actual impressions without danger of 
anatagonizing or offending some whom I valued as 
friends. Hence, on landing at New York, I refused 
to say anything upon those matters to several report-
ers who interviewed me. A little later, the Chi-
cago Tribune asked me to write upon these subjects,
urging the importance of the whole matter to our 
nation, and leaving me entire freedom in viewpoint 
and mode of treatment. In response to its request, 
I prepared a series of articles, which appeared in suc-
cessive issues from January 20 to February 3, 1907.></pWhen>
    <pThe articles were received with general interest
only, and as I have much other Congo matter for 
books and pamphlets-- more directly in the line of 
my professional work-- I was inclined not to reprint 
them. But I soon found myself the subject of bitter 
attack. Malicious and untrue statements were 
made regarding me and my motives. I have con-

<pb facs="viii"/>
cluded, therefore, that it is best that my articles 
should be accessible to all who are interested. What 
I wrote, I am ready to defend. I am not ready to be 
judged from misquotations, or condemned for what 
I never wrote. Hence this book./>
    <p> I am not personally responsible for the title--
The Truth about the Congo. Alhough I believe all 
my statements are true, I should not have selected 
that title for my articles. No man can say all that 
is true on any subject, and I do not arrogate to my-
self a monopoly in truth-telling, either about the 
Congo or any other topuc. But after my announc-
ment under that heading, I decided to let it stand.
I preferred some less assertive title, but I am content.
So I use the same title for this book. The headlines 
of the articles, however, I have suppressed. They 
were not of my preparation and did not adequately
suggest the matter or the treatment. The articles 
are reprinted with no changes except corrections in 
spelling, punctuation, or mistaken words.</p>

    <p>No man more desires the happiness and progress 
of the Congo natives than do I. I know them 
pretty well. I am their friend; they are my friends. 
I shall be glad if what I here present makes them and 
their cause better known to thoughtful and sympa-
thetic men and women. Mere emotion, however vio-
lent, will not help them. Stubborm refusal to recognize 
and encourage reforms, which have been seriosuly 
undertaken for their betterment, will only harm them.</p>

<pb facs="1"
THE TRUTHABOUT THE CONGO
I.
January 20, 1907.

<p>My own interest in the Congo Free State began at 
the St. Louis exposition. As is well known,
that exposition made a special feature of groups
of representatives of tribes from various parts of the world.
These natives dressed in native dress, lived in native 
houses, and so far as possible reproduced an accurate pic-
ture of the daily life to which they were accustomed in 
their homes</p>

<p>Among the groups there brought together was one of 
Congo natives. This group was commonly known as the 
pygmy group, though but four out of the nine members 
composing it made claims to be such. The group was
brought by mr. S.P.Verner, at one time missionary to the
Congo, who was engaged by the exposition to make a 
special journey into central Africa to procure it. Four 
members of the group were Batua, the others were large 
blacks represneting the Bakuba and Baluba.</p>

<p>The idea of visiting Africa was one which I had never 
seriosuly entertained, but in the study of these Congolese 
it seemed to me that there were interesting questions the 
solution of which would well repay a visit. The conse-
quence was, that I determined to visit the Congo Free 
State-- and specifically that part of the state from which
these natives had been brought</p>

<pb facs="2"
    <p>About this time I received considerable literature from
the Congo Reform Association at Boston, the reading of
which had its influence in deciding me to undertake the 
expeidtion.</p>

    <p>After reading this literature I started for the Congo,
fully prepaed to see all kinds of horrors. I supposed that
mutilations, cruelties, and atrocities of the most firghtful 
kinds would everywhere present themselves. I expected
to find a people everywhere suffering, mourning, and in 
unhappiness.</p>

    <p>My errand, however, was not that of a searcher after
all these dreadful things, but purely that of a student of 
human races, with definite questions for investigation.
    I may say that my opportunities for forming an opinion
of conditions in the Congo have been exeptional. Mine 
was no hasty journey, but a tarry in the country extending 
over more than one year.</p>

    <p>While my original plan was to spend the greater portion
of my time in the district ruled by the Bakuba chief,
Ndombe, with but a short period in other parts of the 
state, I had decided before reaching the mouth of the 
Congo to more evenly distribute my time, and to see far
more of the Congo proper than I at first intended. As a 
consequence, I went first into the Kasai district, where I
spent four months, after which, returning to Leopoldville,
I went up the main river to the head of navigation, and 
even beyond, to Ponthierville, the terminus of the newly
built line of railroad. We also went up the Aruwimi, to
the famous Yambuya camp, where the navigation of that 
river is interrupted by cataracts.</p>

<ab>I have, therefore, seen not only the lower Congo, which</ab>

<pb facs="3"
<p>has been so frequently visited in recent years, but traveled
thousands of miles upon the great river and two of its most
important tributaries.</p>

<p>In this extended journey I came into constant contact
with representatives of the three groups of white men who 
live in the Congo Free State-- state officials, missionaries,
and traders. I had repeated conversations with them all,
and have heard opinions upon the Congo State from these
diverse points of view.</p>

<p>My position with reference to Congo matters is peculiar,
doubly so. I may even say it is unique. My journey was 
made at my own expense; I was not the representative of 
any institution, society, or body. I was without instruc-
tions, and my observations were untrammeled by any 
demands or conditions from outside.</p>

<p>While I am under many and weighty obligations to 
scores of state officials, missionaries, and traders, I am not 
prevented from speaking my mind in regard to any and 
every matter. Both to the missionaries, state officials,
and traders I paid board and lodging at every stopping
point-- with the single exception of one American mission 
station-- a fact which leaves me freedom. While the 
state faciliated my visit and my work in many ways, I was 
not, at any time, in relations with it of such a kind as to 
interefere with free observations or free expresion. I
made this entirely clear on my first visit to the state author-
ities at Brussels, and it was understood by them that I 
should speak freely and frankly of everything which I 
should see. On their part, the state authorities expressed 
the liveliest satisfaction that an idependent American
traveler should visit the Congo Free State, and said that</p>

<pb facs="4"
<ab>they did not wish anything concealed or attenuated, as 
they felt sure that such a visit as mine could only do them 
good.</ab>

<p>I have said that my position was doubly peculiar. I 
was not only independent and untrammeled in observation
and expression, but my personal attitude to the whole ques-
tion of colonizaion and administration by a foreign power,
of natives, is radical. Personally I dislike the effort to
elevate, civilize, remake a people. I should prefer to leave
the African was he was before white contact. It is my belief
that there is no people so weak or so degraded as to be 
incapable of self-government. I believe that every people 
is happier and better with self-government, no matter how 
unlike our own form that government may be. I feel that 
no nation is good enough, or wise enough, or sufficiently
advanced to undertake the elevation and civilization of a 
"lower" people. Still less do I approve the exploitation 
of a native population by outsiders for their own benefit.
Nor do I feel that even the development of British trade
warrants intereference with native life, customs, laws, and 
lands. I know, however, that these views are unpopular
and hertical.</p>

<p>In the series of articles, then, I have been asked 
to prepare, I shall try to take the standpoint of the practical
man, the business man, th man of affairs, the philanthro-
pist, the missionary. All these agree that civilized folk 
have a perfect right to interfere with any native tribe too
weak to resist their encroachment. They agree that it is 
perfectly right to trample under foot native customs, insti-
tutions, ideas-- to change and modify, to introduce inno-
vations, either to develop trade, to exploit a country, to</p>

<pb facs="5"
<ab>elevate a race, or to save souls. I am forced, then, to 
look at Congo matters from the point of view of these
eminently practical men.</ab>
    
<p>Of course, I saw much to criticise. It is true that there 
are floggings, and chain-gangs, 
and prisons in the United States. Mutilations are so rarw
that one must seek for them; abd I had too much else to 
do. There is taxiation-- yes, heavy taxiation-- a matter
which I shall discuss quite fully further on. And in con-
nection with taxiation there is forced labor, a matter which,
of course, I disapprove, but it appears as just to all the 
groups of eminently practical men to whom I have re-
ferred. There are, no doubt, hostages in numberS, but I saw
less than a dozen. And the whole matter of hostages is one
which merits careful and candid discussion. And I know
that in many a large district the population is much smaller
than in former times. The causes of this diminution in 
numbers are many and various, and to them I shall return.</p>
    
<p>Flogging, chain-gang, prison, mutilation, heavy taxa-
tion, hostages, depopulation--all these I saw, but at no
time and at no place were they so flagrant as to force them-
selves upon attention. And of frightful outrages, such as
I had expected to meet everywhere, I may almost say there
was nothing. It is, of course, but fair to state that I was 
not in the district of the A.B.I.R. I cannot believe, how-
ever, that conditions in that district are so appalling as the 
newspaper reports would indicate.</p>
    
<p>On the contrary, I found at many places a condition
of the negro population far happier than I had dreamed
it possible. The negro of the Congo--or Bantu, if you</p>
    
<pb facs="6"
<p>please-- is a born trader. He is imitative to a degree.
He is acquisitive, and charmed with novelties. He is 
bright and quick, remarkably intelligent. He readily
acquires new languages, and it is no uncommon thing to 
find a Congo Bantu who can speak six or seven languages
besides his own. In disposition variable and emotional,
he quickly forgets his sorrow. I saw hundreds of natives
who were working happily, living in good houses, dressing 
in good clothes of European stuff and pattern, and saving 
property. That this number will rapidly increase I have 
no doubt.</p>
    
<p>And now, on my return, after having many of my pre-
conceived ideas completely shattered, and feeling on the 
whole that things in Congoland are not so bad, and that 
improvement is the order of the day, I am startled to find 
the greatest excitement. Pages od newspapers are filled 
with stories of atorcities, many of which never happened, s
some of which are ancient, and a part of which, recent in
date, are true.</p>
    
<p>I find a fierce excitement about the Belgium lobby,
vigorous resolutions presented in the senate, and the Presi-
dent of the United States outrunning his most urgent
supporters and advisers, ready to take some drastic action 
to ameliorate the conditions of the suffering millions in the 
Congo Free State. The suprise is so much the greater,
as my latest information regarding the American official
attitude had been gained from the letter written by Secre-
tary Root some months ago.</p>

<ab>What can be the reason of such prodigious and sudden 
change?
What has happened in the Congo since April to produce</ab>
    
<pb facs="7"
<p>the present state of mind? What is the motive under-
lying the bitter attacks upon Leopold and the Free State
which he established? Is it truly humanitarian? Or
are the laudable impulses and praiseworthy sympathies
of two great people being used for hidden and sinister ends
of politics?</p>
    
<p>I do not claim infallibility. I do claim that my having
spent a year in the Congo Free State, independently, should
qualify me to express opinions on the conditions. I have
</p>