<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0051">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from John T. Bradberry to William H. Seward, December 31, 1863</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0051</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from John T. Bradberry to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">2</biblScope>
<date when="1863-12-31">December 31, 1863</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>de Andrade, José Baptista</term>
<term>Graham, Walter</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61162261">Webster, E. H. (Edwin Hanson), 1829-1893</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Benguela (Angola)</term>
<term>Cape of Good Hope</term>
<term>Cassanje (Angola)</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>Fernando Po</term>
<term>Havre de Grace (Md.)</term>
<term>Mossamedes (Angola)</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>St. Helena</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Bradberry, John T.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent for Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda, Angola</placeName>
<date when="1863-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
<date when="1864-03-19"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-05-01" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and additional encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.00051.001"/>

<note>Rec'd March 19, '64.</note>
<note>No 3.</note>

<opener><dateline>Commercial Agency of the U.S. of America<lb/>
at St Paul De Loanda December 31st 1863</dateline></opener>

<salute>Sir</salute>

<p>I have the Honor to enclose Custom House
and Port Charges for the Port of St. Paul De Loanda.</p>

<p>Also Arrivals and Departures for the Quarter
Ending December 31st 1863</p>

<p>Also Official Letters and Blanks Received</p>
 
<p>By this it will be perceived that the Box with 
Flags and Blanks, reached here on the 24th November
about 9 months after it left Washington.</p>

<p>Mail Facilities between this Place and the U.S. 
are very slow and uncertain. By the English Mail it 
is seldom less than three; and often five months between 
the mailing of a letter in New York and its receipt
here, in fact there is no regular mail, except as far as
Fernando Po, where it lays until some English Cruiser
chooses to bring it up</p>

<p>I received the box from St Helena via Cape
of Good Hope, forwarded to me by Walter Graham
Esqr.</p>

<p>The Draft and voucher for stationary I hope
will prove satisfactory</p>

<p>I have also the Honor of enclosing a Tabular
Statement of export Duties and Other Charges 
for this Port. Also Aggregate Amt of Fees</p>

<p>I have the Honor to state that Clearing a
Vessel from this Port is a perplexing operation:</p>

<p>1st Notice of eight days must be given,</p>

<p>2d A Bond with two sureties (merchants) 
in the sum of Four Thousand Mil Reis
Fracos $2.675.59 must be entered into as 
a Guarantee that the vessel will not Engage 
in the Slave Trade</p> 

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.00051.002"/>

<p>This is well, when suspicion attaches to any vessel, but
it is exacted indiscriminately previous to granting a
Clearance, not that there is any fear that a well known vessel
will engage in the Slave Trade, but that the merchants who
sign the bond may realize the Fee, which is forty five
pound or One hundred and twenty five Dollars for
so doing;</p>

<p>The Practice is continued (I am told) in accordance
with an inference drawn from a Law of 1836, there
being no positive law to justify it;</p>

<p>The merchants established here sign the Bond for
for each other, but an American Vessel arriving here
for the first time, encounters much trouble and expense 
in consequence of said Bond.</p>

<p>She must also select a Consignee (if not previously 
Consigned) which obliges her to pay a further sum of One 
hundred Mil Ries a <unclear>Mast</unclear> (Fracos) or $66,66 2/3.</p>

<p><sic>I</sic> the case of the Whaling Schooner Glendower
His Excellency Gov General (José Baptista Andrade)
over-ruled the Custom House authorities in regard 
to both Bond and Consignee, thus saving her a
useless expense of $338.00. She Came here for
supplies only;</p>

<p>I have not succeeded in obtaining a copy of Duties 
on Imports for this province; the present Duties are 
based upon the Tariff Law of 1842, modified for
Colonial Purposes, but I have the assurance that
on the 1st of February next a New Tariff will be 
published. Based on the Tariff on 1863, with 
Colonial Modifications, which will I understand 
increase the Duties on both Imports and exports, 
I will forward it as soon as possible.</p>

<p>At Benguela, Mesamides and Loanda, Duties
must be paid; All other Trading Station are free

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.00051.003"/>

I feel it to be my duty to mention the fact, that the 
Iron Lighters here belonging to the Government are
nearly valueless, being rusted through in many Places,
cargo that would sink (Coal for instance) cannot 
be transported in them safety; in fact they are
not well adapted to this navigation, either in model
or material, Lighters for this harbor should be of 
wood forty five to fifty feet long, and Coppered, 
the model such as are used at Havre de Grace M.d.
very strong, Cheap, light draft of water, Burthensome,
easily managed, and will sail well, when sail is 
put upon them; I have no doubt, such Lighters
could be sent here all ports previously fitted, and
put together here, for one thousand Dollars each.
I am informed that freight alone on one of those
Lighters now here amounted to twelve hundred Dolls
and their term of service has been very short.</p>

<p>For two years last past, trade with the interior
has much been obstructed, in consequence of A War
between the Portuguese and the King (Jaga) of 
Cassange, one of the most powerful Potentates
of the Interior of Africa, and <sic>whos</sic> dominions border
upon the Portuguese possessions. On the 29th of August 
last, a treaty of Peace was entered into between the 
belligerents, the Jaga of Cassange agreeing to Pay the
whole expense of the war. On the 26th of September
the Embassador of the Jaga was received at the
Palace of the Government General, when the Treaty 
was ratified; in consequence it is expected that 
trade with the Interior will revive and Importations 
increase</p>

<p>Our own unhappy civil war has a very 
depressing effect upon American Trade here, in
consequence of the high price of Cotton, heretofore

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.00051.004"/>

the most profitable article of American manufacture 
imported into this Country, also an important auxiliary
to all other article of sale or barter, under present circumstances
the English (who have only one house here)
sell Cotton goods for at least 30 per cent less than
the same article can be bought in the U. States</p>

<p>With despatch No 5 I had the Honor to mention 
the fact of the loss of my Commission and Passport,
I have not been able to recover them, and am under the
necessity of renewing the request that others be
sent to me, nor have I received the necessary <sic>Exequetur</sic> 
requested in the house of the same despatch.</p>

<p>I also had the honor to mention the fact, that
the Salary of Agent at this station is inadequate
to its <sic>propper</sic> support, one must live as do Representatives
of other Countries, or lower his own 
Country in the estimation of the authorities, which
I am not willing to do, luxury is not requisite,
but respectability is.</p>

<p>I am aware that Congress must concur in
whatever is done in the premises, but a recommendation
from Your Honor to the <sic>propper</sic> authorities,
together with the concurrence of the Representative
from my Congressional District (the Hon E. H. Webster)
I feel Confident would procure an increase of 
salary; in default, I would Respectfully solicit 
the appointment of Naval Store Keeper here, or the appointment
to some situation where the salary is
adequate to support the station without engaging
in Commercial pursuits</p>

<closer><salute>I have the Honor to be<lb/>
Your Most Obedient Servant</salute>
<signed>John T Bradberry
Commercial Agent.</signed>

<address><addrLine>W. H. Seward</addrLine>
<addrLine>Sec of State</addrLine></address>

</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
