<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1385">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen, April 26, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1385</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1882-04-26">April 26, 1882</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Gibson, Garretson W.</term>
<term>Worrell, John W.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Buchanan (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</persName>
<roleName>Acting U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1882-04-26"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/58082142">Frelinghuysen, Frederick T. (Frederick Theodore), 1817-1885</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1882-06-01"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-02" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3028.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Jun 1 1882</note>

<note>No 6</note>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, April 26th 1882</p>

<p>Mr M. A Aenmey to the Secretary of State</p>

<p>Subject</p>

<p>Attack by a mob on the Consular Agency of the United States at Grand Bassa</p>

<pb n="Roll3-3029.jpg"/>

<note>No 6</note>

<p>Consulate General of the U.S.<lb/>
Monrovia April 26th 1882</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I sincerely regret to be obliged to report that, a few weeks ago, at Grand Bassa, a demonstration took place, against the person of the U.S. Consular Agent, Mr J. W. Worrell.</p>

<p><sic>Imediatly</sic> <sic>afther</sic> receiving, pr extra messenger, the Complaint from the Consular Agent, I <sic>imformed</sic> the Liberia <sic>Governement</sic> through the dept of State at Monrovia, of what has took place, requesting <sic>must</sic> respectfully, to have a proper inquiry made as to the cause of this revolting act.</p>

<p><sic>Afther</sic> some delay I have received from the dept of State <sic>at</sic> answer, herewith enclosed and marked No 2. Since that time Mr Worrell has visited Monrovia and declared to me that no further <sic>disturbences</sic> has <sic>occured</sic>, and informed me that the whole act of the unruly crowd that evening was <sic>personaly</sic> against him and not a demonstration against the Consular Agency and that in fact nothing but politics was the cause. This expression being made to me <catchwords>by</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon Fredk. T. Frelinghuysen<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-3030.jpg"/>

by Mr Worrell himself, it is my opinion that no further demonstrations of that kind, will take place, as the <sic>Governement</sic> of Liberia has give order to put an exemplary punishment on the perpetrators of this outrage.</p>

<p>With sentiments of the highest esteem<lb/>
I am Sir, your obedt servt.<lb/>
M. A. Aenmey.<lb/>
Actg Consul General.</p>

<p>Enclosures.</p>

<p>1. Mr J. W. Worrell to Mr. M. A Aenmey<lb/>
2. Secretary Gibson to Mr M A Aenmey.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3031.jpg"/>

<p>U.S. Consulate<lb/>
Grand Bassa<lb/>
March 22nd 1882</p>

<p>M. A. Aenmey Esq<lb/>
U.S. Vice Con: General<lb/>
Monrovia</p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Since writing you on the 16th inst I have to further inform you that this Consulate was attacked by an Armed Mob &amp; fired into on two occasions during the evening of the 18th inst, inflicting a slight wound on myself &amp; seriously injuring his honor the mayor of the City Buchanan, who happened to be in my Company on the verando of this Consulate. The actions of The local Authorities <hi rend="underline">here</hi> in defence of this International outrage I am ashamed

<pb n="Roll3-3032.jpg"/>

to say reflects no honor on the Chief whom he represents. Up to the present, by his actions, he has not thought the Consulate &amp; Archives of the U.S. Government worthy of any consideration from the Government of Liberia, notwithstanding he is aware that the Mob went so far as to batter the U.S. Court-of-arms of this Consulate with Bullets on the evening of the above complained of outrage. I also enclose a copy of a notice he has since put up on the corner of the streets and also a copy of my notice to him of the course I intend to take in bringing the matter before the U.S. Government</p>

<p>I am Dear Sir<lb/>
Your obt. servt<lb/>
John W Worrell<lb/>
U.S. Com Agt</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3033.jpg"/>

<p>Department of State<lb/>
Monrovia April 13, 1882.</p>

<p>Sir.</p>

<p>Referring to your despatch of some days ago, calling attention to the outrage committed upon the United States Consulate at Grand Bassa, I have the honor to express the very sincere regret felt by this Government that any such occurrence should have taken place; and to assure you that the proper authorities at that place have been and still are putting forth earnest efforts to detect the parties committing the outrage in order to bring the same to justice</p>

<p>I have the pleasure to inform you however that after the most vigilant inquiry as to the probable cause of the attack, it has been satisfactorily shown that reasons wholly connected with the late political career of Hon. J W Worrell, who occupies the double position of Liberian Senator and United States Consular Agent accounts for it. Notwithstanding the Government will put forth every effort to detect &amp; punish the offenders.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be

<pb n="Roll3-3034.jpg"/>

Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient Servant<lb/>
G. W. Gibson</p>

<fw type="address">Hon M. A. Aenmey<lb/>
U States Legation<lb/>
Monrovia</fw>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>