<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0009">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Brief of Henry I. Kowalsky, of the New York Bar, Attorney and Counsellor to Leopold II</title>
<author n="Kowalsky, Henry I.">Henry I. Kowalsky</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0009</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Brief of Henry I. Kowalsky, of the New York Bar, Attorney and Counsellor to Leopold II.</title>
<author n="Kowalsky, Henry I.">Henry I. Kowalsky</author>
<date when="1905">1905</date>
<publisher>Henry I. Kowalsky</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<biblScope unit="part">select sections of the document</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Book</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Barbour, Thomas S. (Thomas Seymour), 1853-1915</term>
<term>Dufourne</term>
<term>Gibbons, James, 1834-1921</term>
<term>Kowalsky, Henry I.</term>
<term>Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term>Moncheur, Ludovic, Baron, 1857-1940</term>
<term>Morel, E.D. (Edmund Dene), 1873-1924</term>
<term>Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919</term>
<term>Sheldon, Mary French, 1847-1936</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Alaska</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>Boston (Mass.)</term>
<term>Brussels (Belgium)</term>
<term>China</term>
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>Europe</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>New York (N.Y.)</term>
<term>Philippines</term>
<term>United States</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Anglo Saxon</term>
<term>Negro</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-04-03" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-11-13" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-08-22" who="#kln">Initial transcription and encoding.</change>
<change when="2014-08-20" who="#kln">Initial transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">Brief of Henry I. Kowalsky, of the New York Bar, Attorney and Counsellor to Leopold II., King of the Belgians and Sovereign of the Independent State of the Congo, in Matters Touching his Rights and Possessions Abroad, in Reply to Memorial Presented to the President of the United States of America Concerning Affairs in the Congo State by the Congo Reform Association, Supported by the British and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society and the Aborigines' Protection Society.</head>
 
<head type="sub">Answer to Memorial.</head>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Negro Criminals.</head>

<p>A fact that is important in connection with the unjust criticism
of this new State can in a way be deduced from the fact that
here in the United States the negro is about one-sixth of the entire
population, and it is strange to say that, though the negroes have
had civilizing influences about them ever since this government
came into existence, nearly twenty-five per cent. of the prisoners
in penal institutions are black men. If the penal institutions of
this country have been kept so busy with the American negro, what
ought to be expected of the negro of the Congo? And yet there
is no such proportion of criminal life in the Congo as the records
disclose either in England or America.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about two pages"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Morel's Attacks.</head>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about half a page"/>

<p>The success of the
Belgians in the Congo Basin is a confutation of that idea and
the English merchant, ever jealous of inroads made upon his
business and traditionally possessed of the idea that to him belongs
the earth and the fullness thereof, views with alarm the supremacy
of Belgian interests in the Congo and would be well pleased if the
powers signatory to the Berlin Conference, or failing in that, the
government of the United States, would take such action as would
result in disturbances in the Congo, thereby justifying active
interference in the affairs of that State and eventually permitting
England to rehabilitate and act upon the idea that she alone of all
the governments of the earth is the natural protector of the downtrodden
and the oppressed.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about a page"/>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about three pages"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Mrs. French-Sheldon.</head>

<p>Mrs. French-Sheldon, the famous traveler, having made an
independent investigation of Congolese conditions in the Free State,
recently returned to Europe, and, in an interview published in
the Journal of Commerce of January 4th, 1905, announced to the
world that the charges made against King Leopold and the Congo
government were absolutely without foundation. To use her
own words, "The evidence is absolutely conclusive that the labors
of the Congo Free State have added to the material prosperity, the
happiness, and the development of the natives, whilst the opening
up of the country and the introduction of order and system in place
of chaos ill forever redound to the credit of King Leopold and
those with whom he is associated."</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about two pages"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Land Laws, Etc., U.S.</head>

<p>The laws of the United States granting exclusive privileges to
the Alaska Commercial Company for the taking of fur-bearing
animals upon the islands adjacent to the Alaskan Coast are a
striking illustration of the necessity for regulating the control of
public property in order to prevent its annihilation. The laws
of the United States relating to forest reservations, the timber
culture act, the granting of lands' to the Pacific railroads for the
purpose of aiding in their construction, the land laws of the United
States and the general policy of the government with reference to
its property, all point strikingly to the fact that the government
of the Congo in imposing conditions upon the right to use its lands
and exploit its natural resources was acting in accordance with
principles which are at the very base of civilization, and doing
what was absolutely necessary to preserve for posterity the natural
resources of the country.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about a page"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Negro Uplifting.</head>

<p>The people of this country are not ignorant of the difficulties
connected with the uplifting of the negro. When we consider
that in this country millions of treasure and thousands of lives
were offered up in order to strike the shackles from four millions
of slaves, and that the heart-burnings which followed the destruction
of an institution which many members of the Anglo Saxon
race regarded as of divine origin have not been quenched,
it behooves us to be charitable in our estimation of the work performed
by the Congo State and its ruler, King Leopold.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Leopold's Character.</head>

<p>We recall that here, in our own land, this beloved nation of
ours was almost severed in twain -- that million of money were
expended and will still be expended-hundreds of thousands of
precious lives have gone to their deaths, our whole nation has
been bent in sorrow, and we can still hear the sobs of the aching
hearts of those who have lingered behind. All of which make up
in part the sum that it cost to free four million civilized, Christianized
negro slaves in America. Though freed forty years ago,
the problem of their future is still a question that agitates this
country and exercises the mentality of our very best statesmen,
who are in deep meditation for a solution that will fully carry out
the hopes and ambitions of the great Lincoln, who has been and
always will be, revered by a loving and a grateful nation as the
Moses that led the black man from out of bondage. When all of
this is reflected upon, and the thoughtful and unprejudiced mind
looks at the Congo situation, and the work of its sovereign and his
subjects; when they contemplate that nearly two thousand years
of civilization has. been crowded into twenty-five years, within
which time Leopold has unshackled over thirty millions of savage
negroes, they view with admiration this wise statesman and philosopher
king. Twenty-five years ago he adopted as the motto
of the State the sentiment that we are just coming to appreciate
as a method of bringing the American negro to a future, to wit,
the sentiment: "Work and labor." Work and labor mean the retirement
from a state of idleness and irresponsibility into that of
responsibility and industry, and that beneficent result has not been
obtained in the Congo without the cost of many precious lives,
white and black, and great hardship on the part of those who have
been active in bringing about this condition, as well as the expenditure
of millions of money out of the personal and private
purse of Leopold, who has given a life-time to this grand work
and who is still devoting the energy of his splendid three-score
years and ten to the continuance of the betterment of the government
of the Congo Free State. The time is not far distant, if
indeed it is not already present, when the world, white and black,
must attorn in gratitude and treat with great nobility and reverence
the life work of this philosophical, gracious and kindly sovereign.</p>

<p>The American people and its governing power have been
face to face with a kindred subject, to wit, civilizing natives that
came to us as heritage through our late war with Spain. The
kaleidescope of time need not be presented to you, Mr. President,
for you are now using the wisdom of your administration in developing,
civilizing and bringing about religious conditions in the
Philippines, it would be an usurpation of your valuable time to
attempt to recall the great labor attending this great work and
that yet to be accomplished, and though every effort comes from
the heart and conscience of duty, still there are hundreds of carping
critics, who are calling the administration's motives into question,
and would, if they could, tear down all the grand work that has
been built up in the advancement of the wards of this nation.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="two paragraphs"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">U.S. Government -- Action By.</head>

<p>Any official action on the part of the President of the United 
States in the nature of an expression of sympathy with the work
of the maligners of the Congo government, or any executive action
on his part, having in view the investigation of the internal affairs
of the Congo, would be a direct attack upon its integrity as a government,
and, if effectual, would involve a complete or partial surrender
of its governmental functions.</p> 

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about 11 pages"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="main">Appendix.</head>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about 2 pages"/>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="main">Letters.</head>

<head type="sub">Leopold II. to Henry I. Kowalsky.</head>

<p>Dear Colonel Kowalsky:</p>

<p>I beg to confirm to you that I have instructed you to defend
in the United States the case of the Congo Free State which is now
being attacked by a group of English merchants and missionaries,
at present represented in Washington by Mr. Morel.</p>

<p>You have, in the course of your stay here, been enabled to
convince yourself of the unfairness and falseness of these attacks.
and the Free State Government rely on your endeavors to enlighten
statesmen and political men in the United States as to the
true motives 6f this disparaging campaign, to show them the inanity
of the charges and to lay the truth before them, namely that
for the last twenty-five years the Congo State has been working
with a success that accounts for all this hatred and jealousy,
toward introducing into territories, formerly abandoned to barbarism,
civilization and progress and toward improving the material
and moral conditions of existence of the natives.</p>

<p>Under the stress of the indignation aroused in Belgium by the
English calumnies, an extensive association has been formed in
this country under the title of Federation pour la defense des
interets belges a l'estranger (Federation for defending Belgian
interests abroad) which consists of prominent men in the army,
and in commercial and industrial circles.</p>

<p>This association desired to submit to the enlightened mind
of the President of the United States their protests against the
audacious and untruthful statements contained in the Memorial
which Mr. Morel has delivered to Mr. Roosevelt.</p>

<p>At the request of said organization representing as it does
the elite of the Belgian Nation, I beg you to hand the President
the accompanying letter which faithfully set out the higher principles
of the Congo State's internal policy. You Will, in delivering
this communication to President Roosevelt, reiterate to him, on
my behalf, the feelings of high esteem I have for him and the 
unshaken confidence I place in his spirit of justice and impartiality.</p>

<p>I have to express the desire that Mr. Roosevelt will kindly
take cognizance of this address in your presence, so that you may
be afforded an opportunity to give him any further information he
might wish to obtain from you.</p>

<p>The foundation and fairness of the case which you have been
good enough to undertake to defend will supply you with such
numerous and conclusive arguments as to confound the enemies
of the Congo Free State.</p>

<p>A mere examination of the Memorial issued by the Congo
Reform Association 'will show the bad faith of these people when
they affirm that the Commission of Enquiry recently appointed
by the Government of the Congo does not enjoy complete liberty
of investigation nor afford every guarantee of impartiality. This
affirmation is at once denied by a perusal of the instructions of
the Commission, which as will be seen by the accompanying text,
have given them full liberty and full autonomy.</p>

<p>This fact taken alone amongst many others is sufficient to
caution honest people against the biased assertions of our opponents;
these are set at naught by the economic progress realized
by the Congo State as is demonstrated by numbers of facts and
illustrated by the album of photographic reproductions taken in
the Congo, a copy of which will interest President Roosevelt.</p>

<p>Believe me, dear Colonel Kowalsky,<lb/>
Yours truly,<lb/>
Leopold.</p>

<p>(Signed)<lb/>
Brussels, October 4, 1904.</p>

</div2>


<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Dufourne to Theodore Roosevelt.</head>

<p>Brussels, October 3, 1904. Federation pour la Defense des Interets Belges, l'Etranger.</p>

<p>To his Excellency, Theodore Roosevelt,
President of the United States.</p>

<p>Mr. President:</p>

<p>The Federation for the Defense of Belgian Interests Abroad
presents its compliments to the President of the United States
and begs leave to state:</p>

<p>That we are loth to impose upon the President of the United
States considerations which are foreign to the interests of his
government. But inasmuch as certain persons are conducting
within the United States a movement to involve the Government
of the United States in the consideration of their unfounded
charges and interested misrepresentations against the Government
of the Congo Free State, we feel it our duty to present a brief
statement of the objects of the Congo Government to the President
of a friendly power in order that the unjust methods being employed
by the enemies of the Congo Free State may not mislead
the President to encourage Congressional action prejudicial to our
interests before we shall have been fully heard.</p>

<p>Our Association has been formed for the defence of Belgian
interests and possessions abroad. Our people esteem and admire
the people of the United States and have great respect for their
President. The Belgians desire that they shall not be slandered
and vilified in the midst of the American people. They feel it
their duty to assist the American people to a proper understanding
of the lofty purposes which actuate the Government of the
Congo Free State. In this connection the Belgians recall with
pleasure and with pride the fact that the Government of the United
States was the first great nation to recognize the flag of the International
Association of the Congo as that of an independent State.
By its treaties and by its adherence to the Berlin and Brussels
Acts it promised liberty of trade in its part of the Congo Basin,
and it respectfully asserts that it has fulfilled that promise in spirit
and to the letter, insofar as the short term of its existence in a
savage country has enabled it to establish an organization which,
by its prosperity and progress, now' excites the envy of those who
seek to disrupt it.</p>

<p>The principles which actuate the Congo Government are
tersely set out in an essay written by a highly qualified American
subject, which is herewith enclosed. May we humbly beg the
President of the United States to honor us by perusing this concise
exposition of the fundamental principles which underlie, and
which have given such progressive momentum to, the Government
of the Congo Free State?</p>

<p>The principles of the Congo Government are devoted to progress
and civilization. The State's motto is "Work and Progress."
We have always felt that to intelligently follow that motto was
to firmly establish in the midst of conditions of savagery the
habit of industry and a respect for property as well as for life,
according to the universal law of nations.</p>

<p>Concerning the term "Freedom of Commerce," which Congo
enemies are interpreting to mean ungoverned license, we beg to
refer the President to the United States Laws and Penalties concerning
trespass upon and pillage of public lands and their product.
Perhaps no nation in the world has so precisely developed
the law of private and public property nor administered it with
finer understanding of the principles of equity and justice than the
United States. The Congo law relating to property is in consonance
with the law of the world's greatest nations. The great
success which has been attained by the Congo Government for
the betterment of its native inhabitants by the operation of this law
and the order which exists thereunder, has excited the envy and
the avarice of those whose ulterior motive is being cloaked in the
garb of humanitarianism and questionable philanthropy. On the
one hand it is charged that the Congo Government by its methods
seeks to enslave the native in order that he may serve it with
his hands for the benefit of interests whose welfare he does not
share. On the other hand, the libelers of the Congo wilfully
utter not only the unfounded accusation, but the inconsistent
charge, that the government cuts off the hand whose work it seeks
to enslave. Concerning the untruthful character of the testimony
in this respect which has been published against the Congo by the
promoters of the so-called "Congo Reform Association" of Liverpool,
we beg to refer your Excellency to the great mass of
genuine and reliable evidence uttered by Englishmen, Frenchmen,
Germans, Americans, Italians and Belgians in direct contradiction
of the falsehoods which form the traffic of the Association,
whose leading spirit has never been near the Congo nor the
natives who form the pretext of his search for personal notoriety
and aggrandisement.</p>

<p>May we also call your Excellency's attention to the fact that
the Congo Government, when assailed by missionaries at all, is
assailed by a few individual missionaries operating in conjunction
with the Liverpool Association, whose object we shall in due
course expose? The Congo Government has not been assailed by
Catholic missionaries at all. The Catholic missionaries are in
reality seeking the moral, spiritual and intellectual betterment
of the native race, while those of a maetrial faith, who have
sought from the Congo Government and been denied personal
concessions of material value solely, are secretly working in directions
entirely unconnected with the spiritual and moral welfare
of the Congo population. In due time and in the proper place
the government of the Congo Free State will produce its testimony
bearing upon this phase of the campaign begun in England,
and now carried to the United States, against an undertaking
which, within twenty years, has accomplished a greater success
of civilization than has ever before been attained in all the great
continent of Africa.</p>

<p>We beg your Excellency to receive from the hands of our 
representative an abundance of carefully-prepared matter upon
this subject, and to command him in any further desires which
you may wish to express. A cursory outline, limited to only a
few phases of the questions which the enemies of the Congo so
confusedly mince in their wild condemnation of a State justly
founded and intelligently and humanly governed, is not, of course
intended as a sufficient statement of our case. It is merely intended
to introduce your Excellency to the subject on which our
representative and the evidence and literature he will offer to you
may lead you to those wise and equitable conclusions which have
always characterized the highest tribunals of the American
people.</p>

<p>Your Excellency is too well versed in the science of general
government to be influenced by the statement that where individual
acts are committed in violation of enacted penal laws the
government should be primarily charged therewith. If such
were the case penal institutions for the incarceration of violators
of police law would be no part of a nation's structures.</p>

<p>It is not infrequent that the cable bears to us mention that
in some sections of your own free and glorious country an inflamed
mob seizes upon a black inhabitant and burns him at the
stake. Our governmental experience has taught us that such
acts would have been impossible if your government had been
advised in time to prevent them. And yet we know that your
government is the subject of harsh criticism by self-constituted
associations formed in the same country from whence come those
who accuse the sincere governmental effort of the Congo Free
State. The law of the Congo Free State is based upon the loftiest
ideals of humane control of a vast territory and undeveloped interests,
and every part of the State's machinery is employed to
ensure equal justice to all.</p>

<p>The "method of the State" at which Congo accusers hurl
their shafts, cannot be charged with the responsibility for the
lawless acts, in a vast territory of a million square miles, where
the government of that State is vigilently and earnestly seeking
by the extension of its organization and police powers to suppress
and punish all crime and redress all wrongs. If the subjects
of one nation were compelled to submit to the opinion of its unfriendly
neighbors as to the correctness of their habits and conduct,
and were compelled to submit themselves to the penalties
that their neighbors would attach to the alleged misconduct, the
subjects of one nation would be in the prisons of another.</p>

<p>We need hardly call the attention of your government to the
great and humane work which your government is now so
earnestly and with so much sacrifice furthering in the Philippine
Islands, to meet with that broad and sympathetic view of the
situation in all savage countries which, if fairly and justly applied
to the Congo Free State, would place us upon that plane
where co-operation, not criticism, were the merit of our sacrificial
work in the darkest part of Africa.</p>

<p>It has been the pleasure of our beloved King, Leopold II.,
Sovereign of the Congo Free State, to appoint a Commission
composed of eminent men to undertake with the utmost freedom
a judicial investigation upon all and singular the vague charges
from time to time used by the promoters of the "Congo Reform
Association" in prostituting certain public journals published in
England. Your Excellency may be assured of the utmost integrity
of the gentlemen who compose this Commission and that
the Congo Government will afford them all the help in its power
to place the truth before the eyes of the world.</p>

<p>In this connection Congo reformer~pretend that the decisions
of the Congo courts indicate that the government is bad, when
in truth and in fact these very decisions are, in our opinion, proof
of unimpeachable good faith and judicial independence.</p>

<p>Concerning the Congo standing army of 14,000 natives, as
to which some criticism is uttered by the same persons, we need
only indicate that the State Government is so well respected in
the Congo Basin that it is able to control its vast territory with
only seven soldiers to every 625 square miles. We have no doubt
that if the Congo governmental system had not included this
meagre police force for the repression of tribal strife and the
maintenance of order, its critics would have represented the
Congo Government as unprepared to guarantee protection to persons
and to property, and unable to maintain the integrity of its
frontiers. The Congo army is recruited in conformity with the
Belgian law of Conscription, which is a restriction of the universal
service in continental Europe. When heretofore the government
enlisted a part of its army in a neighboring colony, it was requested
to desist, the promises of England to permit such recruiting
notwithstanding. Now the Congo Army is characterized as
barbarian! We are assured that the Congo Government would
have no objection to the advantage of recruiting its army in
China, in a manner following that of the Transvaal.</p>

<p>It is the earnest desire of the Belgian people and those who
are sincerely interested in the welfare and progress of the native
population of mid-Africa, that the good-will and respect of the
people of the United States and their President may continue,
by their sympathy, to enliven the devotion, energy and sacrifice
which the builders of the Congo Free State are expending upon
races which but a few years ago were in a state of the wildest
savagery. The vein of sympathy between Belgium and America
has its highest proof from the fact that we have a large population
of Americans residing in Belgium, where their residence has
always been peculiarly pleasurable to the Belgian people.</p>

<p>Commending to your Excellency our representative, who is
an eminent citizen of the United States and well ·known to its
President, we beg for him that courtesy and attention and the
application of those broad principles which your Excellency invariably
brings to the consideration of all subjects.</p>

<p>We are, Mr. President, with great respect,<lb/>
Your obedient servants,
(Signed) Dufourne,<lb/>
The President of the Federation pour le Defense des Interets Belges a l'Etranger.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="two pages"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Henry I. Kowalsky to Thomas S. Barbour.</head>

<p>New York, November 16, 1904.</p>

<p>Thomas S. Barbour, D.D., Cor. Sec'y,<lb/>
American Baptist Missionary Union, Tremont Temple, Boston, Mass.</p>

<p>My Dear Sir:</p>

<p>Your letter of October 18th addressed to me under care of
Baron Moncheur, Belgian Minister, Washington, D. C., was forwarded
to me at the Hoffman House. I learned of the existence
of this letter through the newspapers before I had the honor of
receiving the original. The important position you occupy as the
executive head of the foreign department of the American Baptist
Missionary Society entitles your letter to respectful consideration.
Absence from the city and important engagements must be my
excuse for not having answered it before this.</p>

<p>I note with pleasure the interest you take in the affairs of
the Congo Free State and your desire for light in regard to the
conditions existing in that country. You say the impressions made
upon your mind by testimony obtained from many sources differ
materially from the statements made by me in my conversations
with newspaper correspondents regarding the subject. I may say
that my views in relation to this subject are in no wise peculiar;
they were arrived at after a full investigation of the testimony
of reputable and disinterested persons and after an examination
of many documents. In fact, I reserved for myself a lawyer's
right of thorough investigation, and of being convinced of the
truth and justice of the cause of the Congo Free State before consenting
to be retained. My continued investigations into the
State's affairs and my observation of the methods of those who are
slandering and vilifying it, only tend to confirm my belief that a
great wrong is being heaped upon a government which is working
nobly and unselfishly to advance civilization and religion among
a race which but a few years since was wild and savage. Ministers
properly following their vocation should be peacemakers,
not tormentors of those who, according to the testimony of honest
travelers, regardless of creed, have embraced this vast field, and
its opportunities to serve God and humanity.</p>

<p>My beliefs represent in the main the views heretofore expressed
by his Eminence, Cardinal Gibbons.</p>

<p>Your proposition to meet me in joint debate in the City of
Washington would have my hearty approval were it not for the
fact that I question the propriety of either you or I engaging, as
mere partisans, in debating a question, which as you well say,
involves a subject of profound interest affecting the well-being
of many millions of people. The subject, in my humble judgment,
is too grave and is fraught with too serious consequences to
warrant the indulgence of any partisanship, and I am not ambitious
to occupy the public eye unnecessarily, especially for the
purpose of debating at random along partisan lines.</p>

<p>Permit me to say in all kindness that your letter indicates the
advocate and controversialist rather than the unbiased seeker after
truth, and I fear that, owing to the weaknesses common to humanity
and of which it is reasonable to assume you and I possess
our share, a public controversy in the form of a debate would
lead only to heated argument not conducive to a correct understanding
of the conditions now existing in the Congo Free State.
What the Congo Government has always desired and what up to
this time it has absolutely been denied, has been the opportunity
to meet and answer specific charges made by a complainant whose
motives are unquestionably fair and impartial and whose charges
are based upon the positive knowledge of a correctly informed
person rather than upon irresponsible information and belief.</p>

<p>In order to render the proposed debate of any value in the
interests of truth, it must occur to you, as to any right-minded
man, that specific charges should be formulated and persons should
be directly accused of the crimes so idly made against the Congo
Government. I ask you, therefore, to specify the exact charges
which are to be the subject of this debate so as to enable me to
frame an answer.</p>

<p>In approaching the discussion of this subject, permit me to
call your attention to the fact that the claim of impeccability is
not asserted by the government in question. It freely confesses
that it is a human institution and that at times it may have failed
to discover and legally punish grave and serious offenses. On the
other hand, it should be conceded by our opponents that the government
of such a people as inhabit the immense domain known as
the "Congo Free State" is not without difficulty, and that the
inhabitants of that region, in common with the other children of
Adam, are somewhat marked by the trail of the serpent.</p>

<p>That atrocities were committed by the natives on each other
in the early life of this State in accordance with tribal customs,
which acts would now be subject to the penal law of the country,
may be conceded. These occur even in highly civilized States, and
it is not to be wondered that they occasionally happen among a
savage and uncivilized people.</p>

<p>The Congo Free State contends, and this contention cannot
be successfully denied, that in the main its government has been
enlightened and civilized. It has always had an eye single to
the welfare and prosperity of its people, and wherever these principles
have been departed from it has been due to the infirmities
of the human instruments it has employed, infirmities common to
all governments and human institutions.</p>

<p>In conclusion, permit me to say that the most disheartening
feature of the attempts of the Congo Government to firmly plant
civilized institutions in this great territory has been the carping
criticism of some of the organizations whose purpose it was believed
to be the planting of the seed of Christianity among the
uncivilized races of the globe. I recall the fact that at the late
Peace Congress held in Boston, it was with difficulty that one of
our friends obtained ten minutes' time to reply to an hour's discussion
presented by the friends of the Honorary Secretary of a
self-constituted Liverpool association. A disgruntled American
missionary to whom concessions in the Congo were refused was
permitted to inveigh against the government without restriction,
but a respectful hearing was denied those who sought to enlighten
your Congress with facts and figure. The Resolutions passed
were not openly given to the members of the Convention to deliberate
upon, but were suddenly sprung upon the body, after a
judicious amount of politics had been done to arrange for their
passage and to avoid dissent. In fact the conduct of the Peace
Congress creates the impression that even good men may not always
be relied upon to act fairly; that they are often inclined to
confound the denial of the commission of a crime with an expression
of sympathy for it. Permit me to further say that neither
you nor I are in a position to speak authoritatively for the United
States Government, and to call your attention to the fact, which
perhaps you have lost sight of, that the government of the Congo
is an independent sovereignty, having absolute control, in common
with all governments; over its own internal affairs, and that it is
responsible only to its own subjects and to the law of nations for
any infractions it may commit.</p>

<p>I am leaving for California immediately, where my legal
engagements will require my attention until the latter part of
December, at which time, if proper issues are framed and it is
desirable in the interests of truth, I may arrange to meet you in
a public debate.</p>

<p>I am,<lb/>
Respectfully,<lb/>
Henry I. Kowalsky.</p>

<p>P.S. -- If this is to your satisfaction, you can give copies to
Washington Post and Star and also Associated Press.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
