<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0904">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward, December 31, 1862</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0904</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 2</biblScope>
<date when="1862-12-31">December 31, 1862</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hanson, Abraham</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1862-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-04-16"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-05" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0078.jpg"/>

<p>No. 7.</p>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency,<lb/>
Monrovia, Dec 31st., 1862.</p>

<p>To the Honorable William H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State of U.S. of A.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to
enclose herein, duplicate copies of the Message
of His Excellency, S. A. Benson, President of Liberia,
to the Legislature.</p>

<p>I also have the honor to enclose duplicate
copies of a "Prospectus" of a plan for
the promotion and extension of Commerce, between
Great Britain, and the West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>I have the honor to remain,<lb/>
With Sincere Respect,<lb/>
Your very Obedient Servt.<lb/>
Abm Hanson,<lb/>
U.S. Com. Agent.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0079.jpg"/>

<note>U.S. Commercial Agency
Monrovia December 31, 1862<lb/>
Abm Hanson Com. Agent</note>

<note>No 7<lb/>
2 Enclosures<lb/>
Received</note>

<note>Annual Message of
President to Legislature of Liberia</note>

<note>Prospectus of a scheme 
of British capitalists for
enlargement of their commerce
with that coast of Africa</note>

<note>Received at Statistical Office May 16/63</note>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0080.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<note>Copy of the Original Prospectus as published in England.</note>

<head type="main">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Incorporated under the Joint Stock Companies' Act of 1856 and 1857, whereby the liability of the Shareholders is limited to the amount of their Subscriptions.</p>

<p>CAPITAL £250,000, in 25,000 SHARES of £10 Each.</p>

<p>FIRST ISSUE 12,500 SHARES.</p>

<p>£1 to be paid on application, and £1 10s. on allotment. The holders of such first Shares to have the preference, pro rata, in all further issues. No call to exceed £2 10s. per Share, nor to be made except at an interval of at least three months from any previous Call.</p>

<p>If no allotment be made, the Deposit will be returned in full.</p>

<list>
<head>Directors.</head>
<item>Thomas Bazley, Esq., M.P., Manchester.</item>
<item>Thomas Bradshaw, Esq., Temple.</item>
<item>George Braginton, Esq., Torrington, Devon.</item><item>Thomas Briggs, Esq., Prestwich Park, Manchester.</item>
<item>Henry Brownrigg, Esq., 33, Lime Street, E.C.</item>
<item>Thomas Clegg, Esq., Manchester.</item>
<item>Frederic Doulton, Esq., M.P., Lambeth.</item>
<item>Ambrose Emerson, Esq. (Messrs. Newby, Carson &amp; Co., Gresham House, E.C.)</item>
<item>Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, F.R.G.S., J.P., Cardiff.</item>
<item>Gerard Ralston, Esq., Consul-General for Liberia, 21, Tokenhouse Yard, E.C.</item>
<item>(with power to add.)</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Bankers.</head>
<item>The London and Westminster Bank, Lothbury, E.C.</item>
<item>Solicitors. Messrs. Cotterill &amp; Sons, 32, Throgmorton Street.</item>
<item>Brokers. Messrs. Huggins &amp; Rowsell, 1, Threadneedle Street.</item>
<item>General Manager. J. B. Langley, Esq.</item>
<item>Secretary. F. W. Stone, Esq.</item>
<item>Shipping and Insurance Agent. Charles Kitto, Esq.</item>
<item>Temporary Offices. 41, Gresham House, E.C.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Prospectus.</head>

<p>The object of the Company is–To establish Trading Stations, Factories, and Depots on the Coast of Western Africa, and by means of organized Agencies, to bring down and collect for shipment at such stations, the valuable products of the Interior; to import Goods, and introduce Machinery for cleaning and pressing Cotton, and for other purposes; and generally to enter into Commercial relations with the Native Traders, by means of barter traffic or otherwise; and thereby to open up, in exchange for British manufactures, a practically illimitable market for Cotton and other products–and to secure their transmission to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>The capabilities of Africa to meet the commercial requirements of Europe are evidenced in the variety of its productions, and the increasing extent of its trading operations; and it has long been a matter of surprise, that the encouragement of Native industry should have been left to associations of a philanthropic character, or to a few Merchants intent upon the enormous profit which exclusive dealings with the Natives incontestably afford.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0081.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Cotton.</head>

<p>The cultivation of the Cotton Plant, and the employment of African labour on its native soil, have already been sufficiently tested. There is abundance of labour seeking employment, a fertile soil well adapted for its growth, and a population actively alive to what will benefit themselves. <hi rend="italics">No expensive or uncertain experiments are required to test the ability or the will of the Natives to supply this country with cheap and good cotton.</hi> The testimony of the officers of the Niger expedition concurs with, and confirms, the evidence of Dr. Livingstone, and other African travellers, that indigenous Cotton is growing in abundance throughout vast districts, covering many thousands of miles of territory, and only waits to be gathered. Some Tribes of the Natives are largely engaged in manufacturing Cotton into clothing for their own use. It is calculated that more than 200,000 pieces of these cloths are annually exported from Africa into the Brazils. In fact, only buyers on the spot are wanted to take from the Natives what they have to offer, giving in exchange manufactured goods suitable to their requirements.</p>

<p>In a letter from Dr. Balfour Bakie, in command of the Niger Expedition, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, which Lord Russell caused to be inserted in the <hi rend="italics">London Gazette</hi> of August 29th, 1862, he emphatically urges his Lordship "to call attention, in England, to the peculiar eligibility of this portion of Central Africa (Bida Nusse), as a Cotton field." Again, speaking of Sudan, and the Yoruba country, he proceeds to say–Here Cotton is already in abundance, and cultivated by a people able and willing to work, and accustomed to its habits and rearing; nothing is required but increased demand, means of purchase, cleaning and shipment. The rest would speedily follow."</p>

<p>Another practical authority–Mr. Clegg, of Manchester, who has an establishment at Abeokuta, states–"for very many years my instructions have been to cease buying Cotton, when more than a halfpenny per pound in the Seed, and my young Africans have again and again written to say, that at that price for more was brought to them than they could buy."</p>

<p>Mr. I. Lyons McLeod, Hon. Secretary to the African Aid Society, in a Letter to the <hi rend="italics">Times</hi>, March 28th, 1861, writes–"It is a well-attested fact, that from Western Africa (shipping port Lagos), Cotton in abundance maybe purchased at 2d. per lb., and allowing for exorbitant overcharge for cleaning freight, &amp;c., it may be sold from the same locality in Liverpool at 4½d. per lb. This Cotton is equal in quality to New Orleans at 6½d. per lb., proving beyond doubt, that from Western Africa, which is nearer to our shores than the Cotton districts of America, we may obtain the same amount of Cotton for £20,000,000, for which we are paying the Slaveholders of the United States £30,000,000. In Western Africa–the Yoruba Country, and along the valley of the Niger," (the localities above referred to by Dr. Balfour Bakie)–"the Natives are ready to supply any amount of Cotton for Manchester and Glasgow Manufacturers."</p>
<p>These testimonies appear to demand the most serious attention and consideration at the present crisis.</p>

<p>The supply of Cotton from the Southern States (which till a recent date formed 80 per cent. of our consumption), cannot be fully renewed for several years; part of the crop of 1861 has been burned, and the remainder may never reach us. In 1862, it is believed, that only about one-fourth of the usual crop has been sown, and it is not likely that a larger area can be placed under Cotton Culture in 1863; so that, if the Civil War were to be ended by any means to-morrow, the full supply of American Cotton could not be resumed till September, 1864. Till that date, the price of middling and ordinary Orleans are not likely to fall below One Shilling per pound.</p>

<p>There is abundant evidence to show that India cannot for many years supply the quantity or quality required. The Egyptian supply is the only one which might be supposed likely to compete with that imported from West Africa; but the Egyptian Cotton imported into England has never hitherto reached 200,000 bales in any one year, and if doubled (which it cannot be for two or three years), it will not suffice to make up the deficiency created by the reduced supplies of ordinary Americans. Besides, the average price of <sic>Egytian</sic> Cotton has been 8d. per pound for several years. African Cotton, equal to middling Orleans, can be delivered in Liverpool, at a cost to the Importer of Fourpence Halfpenny per pound. In the seed, in Africa, it may be procured in unlimited quantities at about one Halfpenny per pound; cleaned Cotton about Threepence. Payments being made in barter, the profits on the Goods reduce the cost price of the Cotton considerably.</p>

<p>It is not the intention of the "West Africa Company" to become <hi rend="italics">Cultivators of Cotton</hi>; the Company will simply be <hi rend="italics">Purchasers of Cotton</hi>, which will be brought down to their Stations by the Native Traders, and thence Shipped to the Ports of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>Several well-known Firms, having used African Cotton in their Manufactories, are able to report favourably of its quality working.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0082.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">General Trade.</head>

<p>The Company will not, however, depend on Cotton alone for realising the good dividend on the capital employed. The interchange of commodities will be widened to the largest possible extent, so as to include every other product of Africa, which will pay an enhanced value in this country. These products, which consist chiefly of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, Gold Dust, Ivory, Hides, Indigo, Copper, Ground Nuts, Pepper, Arrowroot, Gums, Dye Woods, Ostrich Feathers, Timber for Shipbuilding, and other articles of commerce, equally suitable to the requirements of our markets, will also be made the media of trade, so as to suit the industry and keen trading instincts of the various classes of Native producers. The fact that the production of Palm Oil, Shea Butter, and other valuable articles, is in excess of the local demand, can be shown by the latest and most indubitable authorities. The Rev. Samuel Crowther, writing to the Church Missionary Society lately, states, "at the Delta of the Niger alone, millions' worth, in red Oil and black Oil from the kernels of the Palm nut, rot away annually for want of inducement to collect them."* From an official document received through the Board of Trade, it appears that in 1856 upwards of 220,000 tons of these kernels, from which Oil of the value of £3,789,000 might have been extracted, were actually thrown away on the coast. The amount thus lost represents in actual value a sum of upwards of a Million Sterling more than all the tallow exported from Russia in that year; and when it is considered that the tallow was paid for in cash, and that the bulk of the trade with Africa may be carried on by barter of the manufactures of Manchester, Glasgow, Birmingham, the Potteries, and Sheffield, it is impossible to overrate the benefits which will accrue to this country by developing the resources of Western Africa.</p>

<p>As there is no currency in the Country, trade is conducted by means of barter, so that a market for English productions will be opened at every point from which the Company draws its supplies of raw materials; a profit both ways will thus be obtained by the Company, viz: Upon the goods sold in Africa, and <hi rend="italics">vice versá</hi>, upon the Cotton, Palm Oil, &amp;c., imported and sold in the English markets.</p>

<p>The "West Africa Company," will commence operations under peculiarly favorable circumstances, owing to the fact that their Agencies on the West Coast of Africa are already organized; and competent acclimatised persons, native merchants and others, at Abeokuta, Elmina, Lagos, Cape Palmas, and in the Niger river, are ready to act in behalf of the Company the moment it commences business.</p>

<p>From the foregoing statements, taken together with the fact that this Company will possess unusual facilities for successful mercantile operations, owing to its large Capital and connexions, it is confidently expected that its transactions will produce very handsome dividends. Persons having a knowledge of the Africa
trade will readily <sic>undrestand</sic>that to name what would be a probable rate of interest on the Capital worked, would, to the uninitiated, bear the stamp of exaggeration. The Directors, however, feel assured that the Company will eventually assume such dimensions as to invest it with a most important character; and that the development of the resources of Africa will do more than anything else to hasten the extinction of the Foreign Slave Trade, an event not more desirable to philanthropy than to commerce.</p>

<p>* See African Aid Society's Report for 1862, page 10, and generally in confirmation of the statements herein, the Annual Reports of the Cotton Supply Association; "The Cotton Plant and Countries adapted to its Culture," pages 5-15, &amp;c.; D. J. May, Esq., R. N., (Niger Expedition), and the Reports of Mr. Consul Burton; Mr. Davis, Surgeon to the Niger Expedition; ratified as they are by Mr. Consul Campbell; the Rev. Mr. Townsend, of Abeokuta; Dr. R. Ross, Esq.; and by Capt. J. F. Napier Hewett, in his recent work "European Settlements on the West Coast of Africa."</p>

<p>Application for Shares may be made in the accompanying form to the Brokers, Messrs. Huggins &amp; Roswell, 1, Threadneedle Street, London, E.C., or to the Secretary, at the Temporary Offices of the Company, 41, Gresham House, E.C.</p>

<p>[For Special Notice addressed to the Residents on the West Coast of Africa, see over.]</p>

</div2>

<pb n="Roll2-0083.jpg"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">The West Africa Company, Limited.</head>

<p>Capital £250,000, in 25,000 Shares of £10 each.<lb/>
First Issue 12,500 Shares.</p>

<p>Prospectus.</p>

<p>S. Straker &amp; Sons, Printers, 20, Bishopsgate Within &amp; 25, Leadenhall Street.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<p>Coast Allotment.]</p>

<p>SPECIAL NOTICE</p>

<p>To the Merchants, Capitalists, and others on the<lb/>
West Coast of Africa.</p>

<p>The Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," established in England by Act of Parliament limiting the liability of each Shareholder to the amount of his Subscriptions, have <hi rend="italics">resolved to reserve 2,500 Shares for the Capitalists on the West Coast.</hi> Mr. William Grant, of Kissy Road, Sierra Leone, and Captain Davis, of Lagos, are acquainted with the Directors; and copies of the Articles of Association, under which the Company is incorporated by law, are in the hands of the former.</p>

<p>Form of Application for Shares.</p>

<p>To the Directors of "The West Africa Company, Limited," (in England).</p>

<p>Gentlemen,–Having remitted by Draft on &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; the Sum of &#160; &#160; &#160; sterling, I request you to allot me &#160; &#160; &#160; Shares in the Company; and I agree to accept the same or any less number that may be allotted to use me, and to comply with all the rules and regulations of the Company.</p>

<p>Name</p>

<p>Address</p>

<p>Occupation</p>

<p>Date</p>

<p>[The applicant should enclose his application with the Draft addressed to "J. B. Langley, Esq., General Manager West Africa Company, 41, Gresham House, London, England," or in lieu thereof he should forward instructions to his Agent in England <unclear>to</unclear> make application on his behalf, and to pay the deposit (£1 per Share on application, and £1 10s. on allotment). It will be <unclear>necessary</unclear> in case of remittances direct from the Coast that hte whole of the deposit, £2 10s. per Share, should be seat at once.]</p>

</div2>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0084.jpg"/>

<head type="main">Message of the President of the Republic of Liberia to the Legislature, at the Commencement of their Session December 1862.</head>

<head type="sub">Monrovia: G. Killian, Printer, Liberia Herald Office. 1862</head>

<pb n="Roll2-0086.jpg"/>

<head type="sub">Message.</head>

<p>To the Honorable–The Senate, and the House of Representatives of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>Gentlemen,</p>

<p>Nearly nine months absence from the Republic this year, and having returned only a few days previously to the opening of your Session, have rendered me almost entirely dependent on my constitutional substitute, for data–on the home affairs of our common country, which I have not had sufficient time to consider, and put in that shape, by amplification, as we have mutually desired. I shall therefore make communication to you from time to time during the Session, on such matters as I shall deem promotive of the interests of the country.</p>

<p>I have first, to invite the attention of the Legislature to the manifold disturbances and outrages committed by the Little Sess Fishermen. The peace and quietude of our leeward coast have been sadly disturbed by them during the past year. They have been accused, of not only having made war upon, and killed several of the Niffaw people without reasonable cause–as was ascertained by the Secretary of the Treasury during his visit of investigation to the leeward this year, but have also monopolized, all the portering business along the coast, such as the shipping and unshipping of goods, and the usual services performed by Kroomen on board of trading ships. Fishermen connected with other tribes are compelled to forego the benefits which they would derive from such employment, through fear of the treachery, jealousy and illwill of the Little Sess Fishermen, who are very numerous and live on nearly every part of our coast as adventurers. I indulge the hope that the Legislature will, during the present Session, devise some plan, by which the turbulence of this tribe may be restrained so that order and peace may again be restored along the coast.</p>

<p>On the 19th of April, the Government Schooner Quail arrived from

<pb n="Roll2-0087.jpg"/>

the leeward counties bringing with her the Commissioners appointed under the Act passed at your last Session, authorizing the appointment of commissioners to select a site in the interior for the seat of Government.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the dry season was far advanced, they were, nevertheless commissioned and sent on their mission. After an absence of some seventeen days, they returned to this city having in their tour selected two sites in the vicinity of Bees' Mountain in the rear of the Junk Country, either one of which will, they think, meet the object contemplated.</p>

<p>Intelligence was received on the 17th, of April of the return to the Gallinas, in another vessel, of the Captain of the Spanish slave schooner Bueneventura Cubana, which was seized in that river by the Quail June 1861, and which was subsequently wrested from her by H. B. M. S. Torch. The object of the return of the Spanish Captain to the Gallinas, was to procure the slaves purchased with the cargo brought out in the Bueneventura Cubana. The advice boat, steamer Seth <sic>Grosvernor</sic> was immediately dispatched to the Gallinas, with the Secretary of the Treasury in her, with instructions to arrest, seize and bring to this city for adjudication and trial, all vessels and persons that he might find there, engaged in the slave Trade. His visit resulted in an interview with Prince Manna, the native Chief of Gallinas, the Slaver to take off a single slave from the Gallinas. As the steamer passed out of the Gallinas river, a glimpse of the Spanish vessel was descried wide in the offing. I am happy to be able to inform the Legislature, that the two voyages of the spanish Captain to our coast for a cargo of slaves, were entirely frustrated through the <sic>vigilence</sic> of this Government, and that every exertion will be used to prevent the native chiefs living within our Jurisdiction from holding out inducements to the slave dealer to approach our coast.</p>

<p>The Educational interest has had and will continue to have special attention. The Common day schools authorized at the last Session to be increased and put in operation in each county, were established as early as the several School Committees could engage teachers and procure books. They number in the aggregate sixteen schools, to be increased by the number to be established in Grand Bassa County. Books are very much needed.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the long and almost unprecedented dry season this year, occasioning the loss of a large number of early crops of grain, and the resowing of others: succeeded suddenly by a heavy and incessant rainy season, causing great damage to the maturing plantations of various products, especially to those of cotton, scores of acres of which were destroyed–yet, the agricultural interest is of an encouraging character, admitting of a fair comparison with that of last year. The sugar cane crops increased on the St. Paul's, and the quantity augmented by that grown in the leeward Counties. It

<pb n="Roll2-0088.jpg"/>

affords me much pleasure to be able to say that the people of Liberia are paying more attention than ever to the cultivation of the soil, and to the rich products which so readily find a market in foreign countries.</p>

<p>The Government has, during the year imported six sugar mills, which have been judiciously distributed among the several Counties; and it is the intention to import others for the convenience of our farmers, so soon as it shall be practicable.</p>

<p>The actual revenue of the country is insufficient to meet the demands of government since so many public enterprises have been put on foot. The report of the Secretary of the Treasury will clearly demonstrate this. I invite the special attention of the Legislature to this subject; and I shall be happy to meet their wishes in any reasonable measures they may adopt for increasing the revenue of the country.</p>

<p>The receipts from all sources including recaptive African funds during the fiscal year ending 30 September 1862, were–$138-016-42</p>

<p>Total amount of <sic>disbursments</sic> for the same time was. $138.499-29</p>

<p>I will add in this connection that it is my firm purpose during the remaining year of my incumbency to employ every effort to liquidate all demands now against, and such as may be incurred up to the close of the fiscal year by government, in order that my successor may, on his induction, be relieved of unpleasant pecuniary embarrassments. To effect this, retrenchment will be indispensable; and as a consequence, several public enterprises must cease, until that object shall have been secured.</p>

<p>And I have to earnestly request, that you will cause your appropriation for the fiscal year to harmonize with this policy.</p>

<p>Under the appropriation made at your last session with a view to develop the iron resources in the vicinity of Careysburg, advances have been made from the Treasury, to Charles Deputie Esqr., of Careysburg, who, has succeeded, it is said, in demonstrating that the iron ore near that settlement is of superior quality. Samples of the iron smelted from the ore has been submitted to the government. No formal report, however, has as yet been received from him to enable the government to determine upon the propriety of making further advances for that object.</p>

<p>Specimens of ore found on the little Cape Mount river by Mr. J. G. J. Barbour and by him forwarded to the United States to be tested, were, on examination, said to be a rich quality of Coal. See Liberia Herald August 6th, 1862.</p>

<p>A revision of some of the Judiciary Acts is very necessary, in order to define more clearly the Jurisdiction of the Courts. The Attorney General will readily designate to you those conflicting laws, which, as long as they remain will keep up a conflict between the superior and inferior Courts.</p>

<p>Abraham Hanson Esqr. was received Sept. 2nd, 1862, and acknowledged as United States Commercial agent for Monrovia.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0089.jpg"/>

<p>By virtue of a resolution adopted by the Legislature of Liberia at their last session, granting the President of Liberia leave of absence from the Republic during the year 1862, or longer, should he deem it necessary for the restoration of his health, and vesting him with special authority, during his absence, to enter into any arrangements, and to transact any business he might deem promotive of the interest of Liberia, I embarked from this place on the 11th, of March, for Europe via Harper, and arrived in Liverpool on the 11th, of April.</p>

<p>Before leaving Liberia, I had determined that i would extend my visit to the U.S. within a few weeks after my arrival in England, provided my progress in the despatch of the more important public business in Europe, and letters I might receive in England from the U. States should justify it. The many difficulties, and at times sore humiliations we had long been subject to in the enforcement of our Commercial, Revenue and Navigation laws; and in our attempts to suppress the nefarious foreign <sic>trafic</sic> in human flesh and blood with the aborigines within our jurisdiction, rendered the definite and permanent adjustment with H. M. Government of our territorial claims, and boundaries, of paramount importance. Consequently, though I received several lettersi in Europe</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>