<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0925">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader, December 29, 1875</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0925</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1875-12-29">December 29, 1875</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1875-12-29"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66848474">Cadwalader, John L. (John Lambert), 1836-1914</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1876-02-14"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-08" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1044.jpg"/>

<p>No. 12.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Republic of Liberia</p>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
to the<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington U.S.A.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Report required by paragraph Nos. 380 and 381. of the Consular Regulations</p>

<p>Inclosures No. 1. Statement showing the imports and exports between Monrovia and the United States for the year ended Sept. 30, 1875.<lb/>
 " " 2. Statement showing the exports from Monrovia for the ended September 30th 1875.<lb/>
 " " 3 Statement showing the Exports from Monrovia to the United States for the year ended September 30th 1875.<lb/>
<catchwords>Inclosure</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1045.jpg"/>

Inclosure No. 4. Statement showing the Imports at Monrovia for the year ended September 30th 1875<lb/>
 " " 5. Statement showing the navigation at the port of Monrovia for the year ended September 30th 1875.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1046.jpg"/>

<p>No. 12.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia Liberia December 29 1875</p>

<p>Sir/</p>

<p>I have the honor to transmit as required by paragraphs 380. and 381. of the Consular Regulations the enclosed statements of the commerce of this port for the year ended September 30th 1875. It is a source of regret that the statistical report of the commerce of this port has been delayed because of the impossibility to obtain figures from the proper departments of the Government here, and although the accompanying statements may not be perfectly accurate they are such transcript as I could procure from their books; and may be regarded as near to the aggregate amount of the annual imports and exports of this port as is possible under the circumstances to reach. Among the exports coffee and palm oil are the principal; but on account of the <catchwords>inferior</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. John L. Cadwalader<lb/>
Ast. Secretary of State Washington &amp;c</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-1047.jpg"/>

inferior quality of the latter when compared with that obtained from ports on the south African coast together with the fluctuation of foreign markets, the Liberian palm oil is gradually losing its character as a profitable commodity.–coffee though, is rapidly supplying its place. And, seeing that the cultivation of this latter article is becoming generally more and more extensive, and the acknowledged superiority thereof is becoming more widely admitted, it cannot, it would seem, fail to produce the happy result desired by the growers thereof. Ivory though a valuable article is not so largely exported as I believe it might be. The Mandingoes, and "Veys" are the only tribes who give this a little attention; and although the distance at which the elephant is taken is great from the seaboard market of Liberia, and the means of transportation thereunto decidedly primitive, yet the ivory taken from elephants enter somewhat into the exportation
<catchwords>from</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1048.jpg"/>

from Liberian ports. Recently the farmers have been giving attention to the cultivation of ginger in Liberia. Their efforts in that direction have been attended with success sufficient to place the capacity of their soil to produce that article, beyond question, but as yet ginger has not attracted the general attention of farmers here. Arrow root and cocoa are in about the same condition as ginger. The absence from the country of proper manufacturing interests accounts for the small amount of native or other cloths exported. There is in this country undoubted evidence of extensive but undeveloped mineral <sic>rescources</sic>; and in the <sic>abscence</sic> of means there are but faint prospect of any revenue accruing to Liberia from this <sic>scource</sic>. There are several kinds of valuable wood growing voluntarily and in profuse abundance in this country, which should, but does not form a principal staple in exportation. The mahogany, the rosewood, and several kinds of wood of value and use in shipbuilding are found here in 
<catchwords>abundance</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1049.jpg"/>

abundance. The principal articles of importation are provisions, the most of which are brought from the United States. The duties upon the importations are sufficiently high,–not to say severe in some instances. Those articles of provision manufactured in the United States find a preference in this market, notwithstanding a very fair quality thereof is brought to be sold here from England, from Germany, and from the Netherlands. The duty of admission on flour is $1.50 per barrel; and the retail price thereof fluctuates from $15.00 to $20.00 per barrel, while the sale is invariably rapid. Other articles of provision such as: mess beef, pickled pork, lard, butter, crushed sugar, bacon, hams, mackerel in kits and barrels, smoked herring &amp;c, are imported and sold at corresponding prices, and with equally great demand. It will be observed that there is on the list of imports a division:–<sic>miscelaneous</sic>, tobacco falls under that classification on the books of the Department in this Government from
<catchwords>which</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1050.jpg"/>

which the figures are taken. It was desired to give tobacco and a few other articles <sic>seperate</sic> consideration, but on account of the peculiar form in which the books of this Government are kept, it was impossible to consider either that article or the gin and rum, as <sic>seperate</sic> items in the list of articles imported. Tobacco is generally imported from the United States in large quantities and forms a principal article in trade. Gin and Rum are brought chiefly from Germany, and the Netherlands, and like tobacco are classed among the principal articles of importation. The effect of the abusive use of these detestable articles, gin and rum, are clearly seen and felt through out this country–demoralizing the people. impairing their intellect, and performing their usual work of physical and moral ruin. The condition of the finances of this Government is by no means desirable or cheering. The only circulating medium is a paper issued by this Government, the face of which promises redemption in gold, and at present there is
<catchwords>but</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1051.jpg"/>

but little of it in circulation, the possibility is that it has nearly all fallen in to the possession of the traders, foreign and domestic. Those persons, unfortunately for the Government, are in a position to lock up this paper medium for at least a longer time than the Government can afford, and thereby compel the issue of more of this currency; which, when done will surely make the dollar of ten or fifteen per cent less value. All this it seems results from the <sic>abscence</sic> of a coin base, which being more valuable, the currency could at any time be called out of the hands of any who might hold it. It is sad to notice that the continued absence of a coin base will <del>necessarily</del> render the Government unable from time to time to honor her promises to redeem this paper, and thus afford speculators, merchants, and others the opportunity of placing their own value upon this paper currency; this can only tend to excite and shock the timidity of foreign capital that would otherwise perhaps, seek a <catchwords>field</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1052.jpg"/>

field of operation in Liberia, embarrass the agricultural and other industrial <sic>persuits</sic>–and of course, rest heaviest upon the labors of the country. It is for Liberia an unhappy circumstance that fast as she was gradually recovering from the effects of the revolutionary occurrences of 1871, the "Grebos," a powerful and influential tribe of aboriginal Africans residing within the jurisdiction of Liberia, rebelled against her authority, and thereby caused greater embarrassment than has ever before been experienced by this Republic; while the tribe, as such, seem to have experienced but little loss, and evince a strong determination to continue its resistance to the utter extent of its tribal capacity. I desire to inform the Department that the Liberian fiscal year begins on the 30th day of each month of September; and in adopting the 30th September as the date up to which this statement is made instead of the 30th
<catchwords>June</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1053.jpg"/>

June as required by the Regulations, I have been governed by a necessity arising out of the peculiar mode in which the books of the Liberian Government are kept. Owing to the almost entire absence from the record of the Liberian Government of the general statistical reports usually made and kept by governments I am unable to make this report as full as I would desire to do.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
With high consideration<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1054.jpg"/>

<note>Inclosure No. 1.</note>

<note>Original</note>

<p>Statement showing the imports and exports between Monrovia and the United States for the year ended September 30, 1875</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>Imports</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Exports</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Articles</cell>
<cell>Amount</cell>
<cell>Value</cell>
<cell>Amount</cell>
<cell>Value</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Provisions</cell>
<cell>644 Bbls - 77122 #</cell>
<cell>$28762.86</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cotton Goods</cell>
<cell>5765 pcs</cell>
<cell>17293.30</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Woolen -do.-</cell>
<cell>262 " </cell>
<cell>2361.87</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
<cell>372 Doz. - 27821 # - 164 pcs.</cell>
<cell>74200.06</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Ironware</unclear></cell>
<cell>94845 # - 9 Doz.</cell>
<cell>2845.34</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Drugs &amp; Medicines</cell>
<cell>9 cases</cell>
<cell>296.96</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Palm Oil</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>2166 galls.</cell>
<cell>$866.40</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>394 #</cell>
<cell>382.50</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Camwood</unclear></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>148 Tons</cell>
<cell>13680.00</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coffee</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>84050 #</cell>
<cell>16816.00</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ginger</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>145771 #</cell>
<cell>10281.10</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sugar</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>74205 #</cell>
<cell>4530.25</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cocoa</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>94 #</cell>
<cell>10.90</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Arrowroot</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>96 #</cell>
<cell>5.76</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Syrup</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>42 galls.</cell>
<cell>16.80</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Soap</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>3000</cell>
<cell>135.00</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Machinery</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>1 Box</cell>
<cell>10.00</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>J. Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1055.jpg"/>

<note><del>Continuation of</del> Inclosure No. 2.</note>

<note>Duplicate</note>

<p>Statement showing the Exports from Monrovia for the year ending September 30, 1875</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Quantity</cell>
<cell>Value</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties.</cell>
<cell>Countries whither exported.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Palm Oil</cell>
<cell>152759½ galls.</cell>
<cell>$61103.80</cell>
<cell>3055.19</cell>
<cell>England, United States, Hamburg, Rotterdam</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Kernels</cell>
<cell>20262 Bushels</cell>
<cell>9222.70</cell>
<cell>405.24</cell>
<cell>Do. Do. Do.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear extent="one word"/> Manufactured Cloths</cell>
<cell>2640 pcs</cell>
<cell>2640.00</cell>
<cell>52.80</cell>
<cell>Sierra Leone</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Camwood</unclear></cell>
<cell>148 Tons</cell>
<cell>13680.00</cell>
<cell>47.78</cell>
<cell>United States.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory</cell>
<cell>394 #</cell>
<cell>382.50</cell>
<cell>7.65</cell>
<cell>United States</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coffee</cell>
<cell>84080 #</cell>
<cell>16816.00</cell>
<cell>No duties</cell>
<cell>Do. Do.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ginger</cell>
<cell>145771 #</cell>
<cell>10281.10</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sugar</cell>
<cell>102000</cell>
<cell>5100.00</cell>
<cell/>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cocoa</cell>
<cell>94 #</cell>
<cell>10.90</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Syrup</cell>
<cell>42 galls.</cell>
<cell>16.80</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Sap</unclear></cell>
<cell>3000$</cell>
<cell>135.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Machinery</cell>
<cell>1 Box</cell>
<cell>10.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1056.jpg"/>

<note><del>Continuation of</del> Inclosure No 3.</note>

<note>Duplicate</note>

<p>Liberia</p>

<p>Statement showing the Exports from Monrovia to the United States for the year ended Sept.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Quantity</cell>
<cell>Value</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties</cell>
<cell>Countries whither exported</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Palm Oil</cell>
<cell>2166 galls</cell>
<cell>$866.40</cell>
<cell>$43.32</cell>
<cell>United States.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory</cell>
<cell>394 #</cell>
<cell>382.50</cell>
<cell>788</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Camwood</unclear></cell>
<cell>1483 ons.</cell>
<cell>13680.00</cell>
<cell>47.78</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coffee</cell>
<cell>840.80 #</cell>
<cell>16816.00</cell>
<cell>no duties</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ginger</cell>
<cell>145771 #</cell>
<cell>10281.10</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sugar</cell>
<cell>74205 #</cell>
<cell>4530.25</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cocoa</cell>
<cell>94 #</cell>
<cell>10.90</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Arrowroot</cell>
<cell>96 #</cell>
<cell>5.76</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Syrup</cell>
<cell>42 galls.</cell>
<cell>16.80</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Soap</cell>
<cell>3000 #</cell>
<cell>135.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Machinery</cell>
<cell>1 Box</cell>
<cell>10.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1057.jpg"/>

<note><del>Continuation of</del> Inclosure No 4</note>

<note>Duplicate</note>

<p>Statement showing the Imports at Monrovia for the year ending September 30, 1875</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Quantity</cell>
<cell>Value Entered</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties</cell>
<cell>Countries whence Imported</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Provisions.</cell>
<cell>967-115683 # Bbls</cell>
<cell>$43144.31</cell>
<cell>$5177.31</cell>
<cell>United States, England, Hamburg, Rotterdam</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cotton Goods.</cell>
<cell>17293 ps.</cell>
<cell>51879.11</cell>
<cell>6225.49</cell>
<cell> Do Do Do Do </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Woolen -do.-</cell>
<cell>524 ps.</cell>
<cell>4723.74</cell>
<cell>566.87</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Books &amp; Stationery.</cell>
<cell>426 Rms 89 doz. 34 Books</cell>
<cell>639.65</cell>
<cell>79.75</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><unclear>Ironware</unclear></cell>
<cell>379378⅓ # 36 doz</cell>
<cell>11381.35</cell>
<cell>1365.76</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Clothing</cell>
<cell>37 suits</cell>
<cell>543.22</cell>
<cell>65.18</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Drugs &amp; Medicines</cell>
<cell>13 Cs. 4 Doz.</cell>
<cell>1187.83</cell>
<cell>142.63</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
<cell>743 Doz 83463 # 482 pcs</cell>
<cell>222600.19</cell>
<cell>26712.02</cell>
<cell> " " " " </cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1058.jpg"/>

<note><del>Inclosure No. 5.</del></note>

<note><del>Original</del></note>

<p>Statement showing the Exports from Monrovia to the U.S. for the year ending September 30, 1875.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Quantity</cell>
<cell>Value</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties</cell>
<cell>Countries whither exported</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Palm Oil</cell>
<cell>2166 galls</cell>
<cell>866.40</cell>
<cell>43.32</cell>
<cell>United States</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ivory</cell>
<cell>394 #</cell>
<cell>382.50</cell>
<cell>7.88</cell>
<cell> Do Do </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Camwood</cell>
<cell>148 Tons</cell>
<cell>13680.00</cell>
<cell>47.78</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Coffee</cell>
<cell>84080 #</cell>
<cell>16816.00</cell>
<cell>No duties</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Ginger</cell>
<cell>145771 #</cell>
<cell>10281.10</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sugar</cell>
<cell>74205 #</cell>
<cell>4530.25</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cocoa</cell>
<cell>94 #</cell>
<cell>10.90</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Arrowroot</cell>
<cell>96 " </cell>
<cell>5.76</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Syrup</cell>
<cell>42 galls</cell>
<cell>16.80</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Soap</cell>
<cell>3000 #</cell>
<cell>135.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Machinery</cell>
<cell>1 Box</cell>
<cell>10.00</cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
<cell> " " </cell>
</row>
</table>

<p><del>J Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S. Consul Genl</del></p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1059.jpg"/>

<note>Duplicate</note>

<note>Continuation of Inclosure No. 5.</note>

<p>Statement showing the Navigation at the Port of Monrovia for the years ending September 30, 1875.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Entered</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Cleared</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Steamers</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Sailing Vessels</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Total</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Steamers</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Sailing Vessels</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>Totals</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
<cell>No.</cell>
<cell>Tons</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>American</cell>
<cell>Fr. United States</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>395</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>395</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>German</cell>
<cell>" Hamburg</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>330</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>330</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Dutch</cell>
<cell>" Holland</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>230</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>230</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Do</cell>
<cell>" Do</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>294</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>294</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>German</cell>
<cell>" Hamburg</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>382</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>382</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>American</cell>
<cell>" United States</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>327</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>327</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Dutch</cell>
<cell>" Holland</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>260</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>Nil</cell>
<cell>1</cell>
<cell>260</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
</table>

<p>From three to five English Steamers from Liverpool make their arrivals &amp; departures five times a month from this part to Cape Palmas inclusive, without paying the least regard to the "Ports of Entry," <unclear>Page</unclear> or any other laws of the Government of Liberia.</p>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
U S Consul Genl</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1060.jpg"/>

<note>Duplicate</note>

<note><del>Continuation of</del> Inclosure No. <del>3.</del> 2.</note>

<p>Statement showing the Commerce of Grand Bassa during the years ending Septr 30, 1875.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Imports</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell>Exports</cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Value Entered</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties</cell>
<cell>Description</cell>
<cell>Gallons</cell>
<cell>Weight</cell>
<cell>Value Entered</cell>
<cell>Amt of duties</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell><sic>Cacco</sic> (leaf)</cell>
<cell>$9968.25</cell>
<cell>$1638.60</cell>
<cell>Palm Oil</cell>
<cell>106607</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$34412.20</cell>
<cell>$2270.04</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Provision</cell>
<cell>4003.09</cell>
<cell>528.21</cell>
<cell>Palm nut Kernels</cell>
<cell>228 - 12 - 2 - 0</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$6745.80</cell>
<cell>193.29</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Provision</cell>
<cell>4003.09</cell>
<cell>528.21</cell>
<cell>Palm nut Kernels</cell>
<cell>228 - 12 - 2 - 0</cell>
<cell/>
<cell>$6745.80</cell>
<cell>193.29</cell>
</row>
</table>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>