<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0632">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Henry Rider</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp><!-- IF TRANSLATION INCLUDED, USE: transcription, translation, and encoding -->
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0632</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Henry Rider</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Boma, 1888-1895</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Service General Services Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T47</biblScope>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"><!--MONTH DAY, YEAR--></date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<!-- IF THIS IS NOT A LETTER, DISPATCH, OR CORRESPONDENCE OF SOME KIND, DELETE <correspDesc> -->

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Rider, Henry</persName>
<roleName>US Commercial</roleName>
<placeName>Gambia</placeName>
<date when="yyyy-mm-dd"/><!-- FILL IN THE DATE ON THE LETTER -->
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></persName>
<roleName><!-- FOR EXAMPLE, Lieutenant Governor --></roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02-21" who="#unm">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="20170616_100702"/>

<p>Sierra Leone District
Yearly Report
Henry Rider</p>
   
<p>Consular Agent
Freeform the port of entry for the Colony
of Sierra Leone West Africa, lies in 1842
N. and <unclear/> 13 14' /8. It is a place of some 
note and has been burned the metropolis oof 
this particular part of the coast. The port 
contains some six or seven thousand inhab
-itants and the census taken before the late
epidemic returns nearly forty thousand 
people in the colony. The exports of the place
are ground nuts, hides, palm oil, camwood,
<unclear/>, palm kernels, beeswax, ivory and
native gold. Ground nuts and <unclear/>
find their principal market in France and 
are almost wholy shipped in French bottoms,
palm oil, palm kernels, and bees-wax, are
also shipped to France but in smaller
quantities. Palm-oil and hides are the 
principal exports to the United States, besides
which small quantities of groundnut,
camwood and ivory are occasionally
shipped, these freight are confined to</p>

<pb facs="20170616_100721"/>
    
<p>to American vessels. England presents a
market for all the exports of the colony in a quart-
er or less degree. The imports are Tobacco in
hogshead, rum, provisions, and a few dry
goods, from the United States, dry goods and
provisions of every description from England
dry goods, mints, and liquors, from France.
The port does not present a flourishing cena-
-dition, on the contray a stranger is im-
pressed with the streets are grass-grown with
but little havel through them and there are 
dilapidated houses, and lots overrun with 
weeds to be met with at every step; the black
population, with some exceptions, are very
poor and inactive, preferring to remain about 
town earning perhaps enough for a single
meal, to living in the village and cultiva-
ting the land, which with a moderate amount 
of labor would remumerate them kandsomely;
the exceptions are generally liberated Africans,
who by strict economy and much shrewdness
have accumalted money and are, with the 
few Europeans, the business men of the place,
the apathy before spoken of horroer, is entirely</p>

<pb facs="20170616_100726"/>
    
<p>enitrely confined to apperance, for the commer-
cial interests of the place are of considerable
importance, the reverence have increased steadily 
for some years past <unclear/> a corresponding 
increase in the commerce of the colony, the a-
mount of business done with United States
is not inconsiderable as the following returns
for 1859 wil show

</p>
   
<p>Total of American importations $20,209.14.1
.    "   "   0/0 . exportations $50,202.17.
The returns for 1860 I have not been able to 
obtain.</p>
    
<p>The commerce with France is much more 
important than that of the United States, and
the business done with England is very great,
beside many sailing vessels there is a monthly line
of Steamers freighting and these cannot supply
the demand of the port for English good, most 
every packet leaves merchandise behind for want</p>
    
<pb facs="20170616_100732"/>
    
<p>want of room.
A serious drawback to the rapid growth of the colony,
and a heavy burden on the merchants is the very 
high tariff of duties imposed upon goods impor-
ted, many tons of merchandise are now taken to 
the rivers, which with a mere liberal tariff would
find their way direct to Freetown, enclosed I for-
ward a copy of the table of duties. Vessels pay
a homage duty of one shilling and six pence and 
have the priveledge of leaving and returning to 
the port a number of times in the same voyager
providing they are not absent over two months at
any one time, a further charge of three pence a
ton is collected as light dues vessels are also
subject to a harbor masters fee of one pound
sterling for vessels of 100 to 150 tons, and ten
shillings for each 50 tons over.</p>
    
<p>The currency of the colony is that of England,
the sterling pounds, shillings, and pence, all
dollars (silver) are current at par value. Spanish 
and American gold pass at a small disent,
French treaty frame pieces command a small
premium but all other French gold is wholly
uncurrent.</p>

<p>This port is a coaling station for English</p>
    
<pb facs="20170616_100737"/>
    
<p>English steamers cruising about the vieinity, in
on their passage to other stations down the coast,
and quite a large amount of homage is en-
gaged in bringing the coats, the vessels generally
proeuring freight of African timber from the 
adjacent rivers as return cargoes. The slavers
taken as prizes by English cruisers are sent here 
for condemnations, the following, is a list of
those comdemned during the latter part of
last year and for the present year up to date.
1st Sept 29th 1859, a brig name unknown, arri-
ved with 469 slaves on board, she was captured
off hydah by C.M.88. "Spitfire" commander
Chapman; condemned by the Vice Admirally
court; about 300 of the slaves were shipped on
boards thhe bark "Many Sim" Henton Master,
emigrant ship bound for Trinnidad, she
sailed from this port June 19th 1860. It is
reported that many of the slaves left against
their will, and that a number of them
where let out of the yard in which they had 
been kept, 10 go on board the vessel, escaped 
to the bush, but were recaptured, the un-
willingness to leave is accounted for in this
way, the slaves found many entry men</p>

<pb facs="20170616_100743"/>
    
<p>countrymen among the people of Sierra Leone who
persuaded them they ought to remain, and not
allow themselves to be sent away. It seem the
better plan to send them away however, as in 
nine cases out of ten they turn out very bad
if allowed to remain in the colony.</p>
    
<p>2nd Brig Rl Rosarw" captured by N.M.S.S.
'Arrogant' commander Edmonster, rear the line,
arrival here the 24th December 1859, condemned in
the Vice Admirally court Janurary 4th 1860.
3rd A full ship of about 400 tons captured
by H.M.S.S. "Tipton" Lieutant Surton com-
manding in Lat 3'25' N. Long NoN. arrival here
April 17th 1860, the ship was without papers, <unclear/>
or names condemned in the Vice Admirally court.
4th Bark "Cortances" under Urigarayan colrs
formerly the American bark "HopingCloud") captured
by H.M.S.S.'Elect' off Camroons, arrival here
October 3rd 1860 condemned in thr mixed com=
mpion court October 29th 1860 as a prize to 
England and the Urignayan Republic.</p>
    
<p>5th A brig no colors or name Spanish built
captured by H.M.S.S. "Espoir" commander Douglas
off Seabar, Sherbro, arrival Nov. 21st 1860, codemn
and in the Vice Admirally court, this is the 

last</p>    
    
<pb facs="20170616_100748"/>
 
<p>last vessel up to this date (December 26th 1860).</p>
    
<p>A canoe was captured by Thomas Sike 
Eqre harbor master, off Tagreen point Sierra
Leone river on the night of Feburary 21st 1860
she had on board 34 slaves they were all 
liberated.</p>
    
<p>Of Cafe, Bulame, in the Rio Grande river
has occupied the attention of this government,
it is considered a dependent of this colony,
it has been visited lately by Governor + Cill,
and he will attempt another settlement, a 
company of soldiers are to the stationed there
at once. The Portuguese also claim the island
and occupied it until driven out by the 
English the claim I believe has never been
property settled. In the spring and sum-
mer of 1859 an epidemic visited the colony, 
causing about, empty deaths out of a population
of one hundred Europeans, the place is 
but just recovering from the effects of it.</p>
    
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
