<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0092">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from George Bancroft to Mister, September 3, 1846</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Niendorf, Nicholas" xml:id="nn">Nicholas Niendorf</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0092</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from George Bancroft to Mistere</title>
<date when="1846-09-03">September 3, 1846</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>FR ANOM</repository>
<collection>Afrique VI</collection>
<idno>9</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>George Bancroft</term>
<term>Major Bell</term>


</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Staunton, Virginia</term>
<term>Washington</term>
<term>Yorktown</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>George Bancroft</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Washington</placeName>
<date when="1846-09-03"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="nn">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2018" who="pr">Translated.</change>
<change when="2018" who="sab">Encoded.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="20160613_164345.jpg"/>

<ab>
Staunton, (V.A.) 3 Septembre 1846.
</ab>

<ab>
<add>Traduction</add>
</ab>

<p>
Monsieur,

Par une lettre datée de Washingon, le
20 du mois dernier, je vous ai fait connaitre
qu'aussitôt que les documents nécessaires (que l'on
m'envoyait <del>en ce temps même</del> <add>alors</add> de Boston) me seraient
parvenant, Je vous fournirais les explications que vous
me demandiez par votre lettre du 19 du mois
dernier, au sujet du refus fait par la corvette
de l'Union l'Yorktown, de saluer le fort
d'Aumale appartenant aux Français. Ces papiers
sont maintenant entre mes mains, et je puis, d'après
le rapport du Commandant Bell et la correspondance
à la quelle son refus de salut a donné
lieu, vous transmettre les détails suivants.
Il paraît que, le 14 novembre 1845, cet officier
est entré dans la rivière de gabon (Afrique) avec
la corvette de l'Union, l'yorktown, sous ses
ordres. En remontant la rivière, il passa devant
un petit blockhaus élevé sur le bord par les
Français à 3<del>7</del> heures <add>1/2 de</add> l'après-midi, il jeta
l'ancre près de la ville du roi Glass, à 4 milles
environ du <unclear>sus-dit</unclear> blockhaus. Le lendemain à
8 heures du matin, un officier du brick de guerre
français "la Malouisse," vint à bord lui présenter
</p>

<note>
<unclear>Envoy</unclear> <unclear/> à <unclear/>
<unclear/> <unclear/> <unclear/>
le 22 <unclear/> <unclear>1849</unclear> <unclear/>
</note>

<note>
faut
</note>

<pb facs="20160613_164354.jpg"/>

<p>
des compliments du commandant <unclear>il remit</unclear> en
<unclear/> temps une note du commandant <unclear/>
quand les officiers se furent retirés, ce dernier
<unclear/> c'était une lettre de l'officier connaisant
le blockhaus, cependant sa surprise de ce que
le commandant Bell avait passé devant le
<unclear/> sans saluer, <unclear/> où, alors, il demandait officiel
lement le <unclear/> pour le pavillon français.
Le commandant Bell ne tint aucun <unclear/>
de cette demande <unclear/> Il <unclear/> un
officier à bord de la Malouine pour rendre les
<unclear/> d'usage et pour prier en même temps le
commandant de ce brick de vouloir bien se charger
d'une lettre adressée à l'officier commandant les
forces françaises de la station, demande à laquelle
on <unclear/> à l'instant. Le lendemain, le commandant <!-- 'commandant' is hyphenated between 'comman' and 'dant' -->
Bell envoya sa lettre à bord le commandant <!-- 'commandant' is hyphenated between 'comman-' and 'dant' -->
dont de la Malouïne refusa de la <supplied>recevoir</supplied>
à moins que le commandant Bel ne <supplied>saluer</supplied>
ou ne donnait des explications convenables
Il fit connaitre par écrit au commandant <supplied>Bell</supplied>
cette détérmination de sa part. les deux <supplied>propositions</supplied>
furent rejetées après avoir pris des provisions <supplied>l'yorktown</supplied> <!-- 'yorktown' is hyphenated between 'york' and 'town' -->
continue sa croisière.
</p>

<p>
Si le commandant Bell est repréhensible <!-- 'repréhensible' is hyphenated between 'repré-' and 'hensible' -->
pour n'avoir pas envoyé au fort une
proposition d'échange de saluts, le jour même de <supplied>son</supplied>
arrivée, l'officier français commandant a commis <!-- 'commis' is hyphenated between 'com' and 'mis' -->
une erreur plus grande en demandant
comme un droit ce qui est considéré comme
</p>

<pb facs="20160613_164455.jpg"/>

<p>
un acte de courtoisie, et accoré par l'usage aux
pavillons des puissances amies, <add>en entrant sur leurs territoires</add> apres d'être préalablement <!-- 'préalablement' is hyphenated between 'préa-' and 'lablement' -->
entendu avec les autorités pour qu'on
rendit coup de canon pour coup de canon.
Les Français avaient droit à cet acte de courtoisie
dans le gabon. Je regrette ce qui est arrivé, surtout
parce que les Français sont très susceptibles à ce
sujet et spécialement dans le gabon. là en effet,
après la cession du pays, les indigènes se sont
efforcés de <del>rejeter</del> <add><unclear/></add> leur autorité, et les Français
croyent qu'ils ont été soutenus dans ce <supplied>mouvement</supplied>
par les mission navires américains. un fait
semblable s'est déjà produit avec le <unclear/>. <supplied>J'ai</supplied>
cru de mon devoir, en cette circonstance, de <supplied>blâmer</supplied>
la conduite du commandant américain. J'ai
transmis dans le temps un rapport sur cette
affaire au ministère
J'ai ete. . . .
signé: char. W.<unclear/> Skinner.
</p>

<ab>
à l'Honble George Bancroft.
Secrétaire de la marine, à Washington.
</ab>


</div1>
<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="20160613_164345.jpg"/>

<ab>
Staunton, (V.A.) September 3rd 1846.
</ab>

<ab>
<add>Translation</add>
</ab>

<p>
Mister,

By a letter dated from Washingon, the
20th of last month, I informed you
that as soon as the necessary documents (that were
sent to me <del>at this same time</del> <add>then</add> from Boston) are sent
to me, I will supply you with the explanations that you
demanded from me by your letter from the 19th of last
month, on the subject of the refusal made by the corvette
of the Union l'Yorktown, to salute the fort
of Aumale belonging to the French. These papers
are now between my hands, and I may, according to
the report of the Commander Bell and the correspondance
to which his refusal of salute gave
place, transmit to you the following details.
It appears that, on november 14th 1845, this officer
entered in the river of gabon (Africa) with
the corvette of the Union, l'yorktown, under its
orders. In going back up the river, he passed in front of
a little blockhouse lifted on the bank by the
French at 3<del>7</del> hours <add>1/2 in</add> the afternoon, he threw
the anchor near the village of the king Glass, at 4 miles
around <unclear>sus-dit</unclear> blockhouse. The next day at
8 hours in the morning, an officer of the french war
brig "the Malouisse," came aboard to present to him
</p>

<note>
<unclear>Envoy</unclear> <unclear/> à <unclear/>
<unclear/> <unclear/> <unclear/>
le 22 <unclear/> <unclear>1849</unclear> <unclear/>
</note>

<note>
faut
</note>

<pb facs="20160613_164354.jpg"/>

<p>
compliments of the commander <unclear>he returns</unclear> in
<unclear/> time a note from the commander <unclear/>
when the officers retired themselves, this last
<unclear/> it was a letter of the officer knowing
the blockhouse, however his of that which
Commander Bell had passed in front of the
<unclear/> without saluer, <unclear/> where, then, he asked officially
the <unclear/> for the french flag.
Commander Bell holds no <unclear/>
of this demand <unclear/> It <unclear/> an
officer aboard the Malouine to render the
<unclear/> of usage and to pray at the same time the
commander of this brig to charge himself
with a letter addressed to the commanding officer the
french forces of the station, demands to that which
one <unclear/> this instant. The following day, the commander <!-- 'commandant' is hyphenated between 'comman' and 'dant' -->
Bell sent his letter aboard the commander <!-- 'commandant' is hyphenated between 'comman-' and 'dant' -->
of which the Malouïne refused to <supplied>receive</supplied>
unless Commander Bel <supplied>salutes</supplied>
or gives appropriate explanations
He informed by writing to commander <supplied>Bell</supplied>
this determination on his part. The two <supplied>propositions</supplied>
were rejected after having taken provisions <supplied>l'yorktown</supplied> <!-- 'yorktown' is hyphenated between 'york' and 'town' -->
continues its voyage.
</p>

<p>
If commander Bell is reprehensible <!-- 'repréhensible' is hyphenated between 'repré-' and 'hensible' -->
for not having sent to the fort a
proposition of exchange of salutes, the same day of <supplied>his</supplied>
arrival, the french commanding officer committed <!-- 'commis' is hyphenated between 'com' and 'mis' -->
a bigger error in demanding
as a right that which is considered as
</p>

<pb facs="20160613_164455.jpg"/>

<p>
an act of courtesy, and accorded by the usage to the
flags of the powerful friends, <add>in entering their territories</add> after being previously <!-- 'préalablement' is hyphenated between 'préa-' and 'lablement' -->
heard with the authorities so that one
fights back with their canon.
The French had right to this act of courtesy
in gabon. I regret what happened, especially
because the French are very susceptible to this
subjet and specially in gabon. There in effect,
after the handover of the country, the indigenous made an
effort to <del>reject</del> <add><unclear/></add> their authority, and the French
believe that they were supported in this <supplied>movement</supplied>
par les american mission vessels. A similar
fact already produced itself with the <unclear/>. <supplied>I</supplied>
beleived my duty, in this circumstance, to <supplied>blame</supplied>
the conduct of the american commander. I
tansmit in the time a report on this
affair to the minister
I was. . . .
signed: char. W.<unclear/> Skinner.
</p>

<ab>
to the Honorable George Bancroft.
Secretary of the navy, in Washington.
</ab>


</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

