<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0293">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Robert Hamill Nassau to James Gustavus Whiteley, September 18, 1906</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0293</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from Robert Hamill Nassau to James Gustavus Whiteley</title>
<date when="1906-09-18">September 18, 1906</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 226, Liasse 167</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Burrows, Guy</term>
<term>Grenfell</term>
<term>Jones, Alfred</term>
<term>Leigh, John George</term>
<term>Morel, E. D.</term>
<term>Phipps</term>
<term>Uere</term>
<term>Verner</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Baltimore</term>
<term>Boma</term>
<term>Brazzaville</term>
<term>Brussels</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Gaboon River</term>
<term>Libreville</term>
<term>Liverpool</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Paris</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Belgian</term>
<term>English</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Nassau, Robert Hamill</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Germantown, Philada Pa</placeName>
<date when="1906-09-18"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Whiteley, James Gustavus</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-08" who="#kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2017" who="kcd">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="pr">encoded header information.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0293.001.jpg"/>

<p>424 W. Chelten Ave. Germantown, Philada Pa<lb/>
September 18 1906.</p>

<p>James Gustavus Whiteley,</p>

<p>Sir, Consul,</p>

<p>Your communication of date Brussels, July 23. 1906
mis-sent to the Congo Reform Association, finally reached
me Aug. 17. while I was confined under a surgical
operation in the Presbyterian Hospital of this city.
I emerged only a few days go.</p>

<p>You give me your address both in Paris and Baltimore.
I choose the latter address. And, though your letter
leaves somewhat to be desired in the matter of
courtesy, I reply to it.</p>

<p>When I landed in New York on the 7. of last June,
I was, in half an hour, surrounded by half a dozen
reporters. I did not, and do not know whom they represented,
though they doubtless told me. They asked me about
the Kongo atrocities; and I answered freely, as I do
every where. They got my statements somewhat disjointed,
in intervals of the examination of my large lot of
luggage by the Custom House officials. Naturally, they
made some mistakes. I am not on a Lecture-Tour for the
Congo Reform Association of the U.S. At that time, I 
did not know even of that Association's existence.
What I said to them was that, in my missionary addresses
among the Churches during my furlough, I should animadvert 
on those atrocities.</p>

<p>I have not been in the Kongo Free State. There are
3 "Congos": the Kongo Free State, or Kongo Belge; the
Kongo River; and the Kongo Français. What I said to them
was that I had been 45 years in the Kongo-Français, a few
hundred miles north of the Kongo river.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0293.002.jpg"/>

<p>I am a missionary of the American Presbyterian
Church (north) offices at 156 Fifth. Ave New York city
One of my stations being Libreville, in the Gaboon river,
exactly on the equator; Libreville being headquarter
of the Colonial Government of the Kongo-Français until
its authority was divided with Brazzaville on the Kongo.</p>

<p>It is quite possible that I am <sic>unkown</sic> to the Free
State officials. But, they could have heart of me had
they inquired of Rev. Mr. Grenfell and other Baptist
missionaries; of Rev. Messrs. Verner and Phipps of the
Am. Presb. (south); and of the American Missionaries at
Boma. Your officials would argue themselves unknown
if they could not hear of me through the Captains of
any of Elder Dempster line of steamers running as
far south as the Gaboon and Kongo rivers. Or, from my
friend Consul Sir Alfred Jones.</p>

<p>A few hours after I had told those reporters that
story of the flogging to death of that young woman, one
of them followed me to 156 Fifth. Ave, with his written
version of it, and asked me to sign it as correct.
I did not know who he was nor whom he represented. It 
was substantially correct. A month later I was shown
it in the "Journal-Exam". The preliminary and the final
remarks are not mine, though they are true. The story
itself is, excepting the two minor inaccuracies, viz,
that the white man did the flogging; and, that the flogging
was continued on the second day. Indeed, I doubt
whether these two points are inaccuracies. Practically
the white man did do the flogging; it was done for him 
at the point of his pistol: one of his native would not
hesitate to do the flogging himself if it was convenient
for him. And, as to the second day's flogging, I have
no doubt it also was done. He did as bad with that honey.
People familiar with African insects know their abundan-

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0293.003.jpg"/>

ce, their universality and their torture.</p>

<p>I heard this case talked of on the english steamers
at the time. It was commonly known. That was 2 years
ago. I can not recall the persons, captains and passengers,
whom I overheard talking about it. Their version
was one of the "portions" of the girl's body covered
by the honey was her genitals. I have no doubt that it
was so. For the <sic>stamement</sic> was also made that the "service"
in which she was engaged to this man was as his
mistress. Of this also I have no doubt. In my long and
intimate acquaintance with african conditions, I know
that many of the white commercial foreign population
have their native "Wives" more or less openly held.
Some of them treat their young women kindly; some are
cruel. I know of no "service" which young women render
in the trading houses other than a sexual one.</p>

<p>I wish to repeat that I am not, and have not been,
in any way, connected with the American Congo Reform
Association, except that I heartily approve of its object
and its work; a work for which my sympathy was early
extended to Mr. E. D. Morel of Liverpool.</p>
    
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
(s) Robert Hamill Nassau.</p>    
    
<fw type="footer">His Honor,
J.G Whiteley, Consul General of the Congo Free
State to the United States of America.</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0293.004.jpg"/>

<p>Copy.</p>
    
<p>"On November 30., at the post of Uere, a young girl
in the service of a Belgian sergeant was flogged in public
by his orders. The man who administered the flagellation,
after a short time refused to continue the operation,
where upon the sergeant produced his revolver and 
threatened to shoot him. When the flesh had been cut into 
ribbons, the girl was tied to a flagestaff in the center
of the Station. The sergeant then procured some native
honey, and with his own hands covered portions of 
the girl's body with the substance, and she was left in
the burning sun without anything to sustain her during
a whole day. In the evening the sergeant was warned that
if the girl were not released and given food and water
she would certainly die. It was not, however, until 
the following day that the woman was freed from her
bonds and taken to the native quarters, where she died
the same night. A Belgian doctor, who had just arrived
at the post, saw her when at the point of death and beyond
all medical aid, but made no report to the authorities 
of what he had seen and heard".</p>

<p>Quoted from page XXII (22) of the Introduction by John
George Leigh to "The Curse of Central Africa" by capt. 
Guy Burrows: under date of Feby. 1903.</p>
    
<p>The context would make the date "November 30" to be in
1896.</p>
    
<p>R.H.N.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
