<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0214">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from William McCall Davis to James G. Blaine, March 4, 1891</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0214</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from William McCall Davis to James G. Blaine, March 4, 1891</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1891-03-04">March 4, 1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Davis, William McCall</persName>
<roleName>Liberian Commissioner</roleName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date when="1891-03-04"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Blaine, James G.</persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D. C.</placeName>
<date when="1891-04-15"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-09" who="#lkw"> encoded</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#unm"> transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="20170616_150208"/>

<note>Ackd 17 Apr '91</note>

<ab>Hon James G. Blaine,<lb/>
Washington, D.C. U.S.A.</ab>

<ab>Monrovia, Liberia,<lb/>
March 4th, 1891</ab>

<note type="stamp">Diplomatic Bureau<lb/>
Apr 17 1891</note>
<note type="stamp">Department of State Received Apr 15 1891</note>

<ab>Sir,</ab>
<p>The Liberian Consul at Philadelphia, has sent me a copu of the New York
paper called "The World", dated December 18th 1891, on the 7th page of which I find an
article headed "Snubbed by Mr. Blaine," which perports to give a conversation had
with me, but which is false in every essential statement, and is a false, and
I may add, a malicious libel both as to you and myseld. I do not know the writer
of that article, but I have a surmise from the following facts:</p>

<p>I sailed from New York on the 17th of December last in the SS Britannia, and the
day before I sailed I went by appointment to the office of a gentleman on Broadway,
who had engaged me to attend to some legal business for him in Liberia. When
I reached his office I found in his company another person, who was introduced
 to me, and who said that he had a relative, a friend, an Missionary in Liberia,
whom he had not heard frrom for a long while, and that, learning from his friend,
the gentleman, whom I went to see, of my being in the city, he had made it a point to meet me at his
office, with the hope that I might give him some information about his friend.
I told him that I had not heard of sich a person being in Liberia, but that if he
would five me a letter for him, I would indeavor to deliver it, if such a person
could be found. He said he would send the letter to me before I sailed.
The gentleman I went to see then said," Mr. Davis has been to Washinton, on
a mission from his Government. He is friend said "Is that so? Was you mission
successful?" I said yes, partly so. He asked, "Did you see Mr. Blaine, how did
he treat you?" I relied, yes, I saw him, and he treated me very kindly, the short
time that I was with him. He asked, "Well how was it." I said, "The first day
that I called at the State Department I found a dozen or moer persons, ladies and
gentlement, waiting to see the Secretary, but after waiting until about one

<pb facs="20170616_150213"/>


O'clock we were told by outside officials, much to own disappointment, that the 
Secretary would not be at his office that day; so I left my card and went away.
I called after the next day, and after waiting until after twelve o'clock. I was
ushered into the presence of the Secretary whom I found standing up, and he 
said to me on entering the room. "I can only give you a few moments, as the new 
Spanish Minister is now waiting, by appointment to be conducted over, to be 
introduced to the President". I then said, "The Secretary then asked once to call
again the next day and he told his usher to 'bring me right in", as soon as he got to the 
office". I called the next day, but the Secretary did not go to his office that day 
which was a Saturday, and I called the following Monday and Tuesday with the 
same result that I then left Washington, and from Philadephia I had written
a letter to the Secretary to which I was expecting an answer".</p>

<p>They then said that I had not been treated nicely by the Secretary, and that, "If you
had a commissioner from one of the Great Powers, the Secretary would have
found time to attend to you. The gentlemen, whom I went to see then said that
his friend was connected with the Press, and that something ought to be said about 
it. His friend replied."Yes I'll show Blaine up" ! I replied, "I beg that you will 
do no such thing, as I consider that Mr. Blaine treated me very courteous 
and I consider that he showed me special honor in granting me an 
interview at all, under all the circumstances, and when so many others 
had been waiting so much longer than I to get an interview with him"
"One of the gentlemen found waiting to see the Secretary told me that he had
been visiting the Department for fourteen days consecutively, and had not
yet been favored with an interview; one of the officials told me that the 
Secretary was conferring with Delegations from the South American <unclear>States</unclear>
about commercial treaties that he wished to make with them and if
they often went to his residence to confer, and thus caused them to be 

<pb facs="20170616_150213"/>

absent from the Department for several days consecutively. I said I felt quite sure 
that if the Spanish Minister had not then been waiting Mr. Blaine would have 
heard all that I had to say on the subject of my mission. "Here the communication
about my visit to Washington ended, the other reason left, and the gentlemen and I
went on to talk of the matters, about which I had called his office.</p>

<p>From my conversation with those men, judged that they were both political opponents 
of yourself and your administration; and when I saw that article in "The World" I
at once wrote a letter to the Editor refutiating the article as being false in every 
essential statement, and if I were now in the U.S. I think I should endeavour to 
bring an action against the Editor for libel in publishing it. I sent that 
letter to Mr. Rothery, Secretary Consul, of 116 Walnut Street, Philadelphia and have requested him, if "The World"
will not publish it, to have it published in some paper of that city, and to see
that it be brought to your notice, so that you might see that I have done what
I could do to remove any wrong impression that may have been made about you, 
by so grossly misquoting and misstating, what I said, and what I did not 
say about yourself.</p>

<p>Enclosed, please find a copy of my official report made to my Government on 
my arrival home and hope I was aware of the existence of that lying article 
in "The World", which I hope will convince you that I could not have made
the false statements which that article represents me as making </p>

<closer><salute>With profound respect,<lb/>
I have the honor to be</salute> 

<salute>Sir,<lb/>
Your obident servant</salute>
<signed>WM Davis<lb/>
Late Liberian Commissioner</signed></closer>

   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
