<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0986">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to Frederick W. Seward, August 7, 1879</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0986</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to Frederick W. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1879-08-07">August 7, 1879</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Exploration</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71491799">Freycinet, Charles de 1828-1923</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Algeria</term>
<term>Biskra (Algeria)</term>
<term>Niger</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Ouargla (Algeria)</term>
<term>Panama Canal</term>
<term>Senegal</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1879-08-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1879-09-10"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-01" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2182.jpg"/>

<p>No. 27.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, August 7, 1879.</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to the Ass't Sec'y of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Central Africa.</p>

<p>Synopsis:</p>

<p>The projected railway from Algeria to Niger river, and the American Polar Expedition, commercially considered.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2183.jpg"/>

<p>No. 27.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, August 7, 1879.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to again remind the Department of the importance to the Government of securing some direct interest in Africa for the commercial advantages to be thereby attained.</p>

<p>It would be idle to indulge the thought that the English &amp; French governments are influenced by humanitarian, civilizing motives solely, in the acquisition of territory on this continent.</p>

<p><catchwords>Beyond</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. F. W. Seward,<lb/>
Ass't Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2184.jpg"/>

Beyond all such thought is the opening up and development of Africa for the prospective commercial wealth that will accrue to these governments and peoples from such effort.</p>

<p>While now, we may not need additional area, with our great west rolling in mineral richness from the Mississippi to the Pacific; yet we need more markets for our manufactured articles, and the need increases with every new invention made, every article for which we have not an immediate customer, which we produce.</p>

<p>While we may be justly proud of the ground gone over in <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2185.jpg"/>

the last hundred years, yet with corresponding increase of population and industries, in the present century–the markets for our commodities must be increased.</p>

<p>I send you a clipping under the caption France–dated at Paris, Monday, July 14, 930 p.m., in which the fact is stated of a Commission that has been appointed by M. de Freycinet to report as to a projected railway from and between Algeria, Soudan &amp; Senegal to Niger.</p>

<p>A region with a population estimated at 100 millions, and a sail–probably–the most fertile.</p>

<p>The Budget and Senatorial <catchwords>Committees</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2186.jpg"/>

Committees have pronounced in favor of this scheme, which will cost much less than the Panama Canal, and will be of immeasurably greater importance to France.</p>

<p>Now, if a golden harvest were not promised France, in the successful accomplishment of this work–it would not be so seriously entertained.</p>

<p>Now–contrast this French project with the American Polar Expedition, an article upon which is to be found in the Washington Star, dated June 28, '79, which I also enclose.</p>

<p>Here is an expedition gotten up–no doubt–at great <catchwords>expense,</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2187.jpg"/>

expense, and which if successful, can do for science no more than correct and settle conflicting theories as to the region of earth around the north pole.</p>

<p>But when accurate knowledge is obtained, can our commerce claim any advantages from this victory of science?</p>

<p>The consummation of the purpose of the expedition, will be but the settlement of a merely speculative matter, which can satisfy the scientist, and enlarge, without material benefit to the humanity, the world's geographical knowledge.</p>

<p><catchwords>But</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2188.jpg"/>

But here is Central Africa, a fact, partially explored, for which the world must be ever the debtor of those great benefactors of their kind, who have so far successfully labored in this field, and of whose achievements the U.S., of right, claim so large a share.</p>

<p>Now, were the same attention directed here to the known and unknown womb of wealth <sic>imbeded</sic> in this land, the benefit to our revenues and 40 millions of our nation, cannot–readily–from a commercial view, be estimated.</p>

<p>When France, England <catchwords>and</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2189.jpg"/>

and Belgium, shall have occupied this great field bristling in commercial importance, should we have any relation to it, that relation must of necessity–be secondary.</p>

<p>With earnest hope that Africa may not be wholly neglected by us–commercially, and your indulgence for the length to which your attention has been taxed by the perusal of this;</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obd't serv't<lb/>
Jno. H. Smyth,<lb/>
U.S. Consul Gen'l</p>

<p>Inclosures.</p>

<p>1. Clipping, London Times, July 15, 1879.<lb/>
<catchwords>2</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2190.jpg"/>

2. Clipping, Washington Star, June 28, 1879.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2191.jpg"/>

<p>Washington Star<lb/>
June 28, 1879.</p>

<p>The American Polar Expedition.</p>

<p>Geographical Exploration–The Unknown Blank Around the Pole–Solving the Arctic Problem.</p>

<p>The departure of the American expedition from San Francisco for the Arctic regions, which takes place in a few days, gives a local interest to the subject of geographical exploration. The are of the earth's surface remaining unexplored is not great. Summed up, it embraces a portion of Central Africa, Central and Northern Australia, New Guinea and the vicinity of the Poles. The explorations of Livingstone and Stanley have harrowed down the are of the unexplored region in Central Africa to a very small compass, and what was less than half a century ago supposed to be in a great measure an arid and unproductive desert we now know to be well watered, fertile and densely populated. The absence of water and vegetation has baffled all attempts thus far made to explore the interior of Australia. That region is just about as little known now as it was at the time of the discovery of gold in Victoria and New South Wales. But little progress has been made during the last half century in Arctic exploration. Latitude 83 deg. 26 min. is the northernmost point reached thus far by any explorer. This leaves an unknown blank surrounding the North Pole, which at the narrowest point is about eight hundred miles across. The mission of the Jeannette expedition, like that of similar expeditions which have preceded it, is to ascertain, if possible, what this unknown region is. One of the most satisfactory of all recent Polar expeditions has been that sent out by the Swedish government in charge of Professor Nordensjold. The steamship Vega, in which the expedition sailed, was a few days ago reported to have finished the voyage along the northern shores of Europe and Asia; and she is now ploughing her way through the China seas homeward bound to complete the circumnavigation of the two contingents. But the highest latitude reached by the Vega was only 77 deg. 40 min.</p>

<p>The Jeannette will carry the first strictly Polar expedition, setting out from the Pacific and attempting to push forward to the North Pole by the way of Behring Strait. According to <sic>L'eutenant</sic> De Long no vessel has penetrated further north through Behring Strait than latitude 71 deg. Beyond that parallel the explorers will encounter an unknown region. A branch of the Kuro Shiwo, or Japanese Warm Stream, is known to enter the Arctic Sea through Behring Strait, and it is believed that it emerges on the other side of the continent through Baffin's Bay. The drift of ice is consequently northward on this side, while it sets to the south on the other side. Whether this will be an element of danger to the expedition or whether it will help it in the solution of the Arctic problem remains to be seen. It has been regarded by Arctic explorers hitherto as an element of danger, as it practically cuts off the retreat in case of any accident to the ship which may compel the party to take to the ice.</p>

<p>The California Academy of Sciences last evening held a meeting for the consideration of the Arctic problem, at which Lieutenant De Long, commander of the Jeannette, and other members of the expedition were present as invited guests. The academy expected these gentlemen would unfold their plans, but in this respect it was disappointed. Whatever these plans are circumstances may arise necessitating a material revision of them or even their total abandonment. The expedition starts, however, with the benefit of the experience of all other expeditions in the Polar regions to guide it, abundance of money to back it and the prestige of government direction. Even if the expedition fail to reach the North Pole–the goal of every Arctic explorer's ambition–it will no doubt add something to geographical lore and still further reduce the area of unknown territory for further geographical exploration.–[San Francisco Bulletin, June 17.</p>

<p>London Times,<lb/>
July 15th, 1879<lb/>
France.<lb/>
Paris, Monday, July 14, 9-30 p.m.</p>

<p>A Commission has been appointed by M. de Freycinet to report on the feasibility of a railway between Algeria, the Soudan, and Senegal. The population of the Soudan is estimated, remarks M. de Freycinet, at 100,000,000. The Niger traverses half of it. The inhabitants are industrious. The moving sands, formerly considered universal, are only a local accident, and the soil is everywhere similar to that of European soils. A railway from Algeria to the Niger would not exceed 2,000 kilometres and would be much less costly than the projected Panama Canal. A preliminary commission has already recommended the scheme, one ground being that it would repress the internal slave trade; but it enjoins circumspection on account of the imperfect knowledge of certain parts of the Sahara. It therefore suggests a survey for a line of 300 kilometres between Biskra and Ouargla, to be connected with the Algeria and Constantine line, and that explorations should be made beyond Ouargla toward the Niger. The Budget Committee and a Senatorial Committee on Algerian railways have also pronounced in favour of France taking an active part in the opening up of Central Africa. The Commission now appointed is headed by General d'Andigné and Meudes, and includes M. de Lesseps, various senators and deputies, and a number of engineers.</p>

<p>M. Fouquet, deputy of the Aisne and a sugar refiner at Laon, has gone to London on a mission from the Minister of Finance to give evidence before the Parliamentary Committee on the Sugar Question.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>