<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Consulate at
Sierra Leone Oct 26th 1878

John C. Parm
to Department of State
Washington D.C.

Subject
the Arrival at this consulate of three destitute American Seamen 

Abstract of Contents

To inform the Department that I havesent Edward Hydomoon one of the Seamen to Liverpool andhave drawn a draft for his panage, also to acquaint the department of refusel of Thomas O'Brien (Masters of Brig "<unclear/>" ) to take th two remaining seamen and the correspondences <unclear/> therewith.

Enclosures
Copy of correspondence from <unclear/> Randall and Fischer and my reply's.

United States Consulate at 
Sierra Leone
Oct 26th 1878

Sir,
I have the honor to inform you that there arrived at this Consulate on the 6th of Octiber from Honoria Liberia, Henry Willer and <unclear/> Thompson, two destitute American Seamen belonging to the Schooner "Cupid" of Boston <unclear/> said Schooner having been signed by the Liberian Government and afterwards burnt; there being no American Vessel at that port, they were sent to this Consulate by the American Consul at Liberia to be forwarded to America, on the 12h inst there arrived Edward Hynduran another destitute American seamen belonging to the same schooner "Cuid" to be forwarded to the U.S.

There was then in thi port one American Vessel the Boy "Annie and Lillie" of Boston consigned to Vessel Randall and Fischer, Thomas A. Boone Master, Image 291; which was to have sailed for Boston in a few days, I had intended to send the <unclear/> by her, but on the 18th inst Edward Hyndaro slight symptoms of fever and as the steamen "Cartoon" cursived that day from the Legend, thought it best to send him in her, I therefore arranged with leapt" John Griffeth of said steamen for his passage of Liverpool, giving the Captain a dooft on the secretary of state for Ten Pounds sterling, andsentby the same steamen a letter to the Consul of Liverpool, requesting him to forward the seamen to some port in the United States, I am sorry to inform the report Consul that in <unclear/> the <unclear/>, I was compelled to Omit the clause in the regulations, paragraph 169."referring to the drafts drawnfor transportation of destitute <unclear/> seamen to intermediate ports". the Captainrefused to take the man unless that cause was United.

On the morning of the 21st inst the master of the American Brig "Annie and Lily" applied to this Consulate for his clearance and ships papers, I requested the captain to take on board of his Brig Henry <unclear/> and Charles Thompson on the destitute seamen <unclear/> , to be landed at the port of Boston U.S.A. he after some hesitancy agreed to do so, and requested one to have the seamen meet him at the Consulate, prior to their going onboard, I immediately sent to the seamanboarding place (a distance of a quarter of a mile from this Consulate) requesting them to be present at 12 Octock moon, they according come; one of then Charles through on looking wick form an attack of <unclear/> might <unclear/>, I informed them of the mature of the call, and arked them if they were ready snd felt will enough to go to sea? they said "they were provided they were not compelled to workuntil they felt stronger". On the Captains return he refused to take there, saying they were sick and unable to work at Sea; not finding any law whos Masters of American <unclear/> are privilged to refuse taking distitute American Seamen because they are not able to work on their passage home, But <unclear/> a law which compells them to take distitute American seamen, whom requested to dose by the Consul, I refused to give up the the ships papers unless he would take them, amake a declaration in writing, statery the same of his refusal.

Neither of the men had applied to me to be sent to the Hospital, and in my opinion they were not really sick enough to be sent her,though they had asked mre for a dose of salts, which I gave them questionously, climate and change of diet have caused them to look a little amacipated but they would in a few days improve by being at sea, Captain O brien loft the Consulate and in a few moments after I received letter No 1 which I <unclear/> with my reply. 

On the 22nd Captain O'Brien called at this Consulate the seond time forthe ships papers, statingthat the seamen <unclear/> to, had themelves informed him that morning, that they were not well enough to go to sea, I immediately called at this boarding place and inquired of them, had they made such statement? They acknowledge to one that they had, I requested them to make it in writing which they did them delivered to Captain O'Brine the Brig "Annie and Lily's" papers,and he sailed the next day.

Acting upon the statement of the seamen relation to this not being well enough to go to sea, I wrote to the Colonial Surgeon of this place on the 23rd, requesting those admission into the Colonial Hospital for account of this Consulate.

I beg to state for the information of the Department that this Julian Grey the seamen's boarding mistress, informed me that Captain O'Brine visited the seamen at her boarding house on the morning of the 22nd and said to them that if they would make above mentioned statement, the Consul would be obliged to send them by first steamen <unclear/> Liverpool which would enable them to reach home much sooner, and they would not have <unclear/> work on the passage."

In conclusion I beg to say that Thomas O'Brine Master of the Brig "Annie and Lily" of Boston, Seamen to be entirely devoid of sympthy for the destitute American Seamen, and expressed himself very unfeeomingly in my presence, as Master of an American Vessel, in regard to the lawsgoverning merchant ships,

I have the honor to be
Sir 
Your Obedient Servant
John A Parson
U.S. Consul

To
The Honorable
F.W. Seward
Acting Secretary of State
Washington D.C.
















