<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1296">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, November 30, 1900</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1296</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, November 30, 1900</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 5</biblScope>
<date when="1900-11-30">November 30, 1900</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>White, Robert</term>
<term>Gilmore, W.</term>
<term>Leeson, W. F.</term>
<term>Anderson, W. Traill</term>
<term>Bailey, Abe</term>
<term>Perrott, C. H.</term>
<term>Apsey, J. S.</term>
<term>De Jongh, J. L.</term>
<term>Brown, J. Frank</term>
<term>Phillips</term>
<term>Williams, Robert</term>
<term>Lepper, C.</term>
<term>Woodhead, C.</term>
<term>Mosenthal, Fritz</term>
<term>Boxall, E. T.</term>
<term>Timmis, J. A.</term>
<term>Loubser</term>
<term>Hirsch</term>
<term>Henderson, R. H.</term>
<term>Eckstein, F.</term>
<term>Markham, H. W.</term>
<term>Greenacre, Edwin</term>
<term>Harvey</term>
<term>Michell, L. L.</term>
<term>Jeppe, Julius</term>
<term>Rissik</term>
<term>Hignett</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Germany</term>
<term>London, England</term>
<term>Berlin, Germany</term>
<term>South Africa</term>
<term>Canary Islands</term>
<term>Suez Canal</term>
<term>Hamburg, Germany</term>
<term>Bremerhaven</term>
<term>Antwerp</term>
<term>Lisbon</term>
<term>Naples</term>
<term>Port Said</term>
<term>Tanga</term>
<term>Aden</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
<term>Dar-es-Salaam</term>
<term>Mozambique</term>
<term>Beira</term>
<term>Delagoa Bay</term>
<term>Durban</term>
<term>Port Elizabeth</term>
<term>Capetown</term>
<term>Las Palmas</term>
<term>Rotterdam</term>
<term>Natal</term>
<term>Bethlehem</term>
<term>Heilbron</term>
<term>Vereeniging</term>
<term>Johannesburg</term>
<term>Kimberley</term>
<term>Bloemfontein</term>
<term>Springfontein</term>
<term>Fauresmith</term>
<term>Jagerfontein</term>
<term>Winburg</term>
<term>Ficksburg</term>
<term>Harrismith</term>
<term>Transvaal</term>
<term>Wepener</term>
<term>Ladybrand</term>
<term>Ficksburg</term>
<term>Kerksdorp</term>
<term>Leydsdorp</term>
<term>Pietersburg</term>
<term>Wilson</term>
<term>Gilmore, Capetown</term>
<term>Hotel Majestic, Harrogate</term>
<term>Dunvegan Castle</term>
<term>Aberdeenshire</term>
<term>Algoa Bay</term>
<term>Tantallon Castle</term>
<term>Capetown</term>
<term>Aberdeenshire</term>
<term>Fayoum Province</term>
<term>Zululand</term>
<term>'Nqutu, Zululand</term>
<term>Pietermaritzburg</term>
<term>French Somali Coast</term>
<term>Antenior</term>
<term>Geelong</term>
<term>Globe and Phoenix</term>
<term>Lomagunda Development</term>
<term>Selukwe</term>
<term>West Nicholson</term>
<term>United Rhodesian Gold Fields</term>
<term>Chartered Goldfields</term>
<term>Matabele Propriety Mines</term>
<term>Windsor Consolidated</term>
<term>Bibiani Gold Fields</term>
<term>Natal Tobacco Plantations</term>
<term>Zoutpansberg Water Power and Gold Field</term>
<term>Ashanti Gold Reefs</term>
<term>Egba Territories</term>
<term>Lagos Colony</term>
<term>Ogun River</term>
<term>Isheri</term>
<term>Otta</term>
<term>Ifo</term>
<term>Aro Wharf</term>
<term>Abeokuta</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Owne L. W.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1900-11-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Hill, David J.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Assistant Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1901-01-07"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-11-08" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-3159.jpg"/>

<p><add>File
Couver in
aslier reports</add></p>

<p><add>ACKNOWLEDGED
JAN 9 1901
Bureau of <unclear></unclear></add></p>

<p>No. 56. Consular,
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia;
Nov. 30, 1900.</p>

<p><add>3rd. ASST. SECRETARY
JAN 7 1901</add></p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill.
Assistant Secretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Subject.
German subsidised Steamers,
for Africa.</p>

<p>Consular Bureau
JAN 8 1901</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3160.jpg"/>

<p>3</p>

<p>No. 56. Consular,
Legation of the United States,
Monrovia Liberia;
Nov. 30, 1900.</p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Secretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Sir:
Touching the importance
of the African trade, in European
markets, especially in Germany,
I have the honor to enclose,
for the information of the
Department, three clippings,
from a London periodical,
relative Central African
Commerce.</p>

<p>I have the honor to
be your obedient servant,
Owen L. W. Smith,
M. R. and C. General</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3161.jpg"/>

<p>148 <gap/> CENTRAL AFRICAN COMMERCE AND TRANSVAAL TRADER. <gap/> October, 1900.</p>

<p>GERMAN SUBSIDISED STEAMERS
TO SOUTH AFRICA.</p>

<p>A copy has been received at the Foreign Office of a précis by the
Commercial Attaché of the British Embassy at Berlin of the explanatory
statement annexed to the German Bill regarding the
extension of the German subsidised steamers to South Africa. The
memorandum states that it is not intended to enter into direct
competition with the fast steamers of the Castle and Union lines,
but the intention is to place the German ships on a par with the
so-called "intermediate boats," which, on the West Coast of
Africa, travel at about eleven knots, and reach the Cape in twenty-two
days. A fortnightly service right round Africa will be
established, starting alternately to the east, through the Suez Canal,
and to the West by the Canary Islands. The ports called at will
be as follows:-</p>

<p>On the eastern voyage: Hamburg, Bremerhaven, Antwerp, Lisbon,
Naples, Port Said, Suez, Aden, Tanga, Zanzibar, Dar-es-Salaam,
Mozambique, Beira, Delagoa Bay, Durban, East London,
Port Elizabeth, Capetown, Las Palmas, Lisbon, Bremerhaven, and Hamburg.</p>

<p>On the western voyage: Hamburg, Bremerhaven, Amsterdam,
Lisbon, Las Palmas, Capetown, Port Elizabeth, East London,
Durban, Delagoa Bay, Beira, Mozambique Dar-es-Salaam, Zanzibar,
Tanga, Aden, Suez, Port Said, Naples, Lisbon, Rotterdam,
Bremerhaven, Hamburg.</p>

<p>It has been decided not to call at Swakopmund, in the German
South West African Protectorate, as it would be deviating from
the direct route. On the round voyages between Europe and the
Cape, the contract rate of speed is to be twelve knots, both for
ships already afloat, and for the new vessels still to be built for the
African services, when on the West Coast of Africa. The speed
in the East Coast will be the same between Napes and Dar-es-Salaam,
whereas, on other stretches, it is only to be ten and a half
knots, as at present. A branch line, with regular fortnightly
connections is to be established between the ports on the East Coast
of Africa and Hamburg, via the Suez Canal, as far as Beira. For
the carrying out of the above services, in the proposed extended
them, the East African line is to receive and Imperial subsidy of
<unclear>$67,500</unclear> per year, of £22,500 more than it now has under the
existing contract: the duration of the new agreement is to be for
fifteen years. The financial position of the East Africa line, in
spite of the subsidy of £45,000 a year, was by no means satisfactory
in the first years of its services to the East Coast of Africa. The
capital originally, was £300,000; there were large deficits for
several years, and in 1894 the capital was reduced to £250,000,
£50,000 being written off as lost capital. In 1895 there was no
deficit: in 1895 and 1896 6 per cent was paid; and in 1897 and
1898 3 per cent was received by the shareholders.</p>

<p>The future traffic requirements will be: the two large steamers
now ready, five new large steamers still need to be built at a cost of
£125,000 each, and four medium sized intermediate vessels costing
each £65,000</p>

<p>It is proposed that the new contract should come into force on
April 1, 1901.</p>

<p>PROPOSED NEW RAILWAS IN SOUTH AFRICA.</p>

<p>In the course of a most interesting letter to the Morning Post,
the Hon. Robert White deals with the present position of South
African railways and the lines on which future developments will
most probably take place. He gives a list of suggested new lines,
which is worthy of reproduction here. They are as follows:--
1. Harrismith to Bethlehem (fifty-five miles), thence to Heilbron.
As already mentioned, this line is partly commenced. It would
connect <unclear>Natal</unclear> with the Orange River Colony trunk railway, and
open up the grain district. 2. Vereeniging to Johannesburg direct
(thirty-five miles). 3. Kimberley to Bloemfontein (100 miles). 4.
Kimberley to SPringfontein, via Fauresmith and Jagersfontein (130
miles). 5. Winburg to Ficksburg and Harrismith (120 miles). Would
supply Bloomfontein, Kimberley, and the Transvaal from the grain
districts. 6. Aliwal North to Wepener, thence to Ladybrand, Ficksburg,
and Bethlehem (190 miles). Would run right through the rich
grain districts of the Orange River Colony. 7. Springs to Middelburg
(eighty miles). A very necessary line, as it runs through the
<unclear></unclear> coal districts, and could supply Johannesburg. 8. Klerksdorp
Fourteen Streams (150 miles). This is the old road from Kimberley
to Johannesburg, and would open up coal and gold districts. 9.
<unclear></unclear> Poort to Leydsdorp (150 miles). About seventy miles is already
laid (Sela Railway). 10. Pietersburg to the Gwanda Railway (250
miles). Would connect Johannesburg and the south directly with
<unclear></unclear> through the Transvaal.</p>

<p>AFRICAN PERSONALITIES.</p>

<p>Mr. W. Gilmore, of Wilson and Gilmore, Capetown, has concluded
his stay in England.</p>

<p>Mr. W. F. Leeson leaves very shortly for Durban in the interests
of the Natal-Zululand Railway.</p>

<p>Mr. W. Traill Anderson, chairman of the Kimberley Chamber of
Commerce, returned to the Cape of the 15th ult.</p>

<p>Mr. Abe Bailey, one of the most active of the Rand millionaires,
has been spending a brief holiday at the Hotel Majestic, Harrogate.</p>

<p>Mr. C. H. Perrott, of the famous Tenter Street firm, Perrott
and Perrott, has arrived at the Cape on an important business
tour.</p>

<p>Mr. J. S. Apsey, of Johannesburg, has returned to the Cape
preparatory to fresh enterprise in the wholesale import line at the
Rand.</p>

<p>Mr. J. L. De Jongh is in London. He is one of the most
indefatigable of the executive members of the Rand Chamber of
Mines.</p>

<p>Mr. J. Frank Brown, the newly-appointed Postmaster-General
of Natal, left London for Durban on the 15th ult. in the Dunvegan
Castle.</p>

<p>Mr. Phillips will again represent the interests of the Namaqua
Copper Co. at the Cage next month. He sails in the Briton on the
20th inst.</p>

<p>Mr. Robert Williams, of Tanganyika Concessions and Zambesia
Exploring fame, is back in town immensely the better for his holiday
in Aberdeenshire.</p>

<p>Mr. C. Lepper, editor of the TImes of Natal, is on a holiday
visit to London. Mr. C. Woodhead, editor of the Natal Mercury,
returns to Durban on the 20th inst. in the Briton.</p>

<p>Mr. Fritz Mosenthal, one of the principals of the great Algoa
Bay, East London, and Transvaal import firm (Messrs. Mosenthal
and Co.), returned to South Africa in the Scot on the 22nd ult.</p>

<p>Mr. E. T. Boxall, who represents Van Den Berghs, Ltd., at
the Cape, left thither on the 1st ult. in the Kinfauns Castle. He
will also represent C. Farre, Rheims, the big champagne firm.</p>

<p>Mr. J. A. Timmis, whos "Nas" food has been one of the main
constituents of "Tommy's" dietary throughout the campaign in
South Africa, left in the Scot on the 22nd ult. for Capetown.</p>

<p>Mr. Loubser, of the important wholesale house of Messrs. Hirsch,
Loubser, and Co., Algoa Bay and Johannesburg, has joined the
increasing rush of Anglo-African merchants returning to Johannesburg.</p>

<p>On his return to England from America, Mr. R. H. Henderson,
ex-Mayor of Kimberley and head of the large drapery firm there
which bears his name, lost very little time ere he sailed again for
South Africa. He booked by the Tantallon Castle on the 29th ult.</p>

<p>Mr. F. Eckstein, of "The Corner House," Johannesburg,
returned to the Cape in the Norman on the 8th ult. in the full
expectation that when he landed, as he would do on Tuesday last,
the war would be over, and his immediate return to the Rand possible.</p>

<p>Mr. H. W. Markham, of the large Capetown and Johannesburg
firm of that name, left for South Africa by the Tantallon Castle
on the 29th ult. Mr. Edwin Greenacre, of Messrs. Harvey, Greenacre,
and Co., London, Durban, Pietermaritzburg, and Johannesburg, saild by the same mail-boat.</p>

<p>Mr. L. L. Michell, general manager of the Standard Bank of
South Africa, has come to England with some very important
suggestions regarding the financial future of South Africa. He is
practically the Cape Treasurer-General (Sir Gordon Sprigg's alter
ego), as regards the public finances of theh Cape Colony and Rhodesia.
His design for the new South African sovereigns to be minted at
Pretoria is an excellent one--the Queen's head on one side and the
arms of the four colonies quartered on the reverse.</p>

<p>Prominent figures in THrogmorton Street almost every day since
their arrival early last month have been Mr. Julius Jeppe and Mr.
"Cor" Rissik, of Johannesburg. The former is a member of a
famous, and let it be said very progressive, German family, the
heads of which were the founders of the important Johannesburg
suburb of Jeppestown. Always favourites on the Rand Stock
Exchange, Messrs. Jeppe and Rissik were very reluctantly
"Comandeered," but took the earliest opportunity of inviting the British
to arrest them as prisoners of war and place them on parole. They
hope soon to be back again on the Rand, where they will be certain
to work loyally under British rule.</p>

<p>Americans and Germans are already at work in South Africa;</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3162.jpg"/>

<p>October, 1900 <gap/> CENTRAL AFRICAN COMMERCE AND TRANSVAAL TRADER. <gap/> 147</p>

<p>The following table shows the receipts from passenger traffic:--</p>

<p>Line.  Number of Passengers. Receipts. Approximate Agereage Cost of each Ticket. Average Distance Travelled.</p>

<p>Delta Light Railway: 12 months ending September 1899........... 562,000  £ 12,760  5 3/4d. Miles. 8</p>

<p>"Chemins de Fer Econonomiques": 12 months ending November 1899........ 654,000  13,250  5d.  12</p>

<p>As a proof that very low rates pay the promoters of these lines, it
may be mentioned that when the "Chemins de Fer Economiques"
reduced their minimum charge by one-half, the number of passengers
in the first month increased by 60 per cent.; the receipts also increased
in spite of the reduction.</p>

<p>The lines in the Fayoum Province, which are managed by a purely
Egyptian Company, have been too lately op[ened to permit of any fair
comparison being made between them and the older railways. Their
receipts, however, already average £142 per mile per annum.</p>

<p>The Delta Light Railway receipts have increased to £245 per mile
per annum and the maximum obtained on the "Chemins de Fer
Economiques" has reached the figure of £280 per mile.</p>

<p>The rolling-stock of all these lines is as yet quite inadequate to carry
the cotton and other goods brought to them. When this defect has
been remedied, a proportionate increase in their receipts may be
expected. There seems to be no likelihood whatever of the Government
being called upon to pay the guaranteed rate of interest.</p>

<p>There is as yet no indication that these lines compete seriously with
the State railways. The earnings of these latter have not diminished,
as it was at one time thought probably would be the case.</p>

<p>Trade and Commerce in 1900.-- The total value of Egyptian
exports from 1st January to 30th June of the current year is calculated
at £E8,978,489, as against £E7,058,468 during the corresponding period
of last year, that is to say, an increase of £E1,920,021.</p>

<p>The whole of this increase is more than accounted for by the export
of cotton and cotton seed, but against this there has been a diminution of upwards of £E135,000 in the value of the sugar exports, which
suffered from the failure of last year's Nile flood.</p>

<p>The total value of Egyptian imports, including tobacco, from
1st January to 30th June is calculated at £E6,083,896, as against
£E4,998,398 during the corresponding period of last year, that is to
say, an increase of £E1,085,498.</p>

<p>There has been an increase in the value of the imports in every one
of the fourteen categories according to which they are classified, with
the sole exception of "chemical products," which have slightly fallen
off owing to the development of local soap manufacture.</p>

<p>The most notable features of this increase are to be found in--
£E
(a) Cereals............................... 215,717
(b) Textiles.............................. 243,263
(c) Metals and machinery........172,834
(d) Coal and wood................... 149,177</p>

<p>The increases under (c) and (d) must of course be attributed in some
measure to a rise in price, but the marked general development of the
import trade under every head is indicative of a higher standard of
comfort, together with an increased spending power throughout the
country.</p>

<p>British trade has benefited by upwards of half a-million out of the
total increase of £E1,085,498 in the imports, as against some £E100,000
credited to France and Russia respectively, £E170,000 to the Turkish
Empire, and £E30,000 to Germany.</p>

<p>Conclusion.</p>

<p>The progress of Egypt's commercial development in the last decade
has been marked. The total trade in 1888 was valued at £18,629,000,
and in 1899 it had reached £27,495,000, and of this total trade England
commands over 45 per cent.</p>

<p>The great wealth of Egypt lies in her agricultural resources--cotton,
oil seeds, sugar, and other crops. These, in turn, depend on the Nile
flood. With the Nile regulated and controlled by the immense system
of reservoirs and dams now under construction, with a fellaheen freed
from excessive taxation, and with a network of light railways rendering
the produce of the country accessible to foreign markets, it is to be
hoped that the prosperity of Egypt will show the same steady increase
from year to year.</p>

<p>MINING PROSPECTS IN ZULULAND.</p>

<p>AN ADMINISTRATOR'S FORECAST.</p>

<p>A CENTRAL AFRICAN COMMERCE representative had an
interesting chat with Major Hignett, Resident Magistrate of
'Mqutu, Zululand, just prior to his return, on August 23, to
Durban, en route for his magistracy after six months furlough
in the home country. Major Hignett has served both
the Imperial and the Natal Governments in Zululand, first as
an officer in the mounted police, and latterly in a judicial
capacity, continuously for the last eighteen years. His knowledge
of that part of South-East Africa is accordingly both
intimate and valuable, especially as his views are also those of
a thoroughly impartial official.</p>

<p>Major Hignett is, if anything, astonished that people here
are so apt to overlook the excellent chances for voluntary
white immigrants with some capital, small or large, which
Zululand offers.</p>

<p>Major Hignett is, if anything, astonished that people here
are so apt to overlook the excellent chances for voluntary
white immigrants with some capital, small or large, which
Zululand offers.</p>

<p>"In the first place," he said, "Zululand is a great mineral
country. You come across minerals of all sorts wherever you
go. But for the war we ourselves living on the spot would not
have realised, perhaps, the valuable character of the deposits.
But what the war did for Zululand was briefly this: Up to last
October only second-rate mining men, with no financial backing
to speak of, in most cases, and some quite amateur
prospectors had been over the ground. But when the exodus
(compulsory) from Johannesburg drove the firstclass-the
solid-mining engineers and financiers as refugees to
Pietermartizburg and Durban, they found in Zululand a territory
where they could employ their enforced leisure, and the result
has been that many of them are not only surprised, but also so
satisfied with the results, so they assure me, that immediately
they can get back to their headquarters at the Rand, they
will finance and organise the thorough exploitation of
numerous properties.</p>

<p>"Now," continued the Major, "that is not all. Besides the
gold there is the coal, at St. Lucia particularly. To the new
mines there, an extension of the Durban-Tugela (the Natal
North Coast) railway is already being taken in hand; and
along the coast-line which it will tap the possibilities for
sugar and tea-planting are as good as, if not better than, those
which have proved so successful lower down the coast-line in
Natal proper. You have then, mining and industrial, not to
mention the usual pastoral and agricultural, openings of
great importance and promise in a country where the land
is still all Crown land, unalienated as yet to private individuals,
but which will be so alienated in the same way as
Natal has been, as soon, no doubt, as the Commission appointed
by the Government for the purpose, and which but for the
war would have probably ere now concluded its labours, can
get to work. The native tribal locations or reserves once
makred off, the Ministry of Natal, to quote their Proclamation
of two years ago on the subject, wish to arrange, at no
distant date' (i.e., as from November, 1898), for 'the beneficial
occupation by Europeans of suitable vacant land on the
coast, more particularly in proximity to the proposed railway
extension from the Tugela to St. Lucia coalfields, and also lands
in the neighbourhood of townships either existing or to be
established.'"</p>

<p>FRENCH SOMALI COAST</p>

<p>SURTAX ON SPIRITS.</p>

<p>The French Dé pêche Coloniale of the 2nd ult. contains a notification
to the effect that spirituous liquors produced in or imported into the
French Somali Coast Protectorate are to be subject, in virtue of a
Decree of the Governor, to a tax of lfr. 40 centimes per hectolitre and
per degree. This tax is to be independent of any Customs duty which
may be established on spirituous liquors of foreign origin.</p>

<p>But they must make their names known to those who do the business.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3163.jpg"/>

<p>152 <gap/> CENTRAL AFRICAN COMMERCE AND TRANSVAAL TRADER. <gap/> October, 1900.</p>

<p>MINING NEWS.</p>

<p>RHODESIAN GOLD OUTPUT. -- The secretary of the London
Chamber of Rhodesia announces the receipt of a cable from
Balawaye giving the total output of gold from Rhodesia for the
month of August as 10.137oz. The returns month by month have as follows:--</p>

<p>1898. <gap/> 1899. <gap/> 1900.
ozs. dwts. <gap/> ozs. dwts. <gap/> ozs. dwts.
January ...................<gap/>....... <gap/> 6,370 15 <gap/> 5,242 7
February ..................<gap/>.......<gap/> 6,432 18 <gap/> 6,232 15
March ......................<gap/>....... <gap/> 6,614 2 <gap/> 6,285 16
April .........................<gap/>.......<gap/> 5,755 1 <gap/> 5,456 0
May..........................<gap/>.......<gap/> 4,938 13 <gap/>6,553 12
June.........................<gap/>.......<gap/> 6,103 18 <gap/> 6,185 9
July.......................... <gap/>......<gap/> 6,031 7 <gap/> 5,737 12
August..................... <gap/>...... <gap/> 3,144 2<gap/> 10,137 0
September............... <gap/>2,346 10<gap/>5,653 7 <gap/> ........
October....................<gap/>3,913 0<gap/>4,276 8 <gap/>...........
November................<gap/>5,566 13<gap/>4,670 0 <gap/>.........
December................<gap/>6,258 19<gap/>5,289 2<gap/>..........
<gap/>18,085 2 <gap/>62,313 13 <gap/> 41,692 19</p>

<p>The returns from the various mines crushing during August, so
far as they are to hand, are as follows:-</p>

<p>Mine. <gap/> Ore milled. Gold recovered.
Antenior............................... 880 tons <gap/> 584 ozs.
Geelong.............................. 3,770 tons <gap/>951 ozs.
Globe and Phoenix............. 5,907 tons <gap/>4,742 ozs.
Lomagunda Development... 373 tons <gap/> 225 ozs.
Selukwe............................... 2,664 tons <gap/> 1,596 ozs.
West Nicholson.................... 1,010 tons <gap/> 506 ozs.</p>

<p>RHODESIAN MINES.
Crushing Returns.</p>

<p>ANTENIOR (MATABELE).-- Cable from the mine:--"August
crushing--Mill ran twenty-four days nine hours: crushed 880 tons,
gold 584 ozs." (equal to 13.27dwts.).</p>

<p>GEELONG.--Output for August:--"Forty stamps, twenty-eight
days, twenty-one hours; crushed 3,770 tons; gained 951 ozs., equals
<unclear>5.05dwts</unclear>; working expenses, 14s. 3d. Hope able to haul from better
ore 4th level east during latter part September." (July yield
878 ozs.)</p>

<p>GLOBE AND PHOENIX.--The directors have received information
from the mines that the mill ran twenty-four days during
August, crushed 5,907 tons of ore. Duty 6.12 tons per stamp;
yield 4,742ozs., equal to 16.36dwts. average; tailings, 5.82dwts.
Profit £12.911. Working expenses, £6,059, being exceptionally
<unclear>few owing</unclear> to 70 percent. ore coming from dumps, labour being
<unclear>same.</unclear> Value of gold, £4 per ounce.</p>

<p>LOMAGUNDA DEVELOPMENT.--Cable from consulting engineer
dated Salisbury, September 11:--"Bore hole, eastern end of
property--Cut reef. Actual width reef formation, 60ft.; vertical
depth 300ft. This proves payable character reef this depth. August
test crushing. 373 tons--226ozs.; value, nearly £900. Tailings,
<unclear>5dwts;</unclear> average value ore crushed, 17 1/2 dwts."</p>

<p>SELUKWE.--Crushing return for August:--"Ran twenty stamps,
29.39 days: crushed 2,644 tons, produced 1,596 ozs. of gold (equals
12.07 dwts. per ton). Tailings assay, 2.86dwts. per ton." (July
yield, 3,094ozs.)</p>

<p>WEST NICHOLSON.--August output:--"Ten stamps, twenty-nine
days eighteen hours; crushed 1,010 tonsl gained 506ozs.,
equals 10.02dwts. Working expenses, 25s. 2d." (July yield,
519ozs.)</p>

<p>SELUKWE.--A cablegram has been received from the mine
advising that the full battery of forty stamps is now running.</p>

<p>UNITED RHODESIAN GOLD FIELDS.--Cablegram from the
general manager, dated September 5:--"Inez reef--Struck main
<unclear>saft</unclear> 250ft. levell strong. All work progressing well."</p>

<p>CHARTERED GOLDFIELDS.--Old Nick Property--Extract from
the consulting engineer's (Mr. Franklin White) letter, dated Bulawayo,
August 30:--"The mine is opening up well. Assays are
nearly completed. At present the results are as under:--200ft.
level--200ft. length of drive sample: average width, 3.12 ft.;
average assay. 29.6dwts. 300ft. level--30ft. length of drive sampled;
average width, 5.85ft.; average assay, 13.27dwts. The rich point in</p>

<p>200ft. level was not reached in the 300ft., neither is the full width
of reef exposed in either level. The portion not sampled may be
of lower value, but still of good working gold contents."</p>

<p>MATABELE PROPRIETARY MINES.--The consulting engineer
reports that development work has been commenced on the Superb
claims, Gwelo district, on which there is a splendid line of old
workings, and the prospects of finding a payable reef are very
favourable. Two winzes are also being sunk on the Seahorse claims,
Selukwe district, on a line of old workings. He has also laid out
work on the Sebakwe claims, Gwelo district, and the reef where
exposed is 5ft wide. There are on the property three <unclear></unclear> of old
workings on the three reefs. WOrk will also shortly be Commenced
on the Yatala claims (an extension of the Surprise property) in the
Selukwe district.</p>

<p>RED AND WHITE ROSE GOLD.--Extracts from manager's report
for quarter ending July 31:--"Main shaft--Driving has been
started east and west. Third level reached 26th inst., at 411ft.
The extent of ground broken, however, has not been great enough
to have brought about any decided change with reference to the
reef. The width at third level is somewhat greater than that shown
where the reef was broken at second level; the width is probably,
however, local. Third level--Driving is in progress east and west
along the reef. Second level--East drive--This drive has been
carried a distance of 205 ft. In fae of this drive the reef is well
defined and of good width, but indifferent value. The average of
ore exposed is 5.6dwts. over 33.4in. West drive--This drive has
been carried 164 ft. The reef exposed has been of good grade for
94ft. In face of this drive the reef is of good value and well defined: the average of ore exposed is 13.7dwts., over 28.7. In
segregating ore exposed on this level, following results are
obtained:--West drive, 50ft. 10.2dwts, over 47.9; east drive, 44ft.,
22dwts., over 32.9. No. 1 rise west-- This rise has been carried 11 ft.
The reef shows a width of 38ins., the last sample taken at 10 ft.
being 38dwts. No. 1 west winze--Twenty feet started 100ft. west
of shaft. Reef shows width 20ins., and is well defined; average
value of ore is 8.4dwts, over 26ins. No. 1 east drive--This rise
has been carried a distance of 18ft., and will connect with No. 1
cast winze on first level. In the breast of this rise the reef shows
a width of 72ins., but value from pannings has been low. No. 2
east winze has been started in breast of this winze. Reef shows
width 42ins. First level No. 1 winze west--The reef throughout
this winze has shown a favourable width of fair value. The average
value of ore exposed is 9.7dwts., over 44.2ins. Footage to date:--
Main shaft, 411ft.; vertical shafts, 453ft.; drives, 1,836ft.; crosscuts,
233ft.; winzes, 153ft.; rises, 24ft.; total, 3,110ft."</p>

<p>TRANSVAAL MINES.</p>

<p>WINDSOR CONSOLIDATED.--Extract from mine manager's
report to August 9:--"Main shaft has been sunk to a total depth
of 109ft. The crosscut has been driven 4ft. in very hard country,
and will open up the reef at the 100ft. level, giving us large
quantities of stone. No 1 shaft, north stope--Ground broken 5ft.
by 5ft by 3ft., total 30ft. Seven feet of timber erected and passes
formed. Levels are now all in order and ready to send stone to
the mill. I will take care that the development work is kept well
in advance, but there is no lack of stone for the mill. I have
not done a great deal of development work of late, but, now that
we have the steam, I will push on with the sinking in the main
shaft, as I am sure much richer ore will be got at a depth."</p>

<p>WEST COAST MINES.</p>

<p>BIBIANI GOLD FIELDS.--The directors have made a call of
5s. per share (2s. 6d. on account of capital and 2s. 6d. on account
of the premium of £1 per share), payable on October 1 next.</p>

<p>NEW COMPANIES.</p>

<p>NATAL TOBACCO PLANTATIONS, LIMITED.-- Registered
September 5. Capital £5,000, in £1 shares. Objects: To carry on in
South Africa or elsewhere the business of tobacco planters, tobacco
merchants, cigar, cigarette, and smokers' requisite manufacturers,
etc.</p>

<p>ZOUTPANSBERG WATER PWER AND GOLD FIELD SYNDICATE,
LIMITED.--Registered August 27. Capital £10,000, in
£100 shares. Objects: TO carry on in South Africa or elsewhere
the business of miners, metallurgists, engineers, contractors, etc.</p>

<p>ASHANTI GOLD REEFS SYNDICATE, LIMITED.--Registered
September 15, by Templer, Down, and Miller, 3, Pope's Head
Alley, E.C., with 100 members, each liable for £1. Objects: To
carry on in Africa or elsewhere, the business of miners, explorers,
engineers, timber and wood merchants, etc. Table A mainly
applies. Registered office: 3, Pope's Head Alley, E.C.</p>

<p>African Merchants and Exporters should advertise now</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3164.jpg"/>

<p>October, 1900.<gap/>CENTRAL AFRICAN COMMERCE AND TRANSVALL TRADER. <gap/> 151</p>

<p>CUSTOMS DUTIES IN THE EGBA
TERRITORIES.</p>

<p>DETAILS OF A NEW WEST AFRICAN TARIFF.</p>

<p>It is announced that the following regulations of Customs duties
upon goods imported into and exported from the Egba Territories
from and up to the Colony of Lagos came into force on August
1 last:--</p>

<p>1. From and after August 1, 1900, there shall be levied, collected,
and paid to the Egba Government upon such goods, imported into
and exported from the Egba Territories, as are inserted and described
respectively in Schedules I. and II. hereto, the several duties of
Customs as the same are inserted and described and set forth in
the said Schedules.</p>

<p>2. The said duties shall be payable in the case of goods imported
or exported by the Ogun River at the Custom House at Isheri, and
in the case of goods imported by the Lagos Government Railway at
the Custom Houses at Otta, Ifo, or Aro Wharf, and in the case of
goods imported or exported by the man road from Abeokuta to
Lagos at the Custom House at Otta.</p>
 
<p>3. No person shall import goods into or export goods from the
Egba Territories into or from the Colony of Lagos except through
the Custom Houses.</p>

<p>4. All persons importing or exporting goods by the Ogun River
shall call at the Custom House at Isheri and declare the quantity
and particulars of the goods which he is importing or exporting,
and forthwith pay the duties leviable thereon.</p>

<p>5. No canoe or vessel of any description in which goods are
being imported or exported shall proceed a hundred yards beyond
the Custom House at Isheri until the duties leviable upon such goods
have been paid.</p>

<p>6. All persons importing or exporting goods by the Lagos
Government Railway shall, on arrival at Aro Wharf, Ifo, or Otta,
as the case may be, forthwith take all goods in their possession to
the Custom House at such place, and declare the quantity and
description of such goods, and forthwith pay the duties leviable
thereon.</p>

<p>7. All persons importing or exporting goods by the main road
aforesaid, shall, on arriving at Otta, forthwith take all goods in
his possession to the Custom House at Otta, and declare the quantity
and description of such goods, and forthwith pay the duties leviable
thereon.</p>

<p>8. No goods upon which duties are leviable shall be taken from
a Custom House until the duties leviable theron have been paid.</p>

<p>9. The Customs officers, or any person acting on their behalf,
shall be entitled to search canoes, and also to open and search all
packages, loads, and boxes whenever they have reason to suspect
that such canoes, packages, loads, and boxes contain goods upon
which duties leviable under these Regulations have not been duly paid.</p>

<p>10. Every person requiring a receipt for the duties which he
pays may have the same upon furnishing the officer of Customs,
or person acting upon his behalf, to whom the duties have been
paid, with a paper containing particulars of the goods imported
or exported, and the duties paid, such list, after being examined
and signed by the Officer of Customs, or person acting on his
behalf, shall be delivered as a receipt to the person requiring it.</p>

<p>11. Any officer of Customs, or person acting on his behalf, may
detain any person committing, or suspected of having committed,
an offence against these Regulations.</p>

<p>12. Every person concerned in importing goods contrary to these
Regulations, or evading, or attempting to evade, the payment of
duties, shall forfeit treble the value of the goods, or a penalty
not exceeding £100, or, in default of payment within three days,
shall be subject to forfeiture of the goods and to imprisonment for
a period not exceeding on year with hard labour.</p>

<p>13. Every person making a false declaration, or obstructing any
officer of Customs, or person acting on his behalf, shall be liable
to a penalty not exceeding £25, or in default of payment within
three days, to imprisonment not exceeding six months with hard labour.</p>

<p>14. All disputes between importer and exporter and any officer
of Customs, or any person acting on his behalf, and all offences
against these regulations, shall be tried by the Alake or by the
person appointed by the Alake and Council to deal with such
matters.</p>

<p>15. These regulations shall not apply to goods in transit.</p>

<p>There are now, it is stated, no less than 175 miles of light railways
open in Natal.</p>

<p>PORTUGUESE EAST AFRICA.</p>

<p>TONNAGE DUES.</p>

<p>Rhw Liabon Gazette of August 16 contains an Order to the effect
that in view of the representations of the Mozambique Company,
and the Consultative Committee of Foreign Affairs having been
heard on the mater, it is decreed in terms of Section 11 of
Article 7 of the Decree of May 17, 1897, as follows:--</p>


</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>