<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1314">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, June 28, 1901</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1314</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, June 28, 1901</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 5</biblScope>
<date when="1901-06-28">June 28,1901</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Nicoloaus, G.</term>
<term>Jones, A. L.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Coast Castle</term>
<term>Liverpool</term>
<term>Glasgow</term>
<term>Gold Coast, Africa</term>
<term>Sekondi</term>
<term>Ashanti</term>
<term>Takwa</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Owen L. W.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1901-06-28"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Hill, David J.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Assistant Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1901-08-03"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-12-01" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-4076.jpg"/>

<p><add>INDEX BUREAU
REC'D
AUG 3 '01
DEPT OF STATE</add></p>

<p><add>ACKNOWLEDGED
AUG 19 1901
Bureau of Foreign Commerce.
File</add></p>

<p>No. 75. Consular.
Consulate General of the
United States,
Monrovia Liberia,
June 28, 1901.</p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Secretary of State
Washington.</p>

<p>Subject.
Transmission of Newspaper
clippings.</p>

<p><add>Consular Bureau.
AUG 10 1901.</add></p>

<pb n="Roll6-4077.jpg"/>

<p>3</p>

<p>No. 75. Consular.
Consulate General of the 
United States
Monrovia Liberia,
June 28, 1901.</p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,
Assistant Seretary of State,
Washington.</p>

<p>Sir:
I have the honor to
transmit, herewith, newspaper
clippings, "American
Enterprise in West Africa," and
"Liverpool and Liberia."
I have very little faith in
the ability of the "Afro-American
Steamship and Mining
Company of Boston., Hope it may prove to be a means.
I have the honor to be your obedient servant;
Owen L. W. Smith
Consul General.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-4078.jpg"/>

<p>478 <gap/> Gold Coast Globe and Ashanti Agus. <gap/>June 6, 1901.</p>

<p>"No Initial Public Issue."</p>

<p><gap reason="missing"/>E learn with very great interest and an equal
<gap reason="missing"/>mount of delight that steps are about to be taken
<gap reason="missing"/>legal quarters which, it is to be hoped, will at
<gap reason="missing"/>ast check and perhaps squelch altogether the
<gap reason="missing"/>andal which is being fostered in connection with
<gap reason="missing"/>many West African new flotations of the "no
<gap reason="missing"/>ntial public issue" and allied orders   We cannot
<gap reason="missing"/>d do not say that all flotations of this description
<gap reason="missing"/>of the "swindlicate" class; but we fear that a 
<gap reason="missing"/>ery large proportion are doubtful in origin, per-
<gap reason="missing"/>eious in method, and dangerous in aim and result.
<gap reason="missing"/>a word, they are mere and most carefully studied
<gap reason="missing"/>sions of the new Companies Act, 1900--a most
<gap reason="missing"/>practical piece of legislation, abounding in
<gap reason="missing"/>malies, and affording far larger loopholes to the
<gap reason="missing"/>scrupulous promoter than protection to the
<gap reason="missing"/>blic and to sound industrial welfare. That
<gap reason="missing"/>erefore, legal aid should have been retained by
<gap reason="missing"/>uential people this week, with a view to pro-
<gap reason="missing"/>dings against sundry wild-cat foster parents, is a
<gap reason="missing"/>fying indication that the solid men in the
<gap reason="missing"/>rket do not intend to tolerate these shady
<gap reason="missing"/>motions any longer, and that, if possible, an end
<gap reason="missing"/>ay be put to a practice which is calculated to
<gap reason="missing"/>entually kill public support of the really
<gap reason="missing"/>putable and genuine propositions which have
<gap reason="missing"/>mplied with express legal requirements, have
<gap reason="missing"/>en the fullest details of their enterprise, courted
<gap reason="missing"/>blicity, and selected sound business men and
<gap reason="missing"/>pert miners to guide and govern their adminis-
<gap reason="missing"/>tion and practical management. In the mean-
<gap reason="missing"/>e we advise all our readers to regard "no initial
<gap reason="missing"/>blic issue" as possibly, if not always necessarily,
<gap reason="missing"/>anger signal.</p>

<p>The Takwa Railway.</p>

<p>Extension Arrangements.</p>

<p><gap reason="missing"/>is announced, on the authority of the engineers of
<gap reason="missing"/>sruction, Messrs. Shelford &amp; Son, C.E., that the
<gap reason="missing"/>vey of the Sekondi-Takwa-Kumassi line has now
<gap reason="missing"/>n completed right up to the central area of the
<gap reason="missing"/>perties owned by the Ashanti Goldfields Copora-
<gap reason="missing"/>Limited; and further, that the actual con-
<gap reason="missing"/>etion of this eagerly awaited extension is in
<gap reason="missing"/>d. It is the engineers' anticipation that the re-
<gap reason="missing"/>nder of the line may be completed at a rate of
<gap reason="missing"/>t five miles per month. So far there have been
<gap reason="missing"/>reat physical difficulties to overcome, but rough
<gap reason="missing"/>ntry ahead will involve some big cuttings near
<gap reason="missing"/>hbippo. Meanwhile, the Ashanti Goldfields
<gap reason="missing"/>oration has already got about a hundred light
<gap reason="missing"/>ps up to its property, either already working or
<gap reason="missing"/>to make a start. The line is a single rail, but
<gap reason="missing"/>uble line can be laid when traffic justifies. The
<gap reason="missing"/>line is equal to the haviest traffic that will be
<gap reason="missing"/>ed of it--as, indeed, has already been proved by
<gap reason="missing"/>mployment whilst the work of construction has
<gap reason="missing"/>in progress. It has carried heavier machinery
<gap reason="missing"/>the mines will ever need as far as the rail-head,
<gap reason="missing"/>certain amount of mining machinery is being
<gap reason="missing"/>ed up now.</p>

<p><gap reason="missing"/>il.--The following cable has been received from the
<gap reason="missing"/>ny's engineer, Mr. G. Nicolaus: "From a superficial
<gap reason="missing"/>mon likely to turn out very valuable."</p>

<p><gap reason="missing"/>Gold Goast Estates, Limited, have received
<gap reason="missing"/>owing cable from the manager at Sekondi: "Have
<gap reason="missing"/>duries defined by the Government surveyor. Shall
<gap reason="missing"/>ence surveying on Insoryim property on June 4th
<gap reason="missing"/>push this work to every extent in my power."</p>

<p><gap reason="missing"/>porisu (Ashanti).--The following cablegram
<gap reason="missing"/>een received from Cape Coast Castle, under date June
<gap reason="missing"/>m an independent source: "Visited Akriporisu.
<gap reason="missing"/>prospecting being carried on. Staff evidently
<gap reason="missing"/>ing in the interest of company. Am forwarding a
<gap reason="missing"/>by letter.</p>

<p><add>x</add>Liverpool and Liberia.<add>x</add></p>

<p>A Berlin Canard.</p>

<p>THE Berlin Correspondent of the Morning Leader
(London) has discovered a mare's nest, a favourite
acheivement, by the way, of writers on African
topics in the aforesaid pro-Boer journal. The
correspondent in question gravely anounced a day
or two ago that "the German Press is puzzled to
fathom the reason why the President of the Republic
of Liberia, with some of his Ministers, is visiting
Liverpool." The puzzlement is easy of explanation.
The President of Liberia is not in Liverpool, nor
has the Republic's representative in that city any
direct information respecting a presidential visit to 
this country. In fact, he does not think such a
thing is even probable. The Liberian Secretary of
State, Mr. Barclay, will very probably be in Liverpool
next month. Some minor officials may,
probably will, accompany him; and it may be added
that their business will probably have to do with
the fact that they asked Messers. Elder, Dempster,
&amp; Co. to open a branch of the Bank of British West
Africa in Liberia, and that the latter has not at
present entertained the idea, preferring to wait until
matters have become more settled in the Negro
Republic. Messrs. Elder, Dempster &amp; Co. have, in
fact, intimated that nevertheless they would be
delighted to discuss the matter with the Liberian
representatives. But Mr. A. L. Jones
states emphatically that there is no truth in the report that
the President of Liberia is coming to this country.
So that there is no ground for the surmise of Die
Post that he is seeking to obtain a new loan, or for
its "wonder why the English are suddenly [sic]
concerning themselves with this littel Republic"!</p>

<p>Stock Exchange Notices.</p>

<p>THE STOCK EXCHANGE COMMITTEE has appointed
special settling as under:-
WEDNESDAY, JUNE 19th.
Akkoko Gold Mines, Limited--50,000 shares of £1
each, 12s. 6d. paid, Nos. 75,001 to 125,000.
Wassu Gold Reefs, Limited.--40,000 shares of 5s
each, fully paid, Nos. 1 to 7 and 200,008 to 240,000,
and 200,000 vendors' shares of 5s. each fully paid,
Nos. 8 to 200,007.</p>

<p>West Coast Explorers (Parent Syndicate).
--Since the meeting of shareholders held on the 19th ult.
the directors of the West Coast Explorers (Parent Syndicate),
Limited, have received a report by letter from the
chief engineer on the Coast upon the property called
Tuapim, which consists of a very large area, stated to be
about twenty-five square miles The engineer says in his report:
"It is not possible at present to state how far the reef extends.
I have traced it for over one and a half miles along the old
workings and outcrop, and it varies from 4 feet to 14
feet in width, the average being 5 feet to 6 feet. There is
every probability of it running diagonally for some four
and a half miles." As explained at the meeting, the option
upon this property has been taken up by the Prah Gold
Mines, Limited, but after lengthy negotiations this company
have now agreed to terms with them whereby they
are to be paid out, and the company are to take over the
whole business, which they now regard as a most valuable
asset of this syndicate. It is intended to give shareholders
an early opportunity of subscribing as soon as the new
company is ready for issue. The chairman has arranged
with his Glasgow friends that this syndicate shall participate
in the issue of the Kuni River Concession (Parent Company),
Limited, out of which they will be paid a substantial interest
in that company. The reports on this concession indicate it
to be one of the best on the Coast. Out of these two transactions,
apart from the others in hand, this company should
realize a handsome return in cash and shares upon its capital.
A special settlement has now been granted by the Committee
of the Stock Exchange upon the balance of the ordinary
shares of the syndicate, and is fixed to take place on the 20th
inst. The engineer in charge of the expedition
cables: "Have obtained four very valuable concessions;
banket easily worked, varying in width to 12 feet; averaging
2 ozs. 15 dwts. per ton.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-4079.jpg"/>

<p>Gold Coast Globe &amp; Ashanti Argu
A Weekly Journal devoted to West African Interests.</p>

<p>VOL. I, No. 23. <gap/> THURSDAY, JUNE 6, 1901. <gap/> ONE PENNY</p>

<p>The Share Market.</p>

<p>[Exclusive to the GOLD COAST GLOBE.}
Our market expert writes: "The Jungle market
has shown distinct improvement during the past
few days many of the better class shares being
particularly strong; and although they are to-day a
little below the best, this is due probably to the
attractions of Epsom denuding the market of some
of its principal dealers.</p>

<p>Amalgamated have been largely bought, and at
one time were as high as 17 3/4. London and West
African Gold Syndicate have been inquired for up
to 6 7/8, and the Fanti properties continue in good
demand, the Consolidated at 3 7/8 premium, and the
Corporation at 15/16 premium. Abontiakoon also
showed some improvement at 1 5/8 premium.</p>

<p>Taquah and Aboso went to 4 7/8, but close
somewhat easier, still showing a rise of about 5/16
since the carry over at 4 1/2. All these shares,
however, should ultimately go much better, and
certainly in my opinion are the pick of the market.</p>

<p>Bibianis, both fully and partly paid, are somewhat
easier; and considering the capital of the company,
I cannot see that even the present price is justified.
There is, however, a strong group behind them, who
will certainly not readily let them fall away much.</p>

<p>Goldfields of Eastern Akim have also sagged
somewhat, but I do not think holders have much to
fear in this stock."</p>

<p>Tarkwa Insoryim Gold Syndicate, Limited.--
Additional particulars have now come to hand
regarding this enterprise, to which reference
was made in our last week's issue. The latest
information is to the effect that a cablegram has
been received from the manager (at Sekondi), stating
that the boundary has been defined by the Government
surveyor on the property, and that rapid
progress is being made with the work of development.
The shares which have now been placed on
the market have reached already 2 - 2 1/4.</p>

<p>Answers to Questions.</p>

<p>"Gycia" (Sandringham-road, N.E.).--We quite think
that Effuenta are cheap and likely to go much better; but
one ought not to buy for one Account only, as in the dull
state of the markets at present the expected rise may easily
be deferred. Gold Coast Investment should certainly
improve on any move in the markets.</p>

<p>E.E.O. (Sefton Park).--Sell your Clinton's Concessions.</p>

<p>Soap (Saxony-road, Liverpool). --(1) Reliable information
insufficiently obtained to justify a pronounced verdict. (2)
Ashanti Mines are active, rising, and in our opinion a good
description. (3) We have already said we do not fancy
these.</p>

<p>Mining in Ashanti.</p>

<p>The Goldfields Corporation.</p>

<p>A Bright Outlook.
THE completion of the railway to Takwa has not
only added to the zest of the mining industry in the
Gold Coast per se. To the principal companies in
Ashanti it also means a quickening, indeed a great
quickening. The criterion in this instance is
furnished by the Ashanti Goldfields Corporation, which celebrated its fourth birthday on the 25th ult. This
company's engineer-in-chief is returning to England
about the end of the current month; and, as has been
the habit with the directors, the board will hold
a most important consultation shortly after his return,
whereafter, we have good reason to believe,
they will have some very satisfactory information
to make public.</p>


</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>