<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0007">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sydney Olivier, The League of Nations and Primitive Peoples (1918)</title>
<author n="Olivier, Sydney Haldane Olivier, Baron, 1859-1943">Sydney Olivier</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0007</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Olivier, Sydney">Sydney Olivier</author>
<title level="m" type="main">The League of Nations and Primitive Peoples</title>
<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date when="1918">1918</date>
<biblScope unit="part">portions of the booklet relating to the Berlin Conference</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">3-4, 8-10, 11-12</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Book</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bismarck, Otto, Fürst von, 1815-1898</term>
<term>Olivier, Sydney</term>
<term>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Marquess of, 1830-1903</term>
<term>Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Albania</term>
<term>Antilles</term>
<term>Asia Minor</term>
<term>Austria</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>Bosnia</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>East Africa</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Herzegovina</term>
<term>Kingdom of Tripoli</term>
<term>Mesopotamia</term>
<term>Morocco</term>
<term>Persia</term>
<term>Philippines</term>
<term>Poland</term>
<term>Romania</term>
<term>Russia</term>
<term>San Domingo</term>
<term>Serbia</term>
<term>South America</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>Turkey</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-21" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-11-05" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-07-02" who="#kln">modified encoding and document structure</change>
<change when="2014-06-13" who="#kln">encoded transcription of excerpts</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">The League of Nations and Primitive Peoples</head>

<p>There is no sphere of international Politics in
which the application of the principles involved
in the idea of the League of Nations more convincingly
appears to be called for, or in which, if the
builders of such a League are in earnest, it could be
more simply, promptly, and beneficially effected, than
in that of the relations of European to primitive
peoples. For the defects in these relations are, in regard
to matters on which the conscience of mankind is
fully agreed, more glaring and less likely to be overtly
disputed on behalf of any Power than are the causes
of discord between the civilized nations; whilst at the
same time the ground is in a much more favourable
state for the establishment and action of a central
authority, both because of the special character of the
history of the existing relations and of the comparatively
short period and imperfect degree of their development
in the greater part of the area to be dealt
with.</p>

<p>'Foreign Politics', said the late Lord Salisbury,
'mean African Politics.' When he said it, Africa was
in fact the chief sphere of activity of those policies of
the extension of sovereignty, control, and economic
exploitation on the part of European Governments
over territories in the possession of less civilized or
weaker peoples that were then keeping diplomatists
busy. That dictum is as true to-day as ever, in
the very significant sense that, whilst the Powers
partitioned primitive Africa and the Pacific without
coming to blows in the process, the crash of the
world-war has come because, when they had safely
disposed of all the 'primitive' peoples available, and,
after a few tentative demonstrations in South America,
had been chased away from that neighbourhood by
the watchdogs of the Monroe Doctrine, they proceeded
(in rivalry now with Russia and Austria also)
to apply to half-civilized and more-than-half-civilized
Africa-to Morocco and Tripoli, to weak or backward
States in Europe -- Bosnia, Herzegovina, Serbia,
Albania, Turkey -- to Asia Minor, Mesopotamia, Persia
-- very similar processes of encroachment, intervention,
and control, on the same justificatory principles as
they had appealed to in partitioning Africa, and as
are now being applied, on the plea of much the
same arguments, by the Central Empires to Poland,
Rumania, and the dismembered racial groups that
recently made up the Russian realm. Meanwhile,
the United States had entered upon a similar policy
among the surviving possessions of Spain in the
Antilles and the Philippines, with further interventions
in San Domingo and Haiti.</p>

<p>The world-war came, it may fairly be said, because
the general politics of Europe had taken on the
character and the colour of the politics of the 'scramble
for Africa' -- because all Foreign Politics had become
'African' Politics.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about three pages">
<desc>irrelevant to Berlin Conference argument</desc>
</gap>

<p>The fact, however, that acquisitions in Africa were
divided, on something like a basis of give and take,
between European Powers, although it did not create
a permanent international guardianship for primitive
peoples, yet rendered such a creation a much more
obvious and attainable ideal.</p>

<p>And a most important approach was in fact made
towards this ideal, for in regard to the exploitation
of the Congo Basin an International Conference was
assembled, at which the principle of international
guardianship was powerfully advocated and to some
extent established in practice. When Bismarck, at
this (Berlin) Conference (1885) -- in which he had
refused to allow the Pope to be represented -- proposed
to declare that the sole purpose of its proceedings was
to establish freedom of trade and navigation in the
Congo Basin, the British Plenipotentiary deprecated
this limitation, urging that commercial interests
should not be regarded as the exclusive subject of the
deliberations. The United States Minister warmly
supported this attitude. And so the unpretentious
realism of the Prussian confession of purpose was
generously expanded by the pronouncement: "All the
Powers exercising rights of sovereignty in the said
territories undertake to watch over the preservation
of the native races and the amelioration of the moral
and material conditions of their existence, and to
co-operate in the suppression of slavery, and above
all of the slave-trade. They will protect and encourage
all religious, scientific, or charitable institutions
established for these objects or tending to
educate the natives in the advantages of civilization."</p>

<p>Perhaps more importantly still, the Act also provided
for the neutralizing of the Congo Territories
in the event of war between any of the consenting
Powers. But, on the other hand (and this too is important),
whilst the European Powers were prepared
and proposed in the draft Act jointly to guarantee
this neutrality, thus laying a possible foundation for
a similar consensual exclusion of militarism from the
whole of Africa, the United States Senate refused to
concur in this provision, and it was struck out. Consequences
of this omission were (1) that when, simultaneously
with her violation of the neutrality of
Belgium, Germany mobilized her troops in East Africa
(abutting on the Belgian Congo) the Allied European
Powers (not unnaturally) declined to maintain the
neutrality of the Congo State, and prepared for action
against Germany on that side; and (2) that President
Wilson, to whom, at a later date, Germany, having seen
reason to think better of her policy of setting Africa
on fire against the Allies, appealed for intervention on
behalf of neutrality, had to point out that he possessed
no locus standi.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="about one page">
<desc>irrelevant to Berlin Conference argument</desc>
</gap>

<p>What ought to have been done in
the Partition of Africa, what was attempted and in
some degree foreshadowed in the Berlin Congo Act,
must then be done, at any rate with regard to these
lands. These territories of primitive peoples, to
whatever sovereignty they may be committed, must
be given security that they shall be governed conformably
to principles laid down in the light of the
experience in African affairs that the world has
gained during the last thirty-five years -- a conformity
to be enforced by the joint guarantee of the
Powers associated in the settlement.</p>

<gap reason="sampling" extent="remaining four pages">
<desc>irrelevant to Berlin Conference argument</desc>
</gap>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
