<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Commercial Agency of the
United States of Amrica
at Sierra Leone July 9 1870

Sir,
I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of the Department Circular #5 dated at Washington March 6th 1871 and <unclear extent=two words/> herewith a statement of all the information obtain able, as required by the Scheduer accompanying the above circular intended for the U.S. <unclear/> office.

1st the charts published by local authority

2nd The <unclear/> to the Sierra Leone <unclear/> is obstructed by an extensive sand bank called the Middle ground, which in many parts is dry at low water there is a passage on when there of it

The orthern passage is only fit for small vessels and by there Suldon attempted, the principal channel his between Cape Sierra Leone and thi bank, having a <unclear/> passage of more than a mile is bread, carryng a depth of from 5 to 12 fathous.

<unclear/> Rock the only danger on the Southern Shore his W.N. mile disturb from N.W. <unclear/> of the Cape, it shows it half tide and may be easily distingished by its breakers, and it <unclear/> be will <unclear/> in mind that both Flood and ebdtides set directly upon it. 

On its <unclear/> of Cape Sierra Leone on light Louce 69 ft high was <unclear/> in 1849 in which is a field light, visible 9 miles in Chan weather, it <unclear/> in 8 degrees 30 et and 13 degrees 17' 45" and ncars from Carpeule Rock W from western edge of Middle Ground

N.E. 1/2 et

Shipe coming from sea loll probably endeavor to strike <unclear/> in 8 degrees 30 N. with 9 or 10 fatthous of water, they will be about 4 leagues from shore or if the weather be cler they will have seen the high land which soned be brought to near S.S.E.; and when about 4 or 5 leagues from the land , the Cape will be Seen waking like a lord point, with a ridge of Coern into heus close to the Walus' edge and Shorty after the Light house will is seen.

The Cape may be passed within a greater of a mile with a commanding braze in 10 fathous

30. Springe tides 10 ft 6 in
Neato do 7" 0"
Ebb curent Seus out during 
Rainy season at 6miles per hour
and during dry season 4 1/2 miles
Flood duing Rainy sesons 
<unclear/>
1 mile per honor and during 
dry season 2 miles
5th New arrival temparations of the sea 82 degrees Fahrenheit
6th Pilotage inward- 5 chillings <unclear/> per foot draft outward 2 chillings and Six pence per foor draft

The abne changes are established by Government
7th Sight have while Sight 69 fet above its sea showe a red sight resible 9 miles higher of torver frond base is Vane 47 feet

I have the honor to be 
Sir
Your mot obdt servt
J.B. Upton 
U.S. Vice Cou Agent

Honorable
Hamilton Fish
Secretary of State 
Washington

United States of America
at Sierra Leone
J.B. Upton
No. 4

Acknowledging receipts
of despatch No 15
dated April 20 1871