<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Consulate of the United States of America at Sierra Leone 
22nd March 1866

No. 3

Sir,

By the mail packer in despated No2. dated the 16th <unclear/>. I informed you of the change in the Government of this place, or rather of the British colonies on this part of the West Coast of Africa.

Taking into consideration the above change, which Her Majestys governent has deemed necessary, on amount of the growing prosperity, and importance of the the British settlements about this Coast, I would most respectfully suggest it be a fitting opportunity to appoiny a higher cousular office than that of a cousular Agent.

Im making this suggestion I beg leave should I meet with the approval 

Hon W.H. Seward
Secretary of State 

approvsl of the deprtment to request that I might receive the appointment and will state my reasons for feeling some confidence in no doing. 

I am a citizen of the Unite States, (Salem. Wats) of native born parents, I have been a resident of this colony for seven years arriving in April 1859 the <unclear/> of the epidemia of that year which carried off aout 50 of the white inhabitants amoung others John E. Tylor Esq the acting Consul of this place for the United States, and as the Colony lost 40 whites during the <unclear> rains </unclear> of last year I may safely say I have passed through two epidemic reasons <unclear/> my arrival, no with no long a residence and passing through two epidemcis safely I feel I have reason to consider myself thoroughly acclinated.

Fives years and six monts of the seven years I have held the position of Consular Agent of the United State, and as such I have had to do all the work of a cousul, without the full powers, and priviledges of such an officer. 

The three years before the war our commercial transactions with this place wre very large and it was <unclear/> to see from Eight to ten american vessels in port at the same time but in the latter part of 1860 out difficulties <unclear/> interference very much with business and noth imports and exports rapidly decreased, although it improved a little during the years 1861 and 1862 it was however carried on almost entirey under the British flag.

Now that the war is over I confidently expect to see the business of this colony reach its healthiest average of about $300,000 or $350,000 and this with the American trade with Gambia would revel the transaction of business between the United States and the Cpast under the the new Governor Genard to about $550,000 to $600,000 in is really an invest the U.S. Government should consider and give it all the proctection in its power. 

The unfortunate Civil War having cloned American vessels as aleady beginnng to arrive and others are cleaning for the place fron the United States, this will increase the work of the ofice which during the war has certainly been rather slack, an other addition also to the the work now, will be the booking office the the invests of U.S. vessels of war in the port; turn arrival I am informed by Commander Harrell of the "Hearsage" which came into the port to coal, and sailed on the 14th for down the coast, will be frequently hereafter. 

<unclear/> from our commerce requiring a higher Cousular officer, by the provisions of the slave treaty with Great Britain <unclear/> te station of a cousul if not a higher officer here, as this vision of the places <unclear/> as the portion of the of the mixed comission count and in event of absence if judge an arbitration being absent the present position will not allow of acting for them. Such a <unclear> coutriquncy</unclear> has arisin as the judge is I believe in Washington and the Arbitration been obliged to course on amount of severe illness.

There are in the place a French Counsul, Spanish counsul, and out Counsul, Portuguese Counsul, Counsul for the etherlands, and Liberian /counsul. 

The French Government knowing of the change here have given their Cousul authorirty to appoint Cousular agent in all places under the new Governor Geralship, and also are about to send him out a remake steamer to carry him to the dfferent places under the new Government, their Governor Counsel <unclear/> to that importance, excepting in exports, which ours holds it is proprous periods.

Earnestly desiring the reasons herein it forth will convince the department, that this is a Cousulate which should be represented by a higher <unclear> conpedar </unclear> officer of the United States 

I have the honor to be 
Sir
Your obdt Servant
Henry Rider
U.S. Cousular Agent