<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Sierra Leone
In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of
Her Majesty
Queen Victoria
John Pope Hennessy, O.M.G,
Administrator of the Government of the West Africa Settlemets
17th August 1872

An Ordinance to amend the Duties of Customs.

Whereas it is expedient to increase the Import Duties on Spirituous Liquors, Tobacco and Gunpowder, and to abolish the Duties upon articles of food and clothing, and also upon building materials and other goods.

Be it therefore enated by the Government with the advice and consent of the Legislative Councilas follows;

I. The arrival Ordinances mentioned in Schedule A, to this Ordinance annexed nd all other Ordinances and Acts now in force repuguant to or iconsistent with the provisions of the Ordinance, shall be, sad are hereby repealed Provided nevertheless that such Repeal shall not be deemed to extend to any dues, drawbacks, liabilities or penalties imposed, accruing, allowed or due under any of the said Ordinances : but notwithstanding such repeal, all remedies and punishments for levying recovering and enforcing such dues, liabilities and penalties shall still remain in full force and effect and be capable of being enforced and inflicted, and all drawbacks shall be allowed as if such Ordinances were still in the authority or in pursuance of the Ordinances hereby repealed shall be valid and effectual notwithstanding such lipeal.

II. Iu lieu and instead of all other Duties and Drawbacks of Customs now charged and payable, there shall be raised , levied, collected and paid unto Her Majesty her heirs and Successors upon goods which shall from and after the passing of this Ordinance be imported into any oart of te Settlement or transhippe either for consumption or for the purpose of being carried up the Sierra Leone River for any use of purpose whatsoever the several Duties of Customs, and there shall be shallowed upon goods exported the severaal Drawbacks as the same are respectively described and set forth in the Table of Duties following, that is to say:-

Table of Duties
Ale, Bear and Porter the Gallon 6d., or 1/- per dozen quarts, or 6d. per doxen pints.
Cigars, Cigarettes and all Manufactured Tobacco, 2/-
Gunpowder the Barrel of 100 lbs.
Spirits or strong waters not being sweetened mixed with ay article so that the degree of strength cn be ascertained by Syke's Hydrometer, for every gallon of the strength of proof by such Hydrometer and so in proportion for any greater or less strength of proof and fr ny greater or less quantity than a galoon the Gallon, ... ... 2/-
Spirits unenumerated, the Gallon ... ... ... 2/-
Tobacco (unmanufactured) the ... .. 4d.
Wine (except Claret) the Gallon, ... ... ... 1/6
Claret, the Gallon,... ... ... ... 6d.

III. All other goods not enumerated or described in the above Table of Duties shall be free and exempt from duty on the Importation thereof. 

IV. The Importer of any goods nor subject to duties of Customs or his Agent shall deliver to the Collector of Customs a Bill of Entry of such goods in the same manner and form and containing the same particulars as are required on the entry of dutiable goods so far as the same is applicabe, which entry so far as regards the goods shall be a Transcript of the Report and shall therein describe such goods are fre of Duty and the value of such goods as shall have been previously chargeable with duty at value: and such Bill of Entry when signed by the Collector shall be transmitted to the proper officer and be his warrant for the delivery of the goods mentioned therein: and the Impoter, Owner or Consignee of such goods or his Agent shall qithin Fourteen dy after the entry and landing thereof deliver to the Collector a full and true account of the goods so landed. 

V. Ale, Beer and Porter, Tobacco, Wines ad Spirits may be bonded in Licensed Ponded Warehouses for Home Consumption.

VI. No Salt, Slates, Bricks, Coals, Coke, Lime, Tiles or Lumber shall be landed on the Government Wharf.

VII. From and after the First day of October next to nowarehoused good shall be exorted or transhipped for exportation except in registered decked vessels of not less than Ten tons burthen. 

VIII.
