<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1383">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter, March 29, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1383</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1882-03-29">March 29, 1882</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43915538">Havelock, Arthur Elibank, Sir, 1844-1908</term>
<term>McCormick, Alexander H.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Montevideo (Uruguay)</term>
<term>Sinou (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Vice Consul</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1882-03-29"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3981158369766001460009">Hunter, William, 1805-1886</persName>
<roleName>Second Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1882-05-23"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-02" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3019.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received May 23 1882</note>

<note>No 5</note>

<p>United States Consulate General<lb/>
at Monrovia, Liberia<lb/>
March 29th 1882</p>

<p>M. A Aenmey to the Second Asst Secy of State</p>

<p>Subject</p>

<p>Arrival of the U.S. Naval ship Essex</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>Arrival of the ship. Official visit of Commander McCormick on shore. <sic>Entertainement</sic> at the executive mansion, in honor of the arrival of the ship. depart of the ship from Monrovia.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-3020.jpg"/>

<p>No 5</p>

<p>Consulate of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, March 29, 1882</p>

<p>M. A Aenmey to the Second <sic>Assistt</sic> Secretary of State</p>

<p>Sir– I have the honor to respectfully inform the Department, that, the U.S. naval ship Essex arrived at the port of Monrovia, on the morning of the 24th of March; at 10 o'clock a.m. a boat arrived on shore and the officer tendered me a passage to the ship; where I had an interview with Commander McCormick.</p>

<p>The next day, Commander McCormick was officially <sic>recived</sic> by the President of the Republic of Liberia In presence of the Secretaries of State and Interior. I accompanied the Commander to the Executive Mansion, and presented him to the President and aforesaid Gentlemen.</p>

<p>After exchange of the ordinary <unclear>civilitico</unclear>, Commander McCormick informed the President of his instructions in connection with his probable stay on this coast, and also that the ship was short in coals and provisions; for which reasons, he would like to sail <sic>a</sic> soon as practicable for Montevideo</p>

<p>On Monday March 27th in honor of the arrival of the U.S. naval ship Essex, the President of Liberia <catchwords>gave</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3021.jpg"/>

gave an official <sic>entertainement</sic> to Commander McCormick and other officers of the Essex to which, the members of the Consular Corps and principal government officials were invited.</p>

<p>There were present, Commander McCormick and officers of the Essex, the Consular officers of the Netherlands, Sweden &amp; Norway, Haïty and the U.S. of America, the members of Cabinet, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, the Colonel and other officers of the first Regiment and several other officials and distinguished guests.</p>

<p>Sentiments of Friendships and toasts were given as usual at official gatherings; the first toast was proposed by the President of Liberia for the <sic>healt</sic> and prosperity of the President of the U.S. of America.</p>

<p>The same <sic>afthernoon</sic> Commander McCormick was officially informed that 1e the presence of Governor Havelock with two English man of wars in harbor to present their claim <del>upon</del> before the Liberian Government. 2e the daily proceedings of the Commissioners appointed to discuss aforesaid claim, occupied all his time and attention; and there not being any <sic>natif</sic> revolts at the present time, the President requests the Commander, to take on board two <sic>Gen<catchwords>telman</catchwords></sic> 

<pb n="Roll3-3022.jpg"/>

telmen, sent by the Government of Liberia to Grand Bassa, Sinou and Cape Palmas, to summon the Senators from aforesaid County's for an extra session of the Senate to consider the claim of H.B.M. Government.</p>

<p>Wednesday the 29 of March the two <sic>Gentelmen</sic> appointed by the Government went on board and at 5 o'clock pm the Essex weighed anchor and proceeded to Grand Bassa, Sinou and Cape Palmas from which port the Commander will sail on or about the 31st of March for Montevideo.</p>

<p>The <sic>healt</sic> of all on board is reported in good condition</p>

<p>With high consideration of esteem<lb/>
I am Sir your obedt servt<lb/>
M. A Aenmey<lb/>
U.S. Vice Consul Genl</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>