<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0903">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Treaty between Stephen J. Hill, Governor of Sierra Leone, and Banah Boom, King of Sherbro, November 9, 1861</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0903</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Treaty between Stephen J. Hill, Governor of Sierra Leone, and Banah Boom, King of Sherbro</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 2</biblScope>
<date when="1861-11-09">November 9, 1861</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bah-tick</term>
<term>Banah Boom</term>
<term>Banah Yamah</term>
<term>Banah Yomah</term>
<term>Bradshaw, Robert</term>
<term>Brooks, John S.</term>
<term>Dupigny, W. L.</term>
<term>Hill, Stephen John</term>
<term>Jolly, William B.</term>
<term>Lamfembah</term>
<term>Lawson, Thomas George</term>
<term>McCormack, John</term>
<term>Meheux, William</term>
<term>Sessie Boom</term>
<term>Sessie Vendah</term>
<term>Smith, J. H.</term>
<term>Sobrokeh</term>
<term>Taylor, Thomas C.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95738652">Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1901</term>
<term>Yah Banka</term>
<term>Yah Bye</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bendoo (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Sherbro Country</term>
<term>Sherbro Islands</term>
<term>Sherbro Island (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Turtle Islands</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-05" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0076.jpg"/>

<head type="main">Treaty</head>

<p>Between His Excellency Colonel Stephen John Hill, C.B., Captain General and Governor-in-Chief in and over the Colony of Sierra Leone and its Dependencies, and Vice Admiral thereof, for and on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland of the one part, and Banah Boom, King of Sherbro, Yah Bye, Bah-tick, Lamfembah, Sessie Vendah, Thomas C. Taylor, Sessie Boom, Banah Yomah, Sobrokeh, Yah Banka, Banah Yamah, Chiefs of the Sherbro and Turtle Islands of the other part.</p>

<p>Whereas the said Banah Boom, King of Shey or Sherbro country, and the Chiefs and Headmen aforesaid are desirous, that that portion of the Shey or Sherbro Islands should be ceded, surrendered, given over, and transferred from henceforth for ever unto Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, Her Heirs and Successors:</p>

<p>The said Banah Boom, and the Chiefs and Headmen aforesaid do hereby cede, surrender, give over, and transfer from henceforth for ever unto Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, Her Heirs and Successors the full, entire, free, and unlimited right, possession, dominion, and sovereignty, in and over that piece or portion of Sherbro country commonly known as the Turtle and Sherbro Islands, viz. on the West from the Southernmost and Westernmost Island commonly called and known by the name of the Turtle Islands called Hoom, round to the Southeast by Moote, Foto, Kellebagey, Shey, Yelle-a-Byah and all the other Islands commonly known as the Turtle Islands, together with the whole of the Island known among the Natives as the Island of Shey, or Sherbro Island, together with all the Islands and Creeks belonging to the Same, together with all and every right, and title to the Navigation, Anchorage, Waterage, Bays, Waters, Rivers, Seacoasts, Shores, Creeks, and Inlets, Fishing and other Revenues, and Maritime claims, and all privileges appertaining to the same, which portion of the Shey or Sherbro Islands hereby ceded, shall henceforth be annexed to, and be a Dependency of this Colony, and be subject to the Laws now in force, and hereafter to be in force in this Colony.</p>

<p>This Treaty shall be proclaimed immediately on its being concluded and signed, and be made Law throughout the Territories of Banah Boom, King of Shey or Sherbro Island, and the Chiefs and Headmen above-mentioned.</p>

<p>In Witness whereof the contracting parties have signed the same and have affixed their seals thereto.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0077.jpg"/>

<p>Done at Bendoo, this ninth day of November, in the year of our Lord One thousand eight hundred and sixty-one, and in the Twenty-fifth year of the Reign of Her Majesty Queen Victoria.</p>

<p>Stephen J. Hill, L.S. Governor.</p>

<p>Banah Boom, L.S. King of Sherbro.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Yah Bye, L.S. A Lady of Sherbro Island.<lb/>
her x mark</p>

<p>Bah-tick, L.S. Chief of Sherbro.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Lamfembah, L.S.</p>

<p>Sessie Vendah, L.S. Chief of Sherbro Island.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Thos. C. Taylor, L.S. Chief of Sherbro Island.</p>

<p>Sessie Boom, L.S.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Banah Yoman, L.S. Chief of Toomann.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Sobrokeh, L.S. Chief of Sherbro Island.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Yah Banka, L.S. A Lady of Sherbro Island.<lb/>
her x mark</p>

<p>Banah Yamah, L.S. Chief of the Turtle Islands.<lb/>
his x mark</p>

<p>Signed, sealed, and agreed to in our presence this Ninth day of November, One thousand eight hundred and sixty-one.</p>

<p>Robt. Bradshaw, Member of Council.</p>

<p>J. H. Smith, Commander, H. M. S. "Torch."</p>

<p>John McCormack.</p>

<p>Wm. B. Jolly, Merchant.</p>

<p>John S. Brooks.</p>

<p>W. L. Dupigny.</p>

<p>Wm. Meheux.</p>

<p>Thos. Geo. Lawson, Gost. Messenger &amp; Interpreter.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>