<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0952">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to Frederick W. Seward, November 22, 1877</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0952</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to Frederick W. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1877-11-22">November 22, 1877</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Blackledge, J. W.</term>
<term>Cheeseman, Joseph James</term>
<term>Crusoe, H. Lafayette</term>
<term>Nelson, W. F.</term>
<term>Williams, Henry Augustus</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Edina (Liberia)</term>
<term>Grand Bassa (Liberia)</term>
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Montserrado County (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Norway</term>
<term>Sweden</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1877-11-22"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1878-01-12"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-10" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2004.jpg"/>

<p>No 35.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Republic of Liberia<lb/>
November 22, 1877.</p>

<p>J. Milton Turner<lb/>
to the<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Requesting that a Certificate of Appointment be issued to Henry Augustus Williams Esquire, to be United States Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa.</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>Making reference to my despatches numbered 31. and 34., respectively. Mr Crusoe's delivery of property <catchwords>composing</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2005.jpg"/>

composing Archives to Mr. Turner. Mr Turner receipts to Mr Crusoe for same. Mr Turner delivers to, and takes Mr Williams' receipt for said Archives. Mr Williams is Acting Commercial Agent. Transmitting Mr. Williams' Bond, together with the receipts mentioned. Inviting attention to Enclosure No 4. Requesting action be approved, and certificate be issued to Mr. Williams.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2006.jpg"/>

<p>No. 35.</p>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, 22. November 1877.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I had the honor in No. 34. dated October the sixteenth to explain the circumstances which influenced me to offer the position of Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa, to Henry Augustus Williams Esquire, instead of Honorable J. J. Cheeseman as suggested by Mr. Crusoe and approved by me in my despatch No. 31. I have now to inform the Department that while at Bassa, a few days since, Mr. Williams having accepted my offer <catchwords>of</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable <sic>Fredrick</sic> W. Seward<lb/>
Ast. Secretary of State, Washington.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2007.jpg"/>

of the Agency, I took occasion to receipt to Mr Crusoe for the Archives thereof and to deliver the same into the possession of Mr Williams, with instructions to discharge the duties of the office until the pleasure of the Department be expressed with reference to his more permanent occupancy thereof. Mr Williams' receipt to me for the Archives is marked enclosure No 2.; and his Bond for Three thousand dollars ($3,000) as required by law, is also transmitted herewith, and marked enclosure No. 3.</p>

<p>My reason for inviting attention to enclosure No. 4. will be apparent upon the reading thereof: That enclosure is a copy of my despatch to the Government of Liberia <catchwords>requesting</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2008.jpg"/>

requesting permission for Mr Williams to be Acting Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa. The Liberian Government was pleased to extend to Mr Williams the necessary permission as may be seen by reference to enclosure No. 5. which is a copy of the Secretary of State's note upon that subject. It may not be amiss for me to express my <sic>my</sic> hope for the Department's approval, and that the designation of Mr. Williams for that office may prove satisfactory.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir:<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J. Milton Turner</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2009.jpg"/>

<p>Enclosures</p>

<p>No. 1. Inventory of Effects belonging to U.S. Agency at Grand Bassa, as delivered by Mr Crusoe, to Mr. Turner.</p>

<p>No. 2. The same, as delivered by Mr. Turner to Mr. Williams.</p>

<p>No 3. Mr. <sic>William's</sic> Bond for safety of sad Effects.</p>

<p>No. 4. Legation to Secretary of State Blackledge</p>

<p>No 5. Mr Blackledge to the Legation.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2010.jpg"/>

<p>Enclosure No. 1.</p>

<p>Inventory of Effects belonging to the U.S. Commercial Agency at Grand Bassa. Delivered to J. Milton Turner, U.S. Minister Resident <sic>an</sic> Consul General, by H. Lafayette Crusoe late U.S. Commercial Agent. Novbe: 6. 1877.</p>

<p>Record of Treasury Fees.<lb/>
 " " Quarterly Statement of Fees.<lb/>
 " " Relief Afforded American Seamen<lb/>
Seamen Register<lb/>
Ship's Daily Journal<lb/>
Record of Arrival and Departure of American Vessel<lb/>
 " " American Seamen Relieved.<lb/>
Marine Extended Protest<lb/>
 " Note of Protest.<lb/>
Consulate Passports<lb/>
Invoice Book<lb/>
<sic>Miscellanous</sic> Correspondence<lb/>
Letters Received<lb/>
 " Sent<lb/>
Consulate Regulations<lb/>
Commercial do<lb/>
Diplomatic Correspondence<lb/>
Customs Regulations<lb/>
Statutes at Large<lb/>
Registers of Department of State.<lb/>
Annual Report of the Fifth Auditor to <sic>Secretry</sic> Treasury<lb/>
Monthly Reports of Department of Agriculture<lb/>
Trunk Containing a quantity of Forms and Stationery<lb/>
U.S. Flags<lb/>
 " " Seal and <del>Archive</del> Dispatches of Commercial Agency<lb/>
Chest with Contents, property of Estate of Jude Lilley</p>

<p>H. L. Crusoe<lb/>
J. Milton Turner<lb/>
USMR &amp; C Genl</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2011.jpg"/>

<p>Enclosure No. 2.</p>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency<lb/>
Grand Bassa 8th November 1877.</p>

<p>Inventory of Effects belonging to the U.S. Commercial Agency at Grand Bassa, delivered to Henry A. Williams, U.S. Commercial Agent, by Hon. J. Milton Turner, U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General.</p>

<p>1 One Record of Treasury fees.<lb/>
1 One do " Quarterly Statement of fees.<lb/>
1 One " " Relief Afforded American Seamen.<lb/>
1 One Seamen Register<lb/>
1 One Ship's Daily Journal.<lb/>
1 One Record of Arrival and Departure of American Vessels.<lb/>
1 One " " American Seamen relieved.<lb/>
1 One Marine Entered Protest<lb/>
1 One Note of do.<lb/>
1 One Consulate Passports.<lb/>
1 One Invoice Book.<lb/>
1 One Vol. Despatches<lb/>
1 One " <sic>Missellaneous</sic> Correspondence.<lb/>
1 One " Letters Received.<lb/>
1 One " " Sent.<lb/>
3 Three " Consular Regulations.<lb/>
4 Four " Commercial do.<lb/>
7 Seven " Diplomatic Correspondence.<lb/>
12 Twelve " Statutes at Large.<lb/>
5 Five " Registers of Department of State.<lb/>
1 One " Annual Report of the fifth Auditor<lb/>
3 Three " Monthly " " " Department of Agriculture<lb/>
1 One Trunk Containing a quantity of Forms &amp; Stationery<lb/>
2 Two U.S. Flags.<lb/>
1 One Seal &amp; Despatches of Commercial Agency.</p>

<p>J. Milton Turner<lb/>
U.S.M.R. &amp; G. Genl<lb/>
H. A. Williams<lb/>
Actg U.S. Com. Agent</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2012.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<p>Enclosure No. 4</p>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia 20 November 1877.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to regret that the <sic>pemission</sic> of your Government be extended to Henry Augustus Williams Esquire, of Edina Grand Bassa County, to be Acting United States Commercial Agent at that point, until such time as my Government shall think proper to appoint a successor to H. Layfayette Crusoe, Esquire, resigned. Referring, respectfully, in this connection to the reasons assigned by your Government, in your note of the sixth ultimo, <catchwords>for</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Honorable J. W. Blackledge<lb/>
Secretary of State, Liberia.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2013.jpg"/>

for withholding from J. J. Cheeseman Esqr. the necessary permission to act in the capacity herein referred to, it is desired to explain: that the change from Mr. Cheeseman to Mr. Williams was influenced by the belief that my Government does not desire that any gentleman, a citizen of Liberia, should become the acting or commissioned incumbent of the office of United States Commercial Agent at Grand Bassa, provided such gentleman cannot enjoy in that capacity the pleasure of the Government of his own country. However, in view of the stipulation between your Government and that of the United States, to treat each other upon the basis of "the most favored <catchwords>nation</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2014.jpg"/>

nation," it is my duty, Mr. Secretary, to point respectfully to reasons why the reason you give in your note of the sixth ultimo, withholding from J. J. Cheeseman Esqr. the necessary permission to act is believed inapplicable. I beg, Mr. Secretary, that you will allow me to refer you for illustration of this position to the following facts: The late Consul for Sweden and Norway, near your Government, W. F. Nelson, deceased; was a citizen of Liberia, who at his death was both the Consul for the power mentioned, and Mayor of the city of Monrovia: And, I may allude, respectfully, to the present venerable and distinguished Consul for <sic>Hati</sic>, near your Government, who is also the present Judge of the Court of <catchwords>Probate</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2015.jpg"/>

Probate of Montserrado County. It is deemed unnecessary to mention several additional precedents of like nature, which are believed to be at hand. Doubtless, the instances cited will be regarded sufficient to sustain the belief referred to as relating to the reason assigned for withholding the permission necessary for Mr. Cheeseman to act in the interest of the United States while he holds an office in the Government of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir:<lb/>
With high considerations and esteem<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J. Milton Turner</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2016.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<p>Enclosure No. 5.</p>

<p>Department of State<lb/>
Monrovia November 21, 1877.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch of yesterday's date; informing the Government of Liberia, of the appointment - temporary - of Henry Augustus Williams of the County of Grand Bassa, as Acting U.S. Commercial Agent, until such time as the U.S. Government may deem it proper to appoint a successor to H. L. Crusoe Esqr. resigned. In reply, I beg to assure you that the Government of Liberia has no objections of offer to the appointment.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir Your obt. Servt.<lb/>
(sd.) J. W. Blackledge</p>

<fw type="address">J. M. Turner<lb/>
U.S. Min. Res.<lb/>
Monrovia Liberia.</fw>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>