<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.loanda.roll5.xml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title></title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.loanda.roll5</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Copies of Letters by Henry F. Downing</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date when="1888-01">January, 1888</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-27" who="#caa">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="ViewScan_70022.jpg"/>

<note>No. 18</note>
<note>Department of State Received Mar 22 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
<del>St. Paul de</del> Loanda, Febr. 2, 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>How to take oath for Form No. 101</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>(1) To the practice followed at this Consulate,
of having this oath administrated by Consul
to himself, simply witnessed by a <sic>responsable</sic>
person approved by the Department?</p>

<p>(2) The particular oath is understood
in American and required for Form No. 101
does not exist in Portuguese law, and nobody 
is authorized to administer it.</p>

<p>(3) A clear understanding between the 
U.S. government and Consuls in Portuguese
Possessions on this point is desirable.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_70023.jpg"/>

<p>Dear Mr. Chatelain,</p>

<p>1- At one time it was the
custom to have one "Record of
Fees" form swore to before a 
"Tabelliãs" and signed by him
(gratis). I had so much trouble
in hunting one up at times
that I simply wore to the
Record before any responsible
person of good standing and
got his signature and no question
was ever raised. The Record has
to be sent in complete, Fees or
no Fees. The book is not signed.</p>

<p>2- I was not present when the
supply of stationary was opened
and as no list was forthcoming
I am ignorant of the contents
of the p'kge. I always used
any inkstand in the office
that i could lay my hands on.</p>

<p>I will make further enquires.</p>

<p>Yours very truly,<lb/>
Ed: Bannister</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_70024.jpg"/>

<note>No. 18</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
St. Paul de Loanda, Febr. 2, 1892</p>

<p>Honorable William F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>According to Par 503 Consular Regulations, 
the oath required for Form No. 101
is to be taken before a person having authority
to administer oaths</p>

<p>As appears from enclosed note of Mr.
Bannister and my remarks which follow,
the practice of this Consulate on this point
has not been according to the letter either
of Par. 503 or of Portuguese law. To settle
my scruples and those of any honest Consular 
officer in Portuguese Possessions this 
point ought to be definitely regulated by the
Department.</p>

<p>For my first oath to Form No. 101, I 
was governed by the practice of the Consulate.
Closer study and reflection made me doubt
its legality and I went for the second oath,

<pb facs="ViewScan_70025.jpg"/>

to a notary public, "tabelliãs". He refused
to administer the oath, stating that he was not
authorized to do so by law. In order to settle 
this point and find out whether any other 
functionary could perform that office, I called
on a Judge who knows English and is the 
highest authority in the Province on questions of
law, and I laid the question before him.
His answer was that the Portuguese law
recognizes only two kinds of oaths: (1) the 
oath of office of public functionaries, administered 
by a judge (2) the judicial oath, administered
by the judge in court. Any other oath is not
legal, and any functionary administering it 
makes himself liable to prosecution. The signed
declaration of a party is as binding as an oath could
be and the only thing a notary public can do
is to legalize the signature, thus preventing doubts
as to the genuineness of the signature.</p>

<p>Trusting the Department will either sanction 
the course hitherto pursued at this Consulate
or clearly state how that oath is to be taken 
in the future, I have the honor to be, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<p>1 Enclosure: Mr. Bannister's note</p>
 
<pb facs="ViewScan_80000.jpg"/>

<note>No. 20</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda, Febr. 13, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable William F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Since New-Year the political condition
has remained unchanged.</p>

<p>Every by-weekly steamer continues to
bring some 20-50 tramps and criminals
sent by the Portuguese government to colonize
West Africa. Many die, a few manage
to go home at the expense of charitable people
or captains, the rest settles down to work, and
tries to make a living.</p>

<p>The telegraphic news, about middle of
January, of the change of Government in 
Portugal has quieted the spirits and given 
new hopes to the democratic patriots.
The present minister of Colonies, his secretary
and the secretary of the Minister of Foreign
affairs are almost Loanda-people, having
been here so long, and two of the being married

<pb facs="ViewScan_80001.jpg"/>

to white natives of this city.</p>

<p>In order to get over her financial crisis,
Portugal must find money somewhere, and 
the pawning or the selling of some of her Colonies 
is inevitable. I know from personal
friends in ruling circles from the conversation
of the people, and frequent hints of the press
of all colors, that while the sales of colonies 
to England, France or Germany would be strongly
objected to by the people, the pawning or sale 
of Macao, or the Azores, or the Cape-Verde
Islands or Kabinda (near mouth of Congo),
all strategic points of unsupposable importance 
for our navy and our commerce
of the future, to the United States, would 
be viewed with favor, yea hailed with joy,
by the majority of the people.</p>

<p>I can't help drawing again the attention
of the Department even at the risk of appearing 
impertinent, to this unique chance
of securing one, a few, or all of those
splendid ports.</p>
 
<p>I have the honor to be, Sir<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_80002.jpg"/>

<note>No. 23</note>
<note>Department of State Received May 5 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda March 25, 1892</p>

<p>Mr Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Official relations between this Consulate
and the Province of S. Thomé</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>(1) Though comprised within this Consular
district, the Province of S. Thomé has never
had any official relation with this Consulate.</p>

<p>(2) It seems desirable that, when appointed
the U.S. Consul at Loanda be also introduced, 
by the Portuguese Government to the
Governor of S. Thomé.</p>

<p>(3) For complete statistics and better 
reports, the Consulate ought to receive
the Official Bulleting of S. Thomé, as
it already receives that of Angola.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_80003.jpg"/>

<note>No. 23</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, March 25, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>The Islands of S. Thomé (St. Thomas)
and Principe (Prince's Isld.), comprised
within my consular district, form a separate
Province, with a Governor of its own, and with
an Official Bulletin, in which all official
communications and statistics of S. Thomé
are published.</p>

<p>As far as I know, the U.S. Consul at
Loanda, when appointed and approved, is
introduced by the Portuguese Government
to the Governor of Angola alone, and not to
that of S. Thomé, nor has the Official 
Bulletin of S. Thome ever been sent to
this Consulate.</p>

<p>As the Islands of S. Thomé and Principe
are by their large plantations of coffee,
cocoa and other tropical produce constantly

<pb facs="ViewScan_80004.jpg"/>

growing in commercial importance and promise
to have considerable trade relations with the
United States as soon as the means of
communications improve and the production
of either country be made known, it seems
desirable that the incumbent of this Consular
post be officially introduced, by the Portuguese
Government, to the Governor of S. Thomé, and
that the Official Bulletin of S. Thomé be
sent to this Consulate as that of Angola already 
is.</p>

<p>I therefore suggest to the Department
the advisability of requesting those two
favors of the Portuguese Government.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_80005.jpg"/>

<note>No. 24</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, March 31, 1892.</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Receipt of Circulars and Box
containing a flag and Books</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_80006.jpg"/>

<note>No. 24</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, March 31, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable Wm F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have to acknowledge the receipt
of your circulars dated Dec. 10, 30, 31
1891, the contents of which were duly
noted.</p>

<p>I have also received a box containing:</p>

<p>(1) A U.S. flag</p>

<p>(2) One Despatch Book and one Record
Book</p>

<p>(3) Some forms and envelopes</p>

<p>(4) Some twine</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_80007.jpg"/>

<p>U.S. Consulate<lb/>
Loanda, April 13, 1892</p>

<p>F. O. St. Clair, Esquire<lb/> 
Chief of Conslar Bureau<lb/>
Washington</p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>On the receipt of your letter
dated February 16, 1892, I at once wrote to
the missionary in charge at Gaboon requesting
him to give me the information you desire
concerning the U.S property at that post.</p>

<p>Pending his answer, I hasten to give 
you what I already know on the subject.</p>

<p>Mr. Graham C. Campbell; whom
you mention as having the last, on June 30, 1886,
drawn for salary as U.S. Commercial Agent
at Gaboon, has been since then in the
States and is not expected to return to Africa.</p>

<p>Mr. Joseph H. Reading, who sent,

<pb facs="ViewScan_800008.jpg"/>

in February 1887, the last communication you
received from Gaboon, has also been in the
States, for some four years past, and will probably
stay there. He published in 1890 as Philadelphia
a description of the West-Coast entitled "The
Ogowe Band" and was then residing in a 
small town of New Jersey.</p>

<p>Through a Gaboon missionary who called
on me here about two months ago, I know that
at that time the U.S. Coat of Arms was still
hung out at the American Presbyterian Mission
House of Baraka near Libreville, the Capital 
of the "French Congo"; for this is now the official
native of the former Colony of Gaboon.</p>

<p>Probably all the Consular Archives are
there intact as left by Mr. Reading, the
mission station having been uninterruptedly
occupied since his departure.</p>

<p>It is well nigh decided that, owing 
to the prohibition to teach in any but the French
language, all the American Presbyterian
Mission Stations in French territory should

<pb facs="ViewScan_800009.jpg"/>

be passed over to the Paris Evangelical Missionary
Society who has a young work in that region.</p>

<p>The efforts of the American Presbyterian
Mission (North) will then be chiefly directed
to the southern and inland portion of the German
Protectorate of Kamerún, where there is greater 
liberty. The flourishing station of Corisco and
Benita will no doubt be kept up as long as 
Spain allows them to develop peacefully.</p>

<p>As to the expediency of continuing or
discontinuing that consular post, allow me to
suggest that unless they be disinterested
philanthropists, consular officers from America
at $1000.00, in a deadly climate like that
of Tropical Africa, will not in fact can not
be of a quality to honour their country or 
to give satisfaction to the Department of State.
They will never stay long enough in their districts 
to form an intelligent opinion of their
state and resources, or obtain reliable information 
of any sort.</p>

<p>In the present state of Africa, the Department 
of State need Consuls who are or
promise to become, authorities on African questions

<pb facs="ViewScan_800010.jpg"/>

whose word is of greater weight then the accounts
published in daily papers, who ar determined to
make a serious study of their districts, and who
are able to condense the results of their investigations
into readable reports. Such Americans cannot be expected
to spend or sacrifice their lives in tropical 
Africa for $1000.00 per annum.</p>

<p>Any one acquainted with modern Africa, who
peruse our Consular reports on this great Continent
South of the Sahara and north of the Cape, must be
struck with the sad inefficiency of our Consular
in that region, and must realize the need of a 
complete reorganization of that service if it is
do justice to the incalculable importance of that
immense region, not only to humanity at large but
directly to our United States not only morally,
commercially and industrially, but on the highest <unclear>sense</unclear>
politically.</p>

<p>Unless our Government's adhesion to the
Brussel's Act is to be an empty form, it behoves
the United State to be kept posted by its own agents
on the real state of slavery and slave-trade in
Africa and this cannot be without our Consular
system in said region entailing a new phase.</p>

<p>I am preparing a series of reports of
Angola.</p>

<p>Very respectfully yours<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800011.jpg"/>

<note>No. 26</note>
<note>Department of State Received Aug 1 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 22, 1892.</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Transmitting Report on Angola</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<note>Filed for publication: a very fine report!</note>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800012.jpg"/>

<note>No. 26</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 22, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Having often had occasion to notice 
how little the Province of Angola is
known in Europe, and still less in America,
and realizing what benefits may result
to this Province and to commerce in general
if it be presented to the public in a 
condensed description, I have tried to 
fill the gap by giving in few words a
general idea of my Consular District.</p>

<p>I have the honor to transmit to the
Department enclosed, a Report on the
subject. It is not the reproduction of
anything of the kind previously published
in any language, but the result of 
eight years' hard study on the ground.</p>

<p>As soon as possible, I intend to draw
a map of the Province, also entirely

<pb facs="ViewScan_800013.jpg"/>

original, which will greatly facilitate
the understanding of the Report, and which
I hope the Department will publish with
it.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<p>Enclosure:</p>

<p>1 Report entitled
"Brief Description of Angola"</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800014.jpg"/>

<note>No. 27</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, Africa, June 28, 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Miscellaneous News</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>Evasion of the Oporto Rebels; the leading men,
from Mossamedes, Loanda, and Principe. Pardon of the
common soldiers.</p>

<p>Public opinion and feeling in Angola has quieted
down into discouragement, politically as well as
commercially.</p>

<p>Principal features of the new tariff, which was intended 
to favor national industries but is really threatening
the prosperous commerce of Angola with reason.</p>

<p>A new trek of Boers into Southern Angola may be
the starting point of a new African Republic.</p>

<p>King Mushidi of Garenganze is shot by one of Capt
<unclear>Stairs'</unclear> officers, and anarchy in parts of the Kongo State.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800015.jpg"/>

<note>No. 27</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, Africa, June 28, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Since my despatch No. 20, dated February
13, 1892, no material changes have taken place
in the political and commercial situation of this 
Province. Still some events may be of interest
to the Department.</p>

<p>Evasion of the Oports Rebels: Most of the
common soldiers who took part in the Oporto Rebellion
of January 31, 1891, and who had been exiled to
this Province and that of S. Thomé have been 
pardoned in the early part of this year and have
returned to Portugal. Of the chiefs of the rebellion
only one is still here, and for the simple reason
that he has no desire at all to leave Loanda.
All the other leaders of the Rebellion have contrived
to escape to France. One embarked at Mossamedes
on a sailing vessel bound for Gaboon and reached 
his destination without difficulty. The Director of

<pb facs="ViewScan_800016.jpg"/>

the Custom-House at Mossamedes was censured and
the "Official Bulletin" for conniving with the evasion,
but was not otherwise punished. Two other leading
rebels were at Loanda, put in boxes and embarked on French
steamer bound for the North. At Ambriz, however,
sea-sickness caused by the usual heavy rollers of
that coast compelled one of the secret passengers
to open the wicket of his box, and led to the discovery,
of the two fugitives. The captain of the steamer had 
them bound with chains and delivered them to the
Portuguese authorities of Ambriz. Here they were accompanied
to the fort by a detachment of soldiers and by a chasing
crowd who hailed in them the martyrs of the Republic.
After a few days of banqueting with their Republican
friends of Ambriz and receiving 300 dollars subscribed
in a few hours by all the leading traders, the rebels 
again escaped on a sailing-vessel bound for 
Gaboon, when they met their comrade from Mossamedes
and whence all embarked for France. After 
leading men of Ambriz were arrested and brought
to Loanda in a man of war; but as the whole population
of Ambriz had openly taken part in the envasion,
and the population of Loanda too was favoring
it, the men were again sent home unmolested.</p>

<p>A fourth leader of the Rebellion escaped in the same

<pb facs="ViewScan_800017.jpg"/>

manner - with the secret assistance of Republican Government 
officials from Principe (Prince's Island) and the accomplices were not more seriously
prosecuted.</p>

<p>Public feeling. The public opinion of Angola which for
a time leaned strongly towards separation from the metropolis,
ceased agitating this question, when the Dias Ferreira ministry
took the helm of government, because many hoped it would
by a coup d'etat establish the Republic. Then the tariff
question called public attention to another side, and now 
the presiding feeling is one of discouragement. "Everything
is lost; Portugal is dead" is now a frequent expression.</p>

<p>Commercial situation and the new tariff. The main provisions
of the new tariff are: (1) Most duties are charged according to the
weight of the merchandise (2) Portuguese goods are free or
well-nigh so (3) All foreign imports pay much higher duties,
(4) The duty in foreign alcohol is prohibition, (5) The Governor
has no longer the power to exempt any goods from paying
duties, (6) The Kongo District, which enjoyed free-trade
is now, by an agreement between Portugal and the Kongo
State, subjected to a tariff more moderate than that
of the Kongo State. This new tariff does not interfere
much with American imports: machines continue to be free;
kerosene and flour are necessities and Portugal can not
compete in them, and timber pays little more than previously
as to the general effect of the new tariff, everybody is now
agreed that it was a mistake, that its only result will
be a rise in the prices of all necessities and hence
of labor, and the final desertion of these markets by

<pb facs="ViewScan_800018.jpg"/>

the native trade of this far interior (rubber-trade)
which will prefer the Kongo-route. Of all events,
Angola which had enjoyed unusual prosperity during
the terrible crisis of Portugal is beginning to lose confidence 
since the new tariff has come; credit is being
withheld and the air is full of fears for the future</p>

<p>Railroad extension. On the 17th of May the fifth section of the Loanda
railroad was opened to the public. The daily up and 
down trains run now over 220 kilometres. The territories,
Cassoalala, is on the Lucalla river, near Dondo. The
coffee district of Cazengo, which is the main object of
the railroad, is not yet reached, but every new section
of 20 kilometres will already help the planters to bring
their coffee to the terminus of river navigation. The <unclear extent="one word"/>
rates are still too high to compete with the river boats
or to induce the native trader of the interior to make use 
of the railroad. Most of the Angolan natives, too, prefer to walk
over the track rather than pay the fare. The railroad
as far as opened, is still far from paying; but the Government 
guarantees the interest on all the capital actually
spent by the company on the road. This is the reason
why the company does not care to increase either the
passengers or the freight traffic; which could easily be 
done by a general reduction. Poorly built and managed
as this railroad is, it is a decided blessing to the country
and is sure to pay a good dividend when the coffee
region is fully tapped, that is in three to six years

<pb facs="ViewScan_800019.jpg"/>

The new trek of Boers. When, last year, the Boers of
Humpeta, in the district of Mossamedes, helped the
Portuguese government to subdue Bihe, they were so
pleased with that cool and salubrious high plateau
that they wrote to the Transvaal inviting their countrymen,
to come and join them. Now this new trek of Boers, estimated 
at about 200 waggons is daily expected in the south.
The Portuguese government has sent there the officer who
knows best how to deal with the Boers, having married
one of their daughters, and the people and government
hope he will be able to settle the new corners without
conflict. Hitherto the colony of Boers has been a State
within the State, jealously maintaining their own religion,
customs, administration, language and race. They elect their
own commandants, carefully and intermarriage with the Portuguese, 
and only go to war for the Portuguese government
when the latter agrees to pay them what they ask. Nor,
have they ever paid taxes. If, on the arrival of the new
trek, the Boers should decide to found a new Republic,
there is no military power in Angola that could prevent it;
and if the Portuguese government should try to subject the
Boers to the common administration, there is no doubt but
that it would hasten the formation of a Boer State.</p>

<p>It does not take a prophet to foresee the loss to Portugal
of the highlands of Bihe, Gangda and Ambuela, and
the formation in the near future of a State which European
statesmen never dreamt of, when they partitioned Africa.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800020.jpg"/>

<p>King Mushidi of Katanga shot. According to a letter
from Captain Stairs to a missionary in Bihe, King 
Mushidi of Katanga (Garenganze) was shot by an
officer of Stairs, as he was ordering his soldiers to
<del>make</del> fire on the approaching column of Stairs' expedition
I already informed the Department of how Mushidi <unclear>has</unclear>
coolly rejected the British Protectorate offered him by Mr.
Sharpe of the South Africa Company. It appears he was
going to do the same with the expedition of the Kongo
State; but the latter felt strong enough to fight, and
so made short work with the King's resistance. <unclear>Previous</unclear>
to Stairs' expedition, the King had kindly "received the
Kongo-State expedition under Lieut. Le Marinal, whom
I had the pleasure of meeting here in Loanda on his
way to Europe. Though Le Marinal, missionaries on 
the spot, and nation just come from there, I learn that
the country between Kasangi (Cassange) and <unclear extent="one word"/>
at the confluence of the Lulua and Kassai, is in a state of anarchy.
The Kongo State has destroyed the town of their <unclear extent="one word"/>
<unclear extent="one word"/>. Mukonga Kalamba, King of the Bashilange
and the Makioko slave-raiders are carrying as 
many human herds as they can manage, to be sold
as slaves to the middle men who bring the survivors
to the coast, where they are "redeemed" as contract
laborers.</p>

<p>Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800021.jpg"/>

<note>No. 28</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 28 1892</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have to acknowledge the receipt
of your instructions No. 12, dated
March 5, 1892, no. 13, dated April
6, 1892, and of your circulars dated
January 21, 30, February 2, 10, 15, 24,
26, and March 6, 9, 7, 19,16, which have had
due attention.</p>

<p>I also have to thank the Department 
for sending out new seals and 
furniture for the Consular office, which
have reached me in due course
of time. Unfortunately the panes
of the book-case were broken, one because
the weight of the glass had loosened
the wooden list holding it inside and which
was not sufficiently nailed, the other
because a board which had been nailed

<pb facs="ViewScan_800022.jpg"/>

inside got loose.</p>

<p>Hitherto the Governor General used
kindly to exempt Consular effects from
paying duty, but with the new tariff
he is no longer allowed to that, as
all the imports of the government are
now subjected to the common tariff.</p>

<p>Therefore the two last shipments above
mentioned had to be pay 20% ad
valorem, which however was not put 
too high.</p>

<p>I have the honor, Sir, to be<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<p>P.S. Enclosed please find a
circular of Jones &amp; Vorhees, whcih
may have previously come under your
notice; also extracts from a Kongo letter
which may be of interest.</p>

<p>Enclosures:</p>

<p>No. 1 Circular of Jones &amp; Voorhees</p>

<p>No. 2 Extracts from a letter of
Rev. J. Chester Hyde</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800023.jpg"/>

<fw type="head">Law Office of<lb/>
Jones &amp; Voorhees,<lb/>
1405 G Street.<lb/>
John Paul Jones,<lb/>
Reese H. Voorhees</fw>

<p>Washington, D.C., April 15, 1892.</p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>At the request of several gentleman in the Consular service we
have recently examine with care the "Revised Tariff of Official
Fees" as prescribed by Section 508 of the Regulations of 1888, and
have reached the conclusion that several of the items therein specified 
are erroneously and illegally classed as "official fees." If we
are correct in our view of the law these fees are personal emoluments
of the Consul and need not be accounted for to the Government. Our
attention was first especially directed to the fee for administering
the oath to emigrants for the free admission of their animals,
vehicles, and personal effects (Form 93), under the Act of 1883,
(Par. 677), but in the examination of the question we found it necessary 
to consider the whole subject of official and unofficial fees,
and we soon became convinced that under the Regulations many fees 
were accounted for which in reality belonged to the officer.</p>

<p>We are preparing, in connection with the fir of which ex-Senator 
Omar D. Conger, of Michigan, is a member, to bring a series of
suits in the United States Courts to test these various questions, 
and would be glad to act for you. If you will authorize us so to do,
by signing the annexed letter of authority, which need not be 
acknowledged, we will examine your accounts in the Department and
advise you as to what particular fees we think we can recover for you.</p>

<p>We would also be glad to profit by any suggestions which you may
have to make as to the official or unofficial character of any of the
fees whih you are required by regulation or departmental custom
to account for.</p>

<p>We will not, in any event, use your case as a test one, and unless 
the Courts sustain our position, we will not even file your 
claim, but will return the power of attorney to you.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800024.jpg"/>

<p>We will undertake these cases upon a purely contingent fee and
will not call upon you for any contribution, even towards expenses.
In view of this we think a fee of 33 1/3 per cent. of the amount recovered 
would be reasonable.</p>

<p>It will give us pleasure, if you desire it, to furnish you with
special references as to our professional standing, etc., but refer
generally to the Columbia National Bank and the Washington Loan and
Trust Company.</p>

<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
Jones &amp; Voorhees.</p>

<p>P.S. If the enclosed proposition is acceptable to you, please
your reply give us the dates of your consular service, continuous
or otherwise. We wold also esteem it a favor if you would give us
the name of your predecessor and his address, if known to you.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800025.jpg"/>

<p>Know all Men by these Present, That &#160;&#160;&#160;,
&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; have made, constituted, and appointed, and by these presents do
make, constitute, and appoint John Paul Jones and Reese H. Voorhees,
and Omar D. Conger and Chilion P. Conger, either or both of them, my 
true and lawful attorneys, for me and in my name, place, and stead, to act for me and on my
behalf, in the prosecution of whaterver claim I ma have against the United States Government
on account of consular fees erroneously accounted for by me as "official fees."</p>

<p>Giving and granting unto my said attorney, or attorneys, full power and authority to do and
perform every act and thing whatsoever requisite and necessary to be done in and about the
premises, as fully to all intents and purposes as I might or could do if personally present
at the doing thereof, with full power of substitution; and upon the settlement of my said claim I
authorize my said attorneys, or either of them, to receive of the proper officers of the Government
any and all original papers which may have been filed in support of my said claim, and to 
receive the draft which may issue in payment thereof; Provided, that said draft is made payable 
to my order, and not to the order of my said attorneys, or either of them, and to forward
said original papers and said draft to me.</p>

<p>In Witness Whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and seal this &#160;&#160;&#160;
day of &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;, eighteen hundred and ninety-two.</p>

<p>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; [SEAL.]</p>

<p>Two witnesses who can write:</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800026.jpg"/>

<p>Extracts from a letter of
Rev. J. Chester Hyde, M. X.</p>

<p>Equator, Congo State, April 27, 1892</p>

<p>There is an edict soon to be issued restraining all other 
than State flags except in neurtral waters. The Dutch,
French &amp; English flags are not allowed now inland
of Matadi and at stations on the Upper Kongo, except
when the State flag is given preference at the top.</p>

<p>Mr. Greshoff (of the great Dutch African Trading Company)
removes the Dutch and substitutes the State flag when
landing at the State quarters.</p>

<p>The French authorities interdict the use of the
State flag on steamers starting from the French side.
Even canoes without State flags cannot pass Equator
station &amp; a Dutch steamer was fired on for trying 
to thus pass Bangalla.</p>

<p>As for the Belgian flag, it accompanies the
State flag on the Upper Kongo steamers, but is not
allowed on Buildings of the Railroad above Matadi.</p>

<p>I may give you some of my observations during
a visit to recruit my heath to the furthest Baptist
Mission station Upoto and the head Congo Balolo Mission 
station Bonginda on the Lulanga river.</p>

<p>As to currency, cash money is beginning to be
introduced with the advance of the railroad to Palabala,
The State receives only money for stamps and prefers
money for taxes; and we must pay coast labor partly
in cash, which is only obtained as 6%, whereas

<pb facs="ViewScan_800027.jpg"/>

natives will pay in cash for goods and make
allowance for loss beside a fair percentage.</p>

<p>Cloth is in demand everywhere. Brass wire is
a convenient currency from Lukungu to as far as I
have gone. Cloth can be sold to advantages all 
the way especially on the tributaries.</p>

<p>Very small white and blue beads are in demand
on the Lulanga, and large Mayacca or
white beads, the size of ordinary marbles, are in 
great demand at Upoto.</p>

<p>I am sorry to say that the State took off the
the tax on liquor with the 1st of January 1892, and
even with said tax gin in pint bottles was beginning 
to be the currency on the South as well
as the north bank of the Kongo.</p>

<p>Our postage is 50 centimes (10¢) per 15 grammes
(half <unclear>ounce</unclear>) for foreign and 25 centimes for domestic mail.</p>

<p>Ivory is especially sought on the Kassai and
rubber is bought in grant quantities at Luebo by
the Société Anonyme Belge.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks of this place has a beautiful and
substantial house of native woods, except the roof.
He makes tar for pressuring wood of gum copal <unclear extent="one word"/>
to liquid and thinned with palm-oil. When put on
hot, it renders the surface <unclear extent="one word"/> impervious to
water. He will make copal vanish when he
gets up linseed-oil. His roof is of European <unclear>boa</unclear>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800028.jpg"/>

covered with felt treated with this tar, and he
expects, by constantly covering the roof with the
preparation, to make it like one sheet of glass.</p>

<p>He has Medeira cherries, coffee, vegetable
<unclear extent="one word"/>, tomatoes, beans, lettuce, limes, <unclear extent="one word"/>,
malakajas, paw-paws, pine-apples.</p>

<p>His wife is well, and has born him two little
ones while living here. Thirty natives have put
on Christ and been baptized quite recently.
The language is Lu-nkundu, the people are
Ba-lols. Fish are plentiful in the river, hippos
abound. A leopard was scented, and a smaller
animal seen last evening. The leopard had killed
five people already. Mr. Banks killed one before.
Monkeys are numerous.</p>

<p>At Frebu, Rev. C.G. Hartsock, <unclear>A.</unclear>B. of Brown
University lives with his wife together with Rev.
Thos. Moody and wife of Rochester, N.Y. The 
former is building a house of brick.</p>

<p>It is rumored that Arabs are pouring in to the head
waters of the Lopori and the "Commissaire" of this
district is now visiting that country in a steam
<unclear>launch</unclear>.</p>

<p>At Bangala the State authorities have placed
260 liberated boys under Roman Catholic Fathers
to the trained for terms of 5 or 7 years in case of 
the smartest with he understanding that 1/10
of them are to continue in the mission and

<pb facs="ViewScan_800029.jpg"/>

9/10 are to enter the service of the State. They
sing the Magnificat in Latin and the Belgian
national anthem in French; ask grace after and
before meals in the same and show themselves off
in the alphabet fairly well. They also distinguish
"papa fume sa pipe" one letter from another in
concert. Their training is very fair.</p>

<p>The State is constructing excellent buildings of
brick with tile roofs. The hospital is especially
fine, and the physician is so successful as to keep 
it nearly empty, while the deaths are few.</p>

<p>The woods of this country are very superior, being
now used in preference to any sent out from Norway.
Yet on the lower river and in the cataract district
we are compelled to send to Europe.</p>

<p>J. Chester Hyde, M.A.</p>

<note>Extracts from 
a letter of Rev. J. 
Chester Hyde 
about the Congo State</note>

<note>Enclosure No. 2
in Despatch No. 28</note>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800030.jpg"/>

<note>No. 29</note>
<note>Department of State Received Aug 29 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 29 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Requesting leave of absence
to the United States</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_800031.jpg"/>

<note>No. 29</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 29 1892</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>For the reasons enumerated below
I take the liberty to request the Department 
to grant me a furlough to
the United States, for the maximum
time allowable and to begin as soon 
as suitable to me in the early part
of 1893.</p>

<p>(1) Angola offers at the present time
one of the most promising fields for
American enterprise. Simple Consular
reports are not sufficient to induce American
capitalists to invest money in a country
so far and unknown. It requires personal 
conversation to inspire confidence in the
informant and to organize a commercial
undertaking. The first condition of important 
commercial relation between

<pb facs="ViewScan_800032.jpg"/>

America and Africa is the presence in
Africa of reliable American firms. When 
once set a-rolling the ball will soon 
become an avalanche. Mr. Hart, of the Geo.
Squire Mfctg. Co. Buffalo, N.Y., has
been here a few weeks, and has already from
the Loanda District alone, orders for more
than $20.000 of agricultural machinery and
the promise much more in the near
future. On similar and other lives, American
firms and individuals could do as well and
better, if well represented on the spot.</p>

<p>Two German commercial travelers who canvassed 
Angola a year ago got orders for
about $200,000 and since then German
imports are seriously competing with the
English.</p>

<p>(2) The Consular reports from this field
shall not suffer by my furlough, as
by correspondence with my friends here and
by the papers of the Province, I shall be
as well informed in America, and able
to supplement any information in greater
detail.</p>

<p>(3) The Chicago Congress on African ethnology

<pb facs="ViewScan_800033.jpg"/>

in connection with the Expedition, the publication
of my large work on Angolan ethnology, especially
on folk-lore, which is the most important contribution 
to that branch of science ever yet written,
and which is sure to give haste to the above-mentioned 
Congress, and various other scientific
meetings, associations and publications will be 
greatly benefited by my presence, even for a
short time, in America.</p>

<p>(4) Last, but not least, my physical constitution 
will, by that time need the bracing
influence of a more temperate climate, and
my heart and mind some heathenism and corruption of
all sorts.</p>

<p>Trusting my request will be granted,<lb/>
I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90000.jpg"/>

<note>No. 31</note>
<note>Department of State Received Aug 29 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, Africa, June 29 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Request of an allowance for office-rent</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90001.jpg"/>

<note>No. 31</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, June 29, 1892</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Six weeks ago a partner of Newton,
Carnegie &amp; Co. showed me in a clipping from 
an English paper a Washington telegram
purporting that Congress had for the current
fiscal year reduced the income of this
Consulate, as that of other minor ones in
Africa, to the fees.</p>

<p>At the same time I was advised 
not to be such a fool as to stay in Loanda
spending money for a government that ceased 
to support me.</p>

<p>There being a probability of retrenchment
in the budget of this Congress, I somewhat 
expected that my salary would be
stopped after the June quarter, and realizing
the impossibility of my continuing long to
be Consul without any support; was awaiting

<pb facs="ViewScan_90002.jpg"/>

the official announcement of the reduction, in
order to tender my resignation, and shut up
this Consular officer, for without remuneration
as English-speaking person would take it, 
as, however, the official advice of the curtailment 
has not yet come, nor do American
papers confirm that news, I have begun to
doubt its correctness.</p>

<p>Still, as this question has set me a-thinking,
I have come to the conclusion that,
whether the salary be continued or not, its 
would only be just, in presence of the peculiar 
circumstances of this port, of the Department
would assume the expense of office-rent,
not to exceed 7 dollars per month. This 
is the request I now respectfully submit
to your decision.</p>

<p>Considering further the fact, that I am
not engaged in business and give all my 
time to the collection and distribution of non-paying, 
yet highly useful, information on
this vast Consular district, an appropriate
increase of salary, which would per se settle
the office question, would appear yet more
just, and ensure the better standing of this
post.</p>

<p>I am, Sir, your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90003.jpg"/>

<note>No. 38</note>
<note>Department of State Received Sept 15 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, August 2, 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Autonomy of Angola</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>Transmitting extracts of Portuguese
and Angolan papers showing the
trend of public opinion in regard
to the self-government and independence
of Angola and other Portuguese colonies.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90004.jpg"/>

<note>No. 38</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, August 2, 1892</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>As illustrating the growing popularity 
of the idea of self-government
or complete independence, among
the whites as well as natives of Angola
and the echo the same idea is finding
in Portugal, I have the honor to 
enclose two extracts of Portuguese
papers on the subject.</p>

<p>Extract no. 1 is from the "Seculo",
by far the most popular paper of Portugal.</p>

<p>Extract no. 2 is from a new Angolan
paper, the "Commercio d' Angola",
founded by one of the oldest and
most influential white resident.
He is the father-in-law of a former
Governor and of six of the principal

<pb facs="ViewScan_90005.jpg"/>

public officers and merchants.
St. <unclear>Tarora</unclear>, referred to in Extract no. 2,
is a descendant of an old aristocratic family
and has been for about thirty years
an honored judge in the higher courts
of the different Portuguese colonies.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<p>Enclosures</p>

<p>No. 1 Extract from the "Seculo"</p>

<p>No. 2 Extract from the "Commercio d' Angola". </p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90006.jpg"/>

<p>Extract no. 1
From the "Seculo" of Lisbon</p>

<p>Translation.</p>

<p>Independence of Angola.</p>

<p>The newspaper of the important
colony are again concerned about
the state of the Province and
the negligence with which it is
treated by the government of the
metropolis. One of them, thus
finishes an editorial on this
subject.</p>

<p>Let therefore, the unanimous
and arousing cry of all be
"the independence of Angola".
In another article, the following may be read:
"This cannot, nor shall it, continue. The
government is secretly selling the colonies
and we do not want to be English. Therefore,
the only alternative left us is to proclaim
the independence (autonomy) of the Province,
imploring the protection of the United States
of North-America. This, as is well known

<pb facs="ViewScan_90007.jpg"/>

would not be difficult; it will be done
the day we want it. It is, however,
to be lamented, that good and loyal Portuguese,
who long for the greatness of their country, and
love their native land, be forced by their 
ill-omened government to co-operate in
the disintegration of the fatherland."</p>

<p>In another article, mentioning an
injustice committed in S. Thomé, one
reads: "It becomes necessary for us
to change our minds, far from the present
regimen we can expect nothing but injustice
and contempt."</p>

<p>Thus it is that the government by
its favoritism and that of its delegates
is estranging the sympathies of the colonies
and pushing them to revolt.</p>

<p>When the thing is done, it will be too late
to repent.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90008.jpg"/>

<!-- Article in Portuguese -->

<pb facs="ViewScan_90009.jpg"/>

<p>Extract No. 2.
From the "Commercio d'Angola" no. 3.</p>

<p>Translation of marked Passage</p>

<p>"It is one more competent
&amp; authoritative voice, &amp; demonstrate
the lack of wisdom with which the
central government legislate, as a
rule, for the colonies, and to prove 
the absolute necessity of granting
to some of them their administrative
autonomy. . . . . . .</p>

<p>The idea of autonomy has acquired,
in these last times, a great prominence
in the minds of these who love their
country with genuine enthusiasm.
By granting autonomy to Angola,
Portugal would reap two enormous
advantages:</p>

<p>(1) The reduction of defecit in
the colonial budget</p>

<p>(2) The rapid increase of the
indirect receipts by the development
of commerce.</p>

<p>The Portuguese government has

<pb facs="ViewScan_90010.jpg"/>

already admitted the advisability of 
self-government, by turning our the administration
of certain parts of East-Africa to chartered
companies. But circumstances will force
it to carry out this principle more efficaciously, 
if it will not run the risk
of losing, sooner or later, its sovereignty."</p>

<p>P.S. The "Correro de Portugal" of Lisbon,
(devoted to colonial questions) thus begins its
editorial of July 6: "One of the gravest
symptoms is the cry of independence which
is being heard in almost all the colonies.
The Azores, Madeira, S. Thomé and An-
gola already openly raise the banner of
revolt and of annexation to the United States
of America; and in East-Africa, where the
Portuguese element is scanty; There is no
dislike of becoming part of the proposed
Federation of South-African States." And
the editorial, though lamenting the spirit
of disaffection towards Portugal goes
on to show that it is justified.</p>

<p>I may add that again and again whites and
natives say to me, or in my hearing: "Why don't
the United States try to get us?"</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90011.jpg"/>

<note>No. 42</note>
<note>Department of State Received Oct 22 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, September 14, 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Salary for 1892-1893</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>By suppressing my salary two months before 
I am acquainted with said suppression; by not providing
for my support during the interval, nor for my transit
home, nor for my release from my post, the
government forces upon me a loss of from $800
to $1000; while I have fulfilled my part of our contract.</p>

<p>The appropriation for Mozambique in continued by Congress.
I will not desert my post, but await a cablegram
from the Department, instructing me either to stay,
or to go home, or to close up, or appointing me to
Mozambique under certain conditions. Something should
be done to guard American interests in this Consular
district, and to prevent a crying injustice.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90012.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Feb 14 1893</note>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington, Feb. 10, 1893</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Closing of Commercial Agency
and Return to United States</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>The Commercial Agency is closed, as ordered
by the Department.</p>

<p>This fact is communicated to the Governor General 
who publishes it in the Official Bulletin,</p>

<p>The furniture is left in charge of the American 
Mission at Loanda, which is willing to
purchase, or store it.</p>

<p>The archives are packed away in boxes ready
for shipment or removal. They are not worth
paying freight on them.</p>

<p>Offer of services and permanent address
of self.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90013.jpg"/>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington Febr. 10, 1893</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p> In accordance with your telegraphic 
order "Close Consulate" of &#160; &#160;
I have closed the U.S. Commercial
Agency at Loanda and returned
to the United States.</p>

<p>The Governor General of Angola,
officially informed by me, announced
the closing of the Agency in the Official
Bulletin, previous to my sailing.</p>

<p>The furniture and archives of the
Agency I left in charge of Mr. L.
C. Burling of the American Methodist
Episcopal Mission at Loanda. This
mission is willing to buy the furniture
at a cheap rate, or to keep it in trust
until the consulate be re-opened.
The archives I have packed in various

<pb facs="ViewScan_90014.jpg"/>

boxes, ready for shipment, if the Department
should want them removed: The bound
books (Statutes, Commercial Relations, Consular
Reports etc) fill one large case. The Records 
are packed in a separate box; and so are
the unused Forms and the Manuscripts
(Instructions, Circulars and Correspondence),
with the seals.</p>

<p>As the archives do not contain any
document of real value, and as the Mission
is willing to store them for the government,
I would suggest to the Department to
lease them in their present condition
until the Consulate be re-opened.</p>

<p>Even after my exit of office and
return to the States, the Department will
always find me most willing to serve
the government with my experience and
knowledge of Angola and African
matters generally.</p>

<p>"Care of the Smithsonian Institution"
will always find me.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90015.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Feb 14 1893</note>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington Febr. 10, 1893</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Property of
U.S. Gabon Commercial Agency</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents</p>

<p>(1) What the property consists of</p>

<p>(2) American Mission willing to
acquire furniture at a reasonable
price</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90016.jpg"/>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington Febr. 10, 1893</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>On my way hence I visited the U.S. 
Commercial Agency at Gaboon and ascertained 
the state of its property.</p>

<p>It consists of:<lb/>
1 book case<lb/>
1 desk<lb/>
1 lounge<lb/>
1 revolving office chair<lb/>
The customary collections of Consular Reports,
Statutes etc.<lb/>
A trunk containing old letters<lb/>
The usual Records and forums</p>

<p>The furniture has been preserved
in fair condition.</p>

<p>The Records do not contain 
anything of importance.</p>

<p>If the Department decides to sell

<pb facs="ViewScan_90017.jpg"/>

the furniture, the American Mission at
Gaboon, which has hitherto taken care
of it, is disposed to buy it at a moderate
price.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, Sir,<lb/>
your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90018.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Feb 14 1893</note>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington Febr 10, 1893</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Mr. Ed Bannister's irregular
Conduct</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90019.jpg"/>

<p>Commercial Agency of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda, Washington, Feb 10, 1893</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I am sorry to have to inform you of
Mr. Ed. Bannister's irregular conduct in
various matters:</p>

<p>(1) In the settlement of Judson's estates
he kept some money (about $100.-) which
I already mentioned in a previous despatch,
and which I doubt he ever paid to the
Treasury; and he refused to return to me
some papers he had asked of me for said
settlement.</p>

<p>(2) Unbeknown to me he corresponded
as U.S. Vice-Consul with the Chicago Exhibition,
bought and sent to them a native canoe and
machila, telling the people at Loanda that
my appointment as Commercial Agent did
not interfere with his as Vice-Consul.</p>
 
<p>(3) I hear that since my departure

<pb facs="ViewScan_90020.jpg"/>

and the closing of the Consulate officially
made known in the government's Official 
Bulletin for Angola, he still claim to be
and signs himself as U.S. Vice-Consul.</p>

<p>(4) This is the more reprehensible as Mr.
Bannister is acting British Consul at
Loanda and appointed British Consul for
the Kongo Free State.</p>

<p>It might be well for the Department
to stop Mr. Bannister's unlawful use 
of said title by informing the public of
Angola through the Governor and the Official
Bulletin that Mr. Bannister has no
right to act as, or call himself, U.S.
Vice-Consul.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90021.jpg"/>

<note>"Loanda"</note>
<note>Department of State Received Mar 23 1893</note>

<p>118 E. 45 St New-York</p>

<p>March 21, 1893</p>

<p>To Hon. Josiah Quincy<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Instruction no 19, of February 16, last,
by Hon. Wm. F. Wharton, informing me that
the property of the U.S. Commercial Agency
at Loanda Africa, "may remain, for the 
present, in the custody of Mr. L. C. Burling
of the M. E. Mission at Loanda" has in due
course of time reached me here.</p>

<p>For the guidance of the Department,
allow me to state that Mr. R. S. Newton,
formerly U.S. Vice-Consul at Loanda died at
Madeira on his way to England and that his
firm at Loanda is being dissolved.</p>

<p>Through no longer connected with the
department, I shall always be glad to

<pb facs="ViewScan_90022.jpg"/>

give the Consular Bureau any information
it may desire on African affairs, which
continue to be the special object of my 
studies.</p>

<p>The above address, or care of National
Museum Washington, will always find me.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
Late U.S. Coml Agent, Loanda, Africa</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90023.jpg"/>

<note>Index Bureau Dep't of State Received May 8 1893</note>

<p>Vice-Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, March 29, 1893</p>

<p>Mr. Ed Bannister<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Abolishment of Loanda
Consulate.</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>Asking if Loanda Consulate
is abolished and with it the
Vice-Consulate, and if so
requests information as to
his Bond for $2000.</p>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90024.jpg"/>

<p>Vice Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
 Loanda, March 29, 1893.</p>

<p>Honorable<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Some months ago a rumour got
about and came to my ears that the
U.S. Government had decided to abolish
the Loanda Consulate. This rumour
shortly took form in the departure of Mr
Chatelaine, Commercial Agent.</p>

<p>2. I have not as yet received any
others intimation as to the abolishment
of this Consulate, officially or otherwise.</p>

<p>My Commission from the United
States govt. as Vice-Consul is dated
July 17, 1890 and is endorsed with
my Exequatur from the King of
Portugal dated 16 Sept. 1891.</p>

<p>I had to give a Board for $2000
on my appointment, and I would
respectfully request you to inform
<catchwords>me</catchwords>

<pb facs="ViewScan_90025.jpg"/>

me if my post as Vice-Consul
is abolished, and if so why my
Bond has not been returned to me.</p>

<p>If you cannot get more
courteous and suitable people
to represent you here than Mr. Chatelaine
it would be as well you should
keep this Consulate closed.</p>

<p>I am<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Ed Bannister<lb/>
U.S. Vice Consul.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
