<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0009">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, "The Locomotive in Central Africa" (1907)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0009</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to "To Enter Africa from America", made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Locomotive in Central Africa</title>
<author/>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<date when="1907-10">October 1907</date>
<biblScope unit="page">189-192</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term>Livingstone, David, 1813-1873.</term>
<term>Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Amazon River</term>
<term>Atlantic Ocean</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>Buli (Congo)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Egypt</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Kindu (Congo)</term>
<term>Mississippi River</term>
<term>Missouri River</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Ponthierville (Congo)</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Stanley Falls</term>
<term>Stanleyville (Congo)</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Belgians</term>
<term>Bengala</term>
<term>Boers</term>
<term>Englishmen</term>
<term>Italians</term>
<term>Negros</term>
<term>Scandinavians</term>
<term>Swiss</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>African Methodist Episcopal</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-05" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p189" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0009.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Locomotive in Central Africa.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">
               
<p>The work that the African Methodist Church is seeking to do in
Africa, no less than natural affinity, makes any item or occurrence 
connected with that remarkable land eagerly read by the patrons of the A.
M. E. Review. A few years ago there, was little besides adventures with
wild beasts and wilder men to thrill our blood, but to-day the story of the
rapid advance of civilization and its agents, the railroad and telegraph,
is a far more wonderful one than Stanley told when he returned from
finding Livingstone. It is this that makes the following recital from an
exchange correspondent so absorbing and so informing:</p>

<p> In the heart of Africa, 1700 miles from: the Atlantic, a little band of
white men, not 200 in all, direct the labors of 5000 negroes in one of the
most remarkable conquests of nature to the credit of civilization. They
press forward step by step, clearing the tropical forests and surveying the
land, throwing up embankments and laying the ties and steel rails of an
iron highway as they go. In front is a country rich in gold and copper and
the diamond fields of the Transvaal. Behind them are 1400 miles of railroad 
and waterway which nine years ago were veiled in the mystery of
Stanley's "Darkest Africa." The scream of the locomotive pierces the
jungles where lions and leopards had their lairs and droves of wild elephants
stripped the palm trees for their yellow fruit. Telephone bells
wrangle with gray parrots. Churning steamboat wheels invade the dwelling
places of hippopotami among the reeds on the river banks. A saw mill
sings at the spot where Henry M. Stanley, 20 years ago, heard the horns.

<pb xml:id="p190" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0009.002.jpg"/>

drums and savage yells of the cannibals and told his men they must go
down the river before them or die.</p>

<p>The story of this conquest of the jungles of the Dark Continent is so
romantic and amazing and the distances are so vast that this greatest
of romances seems like a dream in a land of dreams. The Africa of the
school books and history must be cast aside. The story belongs to the last
15 years. Turning to the map of Africa new divisions appear in the territory 
south of the Sahara—tableland comprising 5,000,000 square miles, or
1,300,000 square miles more than the area of the United States, Alaska and
our colonial possessions. The conquest of the jungle here related refers 
to the very heart of the Dark Continent under the equator, the 900,000
square miles of the Congo Free State, which, if laid on the map of the
United States, would cover the New England and Middle Atlantic States,
and extend westward on parallel lines nearly to the Rocky Mountains. The
topography of the country at once suggests the more familiar contour of
Mexico. They are alike in the strip of low, unhealthy, tropical forest near
the Atlantic and beyond the mountain chains, with tablelands between
them.</p>

<p>The heart of this country was indeed "Darkest Africa when Livingston 
cast the first glimmer of light upon it in 1867. Stanley's journeys
across it in 1874 and 1877 and on the Emin Pasha relief expedition of 1887-
1888 are so recent that nearly every one remembers how they set the
white man's world by the ears. Africa was then to the nineteenth century 
what America was to the fifteenth—a new Eldorado, a land of
mysteries and wonders.</p>

<p>"Without a railway I do not value the Congo State as worth a dollar,"
declared Stanley after one of his visits to the Dark Continent. He knew
of the vast riches in the tableland behind the mountain ranges, which commerce 
could only approach along one highway—the Congo River. It is
second in the great streams of the world; 2500 miles long and seven miles
wide at its mouth. Only the Amazon is greater in the volume of water;
only the Mississippi and Missouri combined exceed it in length.</p>

<p>The nation that controlled the Congo River, said Stanley, would be
mistress of Central Africa. Sailing up this waterway from the Atlantic,
through no miles of swamp and tropical forest, the trader was halted at
the mountains by a series of cataracts. In all they covered <sic>avout</sic> 200 miles
of the river's course. When Stanley said this vast empire was not worth
a dollar without a railway, he meant that bands of steel must pass these
cataracts and others further up the stream before Central Africa would be
open to the commerce of the world.</p>

<p>Could such a railway be built? In the face of the obstacles it seemed
to be an enterprise with insuperable difficulties—still the dream of the 
explorer in the,land of dreams. The white man must conquer marshes and
jungles with their wild beasts and serpents, mountains unknown except by
name, and vast tableland, drenched with rains that bore disease and death
in their train, the poisoned arrows of savages, a thousand miles of open
water, cataracts and jungles again.</p>

<p>King Leopold, of Belgium, listened and dreamed. Then Stanley’s
wonder tales inflamed the imaginations of men, and others dreamed. Their
cupidity was aroused. The world is not so large that such an empire, even
under the equator, can be neglected. England's policy foreshadowed her
approach to it from the valley of the Nile. Portugal claimed the land south
of the mouth of the Congo and France that on the north. Englishmen and
Boers were advancing on the south. The interest aroused by Stanley's tale
terminated in 1885 in the Treaty of Berlin, whereby the Congo Free State
became neutral territory for a number of years.</p>

<pb xml:id="p191" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0009.003.jpg"/>

<p>By the end of the century, or in a brief two years, the steamers 
numbered 100. The largest of them now has a burden of 500 tons The
waterways of the Congo State have been increased to 9500 miles. Telegraph 
lines, begun in 1892, annihilated 800 miles by 1900. The number of
trading posts increased from 45 in 1882, to over 200 1902; the investments
of commercial capital in the same period from $17,000 to $26,000,000 The
white man found that with temperate habits it was no more difficult to live
on the tableland than in any tropical climate—at New Orleans for example. 
He had planted 2,000,000 coffee bushes and 300,000 cocoanut trees
and had cultivated 5,000,000 india rubber plants by the end of 1902.</p>

<p>The Belgian Company owning the concession for the railways in the
Congo State intended at first to build the lines toward Egypt and the Upper Nile 
in the northwest. Reports of the riches in gold and copper in the
south, however, determined them to push on in that direction and build
the system of iron highways that is now under way. At Stanley Falls the
course of the Congo River turns sharply to the south and a second series
of seven cataracts begins. The railroad that has just been completed circles
these cascades from Stanleyville to Ponthierville, a distance of 75 miles.
The river curves like a bow, and the new railroad may be said to take the
place of the  bowstring.</p>

<p>How was this iron highway constructed 1400 miles from the sea and
in the very heart of the jungle? When the work was started, on January
26, 1903, only 53 white men—Belgians, Italians, Scandinavians and Swiss 
were available, although the number had been increased to more than 100
by the end of last year. Under them were 3000 black men. The expert
machinists, masons and track builders are negroes who came with their
families from West Africa. In that region the Negroes who were savages
15 years ago are running locomotives, working in machine shops, building
the Congo steamers and serving as crews on the railroad trains. The
Congo steamboats have as their pilots the Bengala who tried to kill
Stanley.</p>

<p>These skilled workmen are assisted by apprentices from the Government 
and missionary training schools. The road graders, track layers and
common laborers are Negroes recruited from the neighboring tribes.</p>

<p>Two hospitals were built in Stanleyville for the railroad men—one for
the whites and the other for the blacks. The danger from smallpox is
always great in Central Africa, and every one, even to the wives and children 
of the common laborers, was vaccinated with virus from a plant
near Stanleyville supplied with cattle from Europe. Native policemen were
appointed to maintain order among the laborers. Three physicians accompanied 
the party to regulate the sanitary conditions. Repair shops were
built and prospectors were sent in advance to find clay for the many bricks
which must be used and limestone to be burned into lime for mortar.</p>

<p>These elaborate preparations ended, the army of 3000-odd, with their
wives and children, set forth to conquer the jungle. They clear the forest
for a short distance, as the engineers survey the land. At once the road-
bed is graded and the tracks are laid, so that the construction train can be
brought to the very end of the line with earth and materials. No great
difficulties are encountered in making the embankments, as the road passes
through alluvial soil that is free from rock.</p>

<p>As they advance deeper into the jungle, saw mills are erected, and in
these the Negroes saw the timbers for ties, bridges, and warehouses. The
ties are of bomball trees-the "sham cedar'-a tough durable wood cut
from the neighboring forests. The steel rails are brought from Europe the
freight charges being $2500 for a kilometer of track, or $4160 for a mile.

<pb xml:id="p192" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0009.004.jpg"/>

This expense raised the; cost of the Stanleyville-Ponthierville road to 
between $15,000 and $20,000 a kilometer, or from $25,000 to $33,300 a mile.</p>

<p>Now and again a stream is reached. It is bridged! with rude timbers
at first, these being replaced by structures of masonry and steel. As the
army advances, step by step, the telephone goes with them, the wires to
Stanleyville being fastened to the trees or to steel rails set upright in the
ground. After the telephone comes the permanent telegraph.</p>

<p>The wives and children of the Negroes advance with their husbands
and fathers. In a few hours cabins of palm leaves and grass can be built
close to the tracks. They supply all the shelter the climate requires. Thus
the black men live in little tribal villages, moving forward from time to
time as the railroad advances.</p>

<p>This battle with the jungle lasted three years. The railway around the
second series of cataracts to Ponthierville was opened for traffic on September 
1 last. It was equipped with 14 locomotives and 124 cars. Steam-
boats were launched above the second cataracts and steamed south to
Kindu, along the 186 miles of waterway that had been opened' to them.</p>

<p>At Kindu another line of railroad was started at once to Buli, 180
miles distant, around the third and last series of cataracts in the river.
Here 160 white men and 5000 Negroes are pressing forward through the
jungle toward the gold and copper ore and the diamond mines of the
Transvaal.</p>

<p>The vast riches of the Dark Continent thus being laid bare tax the
credulity. The mind can scarcely grasp the meaning of 2,000,000 square
miles of forest, much of it ebony, teak and mahogany, that stretch from
Sahara to the Cope coal fields more than 1000 miles long, and some of the
richest iron and copper deposits in the world. On the Congo plateau
$8,000,000 worth of rubber is produced every year, not to mention coffee
and tobacco growing wild, pineapples, rice, bananas, corn and cotton flourishing 
in a soil as rich as that on the Lower Mississippi. In the light of
these1 facts it may well be understood why the stock of the Congo State
Railway, 100 at par, is quoted at 5000. Spaniard never found in America
an Eldorado such as this.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
