<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.fr.letter.0273">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Mr. H Davignon, Minister of Foreign Affairs, to Jules Renkin, Minister of Colonies March 5, 1919</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription, translation, and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Dawson, Kendall C." xml:id="kcd">Kendall C. Dawson</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A." xml:id="caa">Chelsea A. Akyaempong</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.fr.letter.0273</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Letter from Mr. H Davignon, Minister of Foreign Affairs, to Jules Renkin, Minister of Colonies</title>
<date when="1919-03-05">March 5, 1919</date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, Brussels, Belgium</repository>
<collection>Archives Africaines</collection>
<idno>Portefeuille 217, Liasse 122</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term/>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bacon</term>
<term>Daniels</term>
<term>Davignon, H.</term>
<term>Chester, S.H.</term>
<term>Morrison</term>
<term>Sheppard</term>
<term>Renkin, Jules</term>
<term>Root</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Boston</term>
<term>Buffalo</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Washington</term>
</keywords>
    
<!-- FILL OUT THE REMAINING CATEGORIES IF APPLICABLE. -->

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Davignon, H.</persName>
<roleName>Minister of Foreign Affaires</roleName>
<placeName>Brussels, Belgium</placeName>
<date when="1919-03-05"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Renkin, Jules</persName>
<roleName>Minister of Colonies</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-01-25" who="kln">renamed file, inserted correct header template</change>
<change when="2018" who="sab">Translated.</change>
<change when="2017" who="KCD">Transcribed.</change>
<change when="2019" who="CAA">Translated.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">Encoded.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="fr" type="document">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.001.jpg"/>

<p>Ministère 
des
Affaires Ètrangères<lb/>
Direction <unclear>G</unclear> No C VII<lb/>
Rappeler dans la réponse les numéros,
le litta de la Direction ainsi que la date.<lb/>
3 Annexes</p>

<p>Bruxelles, le 5 Mars 1909.</p>

<p>Monsieur Le Ministre,</p>

<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous accuser réception
de votre lettre du 27 février 11, no 494.</p>

<p>L'article du "Boston Transcript"
qui s'y trouvait joint et que je vous restitue
sous ce pli, m'avait été envoyé en annexe
á un rapport du Baron Moncheur de 2 février.</p>

<p>Cet article reproduit textuellement
toute une série de passages de la dépèche
adressée le 11 janvier dernier par M. Root
au Ministre du Roi à Washington.</p>

<p>Comme suite à ma lettre du 12 février
dernier j'ai l'honneur de vous communiquer
sous ce pli en copie deux nouveaux rapports
de Washington par lesquels le Baron <fw type="catch">Moncheur</fw>

<fw type="footer">M. le Ministre des Colonies
à Bruxelles</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.002.jpg"/>

Moncheur m'a rendu compte des observations adressés 
par lui d'après mes ordres au Secrétaires d'Etat
et des résultats de ces observations.</p>

<p>Vous constater par le premier
de ces rapports que le gouvernement des Etats-unis 
avait communiqué intégralement à la
"Congo Reform Association" le texte de sa dépêche
l'adressée au Bon Moncheur le 11 janvier dernier.</p>

<p>H Davignon.</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.003.jpg"/>

<p>Copie</p>

<p>Légation de Belgique<lb/>
no 124/70<lb/>
3 annexes</p>

<p>Washington, le 12 février 1909.</p>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre,</p>

<p>L'admonestation adressée par l'honorable
Robert Bacon aux agents de la Congo Reform
Association de Boston à la suite de ma protestation
parait avoir produit de l'effet, car
depuis lors la presse des Etats-unis a fait silence
au sujet de la note américaine et de l'attitude du
Cabinet de Washington au sujet de la reconnaissance
de l'annexion de l'Etat du Congo à la Belgique.</p>

<p>J'ai l'honneur de vous transmettre
quelques articles de journaux se rapportant á d'autres
question concernant le Congo.</p>

<p>Vous trouverez (annexe A) deux articles
annonçante le projet de voyage dans notre
colonie de S.A.R. M. <unclear>ye</unclear> le Prince Albert et contenant
de trés grands éloges á l'adresse de l'héritier
du Trône.</p>

<fw type="catch">L'annexe</fw>

<fw type="footer">Son Excellence Monsieur Davignon
Ministre des Affaires Etrangères
etc. etc. etc. Bruxelles</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.004.jpg"/>

<p>L'annexe B contient une information
qui ce paree dans beaucoup de journaux et d'après
laquelle l'Eglise Presbytérienne, á laquelle appartient
le <unclear>Ro</unclear> Morisson, a changé le <unclear> Ro</unclear> S.H. Chester,
Missionnaire, de prier le Secrétaire d'Etat de
faire surveiller par le Consul américain á Boma
la marche du procés en diffamation intenté contre
Morrisson et Sheppard.</p>
    
<p>Le "Sunday News" de Buffalo qui nous
est toujours très hostile publie un soi-disant
télégramme d'Anvers d'aprés le quel la caoutchoue
est en train de s'épuiser rapidement au Congo. Il
prétend aussi que l'on oblige par la force les nègres
á s'engager pour cinq ans á travailler dans les
mines d'or récemment découvertes (Annexe C)</p>

<p>Veuillez agréer etc.<lb/>
(signé) Bon Moncheur</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.005.jpg"/>

<p>Copie</p>

<p>Confidentielle</p>

<p>Légation de Belgique<lb/>
No 109/61.</p>

<p>Washington, le 5 février 1909</p>

<p>Monsieur le Ministre,</p>
    
<p>Conformément aux instructions contenues
dans votre télégramme d'hier je me suis rendre aujourd'hui
cher le Secrétaire d'Etat pour protester
contre la manière dont la correspondance échangée
récemment entre le Départment d'Etat et la
Légation avait été livrée á la publicité á l'insu
du Gouvernement du Roi.</p>

<p>M. Bacon me témoigna de suite son profond
regret de cet incident et m'expliquer comment
les choses se sont passées.</p>
    
<p>Il parait que son prédécesseur, M. Root,
tout en s'efforçant souvent de calmer la violence
de la Congo Reform Association envoyait parfois
quand l'occasion s'en présentait á M. Daniels
secrétaire de cette société les documents de nature
á l'intéresser. Avant de quitter le Département
d'Etat, M. Root avait donné pour instructions
de donner copie á M. Daniels de ma lettre du 4 <fw type="catch">novembre</fw>

<fw type="footer">Son Excellence Monsieur Davignon,
Ministre des Affaires étrangéres
etc. etc. etc. Bruxelles.</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.006.jpg"/>
    
novembre et de sa réponse du 11 janvier. Cette expédition
fut faite par M. Bacon le lendemain de son arrivée
au Département d'Etat. Toutefois il m'a assuré de
la manière la plus formelle qu'il était loin de se
douter que le Congo Reform Association s'empresserait 
de publier ces documents de la manière qu'elle 
a employée, c'est á dire en donnant á la publication 
une forme quasi officielle en déclarant
qu'elle se faisait en vertu de l'autorisation du
Département d'Etat.</p>
    
<p>Dés que M. Bacon vit l'article paru
dans le Boston Transcript et d'autres journaux
publiant la correspondance au sujet du Congo, il
télégraphia á M. Daniels de cesser immédiatement
toute publication relative á ces documents.</p>
    
<p>Je répondis au Secrétaire d'Etat que
la Congo Reform Association avait pu me connaître
ses intentions au sujet de la publication de la correspondance
dont il s'agit, mais qu'il n'en était pas
moins regrettable et contraire aux usages diplomatiques
que cette société privée eut reçu communication
de ces documents á n'importe quel titre á l'insu de mon
Gouvernement.</p> 
    
<p>M. Bacon renouvela alors l'expression
de son regret et protesta qu'il ne lui serait
jamais venu á l'esprit de manquer en quoi que 
ce soit aux régles de la courtoisie internationale <fw type="catch">á</fw>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.007.jpg"/>
    
á l'égard de la Belgique.</p>

<p>J'ajoutai encore que la Congo Reform
Association pouvant faire une tort moral considérable
á la Belgique en faisant croire au publie
qu'elle est l'organe du Département d'Etat en
ce qui concerne la question du Congo, je croyais avoir
le droit de faire connaître la déclaration que
venait de me faire M. Bacon, comme quoi la publication 
des documents dans la forme oú elle venait
d'être faire n'avait par l'autorisation du Secrétaire
d'Etat.</p>
    
<p>Celui-ci admit que ce droit m'appartient,
mais il m'exprima un vif désir de ne pas
me voir en user, vu la polémique que ma déclaration
ne manquerait pas d'entraîner avec la Congo
Reform Association.</p>

<p>Je répondis alors que le Gouvernement
du Roi resterait juge de l'opportunité qu'il y aurait
de donner ce démenti á nos adversaires.</p>
    
<p>Je crois, Monsieur le Ministre, que 
dans les circonstances actuelles il vaut mieux considérer
l'incident clos en se contentant des explications
du Secrétaire d'Etat et des expressions de
regret qu'il m'a positivement prodiguées.</p>
    
<p>Il m'a promis de télégraphier de nouveau
á M. Daniels de me faire aucun usage, pour <fw type="catch">la</fw>
    
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.008.jpg"/>

la publicité, des pièces relatives á la correspondance
que j'ai échangée avec le Département d'Etat.</p>
    
<p>En résumé il me semble que notre
action aura pour effets 1° de rendre la Secrétairerie
d'Etat plus circonspecte á l'avenir dans ses rapports - 
dévoilés et reconnus - avec la Congo Reform
Association et 2° de provoquer entre M. M. Bacon
et Daniel un échange de vues dont ce dernier
n'aura vraisemblablement pas á se féliciter.</p>
    
<p>Veuillez agréer etc.<lb/>
(signé) Bn. Moncheur.</p>

</div1>



<div1 xml:lang="en" type="translation">

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.001.jpg"/>

<p>Minister 
of 
Foreign Affairs<lb/>
Direction <unclear>G</unclear> No C VII<lb/>
Recall in the response the numbers,
in the Direction as well as the date.<lb/>
3 Annexes</p>

<p>Brussels March 5, 1909</p>

<p>Mr. Minister,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge to you the receipt 
of your letter of the 27th of February 11, no 494.</p>

<p>The "Boston Transcript" article
that you will find attached here and that I am returning to you
sans ce pli, had been sent to me in the annex 
of a report from Baron Moncheur the 2nd of February.</p>

<p>This article reproduces verbatim 
a whole series of passages from the dispatch 
sent on January 11th by M. Root
in the Minister of the King in Washington.</p>

<p>As a result of my letter from last February 
the 12th I have the honor to communicate
herewith in copy two new reports 
from Washington by which the Baron <fw type="catch">Moncheur</fw>

<fw type="footer">Mr. Minister of the Colonies 
in Brussels</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.002.jpg"/>

Moncheur became aware of his addressed observations
after my orders to the Secretaries of State 
and the results of these observations.</p>

<p>You notice by the first
of these reports that the government of the United
States had completely communicated the text 
of his dispatch at the "Congo Reform Association" 
sent to the Bon Moncheur the 11th of last January.</p>

<p>H Davignon</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.003.jpg"/>
        
<p>Copy</p>
        
<p>Legation of Belgium<lb/>
no 124-70<lb/>
3 annexes</p>
        
<p>Washington, the 12th of February 1909.</p>
        
<p>Mr. Minister,</p>
        
<p>The admonition addressed by the honorable
Robert Bacon to the officers of the Congo Reform
Association of Boston following my protest 
appear to have produced an effect, because 
since then the United States press has stayed silent on 
the topic of the American note and the attitude of the 
Washington Cabinet about the recognition 
of the annexation of the Belgian Congo state.</p>
        
<p>I have the honor to transmit herewith 
some articles from newspapers relating others to the 
issues concerning the Congo.</p>
        
<p>You will find (in annex A) two articles
announcing the voyage project in our 
colony of S.A.R. Mr. <unclear>ye</unclear> Prince Albert and contains 
very big praise to the address of the heir 
of the Throne.</p>

<fw type="catch">The annex</fw>
        
<fw type="footer">Your Excellence Mr. Davignon
Minister of Foreign Affairs 
etc. etc. etc. Belgium</fw>
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.004.jpg"/>
        
<p>The annex B includes information
that blocked in a lot of journals and after 
which the Presbyterian Church, which belongs to 
the <unclear>Ro</unclear> Morisson, changed the<unclear> Ro</unclear> S.H. Chester,
Missionary, to request the Secretary of State to 
monitor by the American Consul in Boma
the proceedings for defamation brought against
Morrisson and Sheppard.</p>
        
<p>The Buffalo "Sunday News" that we
are always very hostile published a self-said
telegram to Anvers to express which rubber 
is in the middle of rapidly running dry in the Congo. He
also claims that Negros are forced 
to commit themselves for 5 years to work in the 
recently discovered gold mines (Annexe C)</p>
        
<p>Yours sincerely etc.<lb/>
(Signed) Bon Moncheur</p>
        
<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.005.jpg"/>

<p>Copy</p>

<p>Confidential</p>

<p>Belgian Delegation <lb/>
No 109/61</p>

<p>Washinton, February 5 1909</p>

<p>Mr. Minister</p>

<p>In compliance with the contained instructions
in your telegram from yesterday, I am returning today
to the Secretary of State for protesting 
against the manner which the correspondence was exchanged
recently between the Department of State and the 
Delegation was free to be published to the unknown King's Government.</p>

<p>M. Bacon testified to me the following profound
regret of this incident and explained to me how
these things came to pass.</p>

<p>It appeared that his predecessor, M. Root,
all too often enforced the calming of violence
of the Congo Reform Association in sending from time to time
when the occasion presented itself to Mr. Daniels
secretary of this society the documents of an interesting nature.
Before leaving the Department of State, M. Root was given instructions to 
give a copy to M. Daniels my letter from the 4th<fw type="catch"> of November</fw></p>

<fw type="footer">His Excellency Mr. Davignon,
Minister of Foreign Affairs
etc. etc. etc. Brussels</fw>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.006.jpg"/>

<p>November and from his respoinse from January 11. This expedition
was done by M. Bacon the following day of his arrival
to the Department of State. However, il assured me of
the most formal manner that it was far from 
that the Congo Reform Association was hastened to
publish the these documents of the manner that it 
has employed, this is to say in giving to the publication
an official form in declaring 
that it was in virute of authorization from the 
Department of State.</p>

<p>From then M. Bacon provides the apparent article
in the Boston Transcript and some other journals
pulbishing the correspondance of the Congo subject, he
telegraphed M. Daniels about immediately ceasing
all publications relative to these documents.</p>

<p>I responded to the Secretary of State that the
Congo Reform Association could have known of 
its intentions on the subject of the publication of the correspondance
in which it concerns, but it was not 
les regrettable and contrary to the diplomatic uses
that this private society received communication of
any of these documents titled to the unkown of my Government.</p>

<p>M. Bacon therefore renewed the expression of 
his regret and protested that he would
never lack the spirit of 
what were the rules of international courtesy
<fw type="catch">in</fw></p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.007.jpg"/>

<p>in regarding Belgium.</p>

<p>I added again that the Congo Reform
Association had the power of a considerably wrong moral doing
to Belgium in believing to publish 
that it is the organ of the Department of State in this concerning
the Congo question, I beleived to have the right to know the declaration 
that came to me from M. Bacon's doing, as to what publication of 
documents in the form where it came to be done not having the 
Secretary of State's authorization.</p>

<p>This, here, admits that this right belongs to me
but he expresses to me a keen desire of not
seeing me use it, the percieved argument that my declaration
did not lack of being exercised with the Congo
Reform Association.</p>

<p>I reply with the King's Government
as the remaining judge of the opportunity that there was
giving this denial to our adversaries.</p>

<p>I believe Mr. Minister, that
in these actual circumstances it must be better considered
the incident closed containing itself in explications
of the Secretary of State and some expressions of 
regret that it positively dispense.</p>

<p>He promised me to telegraph the new
Mr. Daniels of using it for</p>

<pb facs="teaa.fr.letter.0273.008.jpg"/>

<p>the publicity, some relative pieces of correspondance 
that I exchanged with the Department of State.</p>

<p>In summary, it appears to me that our 
action will have for number 1 effects of renduring the Secretary 
of State more cautious to the future reports
revealed and recognized - with The Congo Reform 
Association and number 2 of provoking between M. M. Bacon
and Daniel an exchange of views which this last
in all likelihood will not have to be pleased about. </p>

<p>Yours sincerely, etc. <lb/>
(signed) Bn. Monceur.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

