<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0917">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader, June 30, 1875</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0917</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. Milton Turner to John L. Cadwalader</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1875-06-30">June 30, 1875</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Brandon, Harriette</term>
<term>Dawson, J. E.</term>
<term>King, C. T. O. C.</term>
<term>Lewis, John N., Jr.</term>
<term>Matthews, Bachus</term>
<term>Yates, Beverly Page</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Madeira</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Montserrado County (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3272285">Turner, James Milton</persName>
<roleName>Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1875-06-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66848474">Cadwalader, John L. (John Lambert), 1836-1914</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1875-08-04"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-07" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1011.jpg"/>

<p>No. 4.</p>

<p>Legation of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia Republic of Liberia</p>

<p>J Milton Turner<lb/>
to the Department of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Subject/</p>

<p>Report for Quarter ended June 30th 1875</p>

<p>Inclosure No. 1. Rent and Miscellaneous Expense Account<lb/>
 " " 2 Agreement for Office<lb/>
 " " 3. Salary Account<lb/>
 " " 4 Invoice Book<lb/>
 " " 5 Official Letters sent<lb/>
 " " 6  " " received<lb/>
 " " 7 Arrival and Departure of American Vessels</p>

<pb n="Roll3-1012.jpg"/>

<p>No. 4.</p>

<p>Monrovia Liberia June 30th 1875</p>

<p>Sir/</p>

<p>Agreeably with an instruction imparted through the Department's No. 87, I have the honor to transmit herewith my report for the quarter ended this day. In continuation of the subject of my necessity to remove the Archives of my Legation and Consulate, to a more safe location, as <sic>refered</sic> to in my No 155 to the Secretary of State,–dated April 14 1875; I now take the liberty to invite your attention to inclosures one and two of this despatch, and to explain as follows. After a diligent, but fruitless inquiry extending throughout the major part of the month of April, I was compelled to conclude that the premises <sic>refered</sic> to in the above inclosures, were not alone the only place to be obtained for the amount allowed me for rent, but the only place of any description 
<catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1013.jpg"/>

to be rented on any terms whatever, in Monrovia. (It is customary here, for one desiring a house to purchase a lot of ground and build.) The owner of this place would only agree to let me have it on condition that I would advance him a sufficient sum of money to place the premises in tenable repair. This I had no authority to do. But the severe rains of May and June, were at hand, and my condition was then such as to forbid delay in the removal of the Archives to a place where they would be safe from damage and destruction by the rain. It was my strong preference to request instruction from the Department, but the time was too short to allow of my receiving a reply in season to avoid the rain;–I was in a <sic>dilema</sic>, my necessity was imperative. I have, therefore, made the best agreement possible with Mr Yates, and secured the

<pb n="Roll3-1014.jpg"/>

the place in Broad Street for five years. I have paid to him from my personal funds, the amount set forth in voucher No. 2, and signed a contract, copy of which is transmitted herewith and marked 2. I would have informed you of this transaction, at an earlier date, but it seemed to belong more appropriately in my quarterly report. I will be perfectly contented with any manner in which the Department may see fit to reimburse me for the amount advanced to Mr Yates. I have felt authorised to draw for $25.00 of that amount to cover the two months which have elapsed since the 1st of May. Voucher No. 1 is intended to cover my draft dated May 5th 1875, for $8.33/100 paid for rent of the old office for the Month of April. I sincerely hope that my action in this transaction, may, in consideration of the <catchwords>emergency</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1015.jpg"/>

emergency in which I was placed, meet with the sanction of the Department; and, that I have not <sic>incured</sic> displeasure.</p>

<p>I have to report also, that I am without the proper means of keeping my books and official documents in a durable state of file and preservation. I have been confined to an old and rotten, now useless table, instead of a desk <sic>instead of a desk</sic>. On attempting to move the box in which I have <sic>hetofore</sic> kept my despatches, and other official documents on file, it dropped in pieces and is no longer of use. The United States Statutes, government reports, and other beautifully bound, valuable works, sent to me by the Department, are fast accumulating into a handsome collection of useful books,–especially useful in this country. I have therefore, to respectfully request that permission be granted <catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1016.jpg"/>

to me, to order from <sic>Maderia</sic>, or some other near post,–thus saving time and freight–a cheap writing desk and plain book case with shelves, suitable to file the books and documents <sic>refered</sic> to above. I would also like one chair.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir/<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
J Milton Turner</p>

<fw type="address">John L. Cadawalder<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-1017.jpg"/>

<note>Inclosure 2.</note>

<note>Copy</note>

<p>This Indenture of Agreement made and entered into this First day of May AD 1875; between Beverly P Yates of the City of Monrovia Attorney in fact for John N. Lewis Jr., heir to the late Harriette Brandon deceased and late of the city of Monrovia of the one part, and J Milton Turner United States Minister to Liberia of the other part: Witnesseth "to wit," that in consideration of the conditions to be hereinafter specified, he, the said B P Yates Attorney as aforesaid, hath demised and leased, and doth by these presents demise and lease to the said J Milton Turner Minister as aforesaid, a certain house and lot of ground situated in Broad Street in the City of Monrovia Liberia, and being the same <catchwords>premises</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-1018.jpg"/>

premises formerly occupied and owned by the lat Harriette Brandon and belonging at the present writing to the above named John N. Lewis Jr. The said J. Milton Turner to have possess and to hold the above described house and lot of ground and the appurtenances thereunto belonging for the term of five - 5 years beginning at the date herein before mentioned, provided however, the said premises be devoted to the sole and exclusive business of the United States Legation. In consideration for which grant or lease, he, the said J Milton Turner agrees and hereby covenants to pay in equal quarterly installments, a yearly rental of One Hundred and fifty Dollars in the current money of the United States. The said J Milton Turner shall be priviledged to spend for the repairs of the house, the same to be deducted from the fixed rent <catchwords>thereof,</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1019.jpg"/>

thereof, whatever reasonable portion of the rent that may be required to place and keep the said house in <unclear extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> repair. In the event the official term of the said J Milton Turner be terminated by any cause whatsoever, before the expiration of this lease, then, the determination of the continuation of this lease shall be, and remain optional with the official successor or successors of the said J Milton Turner; provided however, that the said B. P. Yates Attorney aforesaid: shall not at any time be required to refund any portion, or part of the rental money, which portion or part thereof, may have been paid in advance, or expended by the said J Milton Turner on the repairs of the house or premises, because of the termination of this lead by the said successor or successors. Provided further: that none of the terms of this agreement nor any part thereof, shall not at any time supersede any law or laws, which may have been or may hereafter be <catchwords>enacted</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-1020.jpg"/>

enacted by the Government of the United States in any way relating to, or effecting this Legation</p>

<p>In witness whereof the said parties have hereunto affixed their hand the day and year hereinbefore named</p>

<p>-sgd- Beverly Page Yates<lb/>
Attorney in fact for John N. Lewis Jr.<lb/>
J Milton Turner U.S. Minister Res.</p>

<p>Witnessed by<lb/>
Bachus Matthews<lb/>
J. E. Dawson</p>

<p>B. P. Yates Atty in fact for J. D. Lewis Jr.
to J Milton Turner U.S. Minister Res.</p>

<p>Let this be registered Beverly Page Yates Judge of Probate Court Montserrado County</p>

<p>Probated this 3rd day of May A.D. 1875<lb/>
C.T.O.C. King<lb/>
Clk. Mo Co Probate Court</p>

<p>Inclosure 2</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>