<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Derek Loun
Ald Calabor
25 May 1864

Sir,
I duly received your letter of 12th April, desiring, on behalf of the government of the United States, a supply of lealabor beau

I have much pleasure in being able to comply with your request and shall lead per mail a small <unclear> bor </unclear> containing lotter. If analysis is the <unclear> olyeeb, </unclear> there will probably be too few <unclear> for any entertive </unclear> experiements. But M Baillee says that "500 or do would perhaps be enough". There are more than that in 10 lbs. Should more be needed I shall be happy to supply them; such if may be well that you give me notice without any long delay, <unclear/> my supply should rew out.

By the present mail steam that 10 /- has been paid per pound in London but as there are for <unclear> sacrifice, specific </unclear> puurpose shall give them for 6/ per pound. 

<!-- right side cut off -->
It is not out of place to state that about four years ago,I supplied some some of these beans to to a <unclear> P </unclear> Mitchell in Philadelphia who, I undertood was <unclear/> in an analysis of African ordeals.

The request come to me though <unclear> one </unclear> of the missionaries at Leouises or Gabon I may further state that the <unclear> fallen </unclear> I believe the only, aeedunt of the Leone is to be found in a "Graduation thesis
published by Messes Olivia and <unclear> Boya</unclear> Edinbaugh. the title a 

"The Characters, actions and <unclear> therea  peutie uses of </unclear> Ordeal Bean Calabar (Physestigma romondosum Bayour) A graduation thesis for which a gold medal was awarded the Edinburgh unworthy. 

By Thoas R. Fraser M. D. Edward . Kin published in the form of a pamhlet and give a full account of the experiements and their results and also experiment eases of diseases in which the bean had been used as a semevy. with government.

I have the honor to be
Sir
Your obedieent servant
Alexander Robb

Henry Esq
U.S. Vice Consul
Sierra Leone 

P.S. I may <unclear extent=eight words/> poison, and should be take out of the <unclear extent=two word/> any acid out happen. There is <unclear extent=three words/> in her eten, or course; but I believe that loss <unclear extent= two words/> may be a fatal dose. Its native name is <symbolism/> (easmmeh)
A.R. 