<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

U.S. Vice Com: Agency
Sierra Leone Aug 1st 1868
Theodore A. Rosenbush

No. 4

Received

Reply to Despatch
No.6 Mr.Riders' place
of birth and appointment. 

Vice. Commercial Agency of the
United States of America
Sierra Leone August 1st 1868

Sir,
I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of a despatch from the Department of State dated June 16th, 1868 No.7 informing me that my assumption of the change of the Commercial Agency's Office and this settlement had been approved of by the Department that accordingly I had appointed Vice Commercial Agent, subject to the conditions of law and the Consular regulations, and that the certficate of my appointment had

W. Seward Esqre
Assistant Secretary

had been sent to the Legation of the United States at London for the purpose of obtaining my official recognition by the British Government.

I have also to acknowledge the receipt of the Forms of Consular Bond, oath of Office and allegiance and Circular N:68, N:69, N:70.

I beg to thank the Department for my appointment and will to the best of my abilities endeavor to carry out it' instructions and gard the interest of the United States Government and it's Citizens.

I m a natice of Hamburg in Germany, but resident in this settlement since January 1847, my appointment emanted from the despatch to which I have the honor to reply at present. 

Not knowing anybody in the United States sufficiently to ask to become bond for me I have written to me Bankers in London to procure me the requisite Bonds, men, citizens of the United States, conceiving that such only the Department requires, on the receipt of the names of my Bondsmen I shall forward the Bond forthwith. 

Being a naturalized British subjct I cannot consistently take the oatch of allegiance as prescribed in the printef form, having in substance subscribed to a similar oath to the British Governement.

<!-- right side partially cut off -->

Not knowing whether the Department keeps other forms of oaths I have taken the <unclear> liberty </unclear> to alter the form sent, <unclear>consistent </unclear> with my conscience, sworn to it befre a Police <unclear> Magistration </unclear> of this place, and enclose it. 

I have communcated any appointment to Sir <unclear> Arthur </unclear> E. Kennedy of the Governor <unclear> in </unclear> Chief of the West African Settlements, who <unclear> provisionally</unclear> recognises it subject to it's approval by the British Government. 

In conclusion I beg to inform the Department hat I am Consul for the Netherlands and Consul for the Republic of Liberia for both of which Offices I hold the Exegular of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain.

I have the honor to be
Sir,
Your obedient Servant
Rosenbush
U.S. Vice-Comm: Agent