<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0066">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>"Items of Intelligence" (1891)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0066</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Items of Intelligence</title>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
<date when="1891-10">October 1891</date>
<biblScope unit="page">123-</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bahia (Brazil)</term>
<term>Busi River</term>
<term>Brazil</term>
<term>French Congo</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Lagos</term>
<term>Leopoldville (Congo Free State)</term>
<term>Limpopo River</term>
<term>Ogowe River</term>
<term>Pungwe River</term>
<term>Sabi River</term>
<term>Shiré River</term>
<term>Lake Victoria Nyanza</term>
<term>Zambesi River</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Catholic</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-01" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p123" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0066.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Items of Intelligence.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>American Negroes for Africa.&#8212;Dr. Blyden, of Monrovia, Liberia,
according to Goldthwaite's Geographical Magazine, believes the problem
of the reclamation of Africa is to be solved through the agency of the civilized 
Negroes of America. In a reception tendered him at Lagos, Africa,
this able and highly-educated member of the Negro race remarked:
"To restore to their homes those who have been transported from the
land of their origin by wickedness and greed of gain should be considered
the highest duty of every Englishman, and I am happy to know that some
decided steps have been taken to bring about this much-desired result."

<pb xml:id="p124" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0066.002"/>

Dr. Blyden says tropical Africa can not possibly be made the permanent
home of white men. Even if they live there a few years they are ultimately 
compelled to leave the country. Their children born there are
apt to be weak and sickly, and the white race can not maintain its vigor
and activity in those regions. The colored people of the States and of
Brazil, he thinks, would be the only best instruments for civilizing Africa.
For about a year steamers have been plying between Bahia and Lagos,
repatriating many former slaves from Brazil.</p>

<p>The Brussels' Agreement.&#8212;June 25 the French Chamber of Deputies,
by a vote of 439 to 104, refused to ratify the Brussels' agreement with reference 
to the suppression of the slave and liquor traffics in Africa. The
Minister of Foreign Affairs and others urged the Chamber to accept the
agreement, the Minister declaring truthfully that it was a question "of a
work done absolutely in the interests of civilization." He affirmed that
the "whole world has desired to contribute something of its generosity
and power to the destruction of this horrible leprosy of slavery." But
many members of the Chamber took offence at the provisions of the
agreement in reference to the right of search by English ships, a point
which has always been a sore one with the French, and one which in generations 
before this has stood in the way of diplomatic efforts for the suppression 
of the slave trade. On this ground the strong vote was obtained
against the ratification of the agreement. We greatly fear that this
action will not only prevent its ratification by other nations, but will
altogether hinder further attempts at united action for the suppression of
the two giant evils which threaten the welfare of Africa.</p>

<p>Great Britain and Portugal in Africa.&#8212;The Portuguese Cortes
having confirmed the draft of the treaty made between Great Britain and
Portugal relative to the boundaries between the territories of the two
nations in Southeastern Africa, the treaty was signed at Lisbon on June
12. By the twelfth article of this new treaty the navigation of the Zambesi 
and the Shiré, including all their branches and outlets, is made entirely 
free for the ships of all nations, and the Portuguese Government
"engages to permit and facilitate transit for all persons and goods of every
description over the waterways of the Zambesi, the Shiré, the Pungwe,
the Busi, the Limpopo, the Sabi, and their tributaries, and also over the
landways which supply means of communication where these rivers are
not navigable." This treaty was passed in the Cortes by a vote of 105
against 6, thus settling apparently a dispute which threatened to be serious
and in such a way as to facilitate the opening of the rich and vast regions.
of South Africa. Free transit through the Zambesi, Shiré, and the Pungwe
will afford all the opportunities that English and American missions may
need for the entrance of missionaries into this portion of the "Dark <sic>Contiment</sic>."</p>

<pb xml:id="p125" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0066.003"/>

<p>Translation of the Bible by a Former Slave.&#8212;At the late anniversary 
of the American Bible Society Rev. Dr. Storrs said: "I hold in
my hand now a translation in the Sheetswa dialect&#8212;I am perfectly bold
in pronouncing that name 'Sheetswa,' because there is only one man in
the room who can correct me if I am wrong, and he is so kind that I know
he will not&#8212;in South Africa, translated by a missionary of the American
Board, Rev. Mr. Ousley, who was himself born a slave, the slave of the
brother of Jefferson Davis. He was set free by the emancipation edict
of President Lincoln, and then determined to get an, education and fit himself 
to administer the gospel at home or abroad. His wife was educated,
like himself, at Oberlin. They are exceedingly intelligent and energetic
Christian people, of sound sense, of great enthusiasm, and are stationed in
East Africa, under the American Board, and it is his translation which I
hold in my hand, just finished to-day&#8212;the translation of the first three
gospels, Matthew, Mark, and Luke. The rest of the Scriptures are going
On to be translated."</p>

<p>The Southern Presbyterian Church has just opened a new station 
in the Congo Free State. The point selected is Boleke, on the Kassai
river, the great southern tributary of the Congo, about a hundred miles
above its junction with the Congo. Boleke is distant from the mouth of
the Congo about 46o miles, 16o of which is overland travel. Two missionaries, 
Messrs. Lapsley and Sheppard, have already reached this remote
out-post and begun their difficult work, and they will be joined this
summer by Mr. Adamson, a mechanic who has already seen service on
the Congo.</p>

<p>"Armed Brethren of the Sahara."&#8212;After a season of preparatory
training, the first section of Cardinal Lavigerie's "Armed Brethren of the
Sahara," or "Templars," as they may very properly be called, have been
solemnly dedicated to their anti-slavery work at Biskra, an oasis on the
borders of the great African desert. At their head is the Viscomte de
Brissac, who after a wild career in Paris became a zealous and devoted son
of the Roman Catholic Church. With him there are, at present, twelve
others, all of whom, like their leader, have bound themselves to remain
celibates, and in their present work for a period not less than five years,
That work is to be the cultivation of dates and palms on the desert oases,
and the opening and defense there of asylums for fugitive slaves escaping
from the slave-trading caravans which are constantly crossing the desert.
This work of course embraces a suitable care for the sick and wounded,
their security in some way from violent seizure, and their earliest possible
transportation to a more secure refuge. This first establishment will, if
the proposed work proves successful, be succeeded by others on desert oases,
or on the borders of the desert. It certainly is a noble work. How these

<pb xml:id="p126" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0066.004"/>

refugees are to be protected against the attacks of hostile slave caravans
we can not see, unless we can find a solution of the problem, and we
probably can, in the fact that these model Templars are all Frenchmen
who will find their protection finder the French flag.</p>

<p>The Gaboon Mission and the French.&#8212;The <hi rend="italics">Journal des Missions
Evangéliques</hi> for July contains the full report of the young missionary
explorers, Messrs. Teissères and Allegret, as to the-projected new mission
to the French Congo. In conclusion they recommend: (1) The acceptance 
of the Gaboon mission now offered by the American Presbyterian
Board to the French Society. This offer is occasioned by the demand of the
French authorities, in whose territory the Gaboon mission is situated,
that all teaching shall be in the French language. (2) That the Gaboon
mission, thus acquired, should become the base of missionary labor among
the interior tribes bordering upon the river Ogowe, which takes its
rise hundreds of miles inland. The directorate of the Société des Missions
assents to these conclusions, but refers the matter to the French Protestant 
churches. No new work can be undertaken without a great advance
in their contributions.</p>

<p>A Steamer for the Congo.&#8212;The fleet of vessels on the upper
river is to receive an addition in the <hi rend="italics">Goodwill</hi>, a steamer built for the
Congo mission of the English Baptist Society. The vessel which has
been in use since 1882, the <hi rend="italics">Peace</hi>, has rendered invaluable service, but is
not large enough nor swift enough for present purposes. The new vessel,
the <hi rend="italics">Goodwill</hi>, is to be 84 feet long and 13 feet beam. Every particle of
the vessel, hull, boilers, engines, and all, will have to be carried on men's
shoulders some 230 miles over a very hilly road. The <hi rend="italics">Herald</hi> of the Baptist 
Society reports that their work extends more than goo miles from
the base at Leopoldville. As yet more than 1,000 miles of the waterway.
of the Congo valley have never been visited by a missionary, and 2,000
miles have been traversed very hurriedly, so that there is a great work for
these missionary vessels to do.</p>

<p>German-African Association.&#8212;One of the most powerful private
associations to which the recent anti-slavery movement has given birth is
the African Association of German Catholics. <hi rend="italics">L'Afrique</hi> reports that
this Association holds many public meetings in different cities, publishes
a journal&#8212;<hi rend="italics">God will es</hi>&#8212;and has 10 diocesan committees, comprising 1,500
circles and about 200,000 members. The central council at Cologne has
received more than $130,000 in money. This to be spent in African expeditions, 
in founding safe retreats for threatened Negroes, in missions
orphan houses, etc., all over the German African possessions. Six thousand 
dollars have been given to aid in the transport of the first German,
steamer for the Victoria Nyanza.</p>

<!-- START ADDING PAGES HERE -->

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
