<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1265">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, April 4, 1899</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Byrd, Samantha" xml:id="slb">Samantha Byrd</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1265</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Owen L. W. Smith to David J. Hill, April 4, 1899</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 6</biblScope>
<date when="1899-04-04">April 4, 1899</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Resistance</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Adams, A. J.</term>
<term>Ashton</term><!--Superintendent-->
<term>Barclay, Arthur</term>
<term>Barsingbi</term>
<term>Cox</term><!--Representative-->
<term>Dennis</term><!--Senator-->
<term>Dossen</term><!--Associate Justice-->
<term>Early, I. H.</term>
<term>Gibson</term><!--General-->
<term>Howard, J. A.</term>
<term>Howard, J. W.</term>
<term>Koch</term>
<term>Montgomery, R. H.</term>
<term>Moore, H. J.</term>
<term>Morris, J. W.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61981404">Puttkamer, Jesko von, 1855-1917</term>
<term>Stevens, J. C.</term>
<term>Tuah, Parkler</term>
<term>Russ, H. C.</term>
<term>Williams</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Coast Castle (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>German Cameroons</term>
<term>Half Cavalla (Liberia)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Britain</term>
<term>Germany</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Grebo</term>
<term>Graway</term>
<term>Gola</term>

<term>Doblee</term>
<term>Mandingo</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smith, Owen L. W.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Minister Resident and Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1899-04-04"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5692608">Hill, David Jayne, 1850-1932</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1899-05-06"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-09" who="#kln">Review and edits.</change>
<change when="2022-10-28" who="#slb">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-3021.jpg"/>

<note>Index Bureau Dept of State Rec'd May 6 '99</note>

<p>No. 26, Consular Series.<lb/>
Legation of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia Liberia,<lb/>
April 4, 1899.</p>

<p>Owen L. W. Smith,<lb/>
To<lb/>
Hon. David J. Hill,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington.</p>

<p>Subject.</p>

<p>Expenses to and from Cape
Coast Castle, Consular Agency;
and residential occupancy,
of port of Legation.</p>

<p>Synopsis.</p>

<p>Charged $130.98, expenses to and
from Cape Coast Castle Agency,
as Contingent Expenses.
Occupies 6 of 11 rooms as
resident for Ministers' family.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3022.jpg"/>

<p>No. 26 Consular Series<lb/>
Legation of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia Liberia,<lb/>
April 4, 1899</p>

<p>Hon. David J. Hill,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge
the receipt of
your No. 17, Consular, of Feb'y
27, 1899, informing me
that the Department did
not demand a personal
visitation to the Cape Coast
Castle, Consular Agency,
and could not, therefore,
pay my expenses to and
from the said Agency, but
would charge the amount
$130.98, to me as Contingent
Expenses, for 1899.
Your dispatch reached
me, April 3, 1899, too late
<catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll6-3023.jpg"/>

to be reported in my Contingent
Expenses report for the
quarter ending Mar. 31, 1899, but
will be so reported in my
report for the quarter ending
June 30, 1899. In reply I
assure you that I have no
disposition to object to whatever
the Department may
think proper in the premise.
Though I did not have a
direct order to visit the Agency,
yet a repeated demand to
show cause why the Agency
should not be discontinued
led me to believe that I
should use every possible
effort to ascertain the true
condition of the affairs of the
Agency. I had written several
times, endeavoring to obtain
the desired information,
but had, in every instant,
fell short of my desire; hence,
I saw no other remedy
<catchwords>than</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll6-3024.jpg"/>

than to go. Yet, if in the judgment
of the Department, I have
transcended the limits of my
authority, I am willing, as
stated in my dispatch of
January 6, 1899, to have same
charged to my account, for
Contingent Expenses.</p>

<p>Relative to the premisses and
rent of the Legation; the building
has 4 rooms, each on
the first and second floors,
and 3 rooms in the attic or
third floor. On the first floor,
2 rooms are occupied as
offices, and 1 as a bed room
for Messenger, as watchman.
On the third or attic floor, 1
room is used as flag room,
while a second on same
floor is used as general
store room &amp;c.</p>

<p>I occupy 1 back room,
on the first floor, 4 rooms
on the second floor and
<catchwords>one</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll6-3025.jpg"/>

one room in the attic or third
floor. You ask what proportion
of the rent I am willing
to pay? At first sight it would
appear that I ought, at least,
to pay one half; but when it
is considered that my living
in the building is a protection
to the property of the Legation
against thieves; as the premises
have been entered twice by
thieves since we have occupied
it; but in each instant have
failed to reach the Archives or
offices; they did succeed in
carrying away effects of my own;
besides making several attempts
to enter the offices, during
my absence, to Cape
Coast Castle, Agency. So
determined were their
repeated attempts, that my
wife placed two guards,
upon the offices, until my
return. Hence, it may been
<catchwords>easily</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll6-3026.jpg"/>

easily, seen that even one third
of the rent, coupled with extra
services, in the protection of the
property of the Legation, would
be high. The Secretary of the
Legation, since the arrival
of his wife, pays $100.00
per annum for an 11 room
house! I am willing however,
to pay whatever, the
Department is pleased to
think proper, not exceeding
$100.00 per annum.</p>

<p>Foreign Governments and
Commercial houses pay
higher for rent, here, than
any other class of occupants.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant;<lb/>
Owen L. W. Smith,<lb/>
M. R. and C. General.</p>

<p>Inclosure.<lb/>
1 Copy President's Message
to the Legislature.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll6-3027.jpg"/>

<head type="main">Message
of the
President of Liberia
Communicated to the
Second Session of the
Twenty Sixth Legislature.</head>

<p>Monrovia.<lb/>
T. W. Howard, Printer.<lb/>
1898.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3028.jpg"/>

<div2>

<head type="main">Message</head>

<div3>

<head type="sub">Gentlemen of the Senate and House of Representatives.</head>

<p>In obedience to the fundamental law of the State we have
again assembled to transact business for the general good of the
nation. In entering upon the discharge of these responsibilities,
it becomes us to acknowledge with unfeigned gratitude the
Beneficent Providence who has thus far sustained us in our
national career.</p>

<p>While informing you of the condition of the State, and
attempting to recommend such measures as in my opinion may
be necessary for your consideration, it is with deep sorrow that
I have to refer to the loss which the country has sustained since
your last session, in the death of several valuable citizens who
filled important positions in the service of the Government.
The late Honorables Judge H. C. Russ, Senator J. W. Morris,
and R. H. Montgomery have passed away leaving a fair record
of faithful service to the State. Several others who were filling
minor positions in the Government, some of whom had just entered
upon the stage of public life and gave promise of usefulness
have also been carried away by death. Among these may
be mentioned the names of J. W. Howard, I. H. Early, A. J.
Adams and J. A. Howard.</p>

</div3>

<div3>

<head type="sub">Foreign Relations.</head>

<p>I am exceedingly gratified to be able to inform you that our
Relations with Foreign Powers continue on a most friendly basis–
a condition of affairs that we cannot too highly appreciate
in view of the state of the civilized world at the present moment.</p>

<p>The sad massacre which took place in Sierra-Leone some
months ago, during which many valuable lives of harmless
missionaries and peaceful citizens of Her Britannic Majesty's Government
were exposed to brutal outrages, afforded me an opportunity
of returning in a small measure, some of the acts of kindness
of that nation to this, by giving aid and protection to
certain distressed refugees from that colony, which was promptly
done. Her Majesty's Government lost no time in expressing
their appreciation of the services so rendered.</p>

</div3>

<pb n="Roll6-3029.jpg"/>

<div3>

<head type="sub">Aboriginal Difficulties.</head>

<p>There have been troubles this year among some of our
Interior tribes which have engaged the attention of the
Government. In accordance with the Resolution passed
at your session in February last authorizing the President
to put on foot a military force for the purpose of
bringing into subjection two rebellious chiefs Barsingbi and
Parkler Tuah, I sent a company of men out on the 22nd of that
month. Captain Williams had no difficulty in arresting the former
of the chiefs. He was soon brought in and is now in
perfect submission to the laws of the Republic. I found it necessary
to impose a fine on him to cover the expense of his capture.</p>

<p>On the 8th of March of the present year, I embarked for
Cape Palmas in company with three members of my Cabinet
Messrs. A. Barclay, H. J. Moore and J. C. Stevens, to adjust
certain matters at that place, chiefly that which is known as the
"Koch difficulty," and which had been the cause of the visit of
the governor of Cameroons here in January. According to an
arrangement with Governor Von Putt Kamer representing the
German Imperial Government, I visited this place in person, in
order to ascertain what damage had been sustained by the German
subject Koch, and to see that his losses be made good. Unfortunately,
Mr. Koch was ill and just about to embark for home.
His agent however came to see me, and assured me that he 
was in the quiet possession of the disputed property, and was
pursuing without any obstruction his agricultural and mercantile
operations. I informed him that I had come down to ascertain to
what extent the firm had sustained damages from the natives
who were charged with disputing their claim to the land upon
which they were operating and to have the matter duly
investigated according to the laws of the Republic. He said that
no instructions had been left with him on that subject, and
therefore declined to assume any responsibility. Finding that
nothing further could be done in this matter I proceeded to look
after other affairs in the county. I had several interviews with
the citizens, explained the objects and policies of the Administration,
and especially its Interior policy, which I was glad
to note was well received. Just about this time I was
invited to meet a gathering of the civilized Greboes of
Cape Palmas in the Rock School house who presented a very
interesting paper emphasizing their allegiance to Government,
with a renewed determination not only to defend and protect
the Constitution and laws of the Republic, but also to work for
the spreading of the Gospel and to do all within their power to
induce their less informed Brethren to join with them. They
declared it to be their intention never to rebel again against the
Government, and to exert their influence to the utmost to prevent
their less civilized brethren from ever taking up arms
against each other.</p>

<p>I availed myself of this occasion to visit Half Cavalla which is
inhabited by a section of Greboes who had just been brought

<pb n="Roll6-3030.jpg"/>

into subjection after maintaining a rebellious attitude for ten
years. Superintendent Ashton, Senator Dennis, Associate Justice
Dossen, Representative Cox, and General Gibson, together with
several other citizens accompanied us on this trip.</p>

<p>We were received by the Chiefs and Headmen in a most
friendly manner and sumptuously entertained. A perfectly loyal
sentiment seems to pervade the tribe.</p>

<p>Returning from Half Cavalla I had an interview with the
Graway people who also accorded us a fine reception and gave
reiterated assurances of continued loyalty.</p>

<p>Returning from Cape Palmas I lost not time in making
arrangements to restore order in the Golah country growing out of
the rebellious tendency of certain chiefs in that section. I organized
a Commission consisting of the Secretary of the Interior,
Senator Jackson, Rev. June Moore, Hon. Supt. Sims Rev. J.
S. Washington and Mr. P. R. Flowers who together with an escort
of two military companies under the command of General
Jones accompanied me on what we hoped would prove a peaceful
mission. It was our object to convene certain tribes, settle
amicably their difficulties, and thus open the road for the ingress
of trade from the interior. At first our mission proved quite
successful. Further out however we were attacked by one Doblee
which led to an engagement and the destruction of his towns.
He escaped but has since been captured and is now a prisoner.</p>

<p>There is still a chief, Parklah Tuah who maintains a <sic>rebellions</sic>
attitude, and whom it is necessary to subdue before the interior
of this county can be considered in a healthy condition for
trade and travel. To accomplish this, I have passed nearly six
months away from the capital, during which time a great deal
has been effected in establishing the prestige of the Government:
and many tribes who held a rather indifferent position toward
the Government have signed papers declaring their allegiance
to the authority and laws of the State. The time that I have
passed in the country in efforts to settle differences, and opening
up roads, has not been wasted. While it is true that all
has not yet been effected. And if the efforts already made he followed
up, there can be no question as to the advantages that must 
accrue to the country. It is admitted that the wealth of the
country is in the interior, and that a great trade in gold-dust,
ivory, rice and cattle, would soon find its way to the coast
markets upon the establishment of safe means of travel.</p>

<p>Tribal jealousies and a spirit of rivalry between sections of
the Golah and Mandingo people, seem to lie at the root of the
disturbances that have hindered the trade for the last several
years.</p>

<p>To remove these hindrances is the purpose of the Government
in the present effort. And I am pleased to observe that
some of the most prominent citizens in the Interior Settlements
have emphasized their appreciation of this object by tendering
not only their services but also their means towards its accomplishment.

<pb n="Roll6-3031.jpg"/>

Among these I have to mention the dames of Senator
Jackson, Rev. June Moore, Mr. Solomon Hill, Mr Vander
Miller and others to say nothing of the patriotic spirit
manifested by the good Ladies of the Settlement of Arthington in
making liberal voluntary contributions of provisions and luxuries
for Major Bracewell and his detachment from that place.</p>

<p>In fact the determined policy of the Government to open
the roads to the Interior and to restore and keep peace on the
public highways has, I am glad to observe the sympathy and
support of the intelligent citizens of the country generally, and
must in the end be effected notwithstanding the petty opposition
arising from political partisan considerations.</p>

<p>That the wealth of the country is in the interior, is a fact
supported by the testimony of all, both citizens and foreigners who
have traveled any distance from the coast. To gain access to the
means needed for building up the State in material prosperity,
as well as to exert a christianizing influence upon the aboriginal
tribes who are our brethren, are the cherished objects of the
Administration. And I trust that you will spare no efforts during
your deliberations in endeavoring to devise the most effectual
ways and means for the accomplishment of these objects.</p>

<p>These can be no doubt that God has special work for nations
as for individuals. If diversities of gifts, positions and social
relations lay the foundations for differences of activities and
influences as it respects individuals, why may not the same be true
with regard to masses of men in nations. I verily believe that
Liberia is a missionary government, and has been trained in a
special school of Providence for the work of leading our brethren
of the interior to the truth, and thus save them from the
iron grasp of heathenism, superstition and ignorance. This
idea has been prominent in my mind during my late efforts in
the Golah country. And whenever opportunities offered for
securing heathen children that would have been otherwise
neglected or left uncared for, I have made efforts to get and bring
them in for educational purposes. Quite a number of such youths
male and female have been placed in the boarding school, of the
Episcopal, Methodist and Baptist Missions. Others have been
placed in well regulated families that they may receive proper
training and education. More than a hundred and twenty
children are so situated.</p>

<p>It is highly necessary for the peace safety, and well being of
the tribes that they be allied to each other under the authority
of the Government; that trade routes be designated leading
from several points of our civilized settlements to the interior
markets. It is also desirable that the Government encourage
the building of native towns on the most healthy sites at reasonable
distances on said trade routes. These towns should be
occupied by at least one of the most influential chiefs, or their
legal representatives, whose duty it shall be to keep the roads
open under the direction of the Government and maintain peace
on the public highways.</p>

<pb n="Roll6-3032.jpg"/>

<p>Each of said chiefs should receive stipends from the public
revenue and have ample tracts of land reserved, for the special
use of themselves and their people which may not be drawn by
emigrants or sold by the Government. This prohibition however
should not be so construed as to prevent missionary
operations at such points from procuring grants of fifty acres of
land for church and school purposes.</p>

<p>The erection of block houses to be garrisoned with a small
police force at suitable distances apart, will be a further guarantee
for order among the tribes.</p>

</div3>

<div3>

<head type="sub">Finance<sic>,</sic></head>

<p>I am pleased to inform you that the law passed at your last
Session providing for a retrenchment of 23% upon all claims
presented by persons performing services for Government was
put into operation on the first day of April of the present year.
The expenses of the State through the execution of the said Act
have been curtailed to a very appreciable extent. There can
be no doubt that if the policy of retrenchment be persisted in
for several years, as it should be, the local debt of the country
will be very near the point of extinction.</p>

</div3>

<div3>

<head type="sub">The Loan.</head>

<p>The necessity for making an arrangement respecting the Loan
of 1871 has pressed upon the Government for many years. During
the present year the <sic>Secretry</sic> of the Treasury and the Attorney
General were sent to England where they affected an
arrangement which will be laid before you. It is to be hoped
that your Honorable Body will carefully examine the same and
if found practicable give it your sanction.</p>

</div3>

<div3>

<head type="sub">Reports.</head>

<p>The several reporting members of the Cabinet will lay before
you their reports with such recommendations as they may deem
necessary to facilitate the effectual working of their departments.
Please give the same your careful consideration, and adopt
such measures as you may consider conducive to the best interests
of the State, in which you shall have my hearty cooperation.</p>

<p>W. D. Coleman.</p>

</div3>

</div2>
    
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>