<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.1384">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter, April 25, 1882</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.1384</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from M. A. Aenmey to William Hunter</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">M-169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1882-04-25">April 25, 1882</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/818337">Garnet, Henry Highland, 1815-1882</term>
<term>Roberts, Matilda Ann</term>
<term>Travis, H. W.</term>
<term>Wiles, J. T.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Aenmey, Marianus Adrianus</persName>
<roleName>Acting U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1882-04-25"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3981158369766001460009">Hunter, William, 1805-1886</persName>
<roleName>Second Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1882-06-02"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-02" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3023.jpg"/>

<note>Department of State Received Jun 2 1882</note>

<note>No 6</note>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia April 25th 1882</p>

<p>Mr M A Aenmey to the Second <sic>Assistt</sic> Secy of State</p>

<p>Subject</p>

<p>Office rent for Legation and Consulate General of the United States</p>

<p>Synopsis</p>

<p>Moving of office, to prevent of being involved in a possible lawsuit, between the owner of the building and Administratrix of the estate of the late minister H. H. Garnet deceased. Condition of the office room.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-3024.jpg"/>

<p>Consulate General of the United States<lb/>
Monrovia, April <sic>26</sic>, 1882</p>

<p>Sir!</p>

<p>I have the honor to advise the Department that I have moved, on the 1e of April inst the office room of the <sic>US.</sic> Legation and Consulate General, to <sic>an other</sic> place; the <sic>rason</sic> for so doing, is, 1e to prevent and involving in a possible lawsuit between the owner of the building, and the administratrix of the estate of H. H. Garnet, for the rent of a dwelling house. 2e the condition of the office room.</p>

<p>The entire building above named and containing 12 rooms was, under a <sic>privat</sic> contract, rented for 2 years, for the annual sum of $300.00 to the late H. H. Garnet, binding no heirs, or Administrators or Legation in case of death or otherwise.</p>

<p>Only one room on the first floor being occupied for office, all the other rooms for family use.</p>

<p>The owner of the house <sic>afther</sic> the death of minister Garnet, keep the Estate responsible for the rent, which estate, seems not willing to pay, and therefore the whole family has left the house, carrying all the furniture etc. and now occupying a house on the St Pauls River <catchwords>the</catchwords>

<fw type="address">The Honble Second Assist Secy of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-3025.jpg"/>

the office room being in a <sic>verry</sic> declined state and the house now entirely unoccupied, for the safety of the archives and furniture, I concluded to move the office to a place where the same is direct under my control, day and night, and also situated in the center of the city.</p>

<p>I have offered to pay for office rent during the quarter ending 31e of march, the amount of $30.00 but refused strictly the pay one cent more, as the contract did not bind the Legation for any time. this offer first being accepted, seems <sic>afther</sic> to have been abandoned, as <sic>nither</sic> owner nor administratrix have called on this office use to date for any payment.</p>

<p>for better satisfaction of the Department, I sent enclosed a true copy of the contract</p>

<p>With renewed sentiments of esteem<lb/>
I am sir your obedt servt<lb/>
M. A. Aenmey,<lb/>
actg Consul General</p>

<p>Enclosure</p>

<p>1. Copy of Contract between Matilda Ann Roberts and the Honble H H Garnet</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-3026.jpg"/>

<note>Copy</note>

<p>The articles of Agreement made and entered into the first day of January A.D. eighteen hundred and eighty two, between Matilda Ann Roberts of the City of Monrovia, Montsurado County, in the Republic of Liberia, of the first part, and the Hon Henry Highland Garnet Minister Resident and Consul General of the United States of America, to Liberia residing in the City, County and Republic aforesaid, of the Second part, witnesseth that Matilda Ann Roberts, party of the first part, for and in consideration of three hundred dollars ($300.00) pr annum, <sic>lawfull</sic> money of the United States of America, to be paid to the party of the first, by the aforenamed Henry Highland Garnet Minister Resident and Consul General of the United States of America, party of the second part, the aforenamed party of the first part doth rent and let out, unto the aforenamed party of the second part, all that lot of land in the City of Monrovia, known as lot No 28 together with all the buildings and <sic>appartenances</sic>, <sic>thereoff</sic> and thereto belonging, and in any wise <sic>appartaining</sic> for the space fo Two Calender years, from date hereof. And the party of the first part, further agrees to keep the fence, around the premises in good repair. And the aforenamed Henry Highland Garnet, consenting to the agreement <catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-3027.jpg"/>

of the party of the first part, hereby stipulate and bind myself to pay the said party of the first part for the use of the above named lot No 28 in the City of Monrovia together with the buildings and <sic>appartenances</sic> thereof, the sum of three hundred dollars ($300.00), <sic>lawfull</sic> money of the United States of America, pr annum, and that I will make said payment in advance quarterly and allowing <sic>rasonable</sic> use and ware of the dwelling house and outerbuildings, will at the expiration of this agreement return the premises in like good order and condition as they are now, when I <sic>enters</sic> upon and into them</p>

<p>In witness where of we <sic>here unto</sic> set our hands in duplicate the day and year first above written</p>
<p>(Signed) M. A Roberts<lb/>
(Signed) Henry Highland Garnet</p>

<p>Witnesses<lb/>
(Signed) H. W. Travis<lb/>
(Signed) J. T. Wiles</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>