<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME" xml:id="INITIALS"><!-- FULL NAME --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionary Activity</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KS"><!-- Corrections, marked up. --></change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">
   
<div2 type="titles">
   
</div2>

<div2 type="article">
              <head>FACTS ABOUT AFRICA AND THE AFRICAN NEGRO.</head>
                       <byline>By the Editor.</byline>
   <p>The <hi rend="italic">Teda</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tibbu</hi>, found in the <geogName>Sahara Desert</geogName>, north of Lake
               Tshad.
<!--"Negro Tribes." This was in its own bubble on the text. What do I do with it? --> Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Wadai</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Baghirmi</hi>,  found east
             of <geogName>Lake Tshad</geogName>.
   <sic>Indabitants</sic> of <hi rend="italic">Bornu</hi>, mixed with Imoshagh and Arabs.
   Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Sokoto</hi>, called <hi rend="italic">Housa</hi>, between <geogName>Lake Tshad</geogName> and <geogName>Niger River</geogName>. 
(These are said to be the most promising nation of <placeName>the
 <fw>     5</fw>
<fw>454                           MISCELLANEOUS</fw>
Sudan</placeName>, whose language persists even against the Arab and English
tongues.
   Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Upper Guinea</placeName></hi>, mostly heathen.
   The <hi rend="italic">Wolofs</hi> of <hi rend="italic">French Senegambia</hi>, near St. Louis. <!-- The region right?-->
   The <hi rend="italic">Susu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Temne</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mende</hi>, around <country>Sierra Leone</country>.
   The <hi rend="italic">Vai</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Krumen</hi>, around <country>Liberia</country>.
   The <hi rend="italic">Ephe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ga</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Tshi</hi>, including  people of <hi rend="italic">Asante</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dahome,</hi> on the <placeName>Gold and Slave Coast</placeName>.
   The <hi rend="italic">Yariba</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Nupe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ibo</hi>,and <hi rend="italic">Efik</hi>, in the <placeName>Lower Niger-basin</placeName>.
   The Moluas, Barua, Baluba, Bashilange,  between Tanganyika,
Bangweola, and he confluence of the Lulua and Kassai.
   The Ma-iaka, Northern Mbamba, Butna, Mbete, Tsaia, Ba teke.
   The Mpongive, Fang, Benga, in French Kongo.
   The Kongo Nation, including the Luaugu, Buende, Sundi, So-
longo, Ndembu, Hungu, Pangu.
   The Ovi-mbundu, Ma-kioko, Ambuella, in the highlands of An-
gola and about the headwaters of the Zambesi.
   The Ova-hereto, in German South Africa.
   The Barotse in the Upper Zambesi valley.
   The Zulus, Kaffir, Bechuana, Batonga, Metabele, Bashona, Ba-
nyai, south of the Zambesi.
   The Makua, including the Lornoe,-Metu, Angoche, in Portuguese
Mozambique.
   The Wa-yao, Makonie, Manganga, around Lake Nyassa.
   The Wa Zaramo, Wa-Zaguha, Wa-Sa^ara, Wa-Gogo, Wa-
Hehe, Wa-Nyamwezi, of German East Africa.</p>
   <p>This showing of tribes and nations, while not perfect, sets forth
the best knowledge we have of the real Negro peoples of Africa. It
should be remembered that we have, in this list, rejected all Hamites,
not Negro, such as the white Hamites along the Mediterranean coast
of North Africa, the mixed people (brown) of the Sudan, the Malay
of Madagascar, the Hottentots of South Africa, the Bushmen, and
the Pygmies.</p>

<p>One would suppose that in all this multiplicity of tribes there would
                  be a hopeless tangle of unrelated tongues, the de-
Negro Languages.  spair of grammarians and philologists, but it has
                  been shown that many widely separated  tribes
may be classified into two: the Bantu, or Negroes south of the Equa-

                          <fw> CHURCH REVIEW                          455</fw>
tor; and the Negroes of Upper Guinea and the Sudan, north of the
Equator; and we are even told that the distinction between them is a
myth, the chief difference between them being traceable to the difference 
in amount of contact with foreign influence on the part of the
two. The Negroes north of the Equator show traces in their language
of the Bantu root origin, but this is so overlaid with a mass of new
language-growths as to be difficult of discernment, while all the 180
languages and 60 dialects of the Bantu south of the Equator are resolvable 
into very few languages, possibly only one, and many dialects 
If it be found, as is strongly suspected, that the original language 
of the tribes north of the Equator be referable to the same
root stock, we shall see this formidable tangle of tongues that has
seemed to erect almost insuperable obstacles to successful missionary
effort, and to forbid the building of a written language and literature,
melt away, leaving the future to point to one great homogeneous people 
in all Central Africa, speaking and writing the same virile language.</p>
   <p>The world has always had great difficulty in understanding what
constitutes a typical Negro any way. What with general ignorance of
the uncontaminated Negro in Fatherland, and the arrogant assertions
and arrant misconceptions of prejudice-distorted American opinions, 
we have been blinding ourselves to the fact, now forcing itself
upon travelers and scholars, that beneath nearly sameness of color in
the Negro tribes, there lies a diversity of temperaments, abilities,
adaptabilities and susceptibilities as great as we have always known
existed among different branches of the Caucasian race.</p>
   <p>The Quarterly Bulletin of Gammon Seminary, to which we are
indebted for most of the facts herein, which we have arranged and
commented upon in our own way, shall be allowed to conclude this
article in its own excellent words:</p>
   <p>The Bantu, or Negroes south of the equator, are in some respects
the most remarkable sections of mankind. Separated from the world
by wide oceans, virgin forests and the Sahara Desert, they have been
less than any other race, subject to foreign influences. No strange
blood has altered their physical constitution, no foreign languages
have permanently mangled the structure and the word-store of their
principal forms of speech; no outside religion has seriously affected
their conceptions of God, the spiritual, the animal and the natural
worlds Now they are receiving Christianity and the highest civilization 
the world has ever known, by methods which,  however crude,

<fw>456                            MISCELLANEOUS</fw>
inconsiderate and unjust they may appear fifty years hence, are yet
far superior to all that our most sanguine forefathers could have anticipated.</p>

   <p>All readers of the daily papers and of missionary journals have become 
familiar with the story of Uganda. The wonderful changes
which have there taken place since 1872, when the first missionary
party entered the country, and which have transformed that semi-
Pagan and semi-Mohammedan country and people into a semi-Protest-
ant and semi-Catholic Christian nation, more progressive and more
promising than some sections of the Italian. Spanish and Portuguese
nations, those changes, I say, are prophetic of what is about to happen 
among all the great Bantu nations we have passed in review.</p>
   <p>If my opinion about the future were asked. I should not hesitate
to declare my conviction that within one hundred years all Bantu land 
will contain more than 500,000,000 inhabitants, will equal Europe in 
civilization, will be united in a great United States of Central
Africa under a new and improved edition of our American Constitution, 
will both speak and write a common language, the mother-tongue of all 
Bantu dialects, as revived by scholars and enriched with
the best developments of its daughters, and will produce masterpieces 
of literature, science, and art, vying with all the best that
Europe and America will then be able to bring forth.</p>
                           <fw>   WHAT MONEY IS.</fw>
   <p>The wise man says, "Money answereth all things." This is true.
Money is a wondrous thing. In a true sense, money is yourself stored
up for future use A boy earns $10.00 per week; when he is paid
and puts the money in his pocket, he pockets a week's worth of him
self. Where he shall lose this stored self is a serious question. In
the matter of storing and losing money is like electricity. You have
your battery charged; you wish to illuminate your room; you make
your proper attachments, and lo ! the room is light. But now you
wish power; you change your attachments, and now the sewing machine 
flies. Again you wish locomotion; you change your attachments
and the trolley car runs. Once more, you wish intercommunication;
change your attachments again and you telegraph to china. Finally,
you wish to kill a man; change your attachments, seat him in the
electric chair, press the button, and he is dead. Money is much like
this. It is stored power, as we said before. It is yourself stored up,
Where shall you lose it?</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
