<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="DAWSON, KENDALL C." xml:id="KCD"><!-- KENDALL C. DAWSON --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KCD"><!-- Corrections, marked up. --></change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="10014_001.jpg"/>

<p> Belgian Legation 
in Washington,</p>
    
<p> Office of 
The Battle Creek Sanatorium
Battle Creek, Michigan,
the 14th of December 1910.</p>
    
<p>Translation-COPY.</p>
    
<p> Count Conrad of Buisseret,
Extraordinary Envoy and Minister Plenipotentiary
of S.M. the Belgian King near the United States of America.</p>

<p> Your Excellence,</p>
    
<p>Before my departure to America for Central Africa,
in the spring of this year, you asked me to let you know,
if possible, if the same grounds of complaint that I had 
still existed, in my capacity as a missionary, alleged against the administration
of the Independent State of the Congo during the reign of His Majesty the 
King Léopold II.</p>
    
<p>I now have the the great pleasure to give you a breif 
report.</p>
    
 <p> You recall that I had to travel in the company 
 of four American gentlemen who had to visit, in the
 Congo, just as many stations de missions as possible during the short lapse
of time in which they were available..</p>
    
 <p> We spent eight weeks in the Belgian Colongy 
 and visited 21 missionary establishments, where we met 
men and women of five nationaities and seven different 
protestant religious societies.</p>
    
 <p>Three of the representative missions were American.
 We crossed 800 miles sailing back up the Congo
 river, and visited certain districts where, under the ancient regime, the
 complaints against the government were of incidents relating to daily life. 
 We made the short voyage by foot and visited the villages.</p>
    
<pb></pb>    
    
<p> sunbathed natives, and certain amongst themselves were in the region that 
was formerly the theater of raids for the rubber, and where 
a lot of stories of cruelty come from that I have related in the 
pass.</p>

<p> Throughout this voyage, and in my encounters with many 
missionnairies who expressed frankly, and with des containes
of natives of which I know the idioms well, I haven't seen a 
single thing that makes me think the same of the continuation of atrocities, 
cruel or injust from the current government officers 
of State towards the natives.</p>

<p>I did not hear from, neither the whites, nor the blacks,
any illusion to a continuation of the ancient state of things in
the coloney.</p>
    
<p> But that which I heard, it's that these big changes 
have been brought in the administration, and that these changes
have introduced favorable conditions for the white 
missionaries and also for the untutored black. (untutored).</p>

<p>I cannot speak for the visited districts by us;
but in these I found that the clamor against the forced
work had ceased, thanks to the changes aready apporés to the administration.</p>
    
<p>Even the missionary's regard, it seems that the way
the governement officials act and their attitude was altered. I
believe that the Protestant missionary is no longer lookd at 
as an enemy, but more like an honest and frank friend. </p>
    
<p> By entering into these secluded villages, we found that
the natives no longer run away or hide, as if 
ils l'eussent fait il y a trois ans. La confiance dans le blanc</p>

<pb></pb>
    
<p>dans ses lois est maintenant en train d' être rétablie. Nous avons
trouvé l'indigène occupé près de sa maison. De nouvelles habitations
étaient en construction. Des jardins plus grands et plus beaux étaient
en culture. La paix règne maintenant, ainsi que la confiance, où la
guerra et le trouble règnaient autrefois. Ces changements sons dûs, sans
aucun doute, aux lois meilleures imposées au peuple par S.M. le Roi
Alber et le Parlement belge.</p>
    
<p>I am also certain, that these changes are permanent
and that the promises of another improveemnt which is  plus étendue
seront accomplies aussitôt que le mécanisme de l'Etat" pourra entreprendre
sa tâche terriblement difficile. Lorsqu'on songe aux grandes
distances qui doivent être atteintes par l'administration, et à l'absence
de facilités par télégraphe et par chemin de fer dans la plus
grande partie de la colonie, on commence à comprendre comment il doit
y avoir un certain délai. Un ordre édicté par le Gouverneur Général
à Boma peut facilement prendre six semaines, et dans certaines saisons
de l'année, au moins deux mois, pour atteindre beaucoup des postes
isolés.</p>
    
<p> It's with great interest that we visisted the agricultural 
establishment of experiments in Eala, on th Haut Congo. We were 
enchanted by the given instruction in the gardening practice and science 
to the native boys in the region.</p>
    
<p> We saw something of <unclear></unclear> in disarray, in regards 
to microbiology and the general study of tropical sicknesses 
in Léopoldville, where the <unclear>amirable</unclear> and patient doctor Broeden for 
numerous years, render splendid services to all coming.</p>
    
 <p>We visited the Boma Government schools and 
found that that which we saw <unclear></unclear> was splendid</p>
    
<pb></pb>
    
<p>beginning, full of promise for the development of the native. </p>
    
<p> We spent some time examining the stations 
of State in Banana, Boma, Matadi, Léopoldville, and Coquilhatville,
and in no way we have nothing seen that can shock, in that which 
concerns the Government. We saw a lot of things intended for
raising the natives, primarily industrial education 
given in these centers at a big number of young people.</p>
    
<p> I just learned this week from one of my friends, 
an english missonary, that a new place for a station 
was granted to his mission. That destroys one of the subjects of serious, 
high complaint so far by the protestant missionaries.</p>
    
<p> I have the great pleasure of adding that these very aggreable 
glimpses we were accorded by the Minister of Colonies 
in Brussels and by the Governor General of Congo in Boma. </p>
    
<p>Hoping that this short account of our voage and that 
what we saw and heard interessted Your Excellence, I
remain,</p>
    
<p>Your humble servant,
(Signed/Joseph Clark.</p>



</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
