<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="DAWSON, KENDALL C." xml:id="KCD"><!-- KENDALL C. DAWSON --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term></term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>French</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term></term>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KCD"><!-- Corrections, marked up. --></change>
<!-- I know Jade did stuff with this, but I don't know the extent, so I can't write credits for her.  Are there details? Scanned? Transcription? OCR? -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<pb facs="10018_001.jpg"/>

<p>Consulat Général
De 
L'État Indèpendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>
    
<p>MEMORANDUM ON THE CATHOLIC MOVEMENT IN FAVOR CONGO.</p>
    
<p>The "Congo Reform Association" has from the beginning,
made its campaign on religious lines. Its agents here are all
protestant ministers, they hold their meeting in churches and
use the societies and organizations of these churches to gather
petitions, to form committies and to carry on their propaganda.
It is they who have made it a religious war and they have been
trying to prevent the Catholic Church from realizing that they
have declared war, while they know that the organization of the
Catholic Church is the most powerful body that could oppose them.
The Church has, however, been on guard for the past two years.
In December, 1904, I was invited to attend a council of the most
important dignitaries and laics of the Church to tell them the
Congo situation and since that time they have stood ready to help
us if the necessity should arise. </p>
    
<p>We had hoped to be able to manage the campaign alone
without their open aid, and we could have done it not been
for this unfortunate Kowalski-Wack affair. The scandal created
by the publicaiton of that affair almost absolutely tied the hands
of our friends in the Senate and created a predjudice against us
in the minds of Senators who otherwise would have been indifferent
or even friendly. Our enemies, taking advantage of the moment,
were pushing the Lodge Resolution. The only thing to prevent the</p>
    
<pb></pb>
    
<p>Consulat Général
De
L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>
    
<p>2.-</p>
    
<p>adoption of that resolution was to bring some new and powerful
force to our aid, and the most powerful organization available
was our natural ally, the Church. Fortunately at that moment
our enemies made the mistake of openly attacking the Cardinal
Gibbons. That gave us an opening. The Cardinal replied to the 
attack by a strong defense of the King-Sovereign's administration.
The statement was published all over the country and immediately
had a good effect not only upon Catholics but also upon protestants,
for the Cardinal is greatly admired and respected by all
creeds. The newspapers referred to the Cardinal's utterance in
their editorials and became more cautious and conservative in regard
to intervention in the Congo. The statement had also undoubtedly 
a very favorable effect on the Government at Washington and we
have reason to believe that since that statement appeared (post
hoc ergo propter hoc) the President has taken a more favorable
attitude. There is no doubt that the President and his party pay
great heed to the opinion of the Cardinal and of the Catholic hoping
to gain the political support of the Catholic vote. </p>
    
<p>The statement of the Cardinal was not enough, however.
It motified the attitude of the Government, but according to the 
views of the most astute politicians among our friends, there was
every probability that the Lodge Resolution would be adopted by
the Senate Committee. The only card left for us to play (and it
is the card most feared by our enemies) was the influence of 
the Catholic Church.</p>
    
<p>The Catholic Church represents to the American politician 
powerful factor in the politics and a great number of votes. It is 
the only thing to offset the numerous petitions coming into the
Senate from small Baptists, Presbyterians and other churches which
also represent votes to the politician. The politician is governed
by fear of his electors. If he is petitioned by a number of his
electors from small Baptist churches to meddle with the Congo he
will be inclined to do it unless he is made aware that he will
offend other voters. We had to make him aware of this. Calling
to our aid the Catholic societies with their large membership of
American voters was our only chance to restrain the Senate from
rash action against us. It is well known in the United States
that every politician is afraid to meddle with any question which
may offend Catholic votes.</p>
    
<p>This step was thought a wise political move by our friends
here who best understand the politics of this country. Baron</p>
    
 <pb></pb>
    
<p>Consulat Général
De
L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>    
 
<p>3.-</p>
 
<p>Moncheur and I cabled what steps we were about to take and received
no objections form Brussels. I obtained the approval and 
support of the Highest dignitaries of the Church and then immediately
started to set in motion our friends of the Catholic,
Belgian and Irish societies throughout the country so that they
might protest to the American Goverment against intervention in
Congo affairs. Fortunately the Senate had adjourned for a holiday
of two weeks at Christmas. This gave me time, by travelling night
and day to cover several thousand mils of territory, to communicate
with such men as Archbishop Messmer, Bishop McFaul, Bishop
Fox, Bishop Maes, and about ten other Bishops besides laics of 
importance and also with the heads of various societies of laymen
and with other organizations.</p>
    
<p>As a result there have been placed before the President
and the Government and before the Senate (upon the reassembling
of the Senate a few days ago) petitions in our favor from individuals
and societies representing nearly two million American 
citizens urging the American Governemnt to refrain from any
interference with the Congo.</p>
    
<p>As well as I can ascertain the following petitions
representing the sentiments of nearly two million are by this time
already before the Government and Congress:</p>
    
    <p><choice><sic>Amiercan</sic><corr>American</corr></choice> Federation of Catholic Societies
    representing 1,500,000 members
    Order of Foresters representing 125,000 members
    Catholic Knights of St. Louis
    Belgian Society of Chicago
    Belgian Protective Society of Denver
    Belgian Protective Society of New York
    Belgian Union of New York
    Belgian Beneficial Society of New York
    Several Catholic Societies of Rochester, State of New York.
    Individual letters from influential citizens, bishops, laics, &amp;c.
    to the President, the Secretary of State and Senators.
    Petitions and protests from 700 or 800 citizens of Denver, New
    York, Rochester, Louisville and Philadelphia.</p>
    
    <p>This expression of sentiment in our favor is now before
    the American Governement representing nearly two million American
    citizens.</p>
    
    <p>Consulat Général
    De
    L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
    Baltimore.</p>
    
    <p>4.-</p>
    
    <p>In addition we expect that in the next few days there will
    reach the American Government the Senate petitions in our favor
    from:-</p>
    
    <p>The Federation of the State of New York
    The Federation of the County of New York
    About 40 differeny socities in New York and Brooklyn
    About 400 or 500 individual citizens of New York
    About 200 or 300 citizens of Chicago
    Ancient Order of Hibernians representing            250,000            members
    Central Verein                    "                 100,000              "
    Catholic <choice><sic>Bortherhood</sic><corr>Brotherhood</corr></choice> of American        "       65,000     "
    Catholic Knights of America         "               20,000               " 
    Western Catholic Union              "               7,000                "
    Bohemian Catholic Union             "               10,000               "
    Catholic Knights of Ladies of America "             8,000                "
    Women's Catholic Order              "               50,000               "
    Irish Catholic Union                "               10,000               "
    44 Federation Societies in 44 different States"</p>
    
<p>The above societies are expected not only to petitions in 
favor of the Congo to the President, the Secretary of State and
the Senate <choice><sic>Committe</sic><corr>Committee</corr></choice> on Foreign Affairs but also to write to the
Senators form their respective States.</p>
    
<p>This is a powerful movement we have started. It gives
us the most powerful support we can have. It will not lose us
any of our protestant supporters and it can cause no harm to any
one except to the enemies of the Congo. Our Catholic support
cannot in any way cause embarrassment to the American Government,
if that Government is well disposed toward the Congo. it is
possible that the American Government, if it wishes to meddle in
the Congo, should have preferred that we shyould not make any 
resistance or any show of strength. If the American Government is
well disposed toward us it will be glad to see us bring <choice><sic>our</sic><corr>out</corr></choice> all our
forces for this will strengthen the American Governments hand
against the anti-Congo agitators. The only real objection the
American Government could have to such a demonstration is that
(if it is illdisposed towards us) fear of the Catholic vote would
prevent it from carrying out its intention and from taking on
extremely hostile attitude towards us. </p>
    
<p>It will be observed that in all this movement I have
kept in the background and made it appear that the Catholic movement
was entirely spontaneous. </p>
    
<pb></pb>
    
<p>Consulat Général
De
L'État Indépendant Du Congo.
Baltimore.</p>
    
<p>5-</p>
    
<p>Our movement may not be entirely successful. We are working
against great odds on account of the Kowalski-Wack affair.
If we succeed it will be snatching victory out of defeat.
In any case, even if the Lodge Resolution is adopted, the fact
that we have Catholic support will undoubtedly prevent the American
Governemtn from any extremely aggressive movement which it might
wish to take.</p>
    
<p>James Gustavus Whiteley
Seventh January. </p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
