<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0012">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Fenton Johnson - The Black Fairy (1913). Analysis</title>
<author n="Nurhussein, Nadia">Nadia Nurhussein</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0012</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>A children's story, Fenton Johnson's "The Black Fairy" appeared in <hi rend="italics">The Crisis</hi> in October 1913, accompanied by a photograph of two young black girls. Johnson was then on the verge of an illustrious career as a poet; his first book of verse was published during the same year. He would go on to publish several books and have many poems included in anthologies. "The Black Fairy" was republished a few years later in <hi rend="italics">The Upward Path: A Reader for Colored Children</hi>, edited by Myron T. Pritchard and Mary White Ovington (a white co-founder of the NAACP), along with an introduction by Robert R. Moton, Principal of the Tuskegee Institute.</p> 
	
<p>The story begins with a young black girl named Annabelle reading a collection of Grimm's fairy tales and wondering if black fairies exist, as she has only read about white ones. After falling into a daydream, Annabelle is greeted by a black fairy, "Amunophis, the Lily of Ethiopia, [who] come[s] to the children of the Seventh Veil," apparently a reference to Du Bois's <hi rend="italic">The Souls of Black Folk</hi>, which calls "the Negro...a sort of seventh son, born with a veil." The young girl learns that the black fairy has lived for 5000 years beside the Niger River, where "long ago a city rested..., and from that spot black men and women ruled the world" until the destructive "barbarians from the North" came. Amunophis then projects a <hi rend="italics">tableau vivant</hi> or film of sorts depicting "the rich past of the Ethiopian" onto the water of a nearby pond: the moving images present African blacksmiths at work and the riches and sculptural art of Ghana and Benin. In a clear effort to demonstrate that African cultural elements survived transatlantic slavery, Johnson writes that the girl hears "traces of the sorrow songs in the weird pathetic strains of the African music mongers." The projected images end with representations of Africans being sold into slavery, with Amunophis leading the slave ship to America in order to serve as a guide to the new world Africans. The fairy leaves Annabelle, promising to return when "there is no longer a white civilization or a black civilization, but the civilization of all men," a utopian vision that would form the hoped-for final image in the fairy's projection.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
