<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0014">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Abyssinia (1906). Analysis</title>
<author n="Gruesser, John">John Gruesser</author>
<author n="Nurhussein, Nadia">Nadia Nurhussein</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0014</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>Bert Williams and George Walker, a famous African American blackface duo, performed in <hi rend="italics">Abyssinia</hi>, written by Jesse A. Shipp and Alex Rogers, with music by Williams and Will Marion Cook. The show toured the United States, often to sold-out crowds, featuring "a cast of over one hundred, lavish costumes and lighting effects, a manmade waterfall and wild animals." Williams and Walker played the roles of Jasmine Jenkins and Rastus Johnson, respectively, the latter of whom has won a lottery and spends his winnings traveling to Abyssinia with his friend. During their travels through the country, they are mistaken for Ethiopian royalty and find themselves in trouble, appearing before the court of Ethiopia's Emperor Menelik. Although a relatively minor character in terms of time on stage, Menelik hovers over the production; his portrait, reproduced on a coin, serves as the central image on the show's songbooks, above smaller portraits of Williams and Walker. In addition, one review of <hi rend="italics">Abyssinia</hi> called the role of Menelik in the show "the dream of the Negro actor." <hi rend="italics">Abyssinia</hi> depicts Menelik as a cruel and merciless ruler. He is shown sentencing a "rebellious chief" to death by dismemberment, after which the emperor would "feed his body to the Hyenas, as a warning to any and all who shall attempt to defy the mandates of Menelik, the second King of Kings of Ethiopia." In contrast, the younger generation of Ethiopian leaders, such as Bolasso, are depicted as modern paragons of Westernized military training. The tension between the older and younger generation can be seen from the beginning of the play, which opens with a song called "Janhoi," or emperor. (The term appears first in a prefatory glossary—more evidence of the writers' research—that defines "Abyssinian words used throughout the play").</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">– John Gruesser &amp; Nadia Nurhussein</hi></p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
