<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0021">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John Edward Bruce - The Black Sleuth (1907-1909)</title>
<author n="Gruesser, John">John Gruesser</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0021</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-01" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>Serialized in the Philadelphia-based <hi rend="italics">McGirt's Magazine</hi> from 1907 to 1909, <hi rend="italics">The Black Sleuth</hi> is an early African American detective novel by the columnist, historian, essayist, and, in his later years, officer in Marcus Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association, John Edward Bruce (1856-1924), aka Bruce-Grit.  Lacking a concluding installment, the story concerns two Yoruba brothers and has scenes set in West and South Africa, the United States, and Europe.  Bruce devotes nine of the serial's seventeen chapters to a counter-discursive African abroad plot that implicitly criticizes Booker T. Washington. It signifies on the white adventure tale set in Africa to expose the narrow-mindedness and inaccuracy of white American beliefs about people of African descent so that U.S. Blacks will embrace their ancestral heritage and forge alliances with people from the continent.  Rather than an intrepid white thrill-seeker confronting savagery and unraveling the mysteries of Africa, a brilliant and brave African student learns firsthand about racial prejudice and violence in the United States.  After studying in Maine and the U.S. South, the titular character, Sadipe Okukenu, meets and impresses a white man on a train who hires him as a detective.  Using his superior powers of deduction, he manages to solve a case involving the theft of a valuable diamond by a band of notorious thieves seemingly even before it takes place.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
