<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0018">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Edgar Rice Burroughs - Tarzan of the Apes (1914). Analysis</title>
<author n="Gruesser, John">John Gruesser</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0018</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>For centuries Africa has inspired the fantasies of Western authors, many of whom—including Edgar Rice Burroughs who produced the most influential of all, <hi rend="italics">Tarzan of the Apes</hi> (1912)—wrote about a continent they had never seen. Like Burroughs's books about Mars, the long-running and astoundingly successful Tarzan series, along with its many film adaptations, were aimed at a popular audience looking for escape. In Tarzan, Burroughs creates the ultimate "noble savage." Being orphaned in the bush as a babe allows him to live unfettered by "civilized" conventions and undertake various adventures. Meanwhile, as the scion of a titled British family, he has the breeding to become king of the jungle and avoid instinctively a whole set of taboos. Thus, having been untainted by his jungle experiences, on leaving Africa, Tarzan quickly masters all the customs of polite society and the best of modern thought while possessing superior strength and survival skills honed in the rainforest. Despite having had no human contact for over a decade and a half, the foundling Lord Greystoke, relying solely on the meager supply of adult and children books left in a cabin by his deceased parents and the image of himself he has seen in a river, learns his place in the world—not only that he is "a M-A-N" and not an ape, but also that Black people may be human beings but a different category of human being from himself. The novel's egregiously racist treatment of apes and Africans assigns all of the supposedly positive attributes of African tribespeople to the apes that raise Tarzan and all the savage and nightmarish characteristics which white fiction attributes to Africans to Tarzan's Black neighbors.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">– John Gruesser</hi></p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
