<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0003">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John A. Kasson, The Congo Conference and the President's Message (1886). Analysis</title>
<author n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0003</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>

<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10-14" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2019-03-21" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-08-05" who="#kln">Edited for new TEI and file naming structures.</change>
<change when="2014-05-05" who="#kln">Edited for new TEI and file naming structures.</change>
<change when="2014-03" who="#kln">Revised earlier version of transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>
<div1 type="analysis">

<div2 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Article Analysis</head>

<p>John A. Kasson held diplomatic posts as U.S. Ambassador to Austria-Hungary from 1877-1881 and to the German Empire from 1884–1885. It was during this latter assignment, that he attended the Berlin Conference (a.k.a. the <hi rend="italics">Kongokonferenz</hi>) of 1884-85 and subsequently persuaded the United States to recognize the sovereignty of the Congo Free State and to ratify the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref>. Kasson proved successful in the first endeavor, but failed to convince President Cleveland to present the treaty to the Senate for ratification.</p>
    
<p>The purpose of Kasson's 1886 article was to convince readers of the necessity for the U.S. Senate to ratify the General Act by the April 1886 deadline. The article opens with a summary of President Cleveland's address in which the president explained his objection to bringing the Act before the Senate based on his belief that the U.S. held "no established interests or control" in the "remote valley of the Congo." Kasson then lays out a detailed summary of what transpired at the conference and the obligations outlined in the Act, emphasizing that the Act does not obligate the United States to commit troops to enforcing freedom of navigation of the Niger and Congo Rivers and free trade in the Congo Basin&#8212;the latter a claim made by the State Department. Kasson concludes that in the interest of promoting Christianity, civilization, and commerce in the Congo region, the United States should either ratify the Act or accept it "as a 'separate act' for which it makes provision."<ref type="footnote" target="n00.01">1</ref></p> 

<p>Kasson was among the few public American voices that encouraged the United States to ratify the General Act of the Berlin Conference. As the article makes clear, the State Department and the President feared that ratifying the Act would bound the country to intervening in foreign conflicts in foreign colonial possessions where the U.S. held no strategic, commercial, or diplomatic interest. Despite the fact that the country was engaged in its own expansion across the continent and overseas in the late nineteenth century (i.e., the "new imperialism"), many U.S. politicians advocated an isolationist foreign policy, with some exceptions made for affairs in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
    
<p>In contrast, Kasson was an expansionist who believed that the United States should abandon the Monroe Doctrine and pursue territories abroad. Kasson played an active role in the conference, persuading the delegates to adopt British explorer Henry Morton Stanley's boundaries for delineating the Congo Basin. He also encouraged the European powers to respect the rights of Africans and African rulers in deciding if and when to cede their land. Kasson's plea for ratification of the Act constituted one important current in the American discourse on the Africa Question which focused on the potential commercial and economic benefits of the agreement for the United States.<ref type="footnote" target="n00.02">2</ref></p>

</div2>


<div2 type="excerpts">

<head type="main">Excerpt Analysis</head>

<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0012.e001">

<p>Kasson lays out the boundaries of the regions covered by the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference,</ref> underscoring the commitment of the signatories to insuring freedom of commerce in the Congo Basin, as well as on the Congo River and all its tributaries to the east as far as Lake Tanganyika and the Indian Ocean and westward to the Atlantic Ocean. In addition, he explains that the Niger and Congo Rivers, their tributaries, and any canals or railroads leading to them, are subject to freedom of navigation in times of war and peace.</p>

</div3>

<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0012.e002">

<p>Kasson lays out the boundaries of the regions covered by the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference,</ref> underscoring the commitment of the signatories to insuring freedom of commerce in the Congo Basin, as well as on the Congo River and all its tributaries to the east as far as Lake Tanganyika and the Indian Ocean and westward to the Atlantic Ocean. In addition, he explains that the Niger and Congo Rivers, their tributaries, and any canals or railroads leading to them, are subject to freedom of navigation in times of war and peace.</p>

</div3>


</div2>

</div1>

</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<note xml:id="n00.01">1. John A. Kasson, &#8220;The Congo Conference and the President's Message,&#8221; <hi rend="italics">The North American Review</hi> vol. 142, no. 351 (February 1886), 120, 133.</note>
<note xml:id="n00.02">2. George Shepperson, "Aspects of American Interest in the Berlin Conference" in Stig Förster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 286-288; P. Duigan, "The Role of the USA" in <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa</hi>, 302. See Edward Younger, <hi rend="italics">John A. Kasson: Politics and Diplomacy from Lincoln to McKinley</hi> (Iowa City: State Historical Society of Iowa, 1955).</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>
</TEI>