<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0007">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Pauline E. Hopkins - Of One Blood. Or, The Hidden Self. (1902-1903). Analysis</title>
<author n="Gruesser, John">John Gruesser</author>
<author n="Nurhussein, Nadia">Nadia Nurhussein</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0007</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>Published serially in <hi rend="italics">The Colored American Magazine</hi> between 1902 and 1903, Pauline E. Hopkins's Ethiopianist novel <hi rend="italics">Of One Blood; or, The Hidden Self</hi> tells the story of Reuel Briggs, a brilliant black Harvard medical student who, fearing discrimination, attempts to pass as white. His duplicitous friend (and secret rival for the affections of the beautiful Dianthe Lusk), Aubrey Livingston, uncovers the truth about Reuel's racial identity and encourages him to apply for a position with an archeological expedition in Meroe. While engaged in this expedition, Reuel discovers a hidden city and learns from its inhabitants that he descends from the royal line of Meroe. This regal lineage is the purported source of Reuel's innate mystical abilities, which he has further developed through scientific study; early in the novel, he re-animates a seemingly dead Dianthe through mesmerism, which he presents to his skeptical medical colleagues as a scientific breakthrough rather than mystical miracle. During Reuel's time in Africa, he receives word that Dianthe (whom he married before leaving the United States) has died, but in fact Aubrey has, through subterfuge and mesmerism, manipulated Dianthe into living with him as his wife. Dianthe, too, appears to have mystical abilities, as her spectral being calls out to Reuel for help. Reuel learns of Aubrey's misdeeds and returns to the United States. Finding Dianthe near death&#8212;the victim of a poison she had intended for Aubrey&#8212;Reuel returns to Africa to reign over his new kingdom.</p>

<p>It is revealed toward the end of the novel that Reuel, Dianthe, and Aubrey are "of one blood" (i.e., siblings). Hopkins explores the various meanings of this Biblical phrase (from Acts 17:26: "Of one blood I made all nations of man to dwell upon the whole face of the earth") here and in other writing. In this novel, she uses the shocking trope of incest to emphasize the blood ties linking white and black Americans, black Americans and Africans, and all races in general.</p> 
	
<p>Written only a few years after the Battle of Adwa between Italy and Abyssinia, Hopkins's novel may have been influenced by relatively recent news about a black nation defeating a white one. Hopkins's descriptions of Telassar alternate between elements of the ancient Aksumite empire (in modern-day Ethiopia, or Abyssinia in Hopkins's time) and the ancient Kush empire (in modern-day Sudan). For instance, the writing Reuel encounters in Telassar resembles Ge'ez (Ethiopic) more closely than it does Meroitic script, but Reuel is welcomed by the inhabitants of Telassar as the reincarnation of Ergamenes, a celebrated king of the Kush empire. This mingling of elements from various African civilizations reflects the general cultural ambiguity surrounding the term "Ethiopia."</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
