<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0017">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sutton E. Griggs - The Hindered Hand; Or, the Reign of the Repressionist (1905). Analysis</title>
<author n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0017</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Analysis</head>

<p>Published in three distinct versions in 1905 and 1906, Sutton E. Griggs's fourth novel and the second to feature Africans and Africa, <hi rend="italics">The Hindered Hand; Or, the Reign of the Repressionist</hi>, was issued by his own Nashville-based Orion Publishing Company. In <hi rend="italics">Unfettered</hi> (1902), untold African wealth enables the protagonist, Dorlan Warthell, to finance his successful plan for solving the race problem in the United States. Significantly less sanguine about what the future holds for African Americans than its predecessor, <hi rend="italics">The Hindered Hand</hi> includes scenes set in Liberia where Ensal Ellwood, one of the two main male characters, works for several months. At its conclusion, the story depicts the West African nation as a possible refuge for Blacks in the United States, a place to which they can escape from the horrors and frustrations of American racial politics, should this prove necessary. As Griggs himself acknowledges in material appended to the novel, which includes references to "Backward Africa," he uses the continent less as a real place than as a device to further a plot otherwise devoted to U.S. race relations that grapples with topics including racial passing, lynching, African American armed violence, and discriminatory justice.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
