<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME"><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title><!-- Includes Author, Journal Name, Article Title. EXAMPLE: D. Augustus Straker, New York Freeman, "The Land of Our Fathers"--></title>
<!-- NOTE: If there is no author, just use the publication name. EXAMPLE: New York Times, "The Congo Free State" -->
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="KS"><!-- Kayla Schirf --></name>
<!--EXAMPLE: <name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>-->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"><!--FILE NAME--></idno><!-- EXAMPLE: teaa.mis.001.01.xml -->
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main"><!-- ARTICLE TITLE --></title>
<author n="LAST NAME, FIRST NAME"><!-- FULL NAME --></author><!-- If no author, delete this line. -->
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope type="vol"><!-- VOLUME NUMBER --></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"><!-- ISSUE NUMBER --></biblScope>
<date when="1000"><!-- MONTH AND YEAR OF PUBLICATION. EXAMPLE: February 1886 --></date>
<biblScope type="page"><!-- PAGE NUMBERS --></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionary Activity</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people"><!-- List the people that are named in the document. Alphabetized. -->
<term><!-- LAST NAME, FIRST NAME --></term>
<!-- Some people may have their own subject heading. Search viaf.org and use the USA title. 
EXAMPLE: <term>Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928</term> -->
<term>Barclay, E. J.</term> <!-- I think the guy on Viaf is too young. -->
<term>Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term> <!--Just referred to as "Dr. Blyden in the text. Possibly wrong person, but description looks right."-->
<term>Bruce, Blanche Kelso, 1841-1898</term> <!-- Referred to as "B. K. Bruce in text, but how many senators are there that have those initials?-->
<term>Campbell, S. J.</term> <!-- Cannot find this person. -->
<term>Cartright</term> <!-- Not enough detail to find this person. -->
<term>Clark, Alexander</term>
<term>Cheeseman, Joseph James</term>  <!-- As J. J. Cheeseman -->
<term>Coleman, William David </term> <!-- as W. D. Coleman-->
<term>Cooper, Henry</term> <!-- I have no idea who this could be on viaf or if he even is on viaf.-->
<term>Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891</term> <!-- It seems extremely likely this is the one referred to as "Bishop Crowther".-->
<term>Davis, W. M.</term>  <!-- No idea who on Viaf this could be. -->
<term>Day, David A., 1851-1897, </term>
<term>Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895,</term>
<term>Eljen, Kobbena</term>
<term>Garnett Barboza, Mary</term>
<term>Garnet, Henry Highland, 1815-1882</term>
<term>Geda</term> <!--Not enough information on who this is.-->
<term>Gibson, Garrison W.</term>
<term>Greer, Hannah</term>
<term>Grimes, H. W.</term>
<term>Hood</term> <!-- No luck finding this person. -->
<term>Hopkins, M. A.</term> <!-- Nothing on viaf. -->
<term>Johnson, H. R. W.</term> <!-- I only get Human Rights Watch Results.-->
<term>King, C. T. O.</term>
<term>Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865,</term>
<term>Moore, June</term>
<term>Moore, H. J.</term>
<term>Parsons, C. L.</term>
<term>Sherman, R. A.</term>
<term>Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891,</term>
<term>Travis, H. W.,</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"><!-- List the places that are named in the document. Alphabetized.-->
<term><!-- PLACE NAME. EXAMPLE: Congo River --></term>
<term>Africa</term>
<term>America</term>
<term>Barbadoes</term> <!--Isn't the modern spelling Barbados?-->
<term>Boporo</term> <!-- I think this is now Bopolu. --> 
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Freetown</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Gold Coast</term> <!-- Country?-->
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Kroo Town</term> <!-- No idea what this is.--> 
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Liberia College</term>
<term>Liverpool</term>
<term>London</term>
<term>Mount Mesurado</term>
<term>Mesurado River</term>
<term>Monrovia</term>
<term>Muhlenberg</term>
<term>the Niger</term> <!-- the river?-->
<term>Savannah, Georgia</term>
<term>Sherbro River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>St. Paul River</term>
<term>Stockton Creek</term>
<term>United States</term>
<term>West Africa</term>
<term>West Indies</term>
<term>York Island</term>

</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<!-- IGNORE THIS FOR NOW
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.mis.001.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>-->

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="KS"><!-- scanned, ocred, and encoded --></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<div2 type="titles">
<head>Henry McNeal Turner,* 
1834-1915 </head>
<p><hi rend="italic">African Letters</hi>, &#10013; from which excerpts follow, represent the reports
which Bishop Turner wrote during his first trip to West Africa
in 1891.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="text">
<head>Seventh Letter &#9766;
of Bishop Turner</head>
<p><name type="city">Freetown</name>, <country>Sierra Leone</country>, <placeName>Africa</placeName>,</p>
<p><date when="1891-11-16">November 16, 1891</date></p>
<p>But why waste time and space with the topography of the country?
Your readers will be more concerned about the people, their habits,
customs, manners, etc. I find about everything here common to
other cities. House builders, rock blasters, lime burners, stone
chiselers and polishers, blacksmiths, wheelwrights, painters, white-washers, 
tailors, watch-makers, jewelers, finest kind of bootmakers,
dress makers, glass polishers, boat caulkers, engineers, storekeepers,
doctors, lawyers, judges, druggists, postmasters, custom house
officers, schools, seminaries, colleges, cathedrals, publishers, editors,
bookbinders, medicine makers, chemists, scholars and everything
except horses and mules. Yes, I hear there are a few jackasses about—four legged 
I mean. We can find two legged asses anywhere. And
what is grander to me than anything else, is the fact that the trades
people are black men and women. Mixed bloods are not excluded,
however. They have a share in everything. Several white men from
<country>England</country> and some from <country>France</country>, <country>Germany</country>, <country>Italy</country> and <placeName>America</placeName> have
come here and married black women and raised up families of mixed
blood. Some have lived with their colored wives awhile and left them
several children to look after, and disappeared; so mulattoes are not
absent at all. But other white men have lived with their colored wives
right along and died with them. A few black men have also gone to
<note> * For biographical sketch see p. 42.</note>
<note> &#10013; Bishop Henry McNeal Turner, <hi rend="italic">African Letters</hi>, Nashville, A.M.E. Sunday
School Union, 1893.</note> 
<note> &#9766; <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 37-41. </note>
<fw>232</fw>
<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
<country>England</country> and elsewhere, and married white ladies, and they have
children, etc.</p>
<p>All the ministers here, except the Baptists, wear robes—the Catholics, 
Mohammedans, English Church, Wesleyan, Methodists, Presbyterians, 
Lutherans and African Methodist Episcopal. <rs type="person">Elder Geda</rs>
looks grandly in a robe, and the people here thought he was used to
it. I smiled but said nothing. Of course I was at home in my robe.
The Catholic and Mohammedan priests wear robes all over the city.</p>
<p>The dress of the people is not uniform at all. Some are dressed
in fine broadcloth, some in silks, bonnets, jewelry and in the fashion;
others in cheaper style; others in shirts, gowns, wraps; others also
as God made them. The old settlers are the bloods or dignitaries;
then comes in the tribal part according to grade. Tribal prejudice
runs high in many cases. The bush crowd are the servants and domestics.</p>
<p>The bush or native heathen do all the drudgery work, such as pulling 
and pushing the carts, wheel chairs, sedan chairs, hammocks,
hearses; carry all boxes, barrels, stones, mortar, bricks; row all the
boats on the river, etc. The people are peaceable; I see or hear of no
fighting; shooting is never heard of. Sometimes an African king may
come from the bush, or country, and kill some runaway wife, then he
is arrested and banished to some island, and made to work the balance 
of his life; but if a king comes to the city and kills a decent
wife, he will likely kill himself before he will be arrested.
I learned that <rs type="person">Bishop Crowther</rs>, of <geogName>the Niger</geogName>, has not been treated
right somehow by the Church of England, and he and his ministers
are about to set up an independent apostolic denomination. I am
urged to go and confer with him, but the object might be misconstrued, 
therefore I shall not go. I do not blame the bishop for kicking,
if what some of the ministers tell me be true.</p>
<p>A singular fact is, that anybody, white or colored, from <placeName>America</placeName>
is welcomed out here in <placeName>Africa</placeName>, either on the coast or back in the
interior, while Englishmen, French and Germans are mostly hated.
The kings hate them especially about robbing them of their lands.
The French are hated as the devil. Americans are looked upon as
the guardians of <country>Liberia</country> and the friends of her black, and it modifies
the prejudice somehow. I do not understand it yet. <country>France</country> is more
intolerant in her claimed possessions than England it seems, and
far less compromising, while the Mohammedans abominate <country>Germany</country> 
about the shiploads of rot-gut whisky they land along the coast
to ruin the more heathen African. The English ships despise the German 
ships about the same; nearly every time they see a German ship
<fw>233</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
at sea the entire crew will curse it about shipping poisoned liquor
to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. The English ships carry a good deal, too, but they ease
their conscience by saying, <q>"Our whisky is all first-class. It is inspected 
before we leave <name type="city">Liverpool</name> and <name type="city">London</name>."</q></p>
<p>The African ladies who come in the city from the bush, for hundreds of miles, 
have to buy white doll-babies for their children.
They want black, brown and yellow dolls. If some of our people will
engage in their manufacture they can sell millions of colored dolls.
<country>England</country>, <country>France</country>, etc., only send out white dolls. The black merchants
out here (and they are plentiful) are crazy for a line of steamships to
<placeName>America</placeName>, like <country>England</country>, <country>France</country> and <country>Germany</country> have, so they can deal
in American goods, medicines, etc.; so the merchants can come over
in ten or fifteen days and return in haste—the sail vessels are too slow.
These black Mohammedan priests, learned to kill, walking around
here in their robes with so much dignity, majesty and consciousness
of their worth, are driving me into respect for them. Some come for
hundreds of miles from the country—out of the bushes—better
scholars than in <placeName>America</placeName>. What fools we are to suppose these Africans 
are fools!
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="text">
<head>Eighth Letter*
of Bishop Turner</head>
<p><name type="city">Freetown</name>, <country>Sierra Leone</country>, <placeName>Africa</placeName>,</p>
<p><date when="1891-11-18">November 18th, 1891</date></p>
<p>The native African has no fear, no cowardice, no dread, but feels
himself the equal of any man on earth. The land, as far as I went, is
rich, water streams in abundance, fruits of every kind, flowers of
every beauty, and while I saw many doing nothing at all, I saw many
hundreds at work, and hard at work, too. They need skilled labor,
however, skilled farmers. Since I found out more, I find horses will
live here and be fat. Dogs are like ours in every particular. The dogs,
roosters, goats and sheep all talk like ours. I told the doctor they were
all I could understand. I could not understand the people, but he
could.</p>
<p>I have just had the honor of my life. <rs type="person">King Kobbena Eljen</rs> of the
Kromantic tribe, a powerful tribe on the <country>Gold Coast</country>, who was captured 
in the late war with <country>England</country>, and who is here as prisoner of
<note>* <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 42-45.</note>
<fw>234</fw>
<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
war, called to pay his respects, through me to his race, as he says
<q>"over the sea"</q>. He means in <placeName>America</placeName>. I kissed his hands a dozen
times, and would have kissed his feet, had he not said, <q>"No, no"</q>.
The king is 64 years old. He is tall, erect and majestic, and is deeply
concerned about the colored people in <placeName>America</placeName>. He wanted to know
when we were coming home.</p>
<p>During the great Ashantee war, he was captured by the English
army, and <country>England</country> tried to get him to sign away his territory and his
people's land. He refused to do it and they brought him to <country>Sierra
Leone</country>, as a prisoner, to be held until he signs away his kingdom. The
king says he will die first. If he would sign the documents, <country>England</country>
would send him back at once in a man-of-war. The African kings and
nobility will make me hate <country>England</country>, grand as old <country>England</country> is in many
respects. The king walks about town but cannot leave. He is loyal
to his race and to his people. He will give his kingdom to his children
in the <country>United States</country>, but not to <country>England</country>.</p>
<p>Well, the ship has arrived which is to carry me to <country>Liberia</country>, and having 
completed my work here, I must close this letter and begin to
pack up. I have not written half, but all I could find time to write.... </p>
</div2>
<div2 type="text">
<head>Eleventh Letter*
of Bishop Turner</head>

<p><name type="city">Muhlenberg</name>, <country>Liberia</country>,</p>
<p><date when="1891-12-04">December 4, 1891</date></p>
<p>Mr. Editor:</p>
<p>I have just strolled as far out in the direction of <placeName>Boporo</placeName>—the Eden
of <placeName>West Africa</placeName>—as my strength and convenience would permit. I
have seen the African in his native town and hut, rather dwellings,
and I have just had a long weep or cry at the grand field for missionary 
operation here, and that I am too old now to engage in it.
But if there were roads cut through the country and bridges for horses
and wagons, I would try it, as old as I am. I am sure I could not stand
the hills and valleys of this rolling country traveling on foot, at my
age, and then the hammock system of travel is too cumbersome for
regular locomotion. But <placeName>Africa</placeName> is the grandest field on earth for the
labor of civilization and the Christian church. There is no reason
under heaven why this continent should not or cannot be redeemed
<note>* <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 55-60.</note>
<fw>235</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>



and brought to God in twenty-five years—say thirty at most. Note the
reasons:</p>
<p>First.—The African can beat the world in learning to speak the
English language, in which all religious terms are found to convey
Christian ideas.</p>
<p>Second.—The young African can come out of the bush, and in a
few months at most, sing and play upon the organ any gospel song
in print, even before he learns to wear clothes.</p>
<p>Third.—The Africans are the most honest people on earth. Where
I am stopping at present, at the Training School of <abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> <rs type="person">David A.
Day</rs>, scores of wild and partly civilized Africans gather and sleep
all about the yards as well as on the piazzas; not a door or window
is shut all night, unless it is raining or windy.</p>
<p>Fourth.—The African is not a pagan, but a child of superstition;
he worships no wooden or brass god, but believes more strongly in
the invisible forces than we do; so it is an easy matter to have him
transfer his faith from superstition to Christ Jesus the Lord.</p>
<p>Fifth.—And here is the crowning phase of this question: The
Africans will give the god-man or god-woman millions of children to
be instructed and trained to read, write, work, sing, pray, farm or
do anything that will make them useful. When you approach the
older ones, and begin to tell them about the benefits of a civilized
life and the virtues of Christianity, they say: <q>"You no change me
now; take all my pickaninnies (children) and teach them, make them
wise and great; not me, I be too old."</q> And they will give you all
their children, and frequently come once a week and bring food for
them to eat. It makes one feel singular to see the almost naked native
African father come out of the bush, and sit around the Training
School, and watch their sons as they walk the yards in decent dress,
and read, write, sing, march, use tools, etc. They are so fond of their
children. Finally, they will walk off home, possibly having not uttered
a word to their child or any one else. The African father seems to be
solliloquizing thus: <q>"Well, I suppose that will be the order of things
in the future; my day will soon be gone, and another dispensation
will be ushered in."</q></p>
<p>One thing stands to the everlasting credit of the African; he is
anxious to learn; a seeker after knowledge; <sic>to-day</sic> he is the most
susceptible heathen upon the face of the globe. He is ready to lay
down any habit, custom or sentiment for a better, or have his children 
do it, which is the same thing. It is said, that often those that
have been trained at schools, will return to the bush and strip off
their clothes and go around like the others. That seems to be true
<fw>236</fw>
<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
from what I have seen in some cases. But what is the result? These
very young men become the leaders and general instructors of their
people; they do not forget their training by any means. They often
become the diplomats of their tribes and negotiate with other tribes
and civilized nations. Their education is not lost, if they go as naked
as a <q>"skinned coon".</q></p>
</div2>
<div2 type="text">
<head>Twelfth Letter*
of Bishop Turner</head>
<p><name type="city">Monrovia</name>, <country>Liberia</country>,</p>
<p><date when="1891-12-05">December 5, 1891</date></p>
<p>Mr. Editor:</p>
<p>I have descended the <geogName>St. Paul River</geogName> and am now in <name type="city">Monrovia</name>,
stopping in the beautiful three-story brick residence of <rs type="person">General R. A.
Sherman</rs>, general-in-chief of the Liberian armies. Everything is
superb in and outside of this spacious and finely-furnished palace.
I would wager anything that <rs type="person">General W. T. Sherman</rs> never lived in
more style, and I am sure he never possessed anything like the social
graces of the Liberian <rs type="person">General Sherman</rs>. The general somewhat
resembles <rs type="person">ex-Senator B. K. Bruce</rs> in stature, color, hair and demeanor. 
He was born in <name type="city">Savannah</name>, <region>Ga.</region>, is about fifty years of age, and
has been here some thirty-seven years. He has fought many battles,
has been wounded repeatedly, and his name is a terror to the native
heathen for hundreds of miles in the interior.</p>
<p>I have seen many sights of interest in the city. <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Dr.</abbr> Blyden</rs> carried
me through the <placeName>Kroo Town</placeName>, introduced me to the king, with whom
I had a long talk. I was surprised at his intelligence and general
information. He was dressed as a gentleman and very polite. His
subjects, or people, treat him with great respect. The city is laid off in
streets and squares, but not equal in extent; sometimes the streets
curve and, in other cases, they so intersect one another as to form a
triangle.</p>
<p>The houses are built of platted sheets of bamboo, which they plat
upon the ground with taste and skill, and in some instances with
peculiar art. Then they are set up and fastened to timbers, and rooms,
kitchens, palaver halls, sitting-rooms and such like are made in the
same building.</p>
<note>* <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 61-65.</note>
<fw>237</fw>


<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
<p>It is useless to talk about the African having no taste and pride.</p>
<p>I have found out another thing since I have come to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. I have
traveled scores of miles through the interior and noted the tact,
taste, genius and manly bearing of the higher grade of the natives.
I have found out that we poor American negroes were the tail-end
of the African races. We were slaves over here, and had been for a
thousand years or more before we were sold to <placeName>America</placeName>. Those who
think the receding forehead, the flat nose, the proboscidated mouth
and the big flat-bottom foot are natural to the African are mistaken.
There are heads here by the millions, as vertical or perpendicular as
any white man's head God ever made. A straight rule laid upon the
face of three-fourths of us in <placeName>America</placeName> will touch the nose and mouth
only; here are native Africans, without number, whose nose and chin
the rule would touch without touching the mouth, which is always
indicative of the highest type of intellectuality. Some of the most
neat and concave feet are found upon thousands of these Africans.
I have seen specimens of 19 tribes, and I have not seen over 100 of
them constructed on as low scale as I have seen in <placeName>America</placeName>. An
African said to be 108 years old, said, <q>"We no used to sell 'big
blood' African to white man, except we capture him in war."</q> I
believe this old man tells the truth; that during the times of the slave
trade there were no <q>"big blood"</q> (first class) Africans sold to the white
man, unless they were war prisoners.</p>
<p><name type="city">Monrovia</name> far exceeds my expectations. Instead of being low,
swampy and alluvial, it is on an elevated cape, three sides laved by
the ocean and fanned by her breezes. It will average about 150 feet
above the sea-level, I think. In the main, the houses are excellent,
two, three and a few four-stories high, with sidewalks very good, but
the streets proper are grassy and not kept in regular order. As they
use no horses and wagons, the streets are not needed; but they are
far superior to hundreds of streets I have seen where horses and
mules are used.</p>
<p>In the rear of <name type="city">Monrovia</name>, however, where a branch of the <geogName>St. Paul
River</geogName>, called the <geogName>Stockton Creek</geogName>, and the <geogName>Mesurado River</geogName> form a
confluence, there are some large mangrove swamps, alluvial, soft and
lagoonish, which evidently emit a great deal of malaria and are
highly productive of fever germs when the wind is blowing from the
land side, just as we have in thousands of places in the <country>United States</country>.
There is no remedy for this, for God is making these two rivers cart
dirt from the high lands to fill up the low; the debris is gradually doing 
its work, and the people must await his time.</p>
<p>The <placeName>Liberia College</placeName> is situated on the side of <geogName>Mount Mesurado</geogName>;
<fw>238</fw>

<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
the curriculum is high and the teachers are well informed. Two more
learned professors are being looked for daily. The college is a credit
to the government of <country>Liberia</country>, for it is a national institution.</p>
<p>I have had the honor of visiting the executive mansion of the
Liberian government, was received with marked consideration, and
the president, who is polished scholar, paid me special attention. I
had seen nine presidents in the <country>United States</country>, but a real black president 
was to me a delightful sight. This administration is praised and
blamed by friends and foes, just as is the case with our presidents.
The Liberian government is in the hands of the following, who form
the executive department: <rs type="person">His Excellency H. R. W. Johnson</rs>,
President, born in <country>Liberia</country>; Secretary of State, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> E. J. Barclay,</rs>
born in <country>Barbadoes</country>, <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; Secretary of Treasury, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> H. W.
Travis</rs>, born in <country>Liberia</country>; Postmaster-General, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> H. J. Moore</rs>,
born in <country>Liberia</country>; Attorney-General, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> W. M. Davis</rs>, born in
<name type="city">Philadelphia</name>, <region>Pa.</region>, Secretary of the Interior, not filled. The Secretary
of the Treasury, for the present, does the duties of the War and Naval
departments. Chief Justice, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> C. L. Parsons</rs>, born in <name type="city">Charleston</name>,
<region>S.C.</region></p>
<p>The president-elect, who will take his seat early in January, 1892,
is <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> J. J. Cheeseman</rs> of <region>Grand Bassa</region>, born in <country>Liberia</country>; vice-president-elect, 
<rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> W. D. Coleman</rs>, born in <region>Kentucky</region>. <rs type="person">Mr.
Cheeseman</rs> is represented as an able man with progressive views.</p>
<p>I visited the Monrovia cemetery a few days ago, and was pleased
with the tombstones, slabs and shafts I saw commemorating the dead.
I counted nearly a hundred, some of which cost over a thousand dollars. 
I saw the grave of my aunt, <rs type="person">"Hannah Greer,"</rs> who died about
the same time my mother did, some three years ago. She was about
ninety years old. She was my oldest aunt of five, and the people here
say she was a grand woman. I hope to send or bring her a marble
head and foot slab from <placeName>America</placeName>. I visited also the graves of <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr>
M. A. Hopkins</rs>, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> and <abbr type="title">Dr.</abbr> Henry Highland Garnett</rs>, <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr>
Alexander Clark</rs>, and <abbr type="title">Mrs.</abbr> <rs type="person">Mary Garnett Barboza</rs>, the distinguished
daughter of <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Dr.</abbr> Garnett.</rs> <rs type="person">Hopkins</rs>, <rs type="person">Garnett</rs> and <rs type="person">Clark</rs> were the three
American Ministers of State, who have died here. There is not a
stone, or a shingle, at the foot or head of the grave of <rs type="person">Dr. Garnett</rs>,
—a shame, a shame, upon us American Negroes!</p>
<p>For forty years before <rs type="person">Mr. Lincoln</rs> issued his proclamation of
freedom, <rs type="person">Dr. Garnett</rs> fought for his race as no other man could, except 
<rs type="person">Douglass</rs>, when the lips of the Southern negro was sealed and
he was gored by the slave-masters to the verge of death. <rs type="person">Dr. Garnett</rs>
periled life and everything for his freedom. Now for us American
<fw>239</fw>
<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
negroes to allow his remains to lie here, as though he was a dog,
is enough to make God blast the whole of us. As I looked at his
grave I wept, and asked God if there was any hope for such an ungrateful 
people. If we do not send a tombstone here to mark his
grave, the whole negro race in <placeName>America</placeName> deserves the contempt of
perdition, to say nothing of heaven.</p>
<p><rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> C. T. O. King</rs> is the agent of the Colonization Society
here. He is a man of excellent parts and evidently understands himself. 
<rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Mr.</abbr> King</rs> thinks that some improvements could be made in
the reception of emigrants from <placeName>America</placeName>, and I think so, too. But
as I will speak about them at the proper place if I live, I will only say
at present, that any persons coming out here should not come as
paupers. While <country>Liberia</country> is the easiest place to make a living on earth
and is the most paradisiacal spot in the world, all things considered;
yet, there is a climatic change which most people must pass through
(many do not), and while they are passing through it, they need rest
and fresh food, which the Colonization Society does not provide,
nor can it without steamships. Hence they need money to purchase
the necessary food and often some medicine. Persons should not
come here and expect to be hirelings; for the native African stands
ready to do all kinds of work much cheaper and better than we can,
except skilled labor. They till the ground and raise all the produce for
twenty-five cents per day, or five dollars per month. A man coming
here with two or three hundred dollars and good sense may be rich
in four or five years. But this is no place for fools and paupers. The
oldest man in <country>Liberia</country> at present is only one hundred and twenty-seven 
years; the oldest woman is one hundred and twenty. A young
man twenty-seven years old has a wife seventy-two years old, and he
is jealous of her and another fellow twenty-four years old.</p>
<p>The ministers of <name type="city">Monrovia</name> are as follows: <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> Garrison W.
Gibson</rs>, of the Episcopal Church; <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> Henry Cooper</rs>, M. E.
Church; <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> Robert J. Clark</rs>, Baptist Church; <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> J. B. Perry</rs>,
Presbyterian Church. All these ministers treat Geda and me with
great courtesy. The Episcopal minister could not offer me his church
to preach in, owing to the canons of his connection but he urged me
to lecture in it. The M. E. Church pastor appropriated our service.
He is a Christian and a gentleman of the highest type. Everybody
seems to be overjoyed at the presence of the A. M. E. Church in
<country>Liberia</country>. The welcome appears to be universal. Many desire that it
shall be the National Church, others declare it will be the Continental 
Church. They have come after me to organize in <name type="city">Monrovia</name> at
once, but for reasons that I shall tell the bishops, I will not.</p>
<fw>240</fw>
<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
<p>A minister of the A. M. E. Zion Church, who had united with
us and claimed to be ordained by one <rs type="person">Elder Cartright</rs>, maintained
that his orders were valid, as <rs type="person">Brother Cartright</rs> was superintendent of
the church here and had been authorized by <rs type="person">Bishop Hood</rs> to ordain.
I denied the right of <rs type="person">Bishop Hood</rs> to confer any such authority upon
an elder and rejected his ordination. I ordained him a deacon, however, 
after due examination. I am sure <rs type="person">Bishop Hood</rs> never did it.</p>
<p>The people here think I am a <q>"rough,"</q> because I will sit in the
draught, eat all kinds of African food, sleep with the windows open,
walk around barefooted, etc., preach or speak every night. But I
believe some people die here because of particularity. I never felt
better in my life; but I cannot say how long this will continue.</p>
<p>They say <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> Alexander Clark</rs>, who died here, had passed
through the acclimating fever and would have lived easily enough
had he not refused to eat food that would strengthen him; he confined 
himself to American hog soup, when the doctor and all begged
him to eat other things. The people here say stinginess killed him.
The report, however, that strong drink killed him is pronounced a
base falsehood. People here say he was purely temperate.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="text">
<head>Fourteenth Letter*
of Bishop Turner</head>
<p><placeName>York Island</placeName>, <geogName>Sherbro River</geogName>, <placeName>Africa</placeName>,</p>
<p><date when="1891-12-09">December 9, 1891</date></p>
<p>Mr. Editor:</p>
<p>I have left <name type="city">Monrovia</name> and am now some seventy-five miles up the
<geogName>Sherbro River</geogName>, interior-ward from the ocean. The native towns
and vast population of our people living on each side of this river,
and all through the bush, is simply wonderful. As you ascend <geogName>the
Sherbro</geogName>, every now and then, small inlets can be seen flowing in from
the land, while trees lock their branches across them, and flower-bearing 
vines festoon them with garlands of fragrant drapery. But,
reverberating through and under these over-arched inlets, you can
hear the voices of scores of natives, as they chant their rowing songs;
for the native Africans sing as they work, especially as they row their
boats, till they burst from under the green sceneries with small canoes
laden with all kinds of fruit. Often a Mohammedan priest sits in front,
<note>* <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., pp. 72-74.</note>
<fw>241</fw>



<fw>APROPOS OF AFRICA</fw>
gorgeously robed, as though he was on watch for whisky; as the
sixty millions of Mohammedans and their plurality of wives (which
of course no Christian can endorse), I verily believe that God is
holding these Mohammedans intact, and that they will serve as the
forerunners of evangelical Christianity; in short, that the Mohammedan 
religion is the morningstar to the sun of pure Christianity.
I have not spoken on any occasion against liquor-drinking in <placeName>Africa</placeName>
but some Mohammedan has come and shaken my hand after service,
and thanked me for fighting whisky. One thanked me <q>"for cursing
liquor"</q>, and said, <q>"Our church and religion all curse it, too; it be
our greatest foe"</q>. God save the Mohammedans, is my prayer, till
the Christian Church is ready to do her whole duty. Beyond the fact
that the Mohammedans allow more than one wife, they are as upright 
in conduct and civil behavior as any people in the land.</p>
<p>I regret to say what I am now going to write, but I promised to do
it, and I suppose I had better keep my word.</p>
<p>The leading men, or a large number of them in <country>Liberia</country>, are disgusted 
with a majority of the representatives that our government
sends over here. They say if our government cannot find sober,
cool-headed, dignified and intelligent representatives of our own
color to send here, ask the president to send white men. <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Dr.</abbr> Henry
Highland Garnett</rs> is the only man sent here, whom all join in complimenting, 
for many years. They say <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Dr.</abbr> Garnett</rs> was a gentleman and
a diplomat of high order. They also speak kindly of <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> Alexander
Clarke</rs>, so far as his sobriety and morality are concerned, but say
that he had no knowledge of diplomacy. Some of our representatives
have so far ignored the rule of diplomatic dignity or decorum that
they have tried to force themselves into the President's Cabinet
meetings. But I will tell no more, as I dislike gossip in any form;
yet they prefer a white man to some of our colored men whom the
Presidents have sent here.</p>
<p>It appears that the American minister is the Dean of the Diplomatic 
Corps at <name type="city">Monrovia</name>, and in any formal meeting or reception he
is the presiding officer, as he ranks the representatives of all other
nations; therefore he should be a model man in every respect.</p>
<p><country>Liberia</country>, as I have said before, is a most beautiful country, and
nature has supplied it with all that heart could wish. I never wanted
to be a young man so badly in my life. I would come here, and, if I
had half as much sense as I have now, I would be worth a fortune in
ten years. Nevertheless, as I have said before, I would advise no one
to come here without a hundred or two dollars. This is not the place
for any one to come without money. Well, if he is a mechanic, viz.,
<fw>242</fw>
<fw>WHEN I WAS IN AFRICA</fw>
carpenter, blacksmith, painter, tailor, watchmaker, or professional,
as a doctor or a lawyer, he might do well enough; but a mere laborer
should bring some money, for the native African stands ready, ten
thousand strong, to snatch up all the mere common labor to be done,
at twenty-five cents per day, or five dollars a month; and two native
Africans can do more hard work in one day than five of our ordinary
men, such is their strength and vigor.</p>
<p>As for the acclimating process, nearly everybody must pass
through it, yet all do not have the fever. Men, and women too, who
have been here ten and fifteen years, tell me they have never had
anything like fever. But if a person comes here, young or old, with
any chronic disease lurking in his system, <placeName>Africa</placeName> is apt to purge it
out, or kill the person in the process of purgation. At all events,
the party will get better or worse. But if a person comes here healthy,
sound and sober, there is no more danger than in any change of
climate.</p>
<p>One thing the black man has here—that is, manhood, freedom,
and the fullest liberty; he feels as a lord, and walks and talks the
same way.</p>
<p>I notice when the English, or even the cultured Africans, speak
of the colored people coming here from <placeName>America</placeName> or elsewhere they
do not use the terms <q>"emigrate"</q>, or <q>"African emigration,"</q> as we do
in <placeName>America</placeName>; but, instead, they invariably say, <q>"repatriate"</q>, or use the
term, the <q>"repatriation of the black man"</q>, or, as some say, the
<q>"negro;"</q> nor are the terms <q>"emigrate"</q> or <q>"immigrate"</q> used among
the common people, as they say, <q>"coming home"</q>, or <q>"When are you
all coming home?"</q> The native African, from the kings down, cannot 
realize that the black man in <placeName>America</placeName> is at home across the sea.</p>
<p>Out of the many receptions given in my honor, or the honor
of the church, and the eloquent address delivered upon the occasions,
I will send the two following, they being the only ones which have
fallen into my hands in manuscript. I failed to get the others by
reason of having to leave so soon. The first was delivered by <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr>
June Moore</rs>, of the Baptist Church, the great friend and comrade of
<rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Rev.</abbr> S. J. Campbell</rs>, at the opening of the Liberian Conference;
the other at the 10 o'clock breakfast tendered to <rs type="person">Elder Geda</rs> and
myself at <name type="city">Monrovia</name>, which was read by <rs type="person"><abbr type="title">Hon.</abbr> H. W. Grimes</rs>.</p>
<fw>R                                          243</fw>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>