<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0678">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Ravoninahitriniarivo and Ramaniraka to Earl Granville, February 7, 1883</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0678</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Ravoninahitriniarivo and Ramaniraka to Earl Granville</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes From the Madagascan Legation in the United States to the Department of State, 1883-1894</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T806</biblScope>
<date when="1883-02-07">February 7, 1883</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Baudais</term>
<term>Ducluc</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Madagascar</term>
<term>Paris (France)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>France</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Ravoninahitriniarivo</persName>
<persName>Ramaniraka</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>London (England)</placeName>
<date when="1883-02-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/13068670">Granville, Granville George Leveson-Gower, Earl, 1815-1891</persName>
<roleName>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</roleName>
<placeName>London (England)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-05-13" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2020-02-24" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="20170614_154158"/>

<p>London<lb/>
February 7th 1883</p>

<p>To,<lb/>
The Right Honorable<lb/>
Earl Granville K.G.<lb/>
Her Majesty's Principal Secretary of 
State for Foreign Affairs,</p>
    
<p>My Lord,</p>

<p>Having carefully considered the report of 
our affairs with the French Government which has 
lately appeared in its "Documents Diplomatiques," we
beg to submit to Your Lordship's friendly attention
the following few brief notes which we feel are alike 
demanded by the interests of truth and the welfare
of our cause.</p>

<p>With regard to the correspondence of Monsr Baudais, 
we shall not trespass upon your time by denying 
in detail the many misrepresentations thereon
made. It was not to be expected that his letters
would give a unprejudiced account of the state 
of affairs between France and Madagascar. But
we did look forward to finding a fair historical 
record of our dealings with French officials
at Paris in the Government document already
referred to, and are sorry to be <sic>compilled</sic> to 
assert that such record has not been given.</p>

<p>Permit us to remind Your Lordship of what we
have already had the honour of stating in our
communication of 9th December 1882 with regard
to the manner in which our business was transacted 
in Paris.</p>

<p>Except at the very beginning of the negotiations,
our affairs were not dealt with by those who had
<catchwords>been</catchwords>

<pb n="20170614_154218"/>

been officially appointed to discuss them on the 
part of France. In all the attempts to come to an 
understanding the French Government was represented 
by intermediaries who we have reason to believe conducted 
the business with their own personal advantage 
chiefly in view. By these gentlemen we were
given to understand that there was not the slightest 
hope of avoiding immediate hostilities with France
except by making some concession to the National
pride. We had clearly refused to acknowledge
the claim to a Protectorate in our Note to Messrs
les Commissaires (No. 23 of Documents Diplomatiques)
on the subject, and continued to do so throughout.
But on being promised by the intermediaries
that a temporary removal of our new Custom
Houses from the North West Coast, and an offer
to grant long leases of land would lead to a 
withdrawal of the threatened protectorate, we 
verbally expressed our willingness, thus to meet 
the French Government halfway; our conversations 
at this time we taken by the intermediaries
&amp; made up by them into the Notes Nos. 24 &amp; 26 of
"Documents Diplomatiques," which we do not 
admit as correct interpretations of our meaning.</p>

<p>Our last words to the intermediaries on this 
subject were to the effect that the removal
of the Custom Houses was to be distinctly regarded 
as only temporary. We were also 
assured that after these verbal agreement
had been placed upon paper we should have an 
opportunity of reconsidering them before being 
expected to affix our signatures.</p>

<p>The next event was our being asked by Monsieur 
Ducluc through a Government Clerk to 
<catchwords>sign</catchwords>

<pb n="20170614_154227"/>

sign a document which has since received the 
name of "Ultimatum" to which we specially desire 
to call Your Lordship's attention. It is not reproduced
in its original integrity in No. 27 of "Documents Diplomatiques" 
but is given in a manned calculated to 
create an unfavorable opinion of our refusal
to sign it.</p>

<p>In the published report a whole paragraph 
has been omitted, the very portion to which our refusal 
attached itself as being contrary to what 
we had been led to expect as the result
of making concessions to National pride. The 
omitted paragraph reads "Il est bien entendre
etc," and will be found in the copy of the 
original document which we have the
honor of now enclosing for Your Lordship's
inspection.</p>

<p>In the face of such an unjust misrepresentation, 
unprecedented we would hope in the 
transactions of civilized Government, it seems
a small matter to call Your Lordship's notice 
to the incorrect statements made by Monsieur 
Baudais to which we have already referred.</p>

<p>But the more we examine his misleading
language, the more we discover the unworthy 
ill-feeling which prompted its use, and hence 
we venture to ask Your Lordship to give a 
moments consideration to the comments we have
made thereupon in the copy of the "Documents
Diplomatiques" which accompanies the present letter.</p>

<p>We have the honor to be, with the highest consideration.</p>

<p>My Lord<lb/>
Your Lordship's most obedient servants<lb/>
(signed) Ravoninahitriniarivo<lb/>
(signed) Ramaniraka</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
