<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0263">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from Frederick W. Seward to George G. L. Wright, January 22, 1862</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0263</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from Frederick W. Seward to George G. L. Wright, January 22, 1862</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gaboon, 1856-1888 T-466</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-466, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1862-01-22">January 22, 1862</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
    


<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
<date when="1862-01-22"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName>Wright, George G. L.</persName>
<roleName>Commercial Agent at Gaboon</roleName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02-20" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw">additional encoding</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#unm">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170615_105437"/>

<p>Department of State,<lb/>
Washington, Jany 22d, 1862</p>

<p>George G. L. Wright Esqr.<lb/>
Appointed United States <del>Consul</del> Commercial Agent at the Gaboon</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>The President having appointed you <del>Consul</del> Commercial Agent of the United States at the Gaboon</p>

<p>I transmit you a printed copy of the Consular Regulations, to 
which your immediate and careful attention is invited; a form of the 
Consular bond, to be executed at once and sent to this Department,
and other documents for the use of your Consulate, of which a list 
is subjoined.</p>

<p>As soon as your bond is received and approved your Passport 
will be transmitted to you, and your <del>Commission will be sent to the Legation of the United States at &#160; &#160; &#160; with instructions to apply to the &#160; &#160; &#160; Government for the usual Exequatur, which, when obtained, will be forwarded to you at &#160; &#160; &#160; with the Commission</del> Certificate of appointment.</p>

<p>You will communicate to the Department the name of the 
State or Country in which you were born, also of the State from
which you have been appointed, and if you have ever resided in 
Gaboon. <del>or any of its dependencies.</del>.</p>

<p>I am, sir, respectfully,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,<lb/>
F. W. Seward<lb/>
Assistant Secretary</p>

<pb n="20170615_105446"/>

<p>Know all men by these presents,</p> 

<p>That we, &#160; &#160; &#160; are held and firmly bound to the United States of America in the sum of three thousand dollars, money of the said United States, to the payment whereof we bind ourselves, jointly and severally, our joint and several heirs, executors, and administrators.</p>

<p>Witness our hands and seats this  &#160; &#160; &#160; day of  &#160; &#160; &#160; ,  18 &#160; &#160; &#160; .</p>

<p>The condition of the above obligation is such, That if the above 
bounden  &#160; &#160; &#160; , appointed &#160; &#160; &#160; of the United States at &#160; &#160; &#160;  
shall truly and faithfully discharge the duties of his said office 
according to law, and shall truly and faithfully account for, pay 
over, and deliver up, all fees, moneys, goods, effects, books, records,
papers, and other property which shall come to the hands of the 
said &#160; &#160; &#160; , or to the hands of any person 
for his use as such &#160; &#160; &#160; , under any law 
now or hereafter enacted, and that he will truly and faithfully 
perform all other duties now or hereafter imposed upon 
him as such  &#160; &#160; &#160; . And these presents
are subject to this other and further condition, that he, the said
 &#160; &#160; &#160; , will not, while he holds the 
said office, be interested in or transact any business as a merchant,
factor, broker, or other trader, or as a clerk or other agent for 
any such person, to from, or within the port, place, or limits 
of his  &#160; &#160; &#160; , directly or indirectly, either in his own 

<pb n="20170615_105453"/>

name, or in the name or through the agency of any other person;
and in case he, the said &#160; &#160; &#160; 
shall violate the provisions of this condition, that then the above named 
obligors shall be liable to said obliges, to a penalty for the breach of 
such condition in a sum equal to the amount of the annual compensation
of said &#160; &#160; &#160; ; which is hereby stipulated,
agreed upon, and admitted by way of liquidated damages, but that
this condition shall not impair or prevent the right of the United 
States to prosecute said &#160; &#160; &#160; for the recovery 
of said penalty against him, the said &#160; &#160; &#160;  
individually, the same as if this bond had not been given; and if the 
said &#160; &#160; &#160; shall conform to all the 
above conditions, then this obligation to be void; otherwise, to remain 
in full force.</p>

<p>Signed, sealed, and delivered, in the presence of&#8212;}</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
