<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.drama.0001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>In Dahomey (1902)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.drama.0001</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">In Dahomey</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76335432">Dunbar, Paul Laurence, 1872-1906</author>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70655904">Shipp, Jesse, 1859-1934</author>
<date>1902</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Drama</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">In Dahomey</head>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Characters</head>

<list>
<item>Je-Je-, a Caboceer . . . Charles Moore</item>
<item>Menuki, messenger of the king . . . Wm. Elkins</item>
<item>Moses Lightfoot, agent of Dahomey Colonization Society . . . Wm. Barker</item>
<item>Shylock Homestead, called "Shy" by his friends . . . Bert A. Williams</item>
<item>Rareback Punkerton, "Shy's" personal friend and adviser . . . Geo. W. Walker</item>
<item>Cicero Lightfoot, President of a Colonization Society . . . Pete Hampton</item>
<item>Dr. Straight . . . in name only, street fakir . . . Fred Douglas</item>
<item>George Reeder, proprietor of an intelligence office . . . Alex Rogers</item>
<item>Henry Stampfield, letter carrier, with an argument against immigration . . . Walter Richardson</item>
<item>Me Sing, a Chinese cook . . . Geo. Catlin</item>
<item>Hustling Charley, promoter of Get-the-Coin Syndicate . . . J. A. Shipp</item>
<item>Leather, a bootblack . . . Richard Connors</item>
<item>Officer Still . . . J. Leubrie Hill</item>
<item>White Wash Man . . . Green Tapley</item>
<item>Messenger Rush, but not often . . . Theodore Pankey</item>
<item>Pansy, daughter of Cecilia Lightfoot, in love with Leather . . . Abbie Mitchell</item>
<item>Cecilia Lightfoot, Cicero's wife . . . Mrs. Hattie McIntosh</item>
<item>Mrs. Stringer, dealer in forsaken patterns, also editor of fashion notes in <hi rend="italics">Beanville Agitator</hi> . . . Mrs. Lottie Williams</item>
<item>Rosetta Lightfoot, a troublesome young thing . . . Aida Overton Walker</item>
<item>Colonists, Natives, etc.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Act 1</head>

<stage>(Public Square with a house doorway. Above the door is a sign: "Intelligence Office." A crowd is assembled around a medicine show pitchman. Applause at rise of curtain. A banjo player acts as an interlocutor as Tambo, and Bones tell one or two jokes. The banjoist sings a song. Dr. Straight, the pitchman, addresses the crowd.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>DR. STRAIGHT</speaker>

<p>After listening to great attempts at beautiful strains of melodious music and a pyrotechnical display of humorous humorosities, quintessence of brevity rather than prolix verbosity, will best accomplish the purpose for which I appear here this evening. Now that I've made everything so plain that even a child can understand, I'll proceed with business. I hold here in my hand a preparation made from roots, herbs, barks, leaf grasses, cereals, vegetables, fruits and chemicals warranted, by myself, to do all that I claim, even more. I'm not here to sell this article but simply to advertise the greatest boon that mankind has ever known. I will forfeit one thousand dollars to ― hold up the money so that they can see it</p>

<stage>(attendants hold up a large sack marked $1000)</stage>

<p>― or I will take the same amount from any dark skin son or daughter of the genius Africanus that I cannot immediately transform into an Apollo or Cleopatra with a hirsute appendage worthy of a Greek goddess.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VOICE</speaker>

<stage>(interrupting)</stage>

<p>Look here, Mr. Medicine man, if you 'specs to sell any of dem bottles of whatever you've got there to anybody in this crowd, you'd better bring your language down to the limitations of a universal understanding. I've been standin' here ten minutes tryin' to figger out what you're talkin' about and I tell you as the old maxim says, "Patience ceases to be virtuous."</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>DR. STRAIGHT</speaker>

<p>Your patience shall be rewarded. I'll come to the point at once. This compound known as Straightaline is the greatest hair tonic on earth. What will Straightaline do? Why it cures dandruff, tetter itch, and all scalp diseases at once and forever. It makes hair grow on bald-headed babies. It makes curly hair as straight as a stick in from one to ten days. Straightaline straightens kinky hair in from ten to thirty days and most wonderful of all, Straightaline straightens knappy or knotty hair.</p>

<stage>(he hesitates)</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>VOICE</speaker>

<p>Well?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>DR. STRAIGHT</speaker> 

<p>In three days.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VOICE</speaker>

<p>I'll take a bottle of dat.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>DR. STRAIGHT</speaker>

<p>Wait, wait, wait, this is not all. I have another preparation, Oblicuticus, "Obli" ― in this case, being an 
abbreviation of the word "obliterate." "Cuti" ― taken from the word "cuticle," the outer skin, and "cuss" is what everybody does when the desired results are not obtained, but there is no such word as "fail." This wonderful face bleach removes the outer skin and leaves in its place a peachlike complexion that can't be duplicated ― even by peaches. Changing black to white and vice versa. I am going to spend only one day in your city, but I am going to convince you by exhibiting a living evidence of my assertions that these two grand preparations, Straightaline and Oblicuticus are the most wonderful discovery of modern times.</p>

<stage>(attendant stands up)</stage>

<p>This young man is a martyr to science. Here you have the work of nature. Here the work of art. Here is the
kinky hair here.</p>

<stage>(stage business with hair and skin color)</stage>

<p>The long, silky straight hair, here the bronze of nature, here the peachlike complexion. Remember, I leave here tomorrow for Gatorville, Florida.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VOICES</speaker>

<p>Give me a bottle, give me a bottle.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>DR. STRAIGHT</speaker>

<p>Wait a minute ― I'm not here to sell, I'm only advertising these two grand articles, Straightaline and Oblicuticus, and after dispensing with a few coin of the realm, if you will accompany me to Skinners, I will place a few bottles of Straightaline and Oblicuticus at your disposal. Mind you, I'm not here to sell but to advertise. I'm not here to make money, but to give it away.</p></sp>

<stage>(he throws coins and exits. A quartet ― The Barbers Society of Philosophical Research ― enters and sings "Annie Laurie")</stage>

<l>Maxwelton's braes are bonnie, Where early fa's the dew,</l> 
<l>And 'twas there that Annie Laurie gave me her promise true.</l> 
<l>Which ne'er forgot will be, and for bonnie Annie Laurie</l>
<l>I'd lay me doon and dee.</l>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<stage>(calcium artist in the summer, member of the B. S. of P. R. in winter)</stage>

<p>I do think the colored race is the biggest set of fools I ever cast my optics against.</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter HENRY STAMPFIELD, letter carrier, from the door of the Intelligence Office.)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>Hello. Mose, what are you kicking about?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>Ain't kickin' at all. Got both feet restin' right on the ground what they belong. I'se just naturally disgusted with the frivolities of the colored population of dis country.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>You shouldn't let trifles annoy you. I'll dare say you'll find the population of Dahomey quite as much a source of annoyance as the colored population of this country. Your exalted opinion of the ideal life to be found in a barbarous country is beyond my comprehension.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>It's all right for you, son, to argue that way, 'cause you 'specs to live and die amongst these white folks here in the United States, but the colonization society that leaves this country for Dahomey takes a different view of the matter. In the first place, we've 'vestigated the country and found out just what's what.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>In other words, the existing conditions.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<stage>(doubtfully)</stage>

<p>Yes. Everything points to success. They tell me that gold and silver in Dahomey is plentiful, as the whiskey is on election day in Bosting. The climate's fine ― just the right thing for raisin' chickens and watermelons. It never snows so you don't need no clothes

<stage>(pauses)</stage>

sich as the people wear here, and who know but what you can get a few franchises from the king to start
street cars, 'lectric lights and saloons to running.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>You've fine, big ideas, but suppose the natives suddenly don't take kindly to the new order of things and refuse to be electric lighted, salooned and otherwise fixed up with blessings of civilization. Suppose they look upon you as intruders and instead of receiving you with open arms

<stage>(pause)</stage>

make war on you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<stage>(slowly)</stage>

<p>If it comes to that, we'll arrange with dem gentlemen like Uncle Sam did with the Indians.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>How is that?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>Kick the stuffin' out of dem and put them on a reservation.</p></sp>

<stage>(GEORGE REEDER, who runs the Intelligence Office, enters and crosses as if to enter the office.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>Hello, there Reeder. I've got a registered letter for you. I was just in the office, but didn't like to leave it.</p></sp> 

<stage>(business of signing receipts, etc.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>I suppose you and Mose were having one of your regulation arguments about Dahomey, eh?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>Bye the bye, when does the Colonization Society leave for Dahomey?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>They don't go direct from here to Dahomey. They leave here tomorrow for Gatorville, Florida, where they join the main body. I don't know when they start for Dahomey. I may go along myself. The fact of the matter is, they are in session in my office at this moment.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<stage>(STAMP starts to exit but MOSE interrupts)</stage>

<p>Just wait a minute, Stampfield. I forgot to give you this letter. It's for my brother. You know he's the fountain head of this whole scheme to go to Dahomey. It's the only thing we ever did agree on.</p>

<stage>(voices inside as if quarreling)</stage>

<p>That's the first argument I've missed since I've been a member of the Society.</p></sp>

<stage>(exit MOSE)</stage>

<sp><speaker>STAMPFIELD</speaker>

<p>Well, Reeder, if you do go to Dahomey, accept my best wishes for success. So long.</p></sp>

<stage>(He exits. Enter the quartet singing "Annie Laurie." They cross the stage and exit, the singing dying out by degrees.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Well, that's a jolly crowd.</p></sp>

<stage>(looking in the direction of the singers. Enter Mrs. STRINGER, a widow and a clothes dealer in forsaken patterns).</stage>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Yes, they couldn't help but be jolly. They haven't got anything on their mind but their hair.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Mrs. Stringer.</p>

<stage>(bows politely)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Has anyone asked for me during my absence?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Only Mrs. Waite.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>It's a wonder she wouldn't get tired of that.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Of what?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Of calling when I'm out, and keeping me waiting for that little bill that's been standing nearly two months. She owes me for the biggest bargain that ever slipped through my fingers. I sold her a silk dress worth three dollars and twenty-five cents a yard that belonged to Mrs. Mountine for a beggarly twelve dollars, and she still owes me ten dollars and ninety-eight cents of that. A bargain debt. I don't see what service a dress that Mrs. Mountine could wear would be to a tiny little woman like Mrs. Waite.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Why, Mrs. Mountine weights 250 pounds if she weighs an ounce and Mrs. Waite not more than 115 pounds or twenty pounds at the most.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Yes, but Mrs. Waite has three children ― all girls.</p>

<stage>(if audience doesn't catch on, add the following)</stage>

<p>And there's enough goods in that dress to make them all dresses. Don't you know, Mrs. Reeder, I've got a notion to take advantage of the cheap rate that the Dahomian Colonization Society is getting from here to Gatorville, Florida. I've got a lot of dresses of good material but ancient as to style I might dispose of. You know they are still wearing</p>

<stage>(name something fashionable about eight or ten years ago)</stage>

<p>in Florida.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Not a bad idea at all. I'm thinking of going myself. If you make up your mind, let me know.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(starting to enter the office)</stage>

<p>Mr. Reeder.</p>

<stage>(coquettish)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>Mrs. Stringer</p>

<stage>(bowing. Exit Mrs. STRINGER)</stage>

<p>Clever woman</p>

<stage>(opens letter)</stage>

<p>Now we'll see who this is from.</p>

<stage>(reads aloud)</stage>

<p>Mr. intelligence man . . .</p>

<stage>(turns letter over and looks at address)</stage>

<p>Send to my address at once two detectives Box 13, Gatorville, Florida. I lost last Friday, which was the thirteenth of the month, a silver casket with a cat drawed on the outside and a cat's eyes on the inside. A friend of mine give me your address and said you could furnish anything from a Chinese laundry to a bull pup, and that is why I write to you for a couple of detectives. Inclosed find second-class fare for detectives and two dollars extra if they find the cat's eye, as it is very valuable. P. S. Don't forget to send the detectives. Respectfully yours, Cicero Lightfoot, Box 13, Gatorville, Florida.</p>

<stage>(laughs)</stage>

<p>Alright, Mr. Lightfoot, I'll try and look out for your case.</p>

<stage>(exits)</stage></sp>

<stage>(Salvation Army in the distance sing "There's a Land..." Enter cross stage from left to right; exits for about
ten seconds, then enters with bass drum large enough to obscure view of SHYLOCK HOMESTEAD, singing and beating drum. Business. Enter RAREBACK. Business. Laughs)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>What are you doing, ah, ah</p>

<stage>(laughs)</stage>

<p>What's the . . . what's the . . .</p>

<stage>(laughs)</stage>

<p>What's the matter? Where'd you get that suit of clothes and what are you doing with that drum?</p> 

<stage>(stops laughing by degrees)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Ha, ha, it's funny, ain't it?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Don't get mad because I laugh, but on the level, you're a sight . . .</p>

<stage>(laughs)</stage>

<p>that coat . . .</p>

<stage>(laughs)</stage>

<p>but you know, I'm your friend.</p>

<stage>(extends hand as if to shake hands. SHYLOCK refuses)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Go on away, go on away. Every dog has his day, and you've had more 'n' your share, and I've figured out your case to a focus. The more days a dog has, the more days a dog wants, and you've jest naturally got dog enough in you to want every day.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>You ain't mad sure enough, are you, Shy? See, I call you by the name that Mother used to call you, Shy. You
ain't mad are you, Sherry?</p>

<stage>(burlesque pathos)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>No, I ain't mad. I've been laughing every since we got off that boat we come up on from down south. Ha, ha, ha.</p>

<stage>(sarcastically)</stage>

<p>I'm laughing 'cause I worked all the winter and then got worked for every cent I made while I was on the boat coming up here. I'm laughing 'cause three days after I git in town after workin' all the winter, I've got to blow the bass drum in the Salvation Army to keep from starving to death.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Well, it ain't my fault that you've got that drum. Neither is it my fault that you worked all the winter and haven't got anything now. I told you not to speculate with your money.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Spec-a-late! Spec-a-late! Den I didn't lose my money shootin' craps? I lost it speculatin'?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>It won't do any good for you and I to squabble over what can't be helped. I'm in just as bad a fix as you are, and I believe all our bad luck came through the silver box I got hold of just about three hours before we struck the wharf.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I don't know nothin' about our bad luck, but I do know all about my bad luck, when the man came on board the boat with that rusty lookin' coat on and wanted to sell that silver box, I was the fust man that reached out my hand to get it, but jist as soon as I seen dat a cat was scratched on the back, I turned round three times, walked backwards four steps, throwed a hand full of salt over my left shoulder, and I give him back that box so quick, if I was superstitious, I'd a swore I seen that cat's whiskers move.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Shy, did you see inside that box?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>No sah, the outside was enough for me.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>There was a cat's eye in that box and it looked as if the eye was alive.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>You know a cat's got nine lives anyhow, and if that cat's eye ain't been dead but once, it's got eight more chances. Look here, you ain't got that thing in your pocket now have you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>No, I just left the fellow that I sold it to just before we got off the boat. Do you remember how many times that box changed hands before I got hold of it?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Yes, fust that man with the rusty yaller coat offered to sell it for a dollar and six bits, then I come purty near havin' it. Say, don't you know every time I think of how near I come to havin' that box, it gives me the shivers.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Why? You ain't superstitious.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Not excruciatingly, but then cats is bad luck, and that's all there is to it, but to get back to the subject, he finally sold the box for six bits and that bowlegged cook that bought it had that box just thirteen minutes when he got broke, and the man he sold it to had thirteen dollars, and after speculatin' with a crosseyed barber about four minutes, the thirteen dollars and the box changed hands again. Jist about that time I begun speculatin' myself, and I lost sight of it until I saw you with it jist before the boat landed. After the boat landed, it was a case of root hog or die til I struck a job blowin' the drum.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>You don't blow a drum, you beat a drum.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>If you carried this drum far as I did, you'd know there's a lot of blowin' attached to this job. Yes, I'm blowing this drum.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Well, we won't argue whether you beat or blow the drum. The financial question interests me more than anything else. You haven't got a cent. Neither have I. What are we going to do?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I'm goin' to keep my job in the Salvation Army.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<stage>(pathetically)</stage>

<p>Shy, I don't like to hear you talk that way. We've been with each other all our lives. It's been a little rocky at times, I'll admit, but we've always managed to pull through our good luck and our bad luck, our sunshine and our rain, but we've shared them all alike</p>

<stage>(pauses)</stage>

<p>together.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<stage>(about to cry)</stage>

<p>You knowed I didn't have a cent when I got off that boat and today's the fust time in three days I've put my feet under a table.</p>

<stage>(pauses to wipe away a tear. RAREBACK also wipes a tear away)</stage> 

<p>Then I didn't have nothin' but pork and beans.</p>

<stage>(business)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<stage>(Enters from Intelligence Office, letter in hand. He starts as if to leave, but stops and mediatatively notices SHYLOCK and RAREBACK)</stage>

<p>I wonder if . . . by Joe, I'll ask them anyway.</p>

<stage>(RARE and SHY start to leave)</stage>

<p>Gentlemen, just a minute. Are you looking for work?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Not if we can find anything else to do.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<stage>(pushing SHY back)</stage>

<p>Yes</p>

<stage>(slowly),</stage>

<p>we would like to have a job.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Yes, we'd like to have a job, but we weren't lookin' for no work.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Shut up! Let me talk to the gentleman. We are not engaged at the present time and wouldn't mind something light.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>My name is Reeder.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>And mine is Rareback Punkerton. Allow me to introduce my friend, Shylock.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>A strange coincidence. One might almost say your names were synonyms with the position I'm about to offer you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>If the job's as heavy as the language, excuse me.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Go ahead, Mr. Reeder.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>I want a little private detective work done in connection with this letter I hold here in my hand. I'll explain. An old gentleman living in Gatorville, Florida, being a little superstitious</p>

<stage>(business for RARE and SHY)</stage>

<p>has lost an insignificant article to which he sets great store. He considers the article of inestimable value and has offered a reward of five hundred dollars for its return. Now, I've come to the conclusion that the old man in question has not lost the article, but being overcareful, he has hidden the aforesaid article from himself, as it were. So I think by careful search you would very likely find the article among some of his effects that he had overlooked; however, he imagines it has been stolen.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>I guess we could handle the case, eh, Sherry?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Well, I hope so, John.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>The lost article is a silver casket.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What's he talkin' about, a coffin?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>The casket in this instance happens to be a little silver box. Beautifully ornamented on the center of a perfectly smooth and highly polished surface is engraved a cat.</p>

<stage>(SHY funny fall business)</stage>

<p>What's the matter with your friend?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>He has cat-aleptic fits.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>If you will step in the office, we will talk the matter over.</p>

<stage>(starts inside)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>You go on and be a detective. I'll keep my job in the Salvation Army.</p>

<stage>(picks up drum)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>REEDER</speaker>

<p>How's that?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Go right ahead, Mr. Reeder. We'll join you in a few minutes.</p>

<stage>(exit REEDER. RAREBACK snatches the drum from SHY and joyfully exclaims)</stage>

<p>You don't want that drum now. You don't know when you're in good luck. The silver box he's talking about is the one I sold the fellow that I just left down in Graball's saloon. We'll go down there, bring him up here. You go in and borrow three dollars from Reeder, buy the box, but we won't tell Reeder we've got it. Then we'll go down to Gatorville, Florida, for a bluff, live a week in clover, then give the old man the box and get the five hundred, eh?</p>

<stage>(slaps SHY on the shoulder)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Get the money first. The way you tell that sounds so natural. I could feel myself separatin' that old man from that five hundred . . if it wasn't for that cat.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Instead of being bad luck, a cat turns out to be the best friend we ever had. After this you ought to hug and kiss every cat you run across.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I've got to admit if it wasn't for that cat's picture, you couldn't tell that box from no other silver box; therefore, I'm bound to respect cats but no fust-class detective ain't goin' round huggin' and kissin' cats, no matter how much he respects them.</p></sp>

<stage>(RAREBACK starts to exit just before SHYLOCK finishes: Song "Ambulance")</stage>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(from a window to a passerby)</stage>

<p>Excuse me, but would you please knock on that Chinaman's door for me.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>PASSERBY</speaker>

<stage>(knocking on the door of the Chinese restaurant)</stage>

<p>Say!</p>

<stage>(the door opens. Chink singing inside doesn't answer at once. Passerby calls again loudly)</stage> 

<p>Say, if you've got time to stop hitting that pipe, there's a lady across the street that wants you!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ME SING</speaker>

<stage>(Chink ME SING appears with pipe in hand)</stage>

<p>You get away. I call policeman.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>PASSERBY</speaker>

<p>Get out, you pigtail. You've got rats in your kitchen.</p></sp>

<stage>(exit laughing. Chinaman continues quarreling in dialect)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(calling loudly)</stage> 

<p>Me Sing, Me Sing! Never mind the man. Bring me something to eat. I'm starving.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ME SING</speaker>

<p>What do you want?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Bring me some Chinese ham and eggs.</p> 

<stage>(addressing friends)</stage>

<p>What do you want?</p>

<stage>(to ME SING)</stage>

<p>One order of bird's nest soup.</p>

<stage>(addressing friend number two)</stage>

<p>and you?</p>

<stage>(to ME SING)</stage>

<p>And one order of shark fins. Be sure and bring over sugar for the tea and above all things, hurry.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>ME SING</speaker>

<stage>(repeats the orders in dialect and exits. "Song of the Colonization Society")</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>The five minute recess has been revoked, and your presence is requested on the inside.</p></sp>

<stage>(After song, enter RAREBACK, SHYLOCK, and HUSTLING CHARLIE, arm in arm boisterously) </stage>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>Why there's nothin' to it. I'm goin' to join this Colonization Society, blow over to Africa with them and get the money. Just imagine reading this over the door, "Hustling Charlie, Keeper of the Royal Dice Box to his Majesty Ruben, the First King of Dahomey," eh, boys?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>I never heard of this scheme before. Tell us about it.</p></sp>

<stage>(business of RAREBACK and SHY looking for box) </stage>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Yes, explain the circumstances.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>Well, there's a society down in Florida that's been pilin' up coin for years. Now that they're flush, they're goin' to go blow. They ain't satisfied to see their noodles ain't swelled on account of their dough, but they figure this country's a dead one. Some bloke tipped off Dahomey as the original Klondike and they're goin' against the brace, hook, line, and sinker. I'm goin' to steer the gang down to Gatorville where the main Gazaboo of the whole push hangs out. Say, fellows, I get two dollars a head from the captain of the dugout that snatches 'em away from this burg, and I've got a contract with a medicine shark, in all cases of sea sickness, we split the purse fifty-fifty. If anybody pegs out on the trip, I've got an undertaker waitin' at the wharf that gives me 35 percent of the net. Am I asleep at the switch, ask me?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Shy and me are going down to Gatorville on a little business ourselves. If you'll let us in on that graft of yours, we might make that trip to Dahomey.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<stage>(starting to leave the office)</stage>

<p>Well, I'll think it over. I've got some business inside, boys.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Wait a minute, Hustler, I've got a little business with you outside. You remember that box with a cat scratched on the back?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>Yes, what about it?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I was just thinkin'. I was just thinkin'.</p> 

<stage>(business)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>Thinkin' what?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I'd like to have that box for a watch charm and I'll give you three dollars for it, cash money.</p>

<stage>(RAREBACK laughs)</stage>

<p>What you laughin' at? You sich a fine detective, I guess you kin get it for two dollars.</p></sp>

<stage>(RAREBACK continues to laugh)</stage>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>I'm sorry I haven't got it, boys. I just sold it to a fellow that was going aboard on a ship that was about to sail. He just got there as they was pullin' in the gang plank.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Is you sure the fellow that went up that gang plank is the one you sold the box to that had the cat scratched on the back?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>HUSTLING CHARLEY</speaker>

<p>No chance to be mistaken.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>When he went up the gang plank, did he have this box with the cat scratched on the back ― in his hand? HUSTLING CHARLEY
Say, since I come to think of it, he had a big satchel in one hand, he was fishin' around in his pockets with the other hand, and the box in his mouth. Say, I'm goin' inside. I'll see you when I come out.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>What in the world did you ask all those questions for?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What's the use of being a detective if you can't ask questions even if you do know it won't do no good.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Well, Sherry, we'll have to keep up our bluff anyway, so we'll go down to Gatorville, Florida, make old man Lightfoot think we are looking for the box he lost, and if we're lucky, we may get a chance to go to Dahomey with this emigration society.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Say, man, have you got any idea how fast you'se carryin' me through life. Ten minutes ago, I was a soldier in the Salvation Army. Five minutes after that I'm a detective, and now you want me to be an emigrant.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(as if suddenly remembering. Smiling)</stage>

<p>My cook.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>Your cook?</p></sp>

<stage>(enter ME SING)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Yes, there he is. Come here, Me Sing.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>For heaven sake. He's a Chinaman.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Don't get excited. He won't bite you. My doctor's put me on a chop suey diet and I'm compelled to have him.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<stage>(calling loudly)</stage>

<p>Rosetta, Rosetta.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ROSETTA</speaker>

<stage>(entering from house, answering)</stage>

<p>Yes, M'am.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>Show Mr. Chop Suey to Mrs. Stringer's room.</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter Mrs. LIGHTFOOT, Dr. STRAIGHT, MOSES LIGHTFOOT, HUSTLING CHARLIE, and REEDER)</stage>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Ladies and gentlemen, allow me to introduce my friends, Dr. Straight, Mr. Reeder, and Mr. Hustler. These is high society gentlemen from the North wid great reputations.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>Well, they don't look it. But I might be mistaken.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>You certainly is 'cause dey know all the secrets.</p></sp>

<stage>(Finale for Act I)</stage>

<stage>Society</stage>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<lg type="verse">
<l>To get in high society</l>
<l>You need a great reputation,</l>
<l>Don't cultivate sobriety</l>
<l>But rather ostentation,</l>
<l>A lot of gold lay'd by in gilt-edged stocks,</l>
<l>A few town lots, let's say a dozen blocks,</l>
<l>A high-toned house that builded upon rocks,</l>
<l>Then you're in society!</l>
</lg>


<lg type="verse">
<l>To get in high society</l>
<l>I've always had an ambition,</l>
<l>And since I've got the brass, now we</l>
<l>Are sure to have position.</l>
<l>A royal prince my little girl shall wed,</l>
<l>For since the days of lords and dukes have sped,</l>
<l>It takes a prince to put you at the head</l>
<l>Of the best society!</l>
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>PANSY</speaker>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Surely you're only mocking,</l>
<l>Such levity is simply shocking</l>
<l>Your prince for me would be too far above</l>
<l>A royal prince is he I love.</l>
<l>Besides where is this prince for me to love?</l>
</lg></sp>

<p>CHORUS</p>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Just to think of a house on some big avenue,</l>
<l>(South Fifth will do.)</l>
<l>And a prince who would spend all his time wooing you,</l> 
<l>(And your money too!)</l>
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>PANSY</speaker>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Love looks not at estate. Oh No!</l>
<l>T'were folly one should think it so.</l>
<l>The beggar maid becomes a queen</l>
<l>Who through her lover's eyes is seen.</l>
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>PANSY AND LEATHER</speaker>

<lg type="verse">
<l>We care not for the world of fools</l>
<l>Love dignifies the soul ― it rules.</l>
<l>The pomp of kings the pride of state</l>
<l>Are naught when love o'er-takes the great.</l>
<l>The humble cot becomes a throne</l>
<l>Whose dwelling place love makes his own,</l>
<l>So all man's heart and being makes his own,</l>
<l>So all man's heart and being sing</l>
<l>Love is the King! Love is the King!</l>
</lg></sp>

<stage>(Curtain)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Act 2, Scene 2</head>

<stage>(Road a short distance from Gatorville. Enter RAREBACK and SHYLOCK disguised) </stage>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Come on, Shy, we're on the right road. Here's a sign post. "Gatorville One . . . one . . . </p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What's that? Gatorville, one hundred miles yet?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>No, no, Gatorville. One mile and some more.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Some more miles.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Come on. It can't be much further. Look, you can already see the house tops.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I've been having that same bird's eye view of dem houses ever since I got off dat train.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>A detective is never supposed to get tired. Why Nick Carter or Old Sleuth would laugh at the idea of a detective wanting rest. At the rate we're going, it will be plumb dark before we get into the town.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I ain't worryin' about gittin' into the town. If those people find out we ain't no regular detectives, the thing to figure on is how to get out of town.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>You're just as much a detective as you're ever going to be. I can see now that you'll never be a Nick Carter or an Old Sleuth.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>You always castin' up reflections. I never heard of dis man Nick Carter or old Hoof either.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Never heard of Nick Carter and Old Sleuth? Why, Shy, they're the greatest detectives in the world. Nick Carter is the only man living that's been shot through the heart forty-one times, and Old Sleuth's been knocked in the head with his arms tied behind him and a gag in his mouth and throwed in every sewer in the country.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>With that kind of treatment as a regular diet, how long is a man supposed to last?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Why say, Shy, that ain't nothin'. Old Sleuth and Nick Carter were both sent out to a western town to trace up some bankrobbers. The robbers got word of it somehow and way-laid the train about thirty miles from town. Imagine a mountain pass about fifty thousand feet above the level of the sea, a bridge suspended in mid-air over a chasm one thousand feet deep. A stormy night. The snow falling thick and fast and not a ship to be seen. The robbers, after removing the middle span of the bridge, fled like specters down the track to a curve a hundred yards away, and there behind a huge boulder lay in wait for the train. On rushed the fast mail. Every passenger was asleep excepting Nick Carter and Old Sleuth, and they were playing pinochle in the smoking apartment of the car. Crack, crack, crack and the whiplike report of a gatling gun rang out on the midnight air. Nick Carter was seen to rise suddenly to his feet and take from the hat rack a bottle of rye whiskey, take a drink and light a cigar and coolly raise the window to prevent the broken glass from entering the wounds made by the bullets of the bandits. Old Sleuth, always on the alert, threw a keg of beer out of window, and the robbers ceased firing long enough to secure the beer, by which time the train was well on its way to the deadly bridge, little dreaming of the danger ahead. Nick Carter sat down to trim his corns, when Old Sleuth whose hearing was wonderfully acute said: "Nick, the middle span is out of that bridge ahead. I can hear the air sucking the broken rails. Something must be done and at once. Quick as a flash, Nick cut the bell cord
with his corn knife, plunged through the window, caught the telegraph wire, which broke with his weight and swung him over the chasm. Letting go the wire, he dropped to the bottom, attached the bell cord to the span that had been removed, which fortunately had landed on a bed of marsh and remained intact, passed the other end to Old Sleuth, who had by this time reached the cow catcher of the engine and with superhuman effort, the span was snatched in place, the lives of the sleeping passengers saved.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>How deep did you say that chasm was?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>One thousand feet.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Then I suppose this Nick Carter having rubber soles on his shoes, hit himself on top de head and bounced back in de smoking department of de car and played pinochle till he got to town.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Nothing so unreasonable as that occurred. An artificial lake at the head of the gap used as a reservoir became flooded and burst its banks, the torrent of water swept through the chasm and carried Nick Carter to the town thirty miles away and landed him on the platform of the depot just as the train pulled in with Old Sleuth standing on the cab of the engine smoking a Child's cigar.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I know it's taking advantage of good nature to ask any more questions, but would you kindly let me know if the robbers was apprehended.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<stage>(laughing)</stage>

<p>Now I can see that you are improving. Only a first-class detective would use that word "apprehended." Yes, they were caught after a number of even more blood-curdling incidents that I've related to you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Jist the finishing incidentals'll do.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>The robbers, after securing the beer that Old Sleuth threw out the windows, descended to a valley twenty-six thousand two hundred and six feet below.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>By actual measurement?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Yes, by actual measurement, and after drinking the beer, lay down to collect their thoughts.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>How many robbers was there?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Three.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I believe that part of the story.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>What part?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>The part where the three robbers after drinking a whole keg of beer between them ― laid down.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Nick Carter opened his satchel on the platform of the depot and took out an air-ship while Old Sleuth, unscrewing the top of his walking cane, removed a large electric light plant.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<stage>(interrupting)</stage>

<p>Never mind. You needn't explain no more. I can see them robbers was up against it.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Come on, Shy, I'll tell you the rest of the story as we go along.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>You ain't going to tell me the rest, 'cause I'm jist naturally ashamed to listen to you.</p></sp>

<stage>(exit RARE laughing, followed by SHY)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Act 2, Scene 3</head>

<stage>(Interior with transparent windows showing a porch. CICERO LIGHTFOOT and wife are busy getting the
room in order)</stage>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<stage>(to Mr. L., who is gazing vacantly at the lights)</stage>

<p>Mr. Lightfoot, if you have no objections, would you mind telling me why you are standing there totally oblivious of your surroundings. You look like you are in a trance.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>I was jest standin' here thinkin' what a shame it was that Master John died so soon after he built this house. You know he traveled all over the world, and it seems to me he had everything put in this house that he had seen in anybody else's house, even these 'lectum lights, and then after all the trouble he went to, make everything so comfortable, he dropped out and didn't have a chance to enjoy it.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>Well, if he hadn't dropped out, you wouldn't have dropped in. Of course, it was very nice of old man Goodman to will you this property, and you ought to be very grateful to him for no other reason than that he outlived all his heirs. But I lose my temper when you say Mars John. Why don't you say Mr. Goodman?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Well, I 'pose I could say Mr. Goodman jest to please you, but when I think of the many kind things Mars John done for me . . .</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<stage>(interrupting)</stage>

<p>There, there, you needn't go over all that stuff again. I know it by heart ― you're as obstinate about this as you are to the faults of that dear daughter of ours.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>You see, if you had been raised down here, you wouldn't feel so bad about the customs of the country. Of course, up there in Boston where you come from, it's different, and poor Rosetta, that chile's jest growed up like a wild weed. She means well.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<stage>(interrupting)</stage>

<p>She might mean well, but she never does well and . . .</p>

<stage>(sound of crash)</stage>

<p>Heavens! What is she done?</p>

<stage>(rushes of calling)</stage>

<p>Rosetta!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CECILIA LIGHTFOOT</speaker>

<p>Dat's Rosetta clearing the dishes off the table.</p> 

<stage>(pause. Crash outside)</stage>

<p>I wonder if there's anything broke?</p></sp>

<stage>(exit. Enter RAREBACK climbing over porch rail burglar fashion. He enters the room, examines the doors, and blows out lights. SHY from outside whistles mysteriously two or three times, then calls for RAREBACK)</stage>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What's the matter with that light?</p></sp>

<stage>(pauses for answer. No answer comes, then he whistles. RAREBACK goes to the porch and leans over the rail, looks down to the ground and says)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Get a move on, you down there. Climb over the fence. Look out. That's a dog house. That's right. Come around the path. There you are. Now climb up this post.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>It's so dark down here I can't see no post.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Pssst.</p>

<stage>(pointing to the post)</stage>

<p>Here's the post. There's a ladder over there. Use that.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I told you once it was dark down here. How you 'spect me to see a ladder. </p>

<stage>(loud noise)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<stage>(indicating the spot)</stage>

<p>That's it. Now pick it up. Place it here and hurry up.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Never mind me hurryin' up. When I get up there, don't you let me find you trying to hurry down.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<stage>(impatiently)</stage>

<p>Stop that noise and come on.</p>

<stage>(leaves porch, comes inside, examines doors. SHYLOCK enters)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Look here, Rareback, ain't we takin' a mighty long chance comin' in these people's house this way?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Pssh, don't talk so loud. There must be a mystery surrounding everything we do.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Yes, and if we keep down these kind of tricks, we'll be surrounded all right enough, and it won't be with no mystery either.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Shut your mouth and listen to me. You know that that cat's eye ain't here in this place, and I know it ain't here. Now we've got to tell this old man some sort of a fish story to keep up our reputation as detectives.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I don't know nothing about no fish.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Psh . . . I have it!</p>

<stage>(whispers to SHY, who laughs)</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I know that yarn backwards.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Someone's coming. Stand still</p></sp>

<stage>(enter CICERO LIGHTFOOT singing softly. On entering the room, he stops suddenly) </stage>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>I thought I left them lights lit.</p>

<stage>(turns on light)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Is your name Cicero Lightfoot?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Dat's my name, but who is you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Tell him who we are, Shy.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>We're a couple of detectives.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>From Boston.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<stage>(mysteriously closes the door)</stage>

<p>Den you'se the gentlemen I sent for. I'm awful glad you come. If you don't find that cat's eye fore I leave, I want you to go right along with us to Dahomey, 'cause I kinda think I know who's got it.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RARE AND SHY</speaker>

<stage>(very loud)</stage>

<p>Good.</p>

<stage>(business for old man as RARE and SHY take out notebooks and write)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>When did you first lose this cat's eye?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>He didn't lose it but once.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Last Friday a week ago.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>R &amp; S</speaker> 

<p>Good.</p>

<stage>(business with notebooks)</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What was your father's first name?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Ephriham Lightfoot.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>R &amp; S</speaker> 

<p>Good.</p>

<stage>(business with notebooks)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Do you drink gin?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>I takes a drop now and then.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Have you any in the house now?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>A gallon jugfull.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>R &amp; S</speaker>

<p>Awful good.</p></sp>

<stage>(RARE pulls SHY's sleeve)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<stage>(to CICERO)</stage>

<p>Excuse me.</p></sp>

<stage>(RARE and SHY hold consultation)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>We've got a surprise for you, ain't we Shy?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<stage>(to RARE)</stage>

<p>I'm ashamed to look him in the face.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>Do you know Captain Kidd?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>What's that got to do with me?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Do you think that he'll stand for it?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RAREBACK</speaker>

<p>We'll tell him anyway.</p></sp>

<stage>(song Captain Kidd)</stage>
 
<stage>Hurrah for Captain Kidd</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>There was once a bold pilot who sailed on the sea,</l> 
<l>And he was wicked as wicked can be.</l>
<l>He never thought nothin' of cuttin' a throat,</l>
<l>Or when it came handy of sinkin' a boat.</l>
<l>His name it was Kidd, though no youngster was he,</l> 
<l>He was like a tax gatherer who sailed on the sea.</l> 
<l>An' 'tis plain that by pirating, stealing, and sich,</l> 
<l>This Captain did grow most tremendously rich.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Then hurrah for Captain Kidd,</l> 
<l>What he did, of course, he did.</l> 
<l>But from all his potted treasures</l> 
<l>I have lifted up the lid.</l>
<l>Then hurrah for Captain Kidd,</l> 
<l>For I've found the gold he hid.</l>
<l>And the money's proves a quid</l>
<l>For the sins of Captain Kidd.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>But the Captain was cautious and going alone,</l> 
<l>He sank a big pot in a hole by a stone.</l>
<l>Then potted his treasure and put on the lid,</l> 
<l>And said, "Now my money is certainly hid."</l> 
<l>But went out to sail on the same evil tack</l>
<l>And alas, I should tell it, he never came back.</l> 
<l>And so while a diggin' down there in my lot,</l>
<l>I chanced on unearthing the Captain's old pot.</l>
</lg>

<p>(Repeat Chorus)</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Spread the news!</l>
<l>Spread the news!</l>
<l>Spread the news!</l>
<l>Mistah Johnsin's found de gol'</l> 
<l>Found de gol' dat once was hid,</l> 
<l>By de pirate Captain Kidd.</l> 
<l>Spread de news!</l>
<l>Spread de news!</l>
<l>Let de people all be told</l>
<l>Mistah Johnsin's found de gold,</l> 
<l>Everybody spread de news.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(exit RARE and SHY and CICERO. Enter Mrs. STRINGER, accompanied by a bunch of girls, all talking at once.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>I'm awfully well pleased that my ideas met with your approval.</p> 

<stage>(all girls talking at once)</stage>

<p>It is very likely that all of you are right, but the trouble is your argument is bunched. Now listen, girls, and I'll show you what an advantage you have in dealing with me. I have the most fashionable dresses in stock to be seen in Gatorville, all of them made, with one exception, of imported silks, satins, and laces of the best quality and workmanship. Now</p>

<stage>(selecting a girl),</stage>

<p>I've got a dark green satin</p>

<stage>(describes old-fashioned dress)</stage> 

<p>that would just suit you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>THE GIRL</speaker>

<stage>(indignantly)</stage>

<p>Suit me!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Yes, if you were going to a Colonial ball.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>

<p>Oh!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(to another girl)</stage>

<p>And I've the most beautiful mourning costume, and mourning would be so becoming to you, your hair, your eyes.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>THE GIRL</speaker>

<p>And my feet and my hands.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>You have got charming feet and hands.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>THE GIRL</speaker>

<p>Yes, but there's nobody dead in my family.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>That's too bad. I . . . I mean you're fortunate. Remember, if I sell any of these dresses, they will be described in the fashion notes of the Beanville Agitator. The original price and the make's name will also be mentioned. Will you look at the dresses, my room is here.</p></sp>

<stage>(pointing to the door, girls exit talking. After exit)</stage>

<p>That last shot was the one that hit the mark.</p> 

<stage>(exit Mrs. S. Enter ROSETTA)</stage>

<stage>Leader of the Colored Aristocracy</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>To be the leader of the color'd aristocracy,</l> 
<l>Is my ambition.</l>
</lg>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse">
<l>Is her ambition,</l>
<l>I have a longing just the same as all the quality,</l> 
<l>For recognition.</l>
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<l>For recognition,</l></sp>

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<lg type="verse">
<l>To have folks say as I pass by,</l>
<l>She moves on a social plane, so very high.</l> 
<l>To get up on her level you needn't ever try.</l> 
<l>She's the leader of the colored aristocracy.</l> 
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<l>She's the leader of the colored aristocracy.</l></sp>

<p>(Refrain)</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>And then I'll drill these darkies till</l>
<l>They're up in high society's hypocracy.</l>
<l>They'll come my way,</l>
<l>To gain entree</l>
<l>To the circles of the color'd aristocracy.</l>
<l>Now to establish swell society for colour'd folks,</l> 
<l>I have a yearning,</l>
</lg>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse">
<l>She has a yearning</l> 
<l>And from the high ton'd 'ristocratic white folks how to lead,</l>
</lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>ROSETTA</speaker>
<l>I have been learning.</l></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<l>She has been learning.</l></sp>

<sp><speaker>ROSETTA</speaker>
<lg type="verse">
<l>All I need is lots of dough,</l>
<l>For that regulates the social scale, you know.</l> 
<l>'Twill put me in position to make the proper show,</l> 
<l>As leader of the color'd aristocracy.</l>
</lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<l>As the leader of the color'd aristocracy.</l></sp>

<p>(Repeat chorus)</p>

<stage>(Exit ROSETTA. Enter SHYLOCK, who opens Mrs. STRINGER's door. Girls scream, he closes door quickly)</stage>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Dem women must a thought I was a mouse.</p></sp>

<stage>(MRS STRINGER comes to the door)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(angrily)</stage>

<p>What do you mean by opening my door without knocking?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>Excuse me.</p>

<stage>(stuttering)</stage>

<p>Is . . . is Mr. Rareback Punkerton in there?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<stage>(indignantly)</stage>

<p>Sir!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I was looking for Mr. Rareback Punkerton.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>What would Mr. Anybody be doing in a room where I was fitting dresses on a lot of young ladies?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I don't know, ma'm, but Rareback ain't very bashful.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MRS. STRINGER</speaker>

<p>Indeed! Well sir, if you come to this door again, I shall have Mr. Lightfoot eject you from the premises, do you understand, eject you from the premises, do you understand, do you understand, eject you from the premises.</p>

<stage>(exits and slams door)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I got a right to have her arrested for threatening my personal safety. Rareback's fixin' to git me and him both in jail. He's got that old man down there in the yard diggin' up the whole place looking for a chest of gold, and ―</p>

<stage>(outside everybody "Hurrah, Hurrah!" SHYLOCK goes to porch and looks down in the yard)</stage>

<p>Dem people's down thar jumpin' up and down like they're crazy. I wonder if dem people found out Rareback
ain't no detective.</p></sp>

<stage>(enter MOSE LIGHTFOOT excitedly dancing and yelling)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>Hurrah, hurrah, hurrah, now for Dahomey.</p>

<stage>(sings)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Hurrah, hurrah, we bring the jubilee</l> 
<l>Hurrah, hurrah, wese going you and me</l> 
<l>Soon we'll be sailing far across the sea.</l> 
<l>Riding to the land of Dahomey.</l></lg>

<stage>(Dance and funny step as if he had pain in his side)</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>What's the matter down there?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MOSES</speaker>

<p>Cicero's found a chest of gold.</p>

<stage>(continues singing "Hurrah" and exits)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>

<p>I must find Rareback.</p></sp>

<stage>(singing mockingly "Hurrah" he exits. Chorus sings out from the side. "Spread the News" and enters. Hold for tableau. CICERO enters last with chest)</stage>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>Now dat I've got this gold, I'm goin' to have my pedigree wrote. There's a gentleman down in Cheaterville dat can find the Royal ancestors for anybody dat got fifty dollars to spare for his trouble. In fact, he said there was a time when every darkey was a king.</p></sp>

<stage>(song)</stage>

<stage>Evah Darkey Is a King</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Dar's mighty curious circumstance</l> 
<l>Dat's a botherin' all de nation.</l>
<l>All de yankees is dissatisfied</l>
<l>Wid a deir untitled station.</l>
<l>Dey is huntin' after title</l>
<l>Wid a golden net to snare 'em!</l>
<l>But dey ain't got all de title</l>
<l>For it is a 'culiar ting.</l>
<l>When a dahkey stahts to huntin'</l>
<l>He is sho' to prove a king.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Evah darkey is a king!</l>
<l>Royalty is jes' de ting.</l>
<l>If yo' social life's a bungle,</l>
<l>Jes you go back to yo' jungle,</l>
<l>And remember dat your daddy was a king.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>Scriptures say dat Ham was de first black man.</l> 
<l>Ham's de father of our nation.</l>
<l>All de black folks to dis very day</l>
<l>B'longs right in de Ham creation.</l>
<l>Ham, he was a king in ancient days,</l>
<l>An' he reigned in all his glory.</l>
<l>So ef we is all de Sons of Ham,</l>
<l>Natcherlly dat tells de story.</l>
<l>White folks what's got dahkey servants</l>
<l>Try an' get dem every thing.</l>
<l>You must nevah speak insulting</l>
<l>You may be talking to a king.</l>
</lg>

<p>(Repeat chorus)</p>

<sp><speaker>ROSETTA</speaker>

<p>Now Uncle Cicero, where is that picture that came from Paris that you was going to show us?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>I almost forgot that of all his pictures, dat was Mars John's favorite.</p>

<stage>(looks at wife sheepishly. She turns away disgusted)</stage>

<p>I show it to you.</p>

<stage>(exposes picture)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>ROSETTA</speaker>

<p>What the name of the picture, Uncle Cicero?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CICERO</speaker>

<p>The Czar of Dixie.</p></sp>

<stage>(song)</stage>

<stage>The Czar</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>There's a man who's mighty grand</l>
<l>Who rules supreme in Dixie land,</l>
<l>He's President, the Mayor, and the Governor,</l>
<l>He's the citizen's private counsellor,</l>
<l>You will find if you engage him in a social chat,</l>
<l>He's gentlemman, a scholar, and a diplomat,</l>
<l>'Mongst the leaders of his race he is the brightest star,</l>
<l>And throughout the whole of Dixie, he is called the Czar.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>He is the greatest thing,</l>
<l>And known afar,</l>
<l>The Black folks always sing,</l>
<l>He is the Czar.</l>
<l>His style is superfine,</l>
<l>He's always right in line,</l>
<l>He says the world is mine,</l>
<l>He is the Czar.</l>
<l>The Black folks always sing</l>
<l>He is the Czar.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>This great man's modern man</l>
<l>And does things on a modern plan</l>
<l>He's the idol of his subjects, he's their guiding light</l>
<l>And they all obey be he wrong or right,</l>
<l>In the world of fashion he is called the Beau Brummell,</l>
<l>For his manners like his clothes proclaim the perfect swell,</l> 
<l>When they held the coronation there were rulers from afar,</l> 
<l>Who were dazzled by the glory of this Dixie Czar.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat chorus)</stage>

<stage>(Curtain)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Act 3</head>

<stage>(Dark stage at rise of curtain. Swamp near the capitol Dahomey with a practical moonrise effect over a small body of water in perspective. Light gradually works up to medium moonlight. Fireflies are seen. Ballet
or chorus are costumed as frogs; the color scheme of costumes and scenery is the same. The chorus or ballet of ten girls and four men are posed beside a stream with backs to audience. Their backs are covered with leaves to look like foliage of the swamp until they turn and dance. The song "My Lady Frog" is sung by two idealized lovers in frog costumes who float down the stream in a canoe. The refrain is taken up by chorus. At the finish of the refrain, the ballet/chorus turn and face the audience to form a picture and they dance)</stage>

<stage>My Lady Frog</stage>

<stage>(sung by chorus)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Where the water-lilies cluster</l> 
<l>'Neath drooping willows;</l>
<l>When the moon so soft and tender</l> 
<l>Peeps through the trees;</l>
<l>Where the vines of brilliant lustre,</l> 
<l>Find mossy pillows;</l>
<l>Where the ferns so tall and slender</l> 
<l>Sway with the breeze,</l>
<l>There lived a lady frog, green pollywog was she;</l>
<l>Her lover tho' was one of brown.</l>
<l>Throughout the whole night long a little song sang he,</l> 
<l>And whispered for the moon was looking down.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(sung by male frog)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>My lady frog of opal hue,</l> 
<l>Here on this log,</l>
<l>I sing to you.</l>
<l>Bright as the flies</l>
<l>That light this bog,</l> 
<l>So are your eyes,</l> 
<l>My lady frog.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(sung by chorus)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>As the lovers sat a-waiting,</l>
<l>From o'er the way</l>
<l>Came a frog with chest a swelling,</l>
<l>A bull frog green.</l>
<l>Told he of a palace waiting,</l>
<l>In grand array,</l>
<l>How the lady of his dwelling,</l>
<l>Would be a queen.</l>
<l>And tho' 'tis sad to say, he took away this maid.</l>
<l>The frog of brown now croaks with pain,</l>
<l>And when the night is still, from o'er the hill, 'tis said</l> 
<l>You hear in mournful tones the old refrain.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat male solo)</stage>

<stage>(Exit Chorus and lights out. Change to Garden of the King of Dahomey)</stage> 

<stage>My Dahomian Queen</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>In Dahomey so grand,</l>
<l>Just along side the strand,</l>
<l>Lives a Moorish maid so near and dear to me.</l> 
<l>When I sought her heart and hand,</l>
<l>She made me understand</l>
<l>That if I wish'd my little bride she'd be.</l> 
<l>When the moon is brightly beamin',</l>
<l>From the azure skies a streamin',</l>
<l>In my cottage I'm a dreamin',</l>
<l>A dreamin' of our weddin' day.</l>
<l>Natives of exalted station,</l>
<l>Potentates from ev'ry nation.</l>
<l>Will be there to hear me when I say ―</l> 
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>My Dahomian queen,</l>
<l>My dusky turtle dove,</l>
<l>What a beautiful scene,</l>
<l>Me and my lady love.</l>
<l>She's so sweet and serene,</l>
<l>Fresh from the jungle green,</l>
<l>She is my Kai-o-ka-lo-nian,</l>
<l>Royal Dahomian queen,</l>
<l>My Dahomian queen.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>When I become a king,</l>
<l>All the jingle bells will ring,</l>
<l>While through the streets on palanquins we're borne.</l> 
<l>'Twill be the grandest thing,</l>
<l>Just to hear the natives sing,</l>
<l>As loyally they fall before my throne.</l>
<l>Caboceers will be our sentry,</l>
<l>'Rabian knights will be our gentry,</l>
<l>The wonder of the twentieth century.</l>
<l>A-makin' even sunlight fade.</l>
<l>Seems the breezes will be sighin'</l>
<l>Nature with itself be a-vieing</l>
<l>A-singin' while my babe and I parade ―</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat chorus)</stage>

<stage>(A women's drill team, costumed as Amazons, enters and executes a precision marching drill. They exit, and
a Dahomian explains their behavior as a local custom. Then the Caboceers march in singing)</stage>

<stage>Caboceers Entrance</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>We are the loyal subjects of King Eat-Em-All,</l> 
<l>The ruler over all our states both great and small.</l> 
<l>Great is his name, more great his fame,</l>
<l>Before his Majesty all nations prostrate fall.</l> 
<l>Forward with chargers dashing,</l>
<l>Their armor brightly flashing,</l>
<l>With bayonets a clashing</l>
<l>Like demons they hunt the fray.</l>
<l>The Caboceers! We greet with cheers!</l>
<l>The Caboceers, long be their years!</l>
<l>The Caboceers! We greet with cheers!</l>
<l>The Caboceers, long be their years!</l>
<l>Mighty their reign and glorious,</l>
<l>Their power all victorious,</l>
<l>Like gods of light before us</l>
<l>They come, the world to sway, to sway, to sway.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Brightest vision of the morning,</l>
<l>Deign to glad our longing eyes.</l>
<l>Come and with thy wonderous coming,</l>
<l>Dim the lustre of the skies.</l>
<l>Mighty ruler of our nation,</l>
<l>Hail we thee with loud acclaim,</l>
<l>Great thy name and great thy station,</l>
<l>Caboceers, long may ye reign.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Chorus enters as African chiefs, soldiers, natives, dancing girls. After march, chorus comes to front of stage, kneels and sings choral descriptive of glories of Cannibal King and Caboceers. At the middle of the choral, they rise at the words "Mighty ruler of our nation" and sway to and fro with swinging palm leaves. At the end, the chorus falls prostrate to the floor on their faces to greet SHYLOCK HOMESTEAD and RAREBACK PUNKERTON dressed as Caboceers. Song: "Every Darkey Is a King." Dialogue follows in which the box with cat's eye is found. CICERO LIGHTFOOT is disgusted with Dahomey and announces his return to America. The musical concludes with two rousing numbers: "Emancipation Day," and a triumphant cake-walk ― most popular dance of the era ― a production number that lasted twenty minutes.)</stage>

<stage>On Emancipation Day</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Streets are gay,</l>
<l>On dey way,</l>
<l>All de alleys done turn'd out.</l>
<l>Mistah Giles</l>
<l>Wid Miss Liles make a figure widout doubt.</l> 
<l>Hyeah dey come,</l>
<l>Lord dat drum</l>
<l>In de black ban' holds de sway.</l>
<l>'Cept the brass,</l>
<l>Give it sass, on Emancipation Day.</l> 
<l>Darkies standin' on tip toe,</l>
<l>Makin' goo-goos at de show.</l>
</lg>
 
<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>On Emancipation Day,</l>
<l>All you white fo'ks clear de way.</l>
<l>Brass ban' playin' sev'ral tunes,</l>
<l>Darkies eyes look jes' lo'k moons,</l>
<l>Marshall of de day a struttin',</l>
<l>Lord but he is gay.</l>
<l>Coons dress'd up lak masqueraders,</l>
<l>Porters arm'd lak rude invaders.</l>
<l>When dey hear dem ragtime tunes,</l>
<l>White fo'ks try to pass fo' coons on Emancipation Day.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>Heah um cry,</l>
<l>My oh my,</l>
<l>When de'cession shows it head.</l>
<l>Majors brown</l>
<l>Ridin' down on cart hosses deck'd in red.</l>
<l>Teeth lak pearls,</l>
<l>Greet the girls standin' dere lak dusky storms.</l>
<l>Oh! my pet,</l>
<l>What a set of owdacious uniforms.</l>
<l>Generals stiff as hick'ry sticks</l>
<l>In de dress of seventy-six.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat chorus)</stage>

<stage>That's How the Cake Walk's Done</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Cake-walking craze, it's a fad nowadays</l>
<l>With black folks and white folks too,</l>
<l>And I really declare it's done ev'rywhere,</l>
<l>Though it may be something new to you.</l>
<l>'Twas introduced years ago down in Dixie you know,</l> 
<l>By Black folks in Tennessee.</l>
<l>So just to show you,</l>
<l>I'm going to do</l>
<l>A cake walk of a high degree.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Bow to the right, bow to the left,</l>
<l>Then you proudly take your place.</l>
<l>Be sure to have a smile on your face,</l>
<l>Step high with lots of style and grace.</l>
<l>With a salty prance do a ragtime dance,</l> 
<l>Step way back and get your gun.</l>
<l>With a bow, look wise, make goo-goo eyes,</l>
<l>For that's the way the cake walk's done.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>My Grandmother told me that she used to be</l>
<l>The best cake walker in the state,</l>
<l>When she walk'd down the line, lord, chile she did shine.</l> 
<l>But of course her style is out of date;</l>
<l>The Parisians, you know, they all walk just so,</l>
<l>They call it ze cake walk dance.</l>
<l>But with me you'll agree,</l>
<l>That the folks from Paree</l>
<l>In this cake walk would have no chance.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat chorus)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Many long years ago there was poor Old Black Joe;</l> 
<l>Use to walk just like this for a prize.</l>
<l>There was big Jasper Brown, the cake walker clown,</l> 
<l>Walk'd like this with his best gal Miss Lize.</l>
<l>Old Tildy Snow, and Bill Jones, with his rheumatic bones,</l> 
<l>To see them walk was fun.</l>
<l>With that old-style prance, they have no chance</l>
<l>When this iate-style cake walk is done.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Repeat chorus)</stage> 

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>