<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0005">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, "Education in Liberia" (1899)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0005</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Education in Liberia</title>
<author/>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
<date when="1899-01">January 1899</date>
<biblScope unit="page">763-765</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>   
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51080627">Browne, Hugh M. (Hugh Mason)</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/103715">Camphor, Alexander Priestly, 1865-1919</term>
<term>Coleman, William D.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/89036420">Cook, O.F. (Orator Fuller), 1867-1949</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14310823">Hartzell, Joseph C. (Joseph Crane), 1842-1929</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/7353241">Parks, H. B. (Henry Blanton), -1936</term>
<term>Scott, I. B.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17098270">Stewart, T. McCants (Thomas McCants), 1854?-1923</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/814506">Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Little Rock (Arkansas)</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>South Africa</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-03-04" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p763" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0005.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Education in Liberia.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">
                       
<p>In his inaugural address one year ago, President William D. Coleman 
of Liberia, used the following language:</p>

<p>"It will be the unswerving policy of my administration to put forth
every effort for the encouragement of higher education in this country, 
and in this connection. I have to call attention to Liberia College of 
this city [Monrovia]. The very unsatisfactory results of the
change made two years ago in giving the presidency, of that institution 
to a foreigner, who, it appears, cannot remain in this country,
but is obliged to pass most of his time in a different climate, and
who up to the present has done nothing toward opening and carrying
or, the same impose upon me the duty of taking the control of the
college, and placing it under such auspices as may be deemed necessary 
for putting it again into active operation * * * * * In
addition to the course of study formerly pursued in the college, I
propose to have others introduced of a technical character, so that
our youth may be trained at home in all the departments of knowledge 
so necessary for the development of the resources and industries of the country."</p>

<p>As we understand it, Prof. 0. F. Cook, the representative of the
New York Colonization Society, and a learned man, is the foreigner
alluded to by the president. The professor is not only white, but a
White man, for there is a distinction to be drawn in American nomenclature. 
A Negro may be a white man, but a White man can
never be a Negro, in American parlance. Prof. Cook is of the upper case 
variety. His inability to stand the climate; and not prejudice 
against his race variety, is urged against his acceptability. The
college is inoperative in consequence. The President is wise in tak-

<pb xml:id="p764" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0005.002.jpg"/>

ing measures for re-opening the institution, into his own hands, for
one of the most crying needs of Liberia is an effective system of education, 
beginning with the primary school and running up to the
college. We suspect that, aside from the present difficulty in keeping 
the college open, the failure to begin an educational system from
the beginning, accounts for the inanition that seems to mark the existence 
and operation of the college. Higher institutions must stand
upon lower schools, and must come in response to a demand constantly fed, 
re enforced and recruited from the common schools.</p>

<p>This well ordered system Liberia does not have, and no man's personality 
or presence as president of the college is going to create a
flourishing institution till there is an unintermittent supply of lower
class youth constantly coming up to feed it.</p>

<p>Of course, the president of the college ought to be at the college.
Liberia should be his home; and President Coleman's complaint is a
good one More than that, the college head should be a Negro; but
after that, there is much to be done before the Republic can hope to
have a real college. It will be remembered that some years ago
Profs. T. McCants Stewart and Hugh M. Brown went out to take
charge of Liberia College. They returned in hopeless discouragement, 
not so much because of the dilapidation and loneliness of deserted 
college halls, as because they could see no source from which
to repeople the classes and rehabilitate the dignity and usefulness of
the institution, in the absence of a common school system.</p>

<p>The declaration in favor of courses in technical or industrial education 
is also wisely made, for the great needs of Liberia as an undeveloped 
country is skilled artisans and machinery. Here is a field
for .the young mechanics and machinists being prepared in American
schools, worthy of all attention. In all Liberia there is not a sawmill, 
ice factory, ice cream saloon, soda-water fountain, foundry, railroad, 
telephone or telegraph line. Unbounded wealth awaits the
Negro who wakes up to the opportunities before him. One thousand 
dollars cash put into any such business in Liberia will equal ten
thousand put into business in America. Skill and machinery are
what Liberia needs. The man or men who can supply them may
count his wealth in six or seven figures in a few years.</p>
   
<p>In connection with the educational question, it is interesting to
note the vigorous and effective work being done by Bishop J, C.
Hartzell, of the M. E. Church. He has proven to be tireless, clearheaded 
and consecrated in his African work, and during the months
he has been in America since his return from his field of labor, he
has labored assiduously and with wonderful success to arouse friendly
and helpful interest in African missions.</p>

<p>The General Missionary Committee, at its recent meeting, appropriated 
$19,850 for Liberia alone, and $14,775 for the Congo mission

<pb xml:id="p765" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0005.003.jpg"/>

Conference, including all the territory south of the equator. The
church has already established in Monrovia the College of West Africa, 
under the presidency of Rev. A. P. Camphor, a graduate of
Gammon Theological Seminary, who went out to Africa with Bishop
Hartzell on his first trip. A cylinder press is now being sent to the
industrial department of the college on which will be printed a newspaper. 
The Bishop is now calling for type, a job press, twenty-five
carpenters' outfits, twenty blacksmith shop outfits, ten tin-shop outfits, 
etc, the outfits to cost on an average of $25 each. Apprentice
schools are to be established in South Africa.</p>

<p>Thus it will be seen that mammoth preparations are going forward
for occupying and developing this great field. Even as we write, six
young workers, prepared for their mission at Philander Smith College, 
Little Rock, Ark., are on their way to Africa under Bishop Hartzell.</p>

<p>Dr. I. B. Scott, editor of the <bibl>Southwestern Advocate</bibl> very tersely
and properly sets forth the plans of the Bishop in his work of evangelization 
in the following sentences: "He proposes to civilize and
christianize the Africans by giving them the labor methods of civilization 
as well as the religious methods. His purpose is to push the industries 
side by side with the gospel and push the gospel through the
industries."</p>

<p>It is a plan that will succeed. And while we of the A. M. E.
Church cannot cope with the great Methodist Episcopal church in
raising money to carry on our work in Africa, we shall do well to
study their plans for the sound judgment displayed in them and, in
so far as they suit the changed circumstances, adopt them.</p>

<p>We have the advantage of the natural sympathy which the Negro
leadership in our church gives and this will accomplish much with
little money; but wise plans are indisputable to successful operation
in any case.</p>

 <p>Bishop Turner and Dr. H. B. Parks are calling for a man to establish 
in South Africa an institution of higher learning. It is a
greatly needed thing. Where is the man, well educated, trained in
business habits, with great executive force and consecrated heart,
willing to labor and to wait? Where is he? He is called for—where
is he?</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
