<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0057">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, J. W. Phelps, "International Equity" (1885)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0057</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">International Equity</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54059696">Phelps, J. W. (John Wolcott), 1813-1885</author>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<date when="1885-01">January 1885</date>
<biblScope unit="page">8-10</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54059696">Phelps, J. W. (John Wolcott), 1813-1885</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Alaska</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
</keywords>
   
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Americo-African</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10-31" who="#kln">reviewed encoding</change>
<change when="2019-04-23" who="pr">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p8"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<head type="main">International Equity.</head>

<head type="sub">By Gen. J. W. Phelps.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>The relation in which Liberia stands towards the United States
is not the same as with other countries. It is still in a colonial condition 
in some respects. A large organized association of the United
States possesses a reserved right with the Government of Liberia to
the unoccupied lands of that Government for the joint purpose of colonization. 
The American Colonization Society has the right to secure
to citizens of the United States who emigrate to Liberia a title to
lands on Liberian soil. These lands are rendered valuable and productive
by and through the agency of the Colonization Society; and
the question arises whether, in equity, the United States can impose
duties upon the produce of these lands.</p>

<pb n="p9"/>

<p>It is evident that by the terms of the Constitution, Congress has
the power to encourage commerce; and it is also evident that any 
obstruction thrown in the way of the Colonization Society, like that
of a duty on the produce of the lands which it grants, operates against
the encouragement of commerce. But not only does the agency of
that Society promote commerce, it is also a benevolent Society; in fact
it is a Missionary Society, and as such may claim the favor with which
the law regards such societies. Its operations may claim the favorable 
regard of the Government by the double title of commercial utility
and national benevolence.</p>

<p>The imposition of a tax by the United States upon the produce
of Liberian lands is virtually the same as imposing a tax or clog upon
the American Colonization Society. To show no equitable discrimination 
in favor of that Society operates like discouragement against it.</p>

<p>It is very far from both the spirit and the letter of the law of July
17, 1862, which makes a liberal provision for the interests of African
emigration from the United States. Under that law our citizens of
African descent justly claim the aid of the Government to help them
on to the Liberian lands which the Colonization Society has the
power to secure to them. It seems questionable to me whether the
executive power of the Government is not under obligation to give
some active attention to that law, if not, indeed, to secure to the Colonization 
Society its rights and interests in Liberian soil against foreign aggression.</p>

<p>An enlightened policy would impel the United States to bestow
upon the Colonization Society whatever revenues might be derived
from duties on Liberian products, be they more or less. The power
that bestows the prospective value of Western lands upon railroad
companies, ought to be equal to the bestowal of the revenue from
Liberian products upon the Society that has actually created those
products, and brought them into the commerce of the world.</p>

<p>In equity, therefore, the United States ought to exempt Liberian
products from duties; or, which would amount to the same thing
bestow them upon Colonization Society. The Americo-African
cannot have any interest in the lands of Alaska, for which over seven
millions of dollars were paid, and he would seem entitled, therefore
to some consideration in the way of lands that are possessed of value
to him, and such as the Colonization Society has the power to secure.
A tenth part of the Alaska purchase money, if bestowed upon the
colonization interests in Liberia, would, probably, give a greater return 
in the way of commercial activity than all Alaska can do.</p>

<p>Morally speaking, we have taxed African labor enough during
the last two hundred years, and may now well show it some favor.</p>

<pb n="p10"/>

<p>We are not sure as to the cost of the last expedition sent by the
Government to the Arctic seas, but we think that we have seen it
stated at somewhere near a million of dollars. For this sum the
American Colonization Society would place ten thousand colonists on
lands in Liberia, the moral and commercial advantages of which, and
perhaps the scientific ones also, would far transcend any which all our
Arctic explorations put together have secured. There would seem to
be almost a perverseness in the way that our Government and people
turn away from their African colony, so grand with future hopes, and
devote their attention to the profitless ices of the uninhabited North.
The sending of ten thousand missionaries to the barbarous nations of
Africa presents a much wider and grander field for the exercise of
Christian piety than some of the objects on which wealth is lavished
in the United States. As the United States is regarded as the asylum
of the oppressed of Europe, so Africa will become more and more the
asylum of our colored population who find themselves oppressed here.</p>

<p>We admit that we cannot claim much on the bare ground of
positive legal right on behalf of the Colonization Society; but we
urge a claim that ought to rest on an equal tenable basis with law,
viz.: that of moral obligation and of duty to the future, which it is
not safe to neglect.</p>

<p>As it was through the lowest class of men, Israelite slaves, that the
highest order of ancient civilization was imparted to succeeding generations, 
and as when that civilization became corrupt, it was then reformed 
and extended to our times again by the humblest order of men,
so there is no fitter instrumentality for extending that civilization to
Africa than the late slaves of the United States. Any view narrower
than this in dealing with the African question in its relation to the
moral duties of the United States, is far from being equal to the issues
of the day, or to the pretentions and real interests of the Republic.
Our manufacturing interests, which are so pampered at home, would
receive a more legitimate expansion by the powerful aid which we
might give, through the colonization of Liberia, to the introduction of
the wants and needs of civilization to the interior of Africa.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

