<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0084">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Washington Bee, "Revolting Savage Rites" (December 13, 1884)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0084</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Revolting Savage Rites</title>
<title level="j">The Washington Bee</title>
<pubPlace>Washington (D.C.)</pubPlace>
<date when="1884-12-13">December 13, 1884</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Connaughton, William</term>
<term>Meshiel, Ferdinand</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Dahomey</term>
<term>Lagos (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Porto-Novo (French Dahomey)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
<term>White Nile River</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-20" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">Revolting Savage Rites.</head>

<head type="sub">A Vivid Description of Mission Life in Africa.</head>

<head type="sub">A Terrible Picture at Cruelty Practised by Fetish Priests&#8212;Human Flesh at Public Sale.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>The Rev. Ferdinand <unclear>Meshiel</unclear> and the Rev. William <unclear>Connaughton</unclear> have arrived from Africa, where they have been converting the natives along the gold coast, around the White Nile and in the Soudan. The society of which they are members is known as the Society of African Missions. An interesting history of the perils of mission life was graphically related by Father <unclear>Meshiel</unclear>. From the reverend father's account human sacrifice and slave trading are still extensively carried on. Father <unclear>Meshiel</unclear> said that at Lagos, near Sierra Leone, where the parent house is established, natives are quite well educated.</p>

<p>"The natives of the second generation," the priest said, "may be called members of a civilized community. At Porto-Novo, Lagos, <unclear>Abekouta</unclear> and other stations it is not rare to find native children carrying off the prizes from the children of European parents who are domiciled in these localities. When a boy has attained the age of thirteen years he is advised by the missionaries themselves to choose a wife from among the girls of the convent school. Agriculture and the various trades are becoming factors in the community. The country was frequently devastated by famine. Whenever the rain fell too abundantly the fruits which constitute the staple diet of the natives, rotted and starvation followed. Corn not being subject to such damage, and bearing easily two crops a year, the people regard its introduction as a gift of Providence.</p>

<p>"After the kings, the priests who practice medicine are, perhaps, the greatest personages in this region. They need only to threaten to leave, and generally they at once obtain any concession they demand from these sovereigns. The huts of the common people are made of bamboo cane, thatched with palm leaves. Fishing and hunting are but little practiced, as they require bodily exertion, which is not agreeable to the natives. The disposition of these people is so mild it is a mystery how they can indulge in the practice of the cruelties, such as human sacrifices, for which they have become famous. The missionaries believe that but for the fetish priests, who are exceedingly shrewd and who have a strong interest in perpetuating these bloody sacrifices, as their power is based on them, the country could be easily civilized. Under the reign of <unclear>Gaezo</unclear>, the late king of Dahomey, human sacrifices had become comparatively rare; but his successor, <unclear>Grery</unclear>, a slave to the fetish priests, has revived them and now they are practiced with greater cruelty than ever. The number of slaves who annually perish in this way is estimated at several hundreds. The king of Dahomey is, as is know, the most ferocious and powerful ruler in the whole region. During  ten months in the year he makes incursions into the neighboring territories, capturing a large number of slaves. In this work he is chiefly assisted by his two celebrated regiments of Amazons. The prisoners taken during these expeditions are divided into three classes. One class is sold to the slave merchants of the interior, another, chiefly women, are fattened and sold to butchers, who, revolting as the fact may be, even to relate, openly sell human flesh in their shops. The third class is reserved for the sacrifices which take place in August and September, during the celebration of the "Grand Customs." These ceremonies have a double purpose: pacifying the god of war <unclear>Ogun</unclear>, and other deities; recalling the memory of dead kings and sending them supplies of men and provisions.</p>

<p>"Among these savages exists a belief that a man passing into the future life takes with him all that is placed in his grave. For this reason, in Dahomey, as in other savage countries, victims and prisoners are placed in the tomb. Not long since the king of Porto Novo died of poison administered to him by a rival for the throne. The funeral ceremonies lasted nine days. During the whole of this time numbers of victims, destined for the "Grand Customs," were sacrificed every night in the fetish forest. The missionaries living in the neighboring huts could hear the cries of the <sic>suferers</sic>, whose mutilated bodies, arranged in lines, were seen every morning in the public square of the town. The heads had been cut off and nailed along the walls of the palace. At 8 o'clock on the morning of the ninth day the new king and his <unclear>suite</unclear>, preceded by the fetish priests moved in procession to the sacred wood <sic>were</sic> the grave of the late king had been dug. The sacrifice began. Seven slaves were killed and their blood mixed with earth to form a kind of plaster with which the grave was lined. The heads of the seven victims, with food of all kinds, were deposited at the bottom. The body of the king was next lowered into the grave. Then were seen approaching nine of his women, draped in their brightest colored garments and purposely intoxicated with British "<unclear>tafia,</unclear>" or rum. Believing themselves to be the objects of an ovation they cast smiles on every side as they passed through the throng. On reaching the edge of the open grave they were made to kneel, and before they had any suspicion were stunned by a blow on the head and flung, still alive, upon the body of their royal spouse. Earth was then thrown in to cover both living and dead. A short distance from the grave a stake was prepared for the burning of the ministers but these astute politicians dressed slaves in their robes of office, and while the poor creatures were perishing made their escape. The sacrifices to the gods are marked by greater and more varied refinements of cruelty. The shrines resemble dog-houses&#8212;appropriate dwellings for their idols, which are hideous-looking monsters. These ceremonies begin with a dance. In front of the shrine a circle is formed by the leaders of the people sitting down, while the rude multitude remain standing. Holding a tuft of human hair in his hand a priest dances in the center, the circle uttering savage cries, clapping their hands or playing wild instruments resembling bells, <sic>tamborines</sic> and <sic>symbals</sic>. During the night the fetish priests provide the god with one or more victims. The most common form of sacrifice to <unclear>Ogun</unclear>, the god of war, is to behead the human offering and nail the body upside down to a tree, the head placed above the feet.</p>

<p>"At other times a young tree is stripped of its branches, bent down by means of a rope, and so held by a kind of trigger. With the exception of the head the victim is inclosed in a wickerwork globe and suspended, head downward, or his head is <sic>incased</sic> in the stumps of the leaves which form the crown of the palm tree. The priest loosens the rope, the tree springs back and the victim is left swinging in the air. Birds of prey soon dispose of his body.&#8212;<hi rend="italics">New York World.</hi></p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
