<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0104">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Missionary Review of the World, "The African Slave Trade" (1889)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0104</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The African Slave Trade</title>
<title level="j">The Missionary Review of the World</title>
<date when="1889-09">September 1889</date>
<biblScope unit="page">705-708</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Abdallah</term><!-- Sultan -->
<term>Bridoux</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/99297727">Drummond, Henry, 1851-1897</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/102441725">Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/49227869">Lavigerie, Charles Martial Allemand, 1825-1892</term>
<term>Ormieres</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry Morton, 1841-1904</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Brussels (Belgium)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>French Comoros</term>
<term>Lake Albert</term>
<term>Lake Tanganyika</term>
<term>Lucerne (Switzerland)</term>
<term>Madagascar</term>
<term>Mpwapwa (German East Africa)</term>
<term>Pemba Island</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Arab</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Catholic</term>
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-09" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p705"/>

<head type="main">The African Slave Trade.</head>

<p>Professor Drummond in the June <hi rend="italics">Scribners'</hi>, and a writer in a recent issue of the <hi rend="italics">United Presbyterian Magazine</hi>, give us a chapter of horrors on the slave traffic as at present carried on in Central Africa, so terrible, so diabolical in cruelty and atrocity as to call loudly for a combination of all the civilized nations of the world to arrest and put it down. The continuance of so tremendous a curse as this, and the rum traffic, with Africa opened, accessible on every side, to Europeans and missionaries from all lands, with great European interests already planted there and railways introduced&#8212;is a disgrace to the civilization of to-day. Combined Europe and America could put a stop to it speedily. The blood of these friendless and slaughtered millions cries aloud to Heaven; and is there no power in Christianity and in the Christian civilization of Christendom

<pb n="p706"/>

to avenge it and cause the horror to cease? Oh, for another Milton to thrill the nations as did the blind bard two centuries ago when the Duke of Savoy slaughtered the Waldensians in the valleys of Piedmont. "Cromwell flew to the rescue, raising £40,000 for the wretched outlaws. Switzerland interfered; the King of Sweden, the Elector of Palatine, and the Landgrave of Hesse Castle interceded," and the bloody work ceased. So would it be in this case, if the nations interested in Africa would rouse themselves and combine their efforts.</p>

<p>Says Professor Drummond:</p>

<p>"Do not let it be supposed that this horror is over, that this day of tribulation is at an end. This horror and this day are now. It is not even abating. <hi rend="italics">Slavery is on the increase.</hi> Time, civilization, Christianity, are not really touching it. No fact in relation to the slave trade is more appalling than this.</p>

<p>"The cause of this revived activity of the slave trade is not far to seek. It is the normal expansion of a paying business. More men engage in it; more capital is invested in it. The Arab never retires from business. With the prophets of his first small caravan he equips and heads a larger one. As the years pass, his flying columns grow larger and larger, and fiercer and fiercer. Now he can attack with impunity a region which, in former days, he must have let alone. Formerly he fraternized and traded with the great interior nations; now he overthrows and carries them off bodily. Having much capital and better fire arms, he can push farther and farther into the country, establishing depots as he goes, which become minor centers of the trade. Long ago the Arab dared not venture beyond a limited distance from the coast line. Now he pervades and almost dominates the continent. As one region after another is drained of its slaves and ivory, fresh and remoter fields have to be sought out. So home after home is made desolate, region after region is ravished, state after state is demolished, nation after nation is mowed down like grass. Such being the state of matters in the interior of the country, to talk of the civilization of Africa, till this butchery is stopped, is but a mockery. . . . It is an open secret that several large and defined markets for slaves exist in many parts of Africa and in the adjoining islands. Off the Zanzibar coast, for instance, the extensive plantations of Pemba are wrought by slave labor. Owing to the nature of the work and the fatal insalubrity of the climate the death rate here is terrible, and a ceaseless traffic with the coast has to be kept up to supply the almost daily blanks."</p>

<p>Says <hi rend="italics">Regions Beyond:</hi></p>

<p>"Cardinal Lavigerie has stated, and the statement has never been called in question, that 400,000 slaves are annually brought to the coast of East Africa. Livingstone reckoned that for every slave embarked from the coast, at least ten human beings had perished, either in the capture or on the march. Many even of the number embarked die on the voyage, or are purposely drowned&#8212;thrown overboard with stones tied to their feet&#8212;to escape capture by the cruisers. This gives <hi rend="italics">over four millions</hi> of our fellow-creatures enslaved, tortured, or killed, year by year, continually, to gratify the inhuman greed of gain of <hi rend="italics">a few murderous Arab thieves</hi>. Is this to be suffered to go on? Cardinal Lavigerie takes a much lower estimate, and assumes that only <hi rend="italics">five</hi> perish for each slave secured, but he is probably below the mark. The track of the slave-caravan is marked by a line of bleaching bones. Never, in any part of the known world, or in the pages of history, has there been such butchery and murder."</p>

<p>Father Bridoux, a Roman Catholic missionary, writes from the south-east coast of Lake Tanganyika that on his journey from Mpwapwa to the lake he passed many caravans of slaves, who were for the most part living skeletons. In spite of their miserable condition, the men wore the slave fork on their shoulders, while the women were fastened together in long lines by chains. All the children who could walk bore burdens in proportion to their size. Father Bridoux tells terrible stories of finding wretched captives who, overcome by weakness, had been left to die along the route, and who were still alive when he saw them. The Comoro Islands, south of Zanzibar and Madagascar, have in the pats been the destinations of many thousands of slaves captured by the Arabs on the mainland. The Sultan Abdallah of the Comoros has now, under the influence of Dr. Ormieres, the French Resident at his capital, issued a proclamation abolishing slavery in his islands. He forbids the purchase and sale of slaves, and

<pb n="p707"/>

announces that any person landing on the Comoros shall be free, whatever his previous condition. There are about 23,000 slaves in the Comoros, who have been brought from the mainland. March 8 the Queen of Madagascar issued a proclamation to her people, in which she says that all slaves who are landed in her dominions shall be free when they touch her soil. "If the natives of Africa are brought across the sea and introduced into any part of Madagascar to be slaves, they shall not be slaves, but free subjects."</p>

<p>From all parts of East Africa comes the same horrible story. On his second journey up the Congo Stanley found 118 villages, which on his first trip he had seen smiling and prosperous, desolated, burnt, deserted! On his present expedition, in the region between the Congo and Lake Albert, he nearly perished with all his party in consequence of famine in the desert produced by the destructive raids of the Arabs. People, villages, stores, fruit-trees, all were gone, enslaved, or killed, or burnt, and naked desolation and gaunt starvation had to be faced, where human hearts and homes abounded a year ago.</p>

<p>The brave words of Prof. Drummond ought to crimson our nation's cheek with shame, and call forth a proper response to his burning question. He asks:</p>

<p>"What will America do to help? Time was when the United States kept a cruiser on the West Coast of Africa to check this trade. But when the attitude of America to the Congo treaty is remembered, and her refusal to touch the question of the exportation to Africa of arms, ammunition and liquor,* can it be said that she keeps her place to-day in that moral reformation of the world which is the duty and privilege of all the foremost nations? Is it true of that Constitution of which she is so worthily proud, that with reference to these questions, and in the words of the Prime Minister of England: "They (the United States) have told us that, owing to the peculiarities of their Constitution, they are not very anxious to enter into obligations with foreign powers?" America has never been provincial. She must not become so. So manifold and pressing are now the interests of her own great country that she might also be pardoned if she did. But the world will be bewildered and disappointed if she separates herself now from the rest of mankind in facing those great wrongs of humanity from which seas cannot divide her and which her poorer brethren in every part of Europe are giving themselves to relieve. America does well in refusing the entanglements of European politics. Let her be careful lest she isolate herself from its humanities. None who know her will fear for a moment that the breadth of her sympathies and the greatness of her national heart will not continue to be shown in her sustained philanthropies, in her joining hand to hand with the advanced nations of the earth in helping on all universal causes which find their appeal in the world's great need and tribulation."</p>

<fw type="note">* The reader will remember that in the Conference in regard to the Congo Free States treaty, our representative refused assent to the provision excluding the importation of liquor, etc.&#8212;an eternal stigma to us!&#8212;Ed.</fw>

<p>Thank God there are signs that the two most crying evils of the nineteenth century, as they apply to Africa, are to receive the consideration which they demand. Two Congresses are to meet this autumn to deal with the difficult and tremendous problem. One is to assemble at Brussels. For more than a year the King of the Belgians has wished to convene a Congress of the signatories to the acts of the Berlin Conference. But the German troubles in East Africa prevented the realization last autumn of this desire. Now most of the Great Powers have agreed to the proposal of such a Conference to be held this coming autumn. It is to consider not only the slavery question, but the scarcely less pressing one of the demoralization of the native races by drink; and also that of the supply to them of arms and ammunition.</p>

<p>The other Conference assembles at Lucerne at the invitation of Cardinal Lavigerie from the 3d to the 10th of August next. The Council of the Canton have granted the use of the local "House of Commons," and invited the Convention heartily. The Convention will, it is hoped, represent most of the experience gathered on the painful subject, and will use

<pb n="p708"/>

its united wisdom to discuss, devise, and recommend the practical measures most likely to succeed in putting an end to the present horrible state of affairs. It will be a popular Congress, composed of the lovers of God and of men&#8212;the ministers, missionaries, philanthropists, travelers, explorers, and other benefactors of the human race. It is hoped that by means of this conference public opinion throughout Europe will be roused so that the governments will unite in such pacific plans as will lead to the suppression of the trade.</p>

<p>"The assembling of these two great Conventions," says <hi rend="italics">Regions Beyond</hi>, "is cause for profound thanksgiving to God. The evil with which they are to grapple&#8212;the East African slave-trade&#8212;has already assumed gigantic proportions, and is still growing greater. Unless it can be arrested and extirpated, the civilization and Christianization of Africa is hopeless."</p>

<p>Says <hi rend="italics">the Christian Union:</hi></p>

<p>"The British and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society has for a long time past been agitating the subject, and has done much to educate and direct public opinion in England. The most effective and hopeful instrumentality, however, is to be found in the organization of anti-slavery societies all over Europe&#8212;the noble work of Cardinal Lavigerie, who, like Peter the Hermit, has gone from country to country, pleading eloquently and passionately for the mute thousands in Africa. These anti-slavery societies are rapidly spreading in Germany, France, Belgium, Italy, Spain, and other countries, and large sums of money are being raised through their endeavors."</p>

<p>It gives us great pleasure to add that the General Assembly of the Presbyterian Church, in which President Harrison is a Ruling Elder, at its recent session in this city, directed its stated clerk to officially announce to the President of the United States that it views with horror the present slave trade in Africa, and to inquire if some steps cannot be taken for a co-operation of this country with European powers for the suppression of the traffic.</p>

<p>The New York <hi rend="italics">Evangelist</hi> adds these pertinent words to this announcement:</p>

<p>"It cannot be charged, under the circumstances, that this action is either premature or too vigorous. It might have been earlier, if the public had been sooner informed of the extent and atrocities of the slave-trade in Africa, as they are portrayed in a recent issue of <hi rend="italics">The United Presbyterian Magazine</hi>, though it might not have been more efficient. The suggestion of our Assembly's resolution should receive prompt and efficient action by Government if the way for it can possibly be opened. It certainly <hi rend="italics">can</hi> be opened, if instead of contenting ourselves with praying 'that Ethiopia may soon stretch out her hands unto God,' and with sending half a dozen white missionaries into Africa every year, we awake to efficient civil and political action under this trumpet call of Divine Providence."</p>

<p>J. M. S.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
