<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0055">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, M. A. DeWolfe Howe, "African Colonization" (1879)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0055</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">African Colonization</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/21262905">De Wolfe Howe, Mark Anthony (1809-1895)</author>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
<date when="1879-07">July 1879</date>
<biblScope unit="page">65-69</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Central America</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>African</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-10-30" who="kln">reviewed encoding</change>
<change when="2019-04-17" who="pr">Transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p65"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<head type="main">African Colonization.*</head>

<fw type="note">* An Address delivered at the Sixty-second Annual Meeting of the American Colonization Society, Washington, D.C., January 21, 1879, by the Rt. Rev. M. A. DeWolfe Howe, D.D., Bishop of Central Pennsylvania.</fw>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>No thoughtful American can withhold the acknowledgment that
there is due to people of African descent, in this country, the best that
can be done for their welfare and happiness. Their ancestors did not,
like those of European stock, come here as colonists of their own accord 
to find new homes, and achieve a higher destiny. They were the
victims of a policy then common to the civilized world. France, Spain
and England drew from the shores of Africa unwilling servants to toil
for them in their colonial possessions. And so, all along our Atlantic
border, the children of Ham, were, before we became a nation, "hewers 
of wood and drawers of water,"&#8212;menials in house and field to
other families of the human race.</p>

<p>In the progress of human events, their descendants, now numbered
by millions, are here no longer in involuntary servitude. All legal impediments 
to their advancement are removed. They are now free to
aspire after any social or civil position to which their intelligence, education, 
and moral worth may entitle them. They may amass wealth,
wield influence, hold office, like any other citizens. And individuals of
their race have achieved such distinction among us. I think there are
very few who are offended by these examples of men who have struggled 
up from the general abasement of their people, disarmed prejudice,
and fairly secured positions of prominence and respect. Enthusiasts,
who once espoused their cause when all this was impossible, and who
have visions of the future of the race which, I apprehend, can never be
realized on this continent, say,&#8212;why not let them remain where they
are, on their native soil, and work out the problem of life, under the advantages 
which now are accorded to them by the amended Constitution?
Doubtless, the great mass of them will continue; and get, and hold
possession of all the titular rights which belong to American citizens.
The removal of 5,000,000 of people across the ocean is too vast an enterprise 
to be seriously considered; most of them will abide where

<pb n="p66"/>

Providence, favoring or adverse, has fixed their lot. Yet it will be a
new chapter in human history if with all the inherent difficulties of
their position&#8212;difficulties which no change in the laws of the land can
possibly annul&#8212;they can attain to the same level of social, commercial,
and civil progression to which a dominant race of overshadowing numbers 
has long ago risen. And this perpetual inferiority will not be in
any great degree attributable to the prejudice which persists in looking
down upon a people who have once been in bondage. It is equally
true that the Indian,&#8212;civilize him as much as you will,&#8212;and the Mongolian,
&#8212;in whatever swarms he may come to our shores&#8212;can never compete 
on the same arena with the race that for a thousand years has been
in the van of human progress, and has the advantage of prepossession of
education, property and power. And so, the African, impeded by his
condition and history in this country, and crowded off from the track
of progress by competitors of traditional precedence and overwhelming
numbers, will, save in a few exceptional cases, earn a precarious livelihood 
by the sweat of his brow, hated and spurned by the laborers of
another race who dig and delve at his side.</p>

<p>The more intelligent and aspiring of African stock have a far more
inviting field of enterprise open before them on their ancestral shores.
A free Colony, which has now risen to the dignity of an independent
Republic, and which has been planted long enough to demonstrate that
it has in it the elements of permanency and progression, offers them an
unstinted share in its noble mission, and in its exalted destiny. <hi rend="italics">There</hi> 
is an unencumbered field in which they may seek advancement in all
that man esteems honorable without encountering invidious rivalry or
universal and indomitable prejudice. Here, at a disadvantage, because
their civilization is inferior to that which surrounds and overshadows
them,&#8212;thither they can carry a degree of moral and mental enlightenment 
which shall entitle them at once to social respect, and incite them
to strive for the prizes of fortune and the honors of office.</p>

<p>For, most of the colonists who have already found a home in Liberia
immigrated under far less favorable circumstances than theirs who now,
and hereafter, may embark on the same great life enterprise. They
went in comparative ignorance, just released from the tutelage of servitude, 
and invested with the terrible responsibilities of liberty in a strange
land. These have been for half a generation in the hard school of self-dependence
&#8212;introduced by philanthropists to the rudiments of book-learning, 
and through freedom have regained the consciousness, and are 
fired with the ambitions of manhood. They can contribute to the common 
stock of society there more of the ingredients which constitute
national strength, prosperity, and honor, than their predecessors could
afford.</p>

<p>The pioneers have broken up the waste and made it ready, and have

<pb n="p67"/>

beaten back the savages that would drive them from the strand;&#8212;now
is the time; and here are the men qualified by a special Providence to
go in with the winnowed grain of a higher civilization, to "possess the
land which the Lord sware unto their fathers."</p>

<p>The time for colonization has not passed by:&#8212;"the fulness" of it
has just come. The tokens of this fact are found both here and in Africa. 
The experiment of political equality, now tried among us for
nearly a score of years has not shown that all distinctions of race are or
will be forgotten. Centuries cannot efface even the factitious lines
of demarkation between the races, which a century of untoward relations 
has produced, and deeply scored. Nature forbids them to
blend; and history pronounces that they cannot stand side by side on
the same plane of elevation.</p>

<p>On the other hand, Africa was never so attractive as now. The
American Colony, to which this Society has sent out more than 15,000
settlers, is more prosperous than ever. It is recognized in the family of
Nations. Its productions and exports are increasing year by year. Its
intercourse with the more intelligent tribes of the interior is constantly 
widening and becoming more profitable. Its schools and other
institutions for the advancement of the people; its laws and administration 
of government, are growing more efficient and better adapted
to their needs. It has had no inconsiderable share in the suppression
of the slave trade, which is now denounced by all civilized nations,
and by the vigilance of their navies is almost banished from the seas.
Just considered as a home for the colored race, where there are none
to jostle them out of the way of progress&#8212;no impediment of law or 
prejudice, or preoccupation on the arena of manly effort, where succeeding 
generations may reasonably hope to surpass their fathers in all
that ennobles man and makes his life a joy to himself and a blessing
to others, Liberia is, I believe, the most inviting spot on the habitable earth!</p>

<p>But, regarding the Colony on the Coast of Africa, planted, enlarged,
cultivated, and defended by colored emigrants from the United States,
as a theatre on which men of the same race can most hopefully exercise 
and develop the manhood that is in them, we do not half appreciate 
its advantages, if we think of it as a mere isolated community, 
bounded by the geographical limits, defined in the treaties with
the barbarous tribes that compass it about; it is the gate of entrance
to interior Africa. And, what interior Africa is we are only beginning 
to know. The researches of Barth and Livingstone, and our own
Stanley, reveal to us that it is swarming with intelligent people, far superior 
to the tribes which on the sea coast have been debased by incessant 
wars, waged for the capture of prisoners to be sole to the
slave traders; that the population of the Continent is estimated at two

<pb n="p68"/>

hundred millions; that it is rich in arable lands and precious minerals; 
that navigable lakes and rivers traverse the interior, and that only 
civilization and enterprise (which are familiar to us, so that the products 
of them seem to us natural elements like fire and water), are required to 
introduce steamboats and railroads, and telegraphs. Then those vast 
resources which have been "hidden from ages and generations" shall 
be brought out and mingled with the commerce of the world, and the 
millions that now "sit in darkness" shall learn to live like men, and to 
die in hope of immortality!</p> 

<p>Among the first colonies of historic times were those planted by the 
Phenicians on the Northern shores of Africa, where France, nominally 
Christian, and thoroughly tolerant, has now her Colony of Algeria. 
England has unfurled her Red-cross banner at Sierra Leone on the West, 
at Cape Colony and Natal on the South, and Zanzibar on the East; and 
America has her watch-tower also in the cordon of Christian civilization 
which almost girts the Continent. The circumvallation about the 
stronghold of ignorance and degradation is well-nigh complete. Why 
do not these allied hosts interchange the signal of onset, and rise up, 
and go in, and possess the land for humanity, and for God? Nay, why 
have not the civilization and enterprise of Europe and America long 
since penetrated "the dark Continent," and brought its people, and its 
products into contact with the commerce of mankind? I answer&#8212;first, 
because the reports of proceedings on the Coasts have made the tribes of 
the interior afraid to deal with the pale-faced and ruthless invaders from 
beyond the sea; second, because the climatic influences of the region 
have been regarded as fatal to the white race; and finally, because hitherto 
there have been no representatives of their own branch of the human 
family who in sufficient numbers have been uplifted by the civilization 
which they have rather seen than shared in other lands, and made willing 
to return to Africa, and there to do or to suffer for the regeneration 
of their "brethren after the flesh." When the Colonies of America and 
Great Britain shall have trained or drawn to themselves from lands 
where they were once in bondage, and always in subserviency, Negro 
men of lofty hopes, and generous impulses, and practical education, and 
daring enterprise&#8212;then Central Africa will be reached by missionaries 
of civilization and religion; its resources will be developed, and circulated; 
its people will thrill with the sense of a new and higher life; and 
the story of its estrangement from the great family of nations will pass 
away. I pity the man of the swarthy skin, who, entrusted with the 
clues of liberty and education, has no ambition to follow them when 
they lead out of darkness and doubt to such a destiny,&#8212;to possibilities 
of good for himself and his progeny, nowhere else to be enjoyed!</p> 

<p>In the distribution of the human race, the sons of Ham were assigned 
to Africa; to its peculiarities of food and climate their constitutions

<pb n="p69"/>

are accommodated. A century of life in other climes has not obliterated 
this natural adaptation. Experiment has proved that colored 
emigrants from America survive and flourish where men of another race 
lose vigor, sicken and die. They are the elected redeemers of their 
Father Land. It waits their coming:&#8212;it sent them forth with tears; it 
will receive them again with joy!</p> 

<p>This Society, which once was impugned as an agent of domestic agitation, 
and again traduced as the enemy of the blacks, has in all time 
numbered among its supporters many of the distinguished divines, patriots 
and statesmen of our country. Its beneficent errand and work is, to 
aid worthy colored persons of either sex, and in any vigorous stage of 
life, who may desire to seek a home on the shores of that fruitful and 
pleasant Continent from which their fathers were torn away; to help 
them in their outfit, and to secure them a freehold on their arrival.</p> 

<p>It is a noble and far-reaching charity, conferring a blessing not only 
on its immediate recipients, but on their children and children's children, 
"even to the years of many generations;"&#8212;not only on these, but by 
them replenishing that well-spring of life and hope, in the desert, the 
overflow of whose waters will refresh, and gladden the waste places that 
lie beyond. And again, the civilization which through this medium 
shall reach at length to the waiting myriads in Central Africa will give 
back a reflected light to the source of its emanation, and the entire 
world will be brighter and happier when there shall no longer be a dark 
and dreary spot on all its habitable compass.</p> 

<p>I stood lately in Westminster Abbey, that Mausoleum of the mighty 
dead, at the spot where rest the weary feet of the great English Explorer, 
by whose adventurous journeys the world has learned so much of the 
"secret places" of the earth; and on Livingstone's monument which 
overhangs the place of his repose, I read the record of his prayer offered 
in loneliness in the wilds of Central Africa; and here I repeat it as 
my own in this place of concourse, "May Heaven's richest blessing come 
down on every one, American, English or Turk, who helps to heal the 
open sore of the world, Amen."</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

