<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0423">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from William Hogan to Hamilton Fish, April 1872</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0423</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from William Hogan to Hamilton Fish</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1872-04">April 1872</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Lewis, Jacob W.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/81928866">Pope-Hennessy, John, Sir, 1834-1891</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Freetown (Sierra Leone)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hogan, William</persName>
<roleName>Acting U.S. Commercial Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<date when="1872-04"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/232585893">Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1872-10-07"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-03" who="#kln">Encoding, transcription edits, and review</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls">Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="204"/>

<note>Department of State Received Oct 7 1872</note>

<p>United States Consulate<lb/>
Sierra Leone Apl <unclear extent="date" reason="illegible"/> /72</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to enclose for 
Your Excellencys perusal a copy 
of the New Tariff made in this 
Colony. Its importance is incalculable 
in developing the trade of 
this place.</p>

<p>I beg to remind Your 
Excellency that up to this time 
my appointment to this office, 
though advised of it through my 
friends Messrs Ezra Wheeler &amp; Co of 
New York, and through seeing it
published in the New York papers
last March, yet up to this 
time I have not heard from 
Your Excellency on the 

<pb n="205"/>

subject.</p> 

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Your Excellency's<lb/>
Obedient Servant<lb/>
William Hogan<lb/>
Acting U.S. Commercial Agent</p>

<fw type="address">To 
The Honorable
Hamilton Fish<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="206"/>

<p>Sierra Leone</p>

<p>In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of
Her Majesty
Queen Victoria.</p>

<p>John Pope Hennessy, C.M.G,<lb/>
Administrator of the Government of the West Africa Settlements.</p>

<p>[17th August, 1872.]</p>

<p>An Ordinance to amend the Duties of Customs.</p>

<p>Whereas it is expedient to increase the Import Duties 
on Spirituous Liquors, Tobacco and Gunpowder, and to 
abolish the Duties upon articles of food and clothing, and also 
upon building materials and other goods.</p>

<p>Be it therefore enacted by the Government with the advice 
and consent of the Legislative Council as follows;&#8212;</p>

<p>I. The several Ordinances mentioned in Schedule A, to 
this Ordinance annexed and all other Ordinances and Acts 
now in force repugnant to or inconsistent with the provisions 
of the Ordinance, shall be, and are hereby repealed 
Provided nevertheless that such Repeal shall not be deemed 

<pb n="207"/>

to extend to any dues, drawbacks, liabilities or penalties 
imposed, accruing, allowed or due under any of the said Ordinances: 
but notwithstanding such repeal, all remedies and
punishments for levying recovering and enforcing such dues, 
liabilities and penalties shall still remain in full force and 
effect and be capable of being enforced and inflicted, and all 
drawbacks shall be allowed as if such Ordinances were still in 
the authority or in pursuance of the Ordinances hereby repealed 
shall be valid and effectual notwithstanding such Repeal.</p>

<p>II. In lieu and instead of all other Duties and Drawbacks 
of Customs now charged and payable, there shall be raised, 
levied, collected and paid unto Her Majesty her heirs and 
Successors upon goods which shall from and after the passing 
of this Ordinance be imported into any part of the Settlement 
or transhipped either for consumption or for the purpose of 
being carried up the Sierra Leone River for any use of purpose 
whatsoever the several Duties of Customs, and there 
shall be allowed upon goods exported the several Drawbacks 
as the same are respectively described and set forth in the 
Table of Duties following, that is to say:&#8212;</p>

<p>Table of Duties.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Ale, Beer and Porter the Gallon 6d., or 1/- per dozen quarts, or 6d. per dozen pints.</cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Cigars, Cigarettes and all Manufactured Tobacco, the lb</cell>
<cell>2/-</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Gunpowder the Barrel of 100 lbs. ... ... </cell>
<cell>2/-</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Spirits or strong waters not being sweetened mixed with any 
article so that the degree of strength can be ascertained by 
Syke's Hydrometer, for every gallon of the strength of proof 
by such Hydrometer and so in proportion for any greater or 
less strength of proof and for any greater or less quantity than 
a gallon, the Gallon ... ... ... </cell>
<cell>2/-</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Spirits being sweetened or mixed so that the degree of strength
cannot be ascertained for every gallon or any greater or less
quantity than a gallon, the Gallon, ... ... </cell>
<cell>2/-</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Spirits unenumerated, the Gallon ... ... ... </cell>
<cell>2/-</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tobacco (unmanufactured) the lb ... ... </cell>
<cell>4d.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Wine (except Claret) the Gallon, ... ... ... </cell>
<cell>1/6</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Claret, the Gallon, ... ... ... ... </cell>
<cell>6d.</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>III. All other goods not enumerated or described in the 
above Table of Duties shall be free and exempt from duty 
on the Importation thereof.</p> 

<p>IV. The Importer of any goods nor subject to duties of 
Customs or his Agent shall deliver to the Collector of Customs 
a Bill of Entry of such goods in the same manner and form 

<pb n="208"/>

and containing the same particulars as are required on the 
entry of dutiable goods so far as the same is applicable, which 
entry so far as regards the goods shall be a Transcript of the 
Report and shall therein describe such goods according to the
terms upon which such goods are free of Duty and the value 
of such goods as shall have been previously chargeable with 
duty at value: and such Bill of Entry when signed by the 
Collector shall be transmitted to the proper officer and be his 
warrant for the delivery of the goods mentioned therein: and 
the Importer, Owner or Consignee of such goods or his Agent 
shall within Fourteen days after the entry and landing thereof 
deliver to the Collector a full and true account of the goods 
so landed.</p> 

<p>V. Ale, Beer and Porter, Tobacco, Wines and Spirits 
may be bonded in Licensed Ponded Warehouses for Home 
Consumption or for Exportation in puncheons, cases, barrels,
half barrels, pipes or hogsheads; but no demijohns of spirits
shall be received into such warehouses except for Home
Consumption.</p>

<p>VI. No Salt, Slates, Bricks, Coals, Coke, Lime, Tiles, 
or Lumber shall be landed on the Government Wharf.</p>

<p>VII. From and after the First day of October next no 
warehoused goods shall be exported or transhipped for exportation 
except in registered decked vessels of not less than Ten 
tons burthen.</p> 

<p>VIII. There shall be further raised collected and paid 
unto her Majesty, her heirs and successors, an export duty of 
Three farthings on every Imperial shipping bushel (or Five 
shillings per ton of Twenty hundred weight net weight) of 
Ground nuts exported from this Settlement on and after the 
1st day of January 1873.</p>

<p>IX. The landing, shipment or transhipment of such 
Ground nuts shall take place if necessary under the supervision 
of a person to be appointed by the Collector of Customs who 
shall be entitled to receive Five shillings per diem for the 
services of the person so employed from the owner or shipper 
of the ground nuts to be paid to the said Collector before 
the vessel on board of which the said ground nuts are shipped 
shall be entitled to clearance.</p>

<p>X. The Master or Consignee of every vessel about to 
leave any part of the Settlement having ground nuts or any 
articles liable to Export Duty on board shall at the time of the 
master delivering his Content or Entry Outwards deposit with 
the Collector one copy of the Bill or Bills of Lading which 
shall be signed by the said master and the consignee of the 
said vessel or party or parties shipping any produce subject to 

<pb n="209"/>

hundred pounds, and in default of payment shall be committed 
to the Common Gaol for any period not exceeding Six 
Calendar months, unless such penalty and the costs attendant 
thereon shall be sooner paid and satisfied.</p>

<p>XIV. This Ordinance may be cited for all purposes 
as "The Customs Ordinance, 1872."</p>

<p>Passed in the Legislative Council this Seventeenth day 
of August, 1872.</p>

<p>Jacob W. Lewis,<lb/>
Clerk of Legislative Council.</p>

<p>Assented to in Her Majesty's name, this Seventeenth 
day of August, 1872.</p>

<p>J. Pope Hennessy,<lb/>
Governor.</p>

<p>Schedule A.</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Date.</cell>
<cell>Title.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>12th July 1853.</cell>
<cell>An Ordinance to amend the Laws in force for granting Duties 
of Customs and certain other Duties or Dues.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>19th July 1854.</cell>
<cell>An Ordinance to amend an Ordinance passed on the Twelfth 
day of July 1853 <sic>intituled</sic> "An Ordinance to amend the Laws 
in force for granting Duties of Customs and certain other Duties 
or Dues."</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>30th March 1864.</cell>
<cell>An Ordinance for altering the Duties on Spirituous Liquors and 
on wines.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>20th Nov. 1871. </cell>
<cell>An Ordinance to impose an additional duty of Four pence per 
gallon on all Spirits and Spirituous Liquors.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>14th March 1872.</cell>
<cell>An Ordinance for the remission of Customs Duties in certain 
cases.</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>Schedule B.</p>

<p>I A. B. Master of the Ship &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; of &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
burthen &#160;&#160; tons register bound to &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; and I C. D. Consignee of 
the said Ship do hereby, severally declare that the whole quantity of Ground Nuts laden 
on board the said vessel do not exceed the quantity of &#160;&#160; tons as per Bill of Lading 
signed by us and deposited in the Custom House and that we now enter the same for 
Exportation.</p>

<p>Witness our hands the &#160;&#160; day of &#160;&#160;&#160; 187&#160;<lb/>
A. B.<lb/> 
C. D.</p>

<p>Declared before me at the Custom House,
Freetown, this &#160;&#160; day of &#160;&#160;&#160; 187&#160;</p>

<p>Signed E. F.<lb/> 
Collector.</p>

<fw type="footer">Printed by Robert Hagon Spencer, Government Printer, Freetown, Sierra Leone.</fw>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>