<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0669">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Robert S. Newton to John Davis, September 9, 1884</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Brown, Sophie" xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0669</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Robert S. Newton to John Davis</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in St Paul Loanda</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">Roll 4</biblScope>
<date when="1884-09-09">September 9, 1884</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Braga</term>
<term>Fay, William E.</term>
<term>Newton, Robert Scott</term>
<term>Queirós, Alberto Carlos d' Eça de</term>
<term>Stover, Wesley M.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bailundo (Angola)</term>
<term>Benguela (Angola)</term>
<term>Bihé (Angola)</term>
<term>Catumbella (Angola)</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Newton, Robert Scott</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Vice Counsel</roleName>
<placeName>Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1884-09-09"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51336046">Davis, John, 1851-1902</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2020-08" who="kln">reviewed and edited.</change>
<change when="2019" who="sab">transcribe, encode.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Scan40003"/>

<note>Department of State Received <unclear extent="date"/> 1884</note>

<p>United States Consulate<lb/>
Loanda 9th September 1884.</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I have the honor to enclose for the information
of the Department, a copy of a statement left me on the 16th of 
last month by Mr Wesley M Stover, Chairman and William
E. Fay, Secretary of the mission established at Bihe in
November 1880, a copy of which I have forwarded to his
Excellency the Governor General requesting him to make full
enquiries unto the matter and do what he can to render them
justice as they seem by their reports to have been disgracefully
treated through the intrigues of a Portuguese Trader named
Braga. Enclosed you will find translation of the Governors 
reply. Messrs Stover and Fay proceeded for Lisbon bound
for America to lay the matter before the Mission of which
they are representatives: the remainder of the mission
are still at Benguella</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Your most Obedient Servant<lb/>
Robt S. Newton<lb/>
U.S. Vice Consul</p>

<fw type="address">The Assistant Secretary
of State<lb/>
Washington.</fw>

<pb n="Scan40004"/> 

<p>Loanda. Aug. 15. 1884.</p>

<p>Robt Newton Esq<lb/>
Vice Consul of U.S.A.<lb/>
at Loanda<lb/>
Africa.</p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>The following is a concise statement of the facts with reference
to our expulsion from Bailundo and Bihé.</p>

<p>The "American Mission" as we are commonly designated was
established in April 1884 in Bailundo and extended to Bihe 
in March of the present year. In both of these countries
we held the most friendly relations with the natives, both the
Sobas and the people at large. In Bihe these amicable
relations continued to the day of our departure and we still
have the invitation of the Loba of that country to come there 
in a body.</p>

<p>In Bailundo our peace was disturbed on the 15th of May by
a letter bearing the signature of the Soba &amp; his counsellors
commanding us to depart from Bailundo and all its
<catchwords>dependencies</catchwords>

<pb n="Scan40005"/> 

dependencies and never to return and forbidding any of the
mission to visit the King in person as was our custom when
carrying on any important negotiations with him.</p>

<p>So sudden a change in the treatment of the Soba who
had always protected us in every way possible to him
required explanation. Negotiations continued for
six weeks brought to light the following facts:</p>

<p>Mr Braga a Trader at Catumbella had gone to Bihé
and there tried to induce the Soba to expel that part of the
mission which was located there, but failed to
accomplish his purpose the Soba not only refusing
to send away those who were there, but inviting the whole
mission to locate in his country, a thing which was
under the circumstances impossible.</p>

<p>Proceeding to Bailundo Mr Braga brought the
full power of his influence to bear upon the Soba there.
He informed him that we intended to kill the Soba
blow up his village, destroy his family, and take
possession of the country. When that information 
<catchwords>failed</catchwords>

<pb n="Scan40006"/> 

failed to move the Soba he told him, we had committed
crimes in our country, and he had been sent by the
Governor of Benguella, to drive us out and if the Soba
should refuse to send us away he would get
himself and his country into trouble.</p>

<p>At the same time Mr B kindly consented to come 
and occupy our village and give the Soba and his men
all the Whiskey they wanted if he would drive us out and
he even went so far in his benevolent offers as to say he
would be willing to burn our houses and kill us all if the 
King would give him permission to do so. But the King
refused. Several of the Mission heard Mr B's Secretary
say that his master advised the King to kill us but the 
King refused.</p>

<p>Though unwilling to have us killed the Soba was
quite unable to withstand the pressure which was brought
upon him to drive us out and we were compelled to 
leave July 4th. Mr B. immediately taking possession
of our houses.</p>

<p><catchwords>We</catchwords>

<pb n="Scan40007"/> 

We reached Benguella July 29th after a severe and to
the ladies and children, perilous journey with our
lives, a little clothing and nothing more. All of our 
large and costly outfit having been of necessity left
behind.</p>

<p>The Governor of Benguella to whom we applied
for redress, has in accordance with his own request been
furnished with an estimate of our loss.</p>

<p>Respectfully submitted on behalf of the mission<lb/>
Sd Wesley M Stover Chairman<lb/>
Sd William E Fay Secretary</p>

<pb n="Scan40008"/>

<note>Translation</note>

<p>Loanda<lb/>
August 28th 1884.</p> 

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I am requested by his Excellency the Governor
General to acknowledge receipt of your despatch of 
yesterday and upon the subject that it treats, he
has already given the necessary orders <sic>tha</sic> a 
strict inquiry be made in the locality to give 
complete light to this affair</p>

<p>The natural surprise of one who finds
himself suddenly expelled from a country
may have given some exaggeration, in the 
manner of representing the facts, and upon
the appreciation of the causes from which they
originated, and it is not lawful to form a 
definite opinion until ampler proofs are
furnished, by the Governor of Benguella whom 
His Excellency the Governor General immediately
requested to send full particulars by next mail
Finally, His Excellency requests me to say that
he was extremely sorry to hear that the American
Missionaries had been interfered with by the
Soba of Bailundo</p>

<p>I have &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c<lb/>
(Signed) Alberto Carlo d'Eca de Queiroz<lb/>
Secretary to the Government</p>

<fw type="address">To the<lb/>
United States Consul</fw>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
