<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.government.0011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Convention between the United States of America and Zanzibar (1886)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.government.0011</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Convention between the United States of America and Zanzibar</title>
<title level="m">The Statutes at Large of the United States of America, from December, 1887, to March, 1889, and Recent Treaties, Postal Conventions, and Executive Proclamations</title>
<pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
<publisher>Government Printing Office, 1889</publisher>
<date when="1886-07-03">July 3, 1886</date>
<biblScope unit="page">1438-1439</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Government Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Barghash bin Said, Sultan of Zanzibar</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/38108124">Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898</term>
<term>Cheney, Frederic M.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/30330745">Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908</term>
<term>Mohamet Salim bin Mahommed Al Mavli</term>
<term>Said bin Sultan, Sultan of Muscat</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Zanzibar</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-01" who="kln">transcription, encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1438"/>

<head>Convention–Zanzibar. July 3, 1886.</head>

<p>Convention between the United States of America and Zanzibar,
enlarging and defining stipulations of the treaty of September 21, 1833.
Concluded at Zanzibar, July 3, 1886; ratification, with amendments,
advised by the Senate, April 12, 1888; ratified by the President
April 20, 1888; ratifications exchanged June 29, 1888; proclaimed
August 17, 1888.</p>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">By the President of the United States of America,<lb/>
A Proclamation.</head>

<p>Whereas a Convention between the United States of America and
His Highness Barghash bin Saïd, Sultan of Zanzibar, was concluded
July 3, 1886, enlarging and defining the stipulations of the Treaty of
September 21, 1883, between the United States of America and His
Majesty Sayéd Saïd Bin, Sultan of Muscat and Sovereign of Zanzibar,
which Convention, as amended by the Senate of the United States, is
word for word as follows:</p>

<p>The Government of the United States of America and His Highness
Barghash bin Saïd Sultan of Zanzibar, being mutually desirous to confirm
and strengthen the friendly relations which now subsist between the two
countries by enlarging and defining the treaty stipulations already existing
between them in virtue of the Treaty concluded on the 21st of September
1833, corresponding to the sixth day of the moon called Jamada Alawel
in the year of the Allhajia 1249, between the United States of America
and His Majesty Seyed Syed bin Sultan of Muscat (and Sovereign of
Zanzibar), which Treaty has continued in force as to Zanzibar, and its
dependencies after the separation of Zanzibar from Muscat, and has been
expressly accepted, ratified and confirmed by His said Highness Barghash
bin Saïd, Sultan of Zanzibar on the 20th of October 1879, corresponding to
the 4th Zulkaadi, 1296, have resolved to conclude an additional treaty to
that end and have appointed as their Plenipotentiaries to wit:–</p>

<p>The President of the United States of America, Frederic M. Cheney,
Consul of the United States at Zanzibar, and His Highness the Sultan of
Zanzibar his private secretary Mohamet Salim bin Mahommed Al Mavli,
who having exhibited to each other their respective full powers, found in
good and due form, have agreed upon and concluded the following articles.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Article I</head>

<p>Notwithstanding the provisions of Article III of the treaty abovementioned,
by which no more than five <hi rend="italics">per centum</hi> duties shall be paid on the 
cargo landed from vessels on the United States entering any port within His
Highness the Sultan's dominions, spirits and spirituous liquors containing
more than 20 <hi rend="italics">per centum</hi> by volume of alcohol, when imported into the
dominions of His Highness the Sultan from abroad in vessels of the United
States, shall be subject to an entry or import duty not exceeding 25 <hi rend="italics">per
centum</hi> ad valorem. Provided that no other or higher import duties shall
be so levied and 

<pb n="p1439"/>

collected upon spirits carried to Zanzibar in vessels of the
United States than are levied and collected upon like imports of spirits in
the vessels of any other nation.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Article II</head>

<p>The Consuls of the United States appointed under the stipulations of the
IXth article of the treaty above mentioned, shall in addition to the
rights, powers and immunities secured by said article, enjoy all the rights,
privileges, immunities and jurisdictional powers which are now or may hereafter
be enjoyed by the Consuls and Consular Agents of the most favored
nations and conversely, the Consuls and Consular Agents which His Highness
the Sultan may appoint to reside in the United States shall have the
treatment of Agents of like grade of the most favored nation.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Article III</head>

<p>This Treaty shall be ratified and the ratifications exchanged at Zanzibar,
as soon as possible.</p>

<p>Done in duplicate each copy being in the English and Arabic languages,
at Zanzibar the third day of July 1886, corresponding to the thirtieth day of
the moon called Ramajan in the year of the Hegira, 1303.</p>

<p>Frederic M. Cheney [seal]<lb/>
Mohamet Salim bin Mahommed Al Mavli [seal]</p>

<p>And whereas the said Convention, has been duly ratified on both
parts, and the ratifications of the two Governments were exchanged
at Zanzibar the twenty-ninth day of June, one thousand eight hundred
and eighty-eight;</p>

<p>Now, therefore, be it known that I, Grover Cleveland, President
of the United States of America, have caused the said Convention,
as amended, to be made public, to the end that the same, and every
article and clause thereof, may be observed and fulfilled with good
faith by the United States of America and the citizens thereof.</p>

<p>In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand, and caused the
seal of the United States to be affixed.</p>

<p>Done at the city of Washington this 17th day of August, in the year
of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and eighty-eight,
and of the Independence of the United States the one hundred and thirteenth.</p>

<p>Grover Cleveland</p>

<p>By the President:<lb/>
T. F. Bayard<lb/>
Secretary of State.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>