<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.government.0007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Memorial Concerning Conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo (1904)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.government.0007</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Memorial Concerning Conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo</title>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<publisher>Congo Reform Association</publisher>
<date when="1901">1901</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Government Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35249995">Arthur, Chester Alan, 1829-1886</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2333037">Barbour, Thomas S. (Thomas Seymour), 1853-1915</term>
<term>Billington, A.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46772111">Bismarck, Otto, Fürst von, 1815-1898</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14846663">Bourne, H.R. Fox (Henry Richard Fox), 1837-1909</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64062958">Casement, Roger, 1864-1916</term>
<term>Chester, W. H.</term>
<term>Clark, Joseph</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/30330745">Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908</term>
<term>Codrington, Robert</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/48046590">Dhanis, Francis, baron, 1862-1909</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32789810">Dilke, Charles Wentworth, Sir, 1843-1911</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39742616">Glave, E. J. (Edward James)</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10626714">Grogan, Ewart Scott, 1874-1967</term>
<term>Hinde, Sydney</term>
<term>Layton, Edwin A.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term>Leslie, S. H.</term>
<term>Mabie, Henry C.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/26633467">McLean, Archibald, 1850-1920</term>
<term>Moray</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41884042">Morel, E.D. (Edmund Dene), 1873-1924</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62351573">Morgan, John Tyler, 1824-1907</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4795204">Morrison, W. M. (William McCutchan), 1867-1918</term>
<term>Murphy, G. B.</term>
<term>Parminter</term>
<term>Pickard, M. Edouard</term>
<term>Pickersgill, William Clayton</term>
<term>Rabinek</term>
<term>Scrivener, A. E.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62614395">Sheppard, William H. (William Henry), 1865-1927</term>
<term>Sjoblom, J. V.</term>
<term>Snyder, D. W.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904</term>
<term>Weeks, John H.</term>
<term>Whitman, C. L.</term>
<term>Williams</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Banza Manteke (Congo)</term>
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>Bolenge (Congo)</term>
<term>Bolobo (Congo)</term>
<term>Brussels (Belgium)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Equateur</term>
<term>Kasai River</term>
<term>Luebo (Congo)</term>
<term>Matadi (Congo)</term>
<term>Palabala Mountains</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
<term>Zambesia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Arab</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-10" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p3"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="sub">58th Congress. 2d Session. Senate. Document No. 282.</head>

<head type="main">Memorial Concerning Conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>April 19, 1904.&#8212;Presented by Mr. Morgan, referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations, and ordered to be printed.</p>

<p>To the Congress of the United States of America:</p>

<p>As authorized representatives of American organizations conducting missionary and philanthropic work in the Independent State of the Kongo, in Africa, we would respectfully invite the attention of your honorable bodies to certain conditions at present existing in that State which affect vitally the well-being of the people, and concern also the rights and interests of persons from other countries desiring to reside in that State and conduct business or philanthropic enterprises. In the gravity of the case as related both to the present and future well-being of so vast a multitude of people and to our own interests and our honorable obligation as a nation, in the fact that statements are widely circulated not only making denial of the existence of these conditions, but tending to confuse the issue presented, and in the seriousness of the action we ask from you, is our excuse for dwelling at length upon the considerations which we submit for your judgment.</p>

<p>The Independent State of the Kongo A Creation of Western Powers.</p>

<p>You will recall that the Government known as the Independent State of the Kongo was unique in its origin. It came into being by act of an

<pb n="p4"/>

assembly representing all the nations of the Western World. In the original movement looking toward the creation of this Government, Leopold, the king of Belgium, bore a leading part. A company of geographers, travelers, and philanthropists, representing a number of European countries, had been called together by him in September, 1876. By this conference an organization known as the International African Association was constituted. A few years later a society was organized for a purpose described by one of its members as that of "studying what might be made of the Kongo River and its basin." This society, including at first representatives of several European countries of prominence in the commercial and monetary world, soon came almost exclusively under Belgian control. Having the same officers with the original International Association, it soon practically superseded that organization and, though in no true sense international, it renamed itself the International Association of the Kongo.</p>

<p>The United States Foremost in Favorable Action.</p>

<p>After some years spent in visits of exploration to the Kongo State, the association reported that it had entered into treaty relations with more than four hundred and fifty chiefs of the Kongo territory, and sought recognition as a quasi political power. Other plans found favor with certain European powers. A treaty was tentatively concluded between England and Portugal, involving large recognition of the rights of the latter country in Western Africa. Representatives of the International Association appealed strongly to our own Government in the interest of opposition to this treaty, and to any other form of agreement unsatisfactory to the association. As a result of this appeal, after favorable recommendation by President Arthur, the United States Government on April 22, 1884, granted recognition to the association in the following terms:</p>

<pb n="p5"/>

<q>In harmony with the traditional policy of the United States, which enjoins a proper regard for the commercial interests of their citizens, while at the same time avoiding interference with controversies between other powers, as well as alliances with other nations, the Government of the United States announces its sympathy with and approval of the humane and benevolent purposes of the International Association of the Kongo, administering, as it does, the interests of the free states there established, and will order the officers of the United States, both on land and sea, to recognize the flag of the International Association as the flag of a friendly government.</q>
 
<p>This action, taken at this critical juncture, proved determinative of the issue presented in the claims preferred by the International Association. The Government of Germany soon assumed a favorable attitude. The Anglo-Portuguese treaty was withdrawn. Conventions were made with the association by Great Britain and other powers. Meanwhile, a conference in which fourteen states were represented, including the American Government, was convened at Berlin, as a result of which, in January, 1885, definite sanction was given to the establishment of a free state in the basin of the Kongo, and principles regulative of its powers were adopted. Six months later, on the 1st of August, 1885, the association adopted formally the new title of the Independent State of the Kongo. Thus a new state, of which Leopold II was recognized as sovereign and sole administrator, was constituted. Such is the remarkable story of the way by which an individual attained to power, unlimited by internal legislative or judicial restraint, over a territory four times as great as that of France or the German Empire.</p>
 
<p>Territory, Climate, and People.</p>

<p>The Independent State of the Kongo includes a territory upwards of a million square miles in extent. Having a frontage of about 400 miles upon the Atlantic coast, it broadens vastly in the interior, comprising nearly all the basin of the Kongo River. This great river, second only to the Amazon in the 
volume of its waters, with innumerable tributary

<pb n="p6"/> 

streams, both enriches the land and affords access to all sections of the great area.</p>
 
<p>The climate in the coast district is unfavorable for protracted residence, but the elevated plateaus of the interior districts offer an attractive temperature and conditions in general favorable to health. Grazing for cattle is found on the grassy plains, and the timber lands, when cleared, prove 
at once reasonably fertile, producing the vegetables common in our markets, while the forests abound in tropical fruits. The most valuable product of the forest is supplied by the india rubber vine, the Independent State of the Kongo leading all other sections of the earth in its supply of this commercial product. It is evident that the resources of the country, rightly conserved and developed, would secure for it wealth indefinitely great and a corresponding position in the world's commerce.</p>
 
<p>The native peoples, of many tribes and languages, are variously estimated as numbering between 20,000,000 and 30,000,000. The earliest white visitors to the country give pleasant testimony to the traits of native character. As a rule they were welcomed and found the people ready to receive instruction. In certain sections considerable progress had been made in the development of the arts. Doctor Hinde, for example, who accompanied the expedition of Baron Dhanis for the overthrow of the Arab slave power, speaks of his surprise in finding "masons, brickmakers, agriculturalists, and ironworkers." (The Fall of the Kongo Arabs, p. 194, cited in Civilization in Kongoland, by H. R. Fox-Bourne, p. 159.) Independence, alertness of mind, curiosity, and readiness to adopt new customs are noted by travelers as characteristics of the people. In no country has missionary work found a people more hospitable or more responsive.</p>
 
<p>There was, therefore, apparently all ground for the hope that the work upon which this newly created government was entering by sanction of the nations, while encountering many difficulties,

<pb n="p7"/> 
 
would result in a constantly broadening development by which increasing blessings should come to the people, and the land should offer an attractive home to neighboring peoples and to any persons in our own country of African descent who might desire to find a home in their ancestral land.</p>
 
<p>The Profession of Disinterested Philanthropy.</p>
 
<p>This hope was encouraged by the profession made by those seeking recognition for the State. The enterprise of King Leopold found favor because it was supposed to represent two noble ideals,&#8212;a generous philanthropy and impartial freedom of commerce for all the world. The announcement made by promoters of the enterprise was definite and reiterated. The proposed State was not to exist for exploitation of the resources of the country with a view to gain to accrue to those establishing it; it was to exist for the benefit of the native people. Indeed, at one stage the secretary of the association had written declaring that the movement had in contemplation "the establishment of a republican confederation of free negroes, the king simply reserving the right to name the president of the confederation." This thought was discredited by other promoters of the enterprise as offering too high an ideal for early realization; but the affirmation of the philanthropic character of the enterprise was incessant. Mr. Stanley, when speaking in advocacy of the movement before the London Chamber of Commerce, said:</p>
 
<q>The founders of the International Association have been called dreamers. Some cannot appreciate rightly, because there are no dividends attaching to it, this restless, ardent sentiment which seeks to extend civilizing influences among the dark races, and to brighten up with a glow of civilization the dark places of sad-browed Africa.</q>
 
<p>Our own Government, in taking the leadership in granting recognition to the State, emphasized the high ideals which it was thought to represent.

<pb n="p8"/> 
 
In his message to Congress in December, 1883, President Arthur dwelt upon the exalted character of these ideals. He said:</p>
 
<q>The objects of this society are philanthropic. It does not aim at permanent political control, but seeks the neutrality of the valley.</q>

<p>Our Government's recognition of the State was, in express terms, an announcement of "its sympathy with and approval of the humane and benevolent purposes" of the association.</p> 

<p>Equally explicit was the understanding determining the action of the conference at Berlin, in which our Government participated, but whose action it did not formally ratify because of the ideal controlling relations with foreign states. The preamble of the "General act of the Berlin conference" declares that the conference is "concerned as to the means of furthering the moral and material well-being of the native populations."</p> 

<p>Prince Bismarck, in an introductory address to the conference, declared that in convening it the Imperial Government of Germany was guided&#8212;</p>
 
<q>by the conviction that all the governments invited agreed in wishing to bring the natives of Africa within the pale of civilization * * * by giving its inhabitants the means of instructing themselves, by encouraging missions and enterprises calculated to spread useful knowledge, and by preparing the way for the overthrow of slavery.</q>
 
<p>At the close of the sessions of the conference Prince Bismarck paid honor to "His Majesty, King of the Belgians," as "the founder of a work * * * which should confer precious service on the cause of humanity," and added:</p>
 
<q>I pray for the prosperous development of the State, and for the fulfillment of the noble aspirations of its illustrious founder.</q>

<p>These expectations were based on the purpose avowed by the King of Belgium himself. "Our only programme, I am anxious to repeat," he said in a published letter, "is the work of moral and material regeneration." President Cleveland was

<pb n="p9"/> 
 
true to the impression widely made when, in announcing the organization of the Independent State of the Kongo, he wrote in his first annual message in December, 1885:</p>
 
<q>It is fortunate that a benighted region, owing all it has of quickening civilization to the beneficence and philanthropic spirit of this monarch, should have the advantage and security of his benevolent supervision.</q> 

<p>Freedom of Trade Guaranteed.</p>

<p>And not only is it true that the aim professedly controlling the founding of the Independent State of the Kongo was philanthropic, the understanding was definite that nothing of the nature of an individual monopoly was contemplated. The State was to be open to unrestricted commerce. This understanding appears in letters written by the promoters of the enterprise before its recognition by our Government, in the language of our state papers, in the pledges recorded in the act of the conference at Berlin, and in the explicit declaration made by the King when the name The Independent State of the Kongo was adopted. It was declared, indeed, that neither directly nor indirectly would the government of the State trade or traffic.</p>
 
<p>President Arthur, in his message of December, 1884, says:</p>
 
<q>The importance of the rich prospective trade of the Kongo Valley has led to the general conviction that it should be opened to all nations on equal terms.</q>
 
<p>Opposition to the tentative treaty by which England proposed recognition of the rights of Portugal in the Kongo Valley was based explicitly upon the fear that under Portuguese administration the commercial rights of other nations would not be safeguarded.</p>
 
<p>The general act adopted by the Berlin conference is explicit in its provision for assuring respect for the full and equal commercial rights of all nations. Its first article provides, under the heading "Declaration relative to freedom of trade in the basin of 

<pb n="p10"/> 

the Kongo, its mouths, and circumjacent regions,' that "the trade of all nations shall enjoy complete freedom."</p>
 
<p>In closing the conference Prince Bismarck said:</p> 

<q>The resolutions we are on the point of sanctioning secure to the commerce of all nations free access to the center of the African continent. The guaranties which will be provided for freedom of trade in the Kongo basin are of a nature to offer to the industries of all nations the conditions most favorable to the development of their security.</q>

<p>Such was the understanding and the purpose of those through whose action the Independent State was constituted. It was not because national governments desired to give to one man commercial privileges of vast value that they consigned the government of this newly-opened territory to his care; it was because they would retain these commercial privileges as a due possession for all peoples that this new State was given its being.</p>
 
<p>The Catalogue of Wrongs.</p>

<p>The fact to which our information concerning conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo makes it our painful duty to ask your attention is that the anticipated realization of these humane, liberal, and just ideals has not been reached by the Government of the Kongo State, but has been and is now directly thwarted by the methods of administration which the Government has adopted. Fidelity to the facts known to us compels the statement that the country to-day, throughout great sections, is suffering from a grievous oppression characterized by well-nigh incredible abuses of the people.</p>
 
<p>The story of personal sufferings is heartrending. Among the wrongs alleged in the documents accompanying our memorial are forced labor; the forced contribution of food stuffs and other supplies for the State stations and the stations of monopolist companies licensed by the State and for the 30,000 men of the regular and irregular militia; 

<pb n="p11"/> 
 
forced military service under conditions unjust alike to the soldiers and the people; direct imposts dependent upon the arbitrary will of subordinate officials or commanders of detachments of the militia, and the exaction throughout the rubber-producing districts of a heavy toll of this product; all this without respect to the consent or desire, and with slight regard to the ability, of the people. The requirements become more and more burdensome as the population diminishes and the supplies obtainable in the territories adjoining native villages are exhausted. In many instances the people are required to make contributions to the State of articles which they do not possess and which they must purchase at a cost greatly in excess of the price allowed them for supplying it. Remuneration for the contributions made is slight. The right to remuneration indeed has been denied. An exponent of the policy of the King's Government declared in the Belgian Parliament that whatever remuneration is given is a gratuity.</p>
 
<p>It is&#8212;so the testimony presented by us indicates&#8212;in connection with the enforcement of these demands made by the State upon the people that the cruelties by which the land is scourged have developed. The native is driven to his task by a remorseless physical compulsion. For evasion of the task, or for failure to perform it to the full on account of whatever inability, punishments of most shocking character are appointed. They include the seizure of women, who, chained neck to neck, are forced away from their homes and held as so-called hostages; the burning of villages; the indiscriminate slaughter of the people, pursued and hunted in the forests to which they flee; the mutilation of the living and the dead.</p>
 
<p>Horror is added to horror in the dreadful catalogue of reported wrongs. It would be difficult to name a form of atrocity belonging to any history of shameless conquest or of primitive savagery which fails to find a place in this record. The impressing of recruits for the army and for the forces
 
<pb n="p12"/>
 
of laborers is accomplished by use of the methods made familiar by the slave raids which it was thought to be the high mission of the government of this State to abolish. Slavery practically is restored throughout the State by the exaction of long terms of service for those professedly free from bondage, and in certain sections the slave market is wide open under government protection. Gruesome stories are told of the custom of leaders of scattered bands of the militia of bringing in the hands of the dead as proof that the retribution required from them has been inflicted, and of orgies of cannibals systematically permitted to prey upon the bodies of their victims as reward for their work of slaughter.</p>
 
<p>The testimony to these enormities is of such a character that, morally incredible as the stories seem, we are unable to doubt that they reproduce all too faithfully conditions prevailing through wide sections of the Independent Kongo State. This testimony, now for many years, has come to the outer world from residents of the State in a steady, unintermittent stream. The list of witnesses includes missionaries, travelers, explorers, consular residents, and agents of the State who have wearied of the work in which confessedly they had participated.</p> 

<p>The Reluctant Testimony of Missionaries.</p>

<p>It should be borne in mind that the missionary is a reluctant witness against the government under which he lives. It is his desire, and it is for his personal interest, to cultivate the favor of the government, and the missionary devoted to his work will bear much rather than risk a total loss of power to be of service to the people. The testimony of missionaries connected with our American societies, as offered by us, includes that of Rev. G. B. Murphy (Document I), whose statement was published in the London Times, November 18, 1895; that of Rev. J. V. Sjoblom (Document II), presented to the British Government in 

<pb n="p13"/>

the year 1898, of whose testimony, as given at a meeting of the Aborigines Protection Society, Sir Charles Dilke, who was present at the meeting, has recently said:</p>
 
<q>I undertake to say that there was not a single person present who was not constrained to believe every syllable he uttered. His statement has never been shaken in any way.</q> 

<p>Another witness adds:</p>
 
<q>Apparently almost a dying man, he spoke with broken voice but intense earnestness, in simple language that left none of his hearers in doubt as to the absolute truthfulness with which he recounted his experience of five years' residence in the Equateur district.</q>
 
<p>Rev. Joseph Clark (Document III), Rev. A. Billington (Document IV), and Rev. C. L. Whitman (Document V), who are now at stations on the Upper Kongo River; and Edwin A. Layton, M.D. (Document VI), and Rev. W. M. Morrison (Document VII), who are now in this country and able, if this is desired, to supplement their testimony by personal words.</p>
 
<p>We would call particular attention to the testimony of Mr. Sjoblom, and to that of Mr. Morrison; the first, relating to a time seven years ago, is graphic and detailed, and the latter makes the reader almost a spectator of the scenes of horror as they are revealed in certain sections of the Kongo State at this very hour. Note his description of his colleague's visit to the stockade where a marauding band of cannibal savages in the service of the State had murdered helpless prisoners, and where 81 severed hands were slowly drying over a fire.</p>
 
<p>To this missionary testimony we would add also that of two missionaries of the English Baptist Mission, Rev. John H. Weeks (Document VIII) and Rev. A. E. Scrivener (Document IX). Both are living in the far interior of the State; the former tells the story of impressions made upon him on a recent return to Africa after a time of furlough, and the latter gives a detailed record of a

<pb n="p14"/>
 
journey made by him in the summer of 1903 through the Domaine Privé of the King.</p>
 
<p>Witnesses of Many Callings.</p>
 
<p>This testimony of missionaries finds impressive reinforcement in the testimony of more transient dwellers in the land: that of Mr. Ewart S. Grogan, who, in the volume From the Cape to Cairo, tells the story of a journey made by him in the year 1899 (see p. 227); that of Mr. Pickersgill, consul of the British Government, given in an official report in 1898 (see citations from this report in Civilization in Kongoland, by Mr. H. R. Fox-Bourne, pp. 177-180); that of Colonel Williams (see Affairs of West Africa, by E. D. Morel, p. 320), an officer in King Leopold's army, who in the year 1891 denounced to the King the outrages occurring under his administration; that of Major Parminter, a pioneer of the earlier days, who in 1892 sought the assistance of the Aborigines Protection Society in exposing the conduct of the Kongo Government, but who afterward was pacified by the King (see pp. 132-134, Civilization in Kongoland); that of M. Moray (see p. 252 of Civilization in Kongoland), a former agent of one of the great monopolist companies now licensed by the King; that of Senator M. Edouard Pickard, a member of the Belgian Senate, who wrote of impressions made during a visit to the Kongo in 1896 (see En Congolie, pp. 95-97, as cited in Civilization in Kongoland, pp. 244-245, 248-249).</p>
 
<p>In these testimonies the same features grow cruelly familiar&#8212;the lash, the raids of soldiers, the terror of the villagers, the weighing of baskets of rubber brought in by trembling natives, the scourging with the chicotte of hippopotamus hide, the burning of villages, indiscriminate massacre, the severed hands, the excesses of cannibalism.</p> 

<p>A Companion of Mr. Stanley.</p>

<p>Perhaps no one of these testimonies made in published volumes is more significant than that of 

<pb n="p15"/>

Mr. E. J. Glave, for a time a subordinate of Mr. Stanley in the Kongo International Association, the author of the volume Six Years in the Kongo, published in 1892, for which Mr. Stanley wrote an introduction in which he gave strong commendation of the character of the author. Mr. Glave revisited the Kongo after an absence of six years, and his record of the scenes witnessed by him as he made his way over the route followed previously with Mr. Stanley is given in articles contributed to the Century Magazine (see articles New Conditions in Central Africa, vols. 53, 54). At first he is perplexed and incredulous.</p>
 
<p>December 6 he writes:</p> 

<q>I do not think the Belgians are going the right way to work.</q> 

<p>December 7:</p> 

<q>It is said, but I must have it corroborated, that the white officer * * * has commissioned several chiefs to make raids and bring him the slaves. They are supposed to be taken out of slavery and freed, but I fail to see how this can be argued out * * *. Peaceful families have been broken up. If these conditions are to exist, I fail to see how the antislavery movement is to benefit the native. (See Century Magazine, vol. 53, p. 907·) </q>

<p>As he advances, the entries in his journal reveal the growth of his deep indignation and abhorrence. December 11 he writes: </p>

<q>The whole country is being beset by the dreadful and thoroughly unjustifiable conduct of the soldiers. (Vol. 53, p. 913.)</q>

<p>December 17 he writes again:</p>
 
<q>I do not think the natives are making much out of this partition of Africa. This antislavery movement has its dark side also. In stations in charge of white men&#8212;government soldiers&#8212;one sees strings of poor emaciated old women, some of them mere skeletons, tramping about in gangs with a rope about the neck, * * * naked, except for a miserable patch of cloth. They are prisoners of war. They form a miserable spectacle. (Vol. 53, p. 912.)</q> 

<p>January 3:</p> 

<q>This station is surrounded by villages paying tribute. It has 5,000 auxiliaries, who are sent all over the country to beat the natives into submission. (Vol. 53, p. 915.)</q>

<pb n="p16"/>

<p>February 28:</p> 

<q>We left Equateur after taking on a cargo of one hundred small slaves, principally boys seven or eight years old, with a few girls among the batch, all stolen from the natives. They talk of philanthropy and civilization. Where it is I do not know. (Vol. 54, p. 708.)</q> 

<p>March 12:</p>
 
<q>Everywhere I hear the same news of the doings of the Kongo Free State&#8212;rubber and murder, slavery in its worst form. (Vol. 54, p. 709.)</q>

<p>April 5:</p> 

<q>I saw the dead body of a carrier lying on the trail. He was nothing but skin and bone. These posts ought to give some care to porters. The heartless disregard for life is abominable. No wonder the State is hated. (Vol. 54. p. 713.)</q> 

<p>Arriving at Matadi, where his death occurred a few days later, Mr. Glave wrote, April 5:</p>

<q>If the Arabs had been the masters, this would be styled "iniquitous trafficking in human flesh and blood," but, being under the administration of the Kongo Free State, it is merely a part of their philanthropic system of liberating the natives. (Vol. 54, p. 796.)</q> 

<p>Report of British Consul&#8212;Action By British Parliament.</p>

<p>A notable confirmation and reinforcement of all this testimony is found in an official report made in February of the present year by Mr. Roger Casement, His Britannic Majesty's consul in the Independent State of the Kongo, by whom official service has been rendered to our own Government in the absence of consular representation in this State. We submit herewith his painstaking and comprehensive testimony, given after a journey through interior districts, the straightforward, regretful fidelity of which, we think, cannot fail to be apparent to every fair-minded reader. (Document X.) A single citation from the elaborate document will illustrate its character. Mr. Casement paid a visit to a large company of refugees who had sought an asylum beyond the borders of the Kongo State. He says:</p> 

<pb n="p17"/>
 
<q>I saw and questioned several groups of these people whom I found to be industrious blacksmiths and brass workers. The statements made to me by them were of such a nature that I could not believe them to be true. * * * On reaching Bolobo in September I obtained information amply confirming the statements. (For extended account of interview with these natives and the stories of massacre and mutilation given by them, see report of Mr. Casement, pp. 60 to 64.)</q> 

<p>In this connection we would call your attention to the fact that, even before the testimony of Mr. Casement had been received, the British Parliament, after an exhaustive investigation of the testimony submitted to it, by unanimous vote took action looking to intervention by the signatory parties of the Berlin agreement. It has addressed these powers upon the subject and has placed in their hands the report of Mr. Casement. The British premier publicly declared that the proofs of the existence of grave abuses were overwhelming.</p> 

<p>Arraignment in Germany and in the Belgian Parliament.</p>

<p>It is noteworthy also that the German Colonial Society, a body with a membership of 32,000, has issued a public appeal in a similar vein, expressing its conviction of the conclusiveness of testimony as to conditions in this State. Even in the Belgian House of Representatives a resolution was strongly supported demanding inquiry into administration of the government of the Kongo State on the around that the charges against it were established beyond disproof or contradiction.</p>
 
<p>The documents and citations presented we offer in part as direct testimony and in part as collateral reports in support of the position we would urge, namely: That there is ample ground for inquiry into conditions in the Kongo State by those to whom right of inquiry belongs. The testimony varies in the gravity of conditions indicated, reports becoming more dark as districts more remote from the coast are touched. Of the situation in regions far removed from missionary stations

<pb n="p18"/>
 
and the path of travelers, where the native soldiers are quite without restraint in following out their impulses, suggestion is given in the record of the journey of Mr. Scrivener through a section of the Domaine Privé and in a chapter of the report of Mr. Casement.</p> 

<p>Proof Made Superfluous by Open Adoption of an Indefensible System.</p>
 
<p>But we have now to remind you that, decisive as is the evidence of wrong suffered by the natives under the rule of the Independent State of the Kongo, the presentation of specific proofs of wrong is made almost superfluous. For the government of the Independent State of the Kongo undeniably has followed a course which involves apparently a central breach of faith with the powers creating it and with the native people whom it was appointed to serve, and this course is such that by it the wrongs to which the testimony cited bears witness are invited and made inevitable. The root of administrative evils in the government of the Independent State of the Kongo is in its monopolization of the territory and the resources of the State.</p>
 
<p>The astonishing claim leading to this action is now traceable in a document issued July 1, 1885, which at the time was supposed to be dictated by concern for the rights of the natives. It declared that "no one may dispossess any native of lands occupied by him," adding that "all vacant land is considered as belonging to the State." Later, through successive public edicts, it became clear that the term "vacant" was to be interpreted as meaning all territory in the State with the exception of the sites of the native villages and the gardens of such villages. Thus was consummated, without offer of compensation to the natives, this appropriation by the government of all the vast Kongo territory save the little areas occupied by villages and gardens.</p>
 
<p>Certain monopolist companies have been created 

<pb n="p19"/>

in which the King has controlling financial interest, either through ownership of a majority of the stock or through demands upon the revenues; but hundreds of thousands of acres are set apart as the "Domaine Privé" of the King. Forest and plain, hill and valley, the river and its affluents, are his private possession.</p>
 
<p>And the claim applies not simply to the territory, but all products of this immense region, native or developed by cultivation, are claimed as the King's personal property, even the produce of the gardens. The natives may not trade in these products; they may only bring them to the King's agents for such compensation as the agents choose to allow.</p> 

<p>An Army of Savages.</p>

<p>The relation of these extraordinary claims to the evils from which the land is suffering is easily traced. The products of the country must he collected by the natives, and, all true motive for industry having been destroyed, no resort remains but that of compulsion. A body of armed men is required for enforcement of the King's will. This body must be secured through raids upon the native tribes, and the more savage tribes are chosen by preference. The captives are taken far from their homes and after a time of restraint are commissioned for the appointed service. This "force publique" in 1896 was a body of 8,500 men; six years later it had more than doubled in numbers. In addition to this native force, the monopolist companies are allowed to raise auxiliary forces, and savage tribes are made the allies of the State for prosecution of the same ends. This force as a whole is now believed to comprise a body of 30,000 men.</p>
 
<p>The character of the work of these men is indicated in the words of M. Edouard Pickard, a member of the Belgian Senate: "Their ferocity equals that of a pack of hounds hunting their quarry." (En Congolie, p. 201 -see citation in Civilization 

<pb n="p20"/>
 
in Kongoland, p. 249.) Unrestrained by natural sentiments of compassion, held severely responsible for securing at any cost the appointed tributes from the people, officered by men incited to their task by promise of "bounties proportionate to the results obtained," these barbaric hordes are let loose upon the people. Their representative in the villages is "the sentry," whose work is to secure the appointed levy of rubber or other products, and who is practically without restraint upon his savage propensities. He is described by one visitor to the country as a "dare-devil aboriginal armed with a rifle, his power limited only by such repression as the Government chooses to use." It was of these men Mr. Glave wrote:</p> 

<q>The black soldiers are bent on fighting and raiding: they want no peaceful settlement. They have good rifles and ammunition, realize their superiority over the natives with their bows and arrows, and they want to shoot and kill and rob * * * whether the victim be man, woman, or child. and no matter how defenseless. (Century Magazine, vol. 53. p 908.)</q>
 
<p>It is apparent that of such a system wrongs and atrocities are the certain product.</p> 

<p>It should be borne in mind that the subordinate agents of Government, if continuing in its service, are made practically helpless. Receiving instruction to furnish a given number of soldiers and a certain amount of rubber, with the understanding that they must employ whatever means are necessary, they know of no methods adequate for the end except those involving appeal to fear. Mr. Glave says that many white officers are averse to the india rubber régime of the State, but the laws command it. It would be unjust not to recognize that the conditions prevailing have aroused distress in men connected with the Government, yet it is to be fared that it is only a few of these who have the interests of the people at heart, and these are powerless to stem the tide of oppression. The punishment of subordinates, whether soldiers or white officers, even if honestly attempted, would 

<pb n="p21"/>

not reach the evil. The fault is not theirs primarily. It belongs to the system and to the authority responsible for the establishment and enforcement of that system. Proofs of individual guilt become of secondary consequence as compared with the question as to the essential character and the certain results of the system which the Government of the State has ordained.</p> 

<p>The Two-Fold Betrayal of Trust&#8212;I. The Defrauding of the People.</p>

<p>From the considerations thus presented it is apparent that the course pursued by the Sovereign of the Independent State of the Kongo has laid his Government open to question in respect to violation of the trusts committed to it. Apparently that Government has not been true to the faith solemnly plighted in behalf of the native peoples. Before the world and before God, the Sovereign pledged himself in the Berlin Conference to safeguard the interests of the natives and to insure to them the benefits of peace and of civilization. The few specimens obtainable of the treaties made by Mr. Stanley with native chiefs in the name of the International Association, before the Berlin Conference had been convened, show that that Association pledged itself to protect the people from oppression, but, in place of protection and fostering care for their welfare, under the Government in which the rights and powers of that Association were merged they have suffered from every form of ill usage which a savage inhumanity could devise, and the ruler who promised them protection has imposed upon them the one wholesale wrong, the parent of all lesser acts of injustice, the cruelty of dispossessing them of their ancient rights in their native land. In these lands they held dominion under tribal government, hunting in the forests and gathering the products of forest and field. Now the people practically are slaves upon their native soil. They may not for their own benefit collect its produce; they may not barter

<pb n="p22"/>

it for merchandise; they may only bring it to the agents of the Kongo for such return as it is the pleasure of the agents to make. This is slavery in fact. It is the imposition of bondage under the name of government.</p>
 
<p>The Two-Fold Betrayal of Trust&#8212;II. The Defrauding of the Nations.</p> 

<p>And the crime against the natives is a crime against the nations. The people may not trade, and have nothing with which to trade. So the trader from another land may not buy. The Berlin agreement, in it opening article, affirmed that the trade of all nations should enjoy complete freedom. So solicitous was the conference at Berlin for the safeguarding of this right that, in the protocol of the general act of Berlin, it was provided that no modifications of the agreement should be introduced tending to hamper the liberty of trade. No other thought could have been in the minds of the members of this conference than that of freedom in the only kind of trade possible in Africa,&#8212;the collecting and sale by the natives of their products in exchange for such European merchandise as they should desire to secure. To-day, with the exception of the narrow district of the lower Kongo, where free trade, hampered 
by taxation, still exists in diminishing volume, the entire territories of the Kongo State have been converted into a vast monopoly.</p> 

<p>Above Stanley Pool trade do not exist. For fifteen years the great territory of the Domaine Privé of the King has been closed to all commercial enterprises. The territory along the Kassai River, for a time left to freedom of trade, has now been forced into a monopoly, with the State as its chief stockholder. The commercial companies representing the King were reconstructed a few years since, being brought under the law of the Kongo State by which they are not required to make public their transactions. The earlier traders have been dispossessed and driven
 
<pb n="p23"/>

from the country. The purchase of products from a native by a foreign trader is now a crime, exposing the trader to severe legal penalties and severer arbitrary punishments. The story of the execution of Mr. Charles Henry Stokes (see Civilization in Kongoland, pp. 200-202, 266-270), a trader in ivory who was hanged by a representative of the Government in 1895, and that of the arrest and subsequent death of Herr Rabinek, who originally possessed a license for trade but was refused recognition after reorganization of the Katanga Company, are suggestive of the fortune appointed for those who presume upon the binding force of the pledges given originally by the government of the Kongo State.</p>
 
<p>Such is the system and policy openly adopted and defended by the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo&#8212;apparently, the direct negation of the two principles made prominent in its original professions and determinative of the action at Berlin.</p>
 
<p>But a presentment against the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo might not inappropriately be based also on another ground, 
that of the results following from this rule. The development confidently looked for has not resulted from the experiment entered upon with the solemn sanction of western powers.</p> 

<p>Accusing Figures.</p>

<p>One need but consult official reports to discover conclusive evidence of this. Among public expenses we find an item of 7,700,000 francs for the 
public force, the soldiery by whom the exactions of government are enforced, while for public works the expenditure is 1,000,000 francs.</p> 

<p>Not less suggestive are figures relating to the commerce of the country. For the year 1901 exportation was $10,035,200; of this amount exports of rubber and ivory represented $9,585,800. Thus the exportation of other products, representative of such industries as develop the capabilities 

<pb n="p24"/>

of the people and the resources of the country, were but $449,400. It should be added that about 97 per cent of the small general trade thus reported is almost exclusively the exportation of palm products from the Lower Kongo by the Dutch house. Of the export of rubber, about 50 per cent is from the private domain of the King, the remainder from territories worked by the monopolist companies.</p>
 
<p>Equally instructive is the comparative table of exports and imports. During a period of four years we find a total exportation of $36,800,000, the imports during the same period being $17,346,000&#8212;the importation thus representing less than one half the exportation&#8212;a situation said to be without parallel in European colonies. When to this it is added that 70 per cent of this importation represents supplies for government, stores for the railway, arms and ammunition for the military force, it will be seen how small is the inflow to the State as a whole from the products of the world's industry and invention, and how insignificant is the tidal rill from the great ocean of the world's comforts which trickles beyond the relatively favored district by the Atlantic coast. When it is recalled that Mr. Stanley predicted for Great Britain alone an annual trade with the Kongo of £20,000,000, the failure of the rule of its government to realize the possibilities supposed to be opened before it becomes apparent.</p> 

<p>The Absence of the School and the Hospital.</p>

<p>And we seek in vain in the Kongo State for those forms of service which it is the high privilege of civilized governments to render to their peoples. Where is the school system which it should have founded? Where is the hospital system with which it should have ministered to the physical need of the people? Apparently the one movement bearing a resemblance to philanthropic effort is the plan by which orphans, with the State's

<pb n="p25"/>
 
approval, may be taken under the care of religious or philanthropic associations; but these orphans are the hapless little ones left parentless and homeless by the military raids, and visitors to the country reproduce no more dreadful scenes than those connected with the transportation of these children from their village homes to those to whose care they are committed. Certain material enterprises, as the railway, bear witness to great energy and perseverance, though themselves identified with terrible cost to the lives of the natives; but these enterprises are connected directly with the one aim which unhappily seems to have absorbed the energies of government, that of enriching itself by a swift exploitation of the natural products of the State.</p> 

<p>A Broken-Spirited People.</p>

<p>This presentment against the government of the State on the score of the results following upon its work is not simply of a negative character. The misrule of government affects directly the life of the people, in that it takes away all incentive to labor by depriving them of the rewards of toil. In the interior districts the people have no heart for the planting of gardens or for the building of dwellings. They live in continual alarm, fearing the coming of the soldiery. Homes are ill-kept, houses falling into decay are not repaired.</p> 

<p>The picture revealed in the concurrent representation of impartial witnesses is a melancholy one. Mr. Stanley, arriving at the mouth of the Kongo on the 14th of August, 1879, as the representative of the International African Association, set before himself a proud programme:</p>

<q>To ascend the river with the noble mission of sowing along its banks civilized settlements, to peacefully conquer (the country) and subdue it, to remold it in harmony with modern ideas into national states within whose limits the European merchant shall go hand in hand with the dark African trader, and justice and law and order shall prevail, and murder and lawlessness and the cruel barter of slaves shall forever cease (see The Congo, vol. 1, p. 59).</q> 

<pb n="p26"/>

<p>As illustrating the unhappy contrast with this forecast presented in the conditions realized to-day, we may quote the testimony of the consul, Mr. Roger Casement, regarding one representative station in the State:</p>
 
<q>I must confess with pain and astonishment * * * that I felt I was visiting a penal settlement. (From letter of Mr. Casement to the vice-governor-counsel of the Kongo State, September 4, 1903.)</q> 

<p>The Exhausted and Depopulated Land.</p>

<p>Terrorism holds sway. The methods of the slave régime are reinforced by the inexorable authority of the Government itself. Cannibalism is carried to regions where before it was unknown. The lands are depleted. The profuse bleeding of the rubber vines has brought about their destruction in wide areas. The State is reaching on for new territories over which its devastating work may spread. The deportation of young men, the massacres and the flight of the people, are draining the population of the territory. In no one feature are the testimonies submitted by us in more painful agreement than in their description of the depopulation of the country. Every returning missionary, every traveler revisiting the land, bears testimony to this.</p> 

<p>Mr. Scrivener, in his record of the journey recently made through a section of the Domaine Privé, says that one may walk for five days without seeing a single village, where once village life abounded. "The most striking characteristic of the land," so another witness writes, "is the absence of human life. It is not, after you have passed the arid mountains of Palabala, poor or unfertile; but it is empty." (M. Mille, Au Congo Belge, p. 49.)</p>
 
<p>M. Edouard Pickard, of the Belgian Senate, after his journey in 1896, speaks of "the desolation resulting from the engineering exploits"; of the "mutilated forests where until lately villages had nestled"; of "great heaps of cinders amid deserted 

<pb n="p27"/>

palm groves and trampled-down banana fields." He adds:</p>
 
<q>The terror caused by the memory of inhuman floggings and of massacres haunt their brains, and they go as fugitives to the hospitable bush or across the frontiers. (En Congolie, p. 95; cited p. 244, Civilization in Kongoland.)</q>
 
<p>Mr. Grogan, in his work, "From the Cape to Cairo," says:</p> 

<q>A country formerly well populated and apparently responsive to just treatment is now practically a howling wilderness. The scattered inhabitants live almost without cultivation in the marshes, thickets, and reeds, madly fleeing even from their own shadows. * * * The very white men who should be keeping peace where chaos now reigns supreme, spend thousands in making of peace a chaos of their own. (From the Cape to Cairo, p. 227.)</q>
 
<p>But the natives may not all abandon the country. There are other perils in the outlook. It is apparent that the policy of the Government is not winning the friendship of the people. Mr. Robert Codrington, commissioner for Great Britain in the neighboring territory of Northern Zambesia, who wrote after a tour in the Kongo district, says:</p> 

<q>The natives are continually in rebellion and the country is unsafe except in the immediate vicinity of the military commissaires, and within the spheres of the missionaries. (Geographical Journal, May, 1902, p. 601.)</q> 

<p>Mutinies in the army are frequent. The Kongo State may yet work out its own doom. The forces of savagery may turn upon it. The question raised by one writer is a startling one:</p> 

<q>When the present rule is ended, what will remain for Europe and America to deal with? * * * a vast region with undying hatred of the whites&#8212;a great army of cannibal levies, trained in the usage of modern weapons and taught the worst vices of depraved men in civilized lands.</q> 

<p>Chosen Methods Inexcusable.</p>

<p>It is clear that there can be no defense for this desolating and hazardous work. The dreadful story reveals no palliating feature. Had the cooperation of the people been sought in just enterprises reasonably conducted, they would have been 

<pb n="p28"/>

found willing allies. These peoples of Central Africa are not unamenable to, gentle influences. Mr. Glave writes of his observations in one section invaded by the raid of rubber:</p>
 
<q>Everywhere the natives are friendly and polite. They are not lazy, good-for-nothing people. Their fine powers are obtained by hard work, sobriety, frugal living.</q>
 
<p>And again, in almost the last words written before his death, he says:</p> 

<q>The methods employed by the Government are not necessary. Years ago, when I was on duty at the equator without soldiers, I never had any difficulty in getting what men I needed, nor did any other station in the old, humane days.</q>
 
<p>He adds:</p>
 
<q>It is only the State officials who make war. Seldom do the traders (of the older class) have any trouble, and the missionaries never (see Century Magazine, vol. 54, p. 714).</q> 

<p>The Ground of Missionary Action.</p>

<p>Our interest as missionary organizations in the record we have been presenting is due not alone to desire for advancement for the special work in which we are engaged, though this work&#8212;in its beginnings antecedent to the founding of the Kongo State&#8212;was formally recognized in the action of the Berlin Conference and in the proclamations of the King as essential to realization of the philanthropic aims for which professedly the State was established. Our missionaries have sought, to quote the language of the Berlin agreement, "the moral and material well-being of the native population." What the State has failed to do they have endeavored to do. They have reduced languages to writing; they have taught the people; they are establishing schools; they are developing useful arts, and they are seeking to supplant the gross superstitions and inhumanities of the people by Christian beliefs and practices. This work, which the State had engaged to encourage and support, is sadly impeded by the conditions now developed.</p>
 
<pb n="p29"/>

<p>Our complaint is not a personal one. Our missionaries personally have not been ill-used. Yet we have definite complaint as respects the security of missionary work which, as furnishing a definite instance of the failure of the State to regard its treaty obligations, we have submitted to the State Department of our Government. Lands, withheld in general from private purchasers, are denied to our representatives. Within the past four years it has been found quite impossible to purchase land or to secure leases of land for more than a very limited period of time. Thus the guaranty of permanence essential for the development of our work is destroyed. Our Government's treaty with the Kongo State definitely secured to missionary organization the right to build, and thus implicitly the right to buy land upon which to build. While sales of land are refused, the law forbids that a missionary shall remain for more than fifteen days in any place in which he does not hold a title to land; thus the stay of missionaries in the country practically is threatened. Our missionaries, moreover, at certain stations becoming increasingly numerous, are forbidden to buy supplies from the people, even the sale of food products by the natives being prohibited; they must bring these to the State agents. The missionary would gladly buy of the native at a fair price, but this privilege is denied him. Our missionaries, thus forced to depend on the station posts for all food supplies, are made involuntary abettors of the wrong practiced upon the people.</p>
 
<p>In other ways also the work our representatives would gladly accomplish for the uplifting of the people is thwarted. The natives, terrorized, flee from the approach of the unknown foreigner. The missionary in his touring finds villages vacated and leveled to the ground. The periodical flights of the people in certain districts render continuity of work impossible, and the total extermination of the people, accomplished now in several sections, obviously is fatal to the purpose represented by 

<pb n="p30"/>

the missionary's presence in the land. The humane aims of missionary effort, philanthropic and Christian, are hindered and defeated through the opposing blighting influence by which the land is desolated.</p>

<p>But a larger reason influences our representatives and ourselves in this appeal&#8212;that of regard for a people suffering from dreadful inhumanities. Those whose residence in the country gives them knowledge of these wrongs cannot remain silent without guilt. Repeated representations made to the Kongo Government by our missionaries having proved ineffectual, they and we are compelled by motives of common humanity and by regard for justice to bring our appeal to a higher resort.</p> 

<p>The Missionary A Refuge for A Haunted People.</p>

<p>The missionary cannot escape direct relation to this issue. The appeal of the people is constantly pressed upon him. Men, women, and children flee to the missions seeking protection. A white officer, unacquainted with the missionary whom he was addressing, after a cruel raid, jokingly remarked that he had killed many people and secured a fine lot of curios. He said that while his soldiers were firing upon the villages the people ran wildly about crying, "Sheppite, Sheppite." It was their name for Rev. W. H. Sheppard, the associate of Mr. Morrison, whom they were beseeching to come to their aid. The motive actuating our missionaries and ourselves, as we bring to you our request, is embodied in a sentence of a letter addressed by Rev. J. H. Weeks, of the English Baptist Missionary Society, to officials in the Kongo Government:</p> 

<q>I deeply regret having to write this letter to you, but I cannot sit quietly and see these unfortunate folk crushed out of existence by oppression and cruelty without making a protest in the name of religion and of humanity.</q>

<pb n="p31"/>
 
<p>Futility of Appeal to the State Government.</p>

<p>We think it will be clear to you that the case which we thus bring to your attention is one demanding the intervention of those responsible for the founding of the Independent State of the Kongo. May we urge that you shall not fail to note that appeal to the Government of that State would not meet fittingly the requirements of the case? In responsibility for the conditions now prevailing in this stricken land obviously the Government is involved, and it is scarcely appropriate to ask an alleged offender to make inquiry as to his own wrongdoing. The testimony to the existence of wrongs is testimony also to indisposition in the Government to remedy these wrongs.</p>
 
<p>The possibilities belonging to appeal to the Kongo Government have already been exhausted. Delay in bringing the story of these enormities formally to the attention of western governments is attributable to unwillingness to believe that the facts could be known to the Administration, and to the hope that when known they would secure redress. But all reports, personal and official, private and public, if receiving any attention have won at most only the renewal of professions of innocence and of disinterested and humane intentions. Investigations have not been so conducted as to satisfy the complainants. It is alleged that witnesses have been terrorized; indeed, the native dare not testify in a court whose highest authority is the Government under which he suffers. He has no resort but a patient bearing of wrongs that he may avoid wrongs yet more dreadful. The victims of a shocking outrage when told by an amazed visitor that they should complain to the State replied: "We should not be believed; they would put us in chains at once," and when told they should carry the bodies of their murdered dead in canoes to the official they replied, "We never could get past the sentries."</p> 

<p>It is clear that, inasmuch as it is part of the testimony of the witnesses in the case that complaints 

<pb n="p32"/>

have been made often to the Government only to be disregarded, that the so-called investigations have been an evasion, that, indeed, the system to which the Government is definitely and persistently committed is the fons et origo of the evils, these testimonials will have received the attention due them only when provision is made for investigation by a power external to the State. All replies proffered by the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo to the accusations made against it essentially are this: "The accusations are false." The question of the truth or falsity of the charges is the question at issue, and inquiry impartially conducted from without offers the one rational method for reaching a just answer to this question.</p>
 
<p>Interposition A Right of the Powers.</p>
 
<p>The right of the nations to interpose for the suppression of these evils seems clear. It has indeed been claimed by the Government of the Kongo State, as, for example, in reply to the note of the British Government, that, while the State "as created by international action, having been created, it is a sovereign power responsible only to itself for the administration of its internal affairs. If this claim were sound, it would be true that the action of the powers at Berlin, which gave the King a sovereignty unlimited by internal restraint, created the one wholly autocratic and irresponsible government in all the civilized world. The validity of this claim of one man to a gift of so fabulous value, involving so sweeping sacrifice of the primitive rights of more than a score of millions of people and the allied rights of all mankind, cannot be thought admissible. The question of gravest international concern is this: Is it true that a sovereign and absolute power was created at Berlin which is responsible only to itself, and that the pledges solemnly made to other powers, including our own Government are binding

<pb n="p33"/>
 
only in so far as in its sovereign discretion it may choose so to consider them?</p> 

<p>The Independent State of the Kongo acquired its international status by a formal acceptance of the provisions of the act of Berlin. This act is its charter, unique, and in its spirit as benignant as any known to the history of Christian civilization.</p>
 
<p>As President Cleveland, in his message of December, 1885, recognized, "The Berlin convention laid down certain obligations, purporting to be binding on the signatories." In the binding nature of these obligations the right and duty of subsequent supervision is involved. It is a fact of the highest importance that this right and duty were recognized distinctly in the report of a committee of the conference, in which it is said:</p>
 
<q>With regard to these native populations the conference must assume the position of an official guardian. The necessity of insuring the preservation of the natives, the duty of helping them to obtain a higher and better political and social status, the obligation to instruct them and initiate them into the advantages of civilization are unanimously recognized.</q> 

<p>But, in addition to these declarations of the purpose of the conference, it is also true that the Berlin agreement makes definite reservation of the right of revision of that agreement as belonging to the powers represented in the conference. Article 36 of the general act of Berlin provides: </p>

<q>The signatory powers of the present general act reserve to themselves the right to introduce into it subsequently, and by common accord, such modifications and improvements as experience may show to be expedient.</q>
 
<p>It is furthermore true that the appeal made by the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo to the conference at Brussels, in the year 1890, for authorization for the imposing of import duties, involved definite concession on the part of that State of right of supervision and revision as belonging to the parties creating it. If the State might without impropriety violate in respect of other features the compact made in the Berlin act, 

<pb n="p34"/>

it might without impropriety disregard its prohibition of import duties.</p>

<p>The Right, A Responsibility.</p>

<p>Concession of right implicitly involves an admission of obligation. The great treaty powers have continuing rights as supervisors and directors in the enterprise conducted by the King. The King is their trustee, to execute the power conferred by the treaty, and is answerable to them for the use of the powers intrusted to him. Is it too much to say that the great powers of the west are under obligation to communicate with the ruler of the Independent State of the Kongo concerning the statements relating to his rule, apparently so thoroughly supported, and to take such measures as will guarantee to these unhappy people the rights established for them in the treaty of Berlin?</p>

<p>Relation of Our Own Government to This Responsibility and Right.</p>

<p>This right and responsibility belonging to other nations we trust will be recognized as belonging to our own American Government. We are not signatories of the act of the Berlin Conference. Does this fact deny to us the right of action at the present juncture? We think this position must be regarded as indefensible.</p>
 
<p>It may, we think, justly be held that the sacred primal right of membership in the family of States in itself would justify inquiry and protest under the laws of nations.</p>
 
<p>The foremost part borne by us in the recognition and practical creation of the Kongo State cannot be regarded as without bearing upon the question of our relation to the present situation.</p>
 
<p>Our presence in the conference at Berlin, and our implicit indorsement of its action, which fell short of a technical ratification only because of considerations of a technical nature, further accentuates our interest in a just discharge of its 

<pb n="p35"/>

pledged obligations by the Government of the Kongo State.</p>
 
<p>The right involved in full participation in the conference at Brussels belongs to our Government. The charges made against the Independent State of the Kongo involve disloyalty to the understanding, and to the definite declarations of that conference as the) involve disloyalty to the conference at Berlin.</p>
 
<p>Furthermore, obviously the right of a party to a treaty is ours. Our treaty of 1891 secures to us definitely the right of freedom of trade, the right of all citizens to reside and build in the State. And this treaty, furthermore, formally secures to us all rights of the signatories of the Berlin agreement and the rights conceded to the most favored nation. It is these rights which by common report are violated by the deeds and claims of the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo.</p> 

<p>We would ask your attention to certain specific provisions of the Brussels agreement and of our existing treaty with the Kongo State. We are convinced that, if indorsing the position that this right belongs to our Government, you will hold that in our case, also, the right involves an obligation&#8212;grave as the seriousness of the wrongs to which it relates.</p> 

<q>[From the general act adopted at Brussels.]</q> 

<q>Preamble.</q>

<q>Being equally actuated by the firm intention of putting an end to the crimes and devastation engendered by the traffic in African slaves, of efficiently protecting the aboriginal population of Africa, and of securing for that vast continent the benefits of peace and civilization * * * .</q> 

<q>Art. II. Section I. These stations shall have the following subsidiary duties:</q> 

<q>1. To support, and, if necessary, to serve as a refuge for the native population * * * to initiate them in agricultural labor and in the industrial arts, so as to increase their welfare; to raise them to civilization and bring about the extinction of barbarous customs * * * .</q>
 
<q>2. To give aid and protection to commercial enterprises * * * and to prepare the way for the foundation of permanent centers of cultivation and of commercial settlements.</q>

<pb n="p36"/>

<q>3. To protect, without distinction of creed, the missions which are already or that may hereafter be established.</q>
 
<q>Art. V. The contracting powers pledge themselves * * * to enact * * * a law rendering applicable, on the one hand, the provisions of their penal laws concerning grave offenses against the person to those organizing and abetting slave hunting, to those guilty of mutilating male adults and children, and to all persons taking part in the capture of slaves by violence * * *.</q> 

<p>From our treaty of 1891 we make these citations:</p>

<q>Article I. There shall be full, entire, and reciprocal liberty of commerce, establishment and navigation between the citizens and inhabitants of the two high contracting parties.</q>
 
<q>The citizens and inhabitants of the United States of America in the Independent State of the Kongo and those of the Independent State of the Kongo in the United States of America shall have reciprocally the right, on conforming to the laws of the country, to enter, travel, and reside in all parts of their respective territories, to carry on business there. * * *</q> 

<q>They can freely exercise their industry or their business, as well wholesale as retail, in the whole extent of the territories. * * *</q> 

<q>In like manner they will enjoy reciprocally the treatment of the most favored nation in all that relates to rights, privileges, exemptions, and immunities whatsoever concerning their persons or their property, and in the matter of commerce, industry, and navigation. * * *</q>
 
<q>Art. IV. The citizens and inhabitants of the two countries shall enjoy, in the territory of the other, a full and entire liberty of conscience. They shall be protected in the free exercise of their worship; they shall have the right to erect religious edifices and to organize and maintain missions.</q>
 
<p>We would ask also that in view of the provision of our treaty, which concedes to us all rights accorded to the most favored nation, the language of the Anglo-Kongo convention of 1884 be taken into consideration.</p> 

<q>They shall have the right of buying, of selling, of letting and of hiring lands and buildings, mines, and forests situated within the said territories, and of founding houses of commerce. (Article II, Anglo-Kongo convention.)</q> 

<p>We would respectfully call your attention to the fact that, besides those forms of procedure by which international inquiry and interposition may
 
<pb n="p37"/>

be promoted, a definite line of action is opened for our Government by Article XIII of our treaty with the Independent State of the Kongo. This provision reads:</p> 

<q>In case a difference should arise between the two high contracting parties as to the validity, interpretation, obligation, or enforcement of any of the provisions contained in the present treaty and it could not be arranged amicably by diplomatic correspondence between the two governments, these last agree to submit it to the judgment of an arbitration tribunal, the decision of which they bind themselves to respect and execute loyally.</q>
 
<p>By this provision, if in no better way, the question as to the consistency with treaty obligations of the fundamental system established in the Independent State of the Kongo may reach a definite, judicial decision.</p>
 
<p>The Gravity of the Obligation.</p>
 
<p>The obligation resting upon us as a Government seems to us a grave and solemn one. The position of our Government is such that it can act without suspicion of unworthy motive and with influence indefinitely great. And, independently of the demand for protection for a helpless people, a question is at stake which is of commanding moral and political interest. May a State appropriate for its own aggrandizement the land, the products, all the emoluments, of a vast national territory? It is the issue of the closed door, closed against the people of the house and against the people of all lands. If the coming together of the powers were not demanded by need for inquiry into reported abuses, it would seem amply justified by the necessity for international judgment upon the astounding claim represented by the Government of the Independent State of the Kongo.</p> 

<p>And the issue relates not simply to the Belgian-Kongo rule; it relates to the Belgian-Kongo theory. The evil practice of the Kongo State is infectious. Proofs of this are not wanting in other African 

<pb n="p38"/>

territory. Shall this practice be further developed and the world's fields be appropriated for selfish aggrandizement? The menace is a serious one to the commercial interests of our Government and of all governments. The need is urgent that calm consideration and resolute action shall put upon this theory the stamp of international disapprobation and abhorrence. We believe that this is not a time when America can afford to keep silent. We are convinced that our Government would scarcely be willing that such an issue should be determined without its participation in deliberation and action.</p> 

<p>It has been held, and with reason, that the Independent State of the Kongo should prove as a second China as a market for the absorption of manufactured goods. Already rich areas are almost hopelessly impaired, and the depopulation of the land and the incitement of a brooding hatred in the hearts of the people threaten irrecoverable loss of the wealth rightfully belonging to the world.</p>
 
<p>It is on these high grounds we would bring to you our appeal: On the ground of concern for high political principles; on the ground of the rights of our citizens who would be branded as common thieves if they were to attempt in the Kongo State exercise of their just rights in respect of trade; on the ground of righteous protest against the violation of pledges solemnly given; above all, on the ground of that humane interest in the well-being of mankind, which influenced our Government in its recognition of the International Association of the Kongo and which increasingly is characteristic 
of its action in the parliament of the nations.</p>
 
<p>Our Request.</p> 

<p>We therefore pray your honorable bodies that you will take such action as seems to you most fitting for the promotion of a strict and impartial inquiry into present conditions in the Independent State of the Kongo through a tribunal external to the State, and that you will follow this action 

<pb n="p39"/>

with such other action as may be found necessary and appropriate for the correction of the evils from which that State is suffering. We are convinced that by every worthy consideration related to the case this course is commended. Reports of alleged wrongs certainly are sufficient in volume and definiteness to justify inquiry. The Government of the State itself should desire such investigation for the vindication of its good name if it be unjustly aspersed. The action asked by us, moreover, we are persuaded is favored by that instinctive love of just government and that compassion for helpless sufferers to which as a nation we are committed by the traditions of our past and by the generous sentiment and impulse of our people.</p> 

<p>Respectfully submitted, in behalf of the Conference of Missionary Societies.</p> 

<p>Thomas S. Barbour, Chairman.<lb/> 
W. M. Morrison, Secretary.</p> 

<p>April 16, 1904.</p> 

<p>Members of the conference: Henry C. Mabie, D.D., home secretary, American Baptist Missionary Union; Thomas S. Barbour, D.D., foreign secretary, American Baptist Missionary Union; S. H. Leslie, M.D., missionary, American Baptist Missionary Union at Banza Manteke, Africa; W. H. Chester, D.D., secretary, Southern Presbyterian Board; Rev. W. M. Morrison, missionary, Southern Presbyterian Board at Luebo, Africa; D. W. Snyder, M.D., missionary, Southern Presbyterian Board, formerly at Luebo, Africa; Rev. Archibald McLean, president, Foreign Christian Missionary Society; E. A. Layton, M.D., missionary, Foreign Christian Missionary Society at Bolengi, Africa.</p> 

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>