<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0082">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>"The World's Highway: More About the Congo" (1907)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0082</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The World's Highway: More About the Congo</title>
<title level="j">Voice of the Negro</title>
<biblScope unit="volume"/>
<biblScope unit="issue"/>
<date when="1907-02">February 1907</date>
<biblScope unit="page"/>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Daniel, John</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3252542">Root, Elihu, 1845-1880</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/45085839">Starr, Frederick 1858-1933</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Boston (Massachusetts)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term>Great Britain</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Congos</term>
<term>Kishenevs</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-19" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0082.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The World's Highway</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<p>More About the Congo</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>In this number of The Voice we publish a well written and copiously illustrated article on the Congo situation. The article was prepared with great care and by a man who has studied the situation from every side. Mr. John Daniel, Secretary of the Congo Reform Association, has no axe to grind in taking up this fight for the Congo native and against Leopold. He would far rather believe that the conditions are different from what they are, but there are no facts to sustain that belief.</p>

<p>Professor Frederick Starr of the University of Chicago has been sojourning in the Congo Free State for the last twelvemonth. In his series of articles appearing in the Chicago <hi rend="italics">Tribune</hi> he is inclined to discourage the present agitation and to question the motives behind the agitation. However, Professor Starr admits that "there are brutalities, chaingangs and mutilations in the Congo." He claims, however, that the United States is not in a position to rebuke a government which tolerates such infamies, because we have the same conditions in the Southern part of this country. That is a true and cutting statement. There are Congos and Kishenevs right here at home. A famous actress recently on leaving England for America remarked that she intended only to visit the civilized parts of the country. She explained her statement by saying that she did not intend to go "South of Washington nor West of Chicago." We have all along contended that to be consistent Congress ought to appoint a commission to investigate the South. This is said in no spirit of rancor. It is unfortunately true that the catalog of Southern infamies against the Negro may be stretched out almost to infinity without interruption, and the actual facts about conditions are not very well known in the North. The North and East almost invariably get a distorted version of the facts. If the truth could get a hearing in Congress we are sure a strong wave of indignation would sweep over the nation. Remedies for the present unequal and unjust conditions would follow. Then we would be in a better position to assume the role of critic to Belgium and Russia.</p>

<p>But, even though we still have tremendous beams in our own eyes, if we can remove the mote from the other fellow's, we shall have done some good. It will make our own position untenable. It will pave the way for meetings of protest in great European centres of population against American atrocities. By and by some European nation whose voice must be respected will demand the establishment of justice between man and man in the South. That is a selfish justification of our present course in favoring the agitation on the Congo atrocities. It will be noticed that in Mr. Daniels' article he has made no direct appeal to our readers for aid in the work which the association is so nobly doing. The main object of the association is to bring pressure to bear upon the Government in this matter so that it will take action. This pressure

<pb xml:id="p2" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0082.002"/>

must be brought about mainly through the expression of public feeling against the brutalities of Leopold and his cohorts. The association does its work by means of literature sent throughout the country, public addresses, a large correspondence and forceful representation to the different branches of our Government. If the Lodge resolution passes the Senate, Secretary Root must be urged to go ahead with the work without waiting for Great Britain to act. We must create a wave of international indignation that will culminate in an international conference. There are two things we want our readers to do. First, we want every one of them to write a strong letter to Secretary Root calling for action in this matter. Second, we want all of our readers who can to send a dime each to the Congo Reform Association, 723 Tremont Temple, Boston, Mass., to help carry on this work. We urge the colored people to remember that these are their brethren across the sea. We appeal to the white man's humanity. Now is the time to act.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
