<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>William Coppinger, "The Continent of the Future" (1881)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0013</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Continent of the Future</title>
<author n="Coppinger, William, 1828-1892">William Coppinger</author>
<editor/>
<pubPlace>Hampton, VA</pubPlace>
<publisher>Normal School Steam Press</publisher>
<date when="1881">1881</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Antusa</term>
<term>Arthington, Robert</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22441664">Behm, Ernst, 1830-1884</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term>Bolliglia</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22148544">Brazza, Pierre Savorgnan de, 1852-1905</term>
<term>Browning</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/80787">Cameron, Verney Lovett, 1844-1894</term>
<term>Chouver, J.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/161996663">Coppinger, William, 1828-1892</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39456173">Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891</term>
<term>Della Salla</term>
<term>Demeitri</term>
<term>Drake, F. J.</term>
<term>Dumbleton</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66543224">Duponchel, A. (Adolphe), 1821-1903</term>
<term>Ferreira, Antonio de Carvalho Fonseca Henriques</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/11129">Galliéni, Joseph Simon, 1849-1916</term>
<term>Gouldsbury</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43915538">Havelock, Arthur Elibank, Sir, 1844-1908</term>
<term>Hayes, James O.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27367745">Holub, Emil, 1847-1902</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44605276">Lenz, Oskar, 1848-1925</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term>Lombard</term>
<term>Mamoli</term>
<term>Matheis</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5231264">Moustier, M. (Marius), 1853-1886</term>
<term>Pastori</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/106968119">Petermann, A. (August), 1822-1878</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/67249204">Piaggia, Carlo, 1827-1882</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54448448">Pogge, Paul, 1839-1884</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10149663">Popelin, Emile 1847-1881</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17356103">Rohlfs, Gerhard, 1831-1896</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27187771">Schweinfurth, Georg August, 1836-1925</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/65976458">Sechele, Kgosi, approximately 1810-1892</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18600856">Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64121517">Soleillet, Paul, 1842-1886</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894"><term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry Morton, 1841-1904</term>
<term>Stevenson, James</term>
<term>Stocker</term>
<term>Thomson, Joseph</term>
<term>Vassian, L.</term>
<term>Vreeland, C. E.</term>
<term>Yates, Beverly P.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5113439">Zweifel, J. (Josuah)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abyssinia</term>
<term>Algeria</term>
<term>Alima River</term>
<term>Ambriz River</term>
<term>Ancobra River</term>
<term>Arabia</term>
<term>Asumare (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Atlantic Ocean</term>
<term>Bamaka (French Soudan)</term>
<term>Barotse Valley</term>
<term>Bengasi (Tripoli)</term>
<term>Benguela (Angola)</term>
<term>Beyrout (Syria)</term>
<term>Bihé (Angola)</term>
<term>Blue Nile River</term>
<term>Brass (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Brewerville (Liberia)</term>
<term>Boporo (Liberia)</term>
<term>Bornu Empire</term>
<term>Brass (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Cairo (Egypt)</term>
<term>Calcullo (Angola)</term>
<term>Canary Islands</term>
<term>Cape Coast (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Cape Verde</term>
<term>Cape Juby (Morocco)</term>
<term>Cape of Good Hope</term>
<term>Ceylon</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Dakar (Senegal)</term>
<term>Darfur</term>
<term>Delagoa Bay</term>
<term>Derna (Tripoli)</term>
<term>Dominica (West Indies)</term>
<term>Dondo (Angola)</term>
<term>Egypt</term>
<term>Elmina (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Empire of Uadai</term>
<term>Freetown (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Gambia</term>
<term>Gambia River</term>
<term>Gaboon River</term>
<term>Isangila (Congo)</term>
<term>Jerusalem (Ottoman Empire)</term>
<term>Kabenda (Congo)</term>
<term>Kafrio River</term>
<term>Khartoum (French Soudan)</term>
<term>Kingdom of Loango</term>
<term>Lake Nyassa</term>
<term>Lake Quilimane</term>
<term>Lake Tanganyika</term>
<term>Lake Toana</term>
<term>Lake Victoria Nyanza</term>
<term>Lagos (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Lokoja (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Madeira</term>
<term>Maliwanda</term>
<term>Mambe</term>
<term>Marfa River</term>
<term>Mecca (Ottoman Empire)</term>
<term>Medina (Liberia)</term>
<term>Medina (Senegal)</term>
<term>Mellacouri River</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Morocco</term>
<term>Nyampanga Island</term>
<term>Natal</term>
<term>New York (N.Y.)</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Ogowe River</term>
<term>Onitsha (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Port Lokko (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Red Sea</term>
<term>Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</term>
<term>Rovouma River</term>
<term>Sahara Desert</term>
<term>Sego (French Soudan)</term>
<term>Senegal</term>
<term>Saint Louis (Senegal)</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
<term>Saint Vincent</term>
<term>Senegambia</term>
<term>Suakin (French Soudan)</term>
<term>Scarcies River</term>
<term>Shire River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Socotra</term>
<term>South Africa</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loando</term>
<term>St. Thomas (St. Thomas and Prince)</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
<term>Sugaree River</term>
<term>Tacquah (Gold Coast)</term>
<term>Timbuctoo (French Sudan)</term>
<term>Transvaal</term>
<term>Tebreck (Tripoli)</term>
<term>Tenerife (Canary Islands)</term>
<term>Timbo (Fouta Djallon)</term>
<term>Tripoli</term>
<term>Tunis (Tunisia)</term>
<term>Vivi (Congo)</term>
<term>Western Islands</term>
<term>White Nile River</term>
<term>Zambezi River</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
<term>Zomba (Malawi)</term>
<term>Zululand</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Bechuanas</term>
<term>Galla</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Abyssinian</term>
<term>Baptist</term>
<term>Coptic</term>
<term>Episcopal</term>
<term>Heathen</term>
<term>Islam</term>
<term>Judaism</term>
<term>Methodist Episcopal</term>
<term>Southern Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-08-12" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Continent of the Future</p>

<p>Africa and its Wonderful Development&#8212;Exploration,
Gold Mining, Trade, Missions and Elevation.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The tide of modern civilization and religious development
is sweeping round the globe. With the rapid advance of India,
the unparalleled strides of Japan, and the steady progress of China to
the new era, Africa is about to reveal its long-kept secrets and its possibilities
of contributing to the elevation of its inhabitants and the
welfare of the world. Commerce, capital, science, philanthropy and
religion have joined hands to penetrate the mysterious land and cast
light on its gloomiest portions. Africa is very nearly everywhere regarded
as the continent of the future.</p>

<p>GOVERNMENTAL.&#8212;France seems about to absorb Tunis and Tripoli,
and to unite Algeria to her Senegal possessions. The Chambers
have voted eight millions of francs ($1,600,000) for two railroads: (1)
from Algiers to Timbuctoo, across the Sahara, and (2) from Saint Louis,
Senegal, to Bamaka and Sego. Two millions of francs ($400,000) have
also been appropriated for the construction of a telegraph line from
Dakar to Saint Vincent, to place Senegal in telegraphic connection
with Europe. A loan is proposed of forty-five millions of francs ($9,000,000)
for the formation of three hundred villages and the introduction
of two hundred thousand colonists into Algeria. This expanding
colony is just fifty years old. In 1830 the total exports and imports
did not amount to two million francs ($400,000.) They have 
now reached three hundred and sixty-five million francs, ($63,100,000.)</p>

<p>M. Soleillet and M. Doponchel give the result of their long and
thorough <sic>reconnoissance</sic> as highly favorable to the project of crossing
the Sahara by steam, and they describe the desert as far more fertile
than is commonly believed. The latter says: "What is being so
successfully accomplished by England in India, by the United States
in North America, and by Russia in Central Asia, that should we try
to do in emulation of their example&#8212;seek a continent whereon to
extend our beneficent influence, and find, by the employment of our

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.002"/>

idle capital, at once a new market for the products of our industries
and manufactures, and a vast centre of agricultural production, able
to supply us, at small cost, with the raw materials not indigenous to
our soil, which we now only obtain with difficulty from foreign sources.</p>

<p>The expedition under Gallieni is stated to have reached Saint 
Louis from Timbuctoo, having completed a survey for a railroad between
those points which is pronounced to be entirely feasible. He 
met with a friendly reception, and formed treaties with numerous 
tribes, whereby France is granted a right of, way, and may establish
ambassadorial or military representatives at the proposed principal
stations. M. Matheis has been commissioned by the French Government 
to explore the country from the bend of the Niger to Lake
Tchad. M. L. Vassian, an attache of the French Department for Foreign
Affairs, is to reside for a time at Khartoum, to study the nature of 
the commercial relations to be formed with Soudan.</p>
 
<p>At a conference at Paris in relation to the territories between Sierra
Leone and the Gambia, it is understood that the decision reached 
was that the French are to retain the Mellacouri and the English the
Scarcies. The newly appointed Governor of Sierra Leone, Arthur Elibank 
Havelock, Esq., was one of the representatives of the British
Government at the conference.</p>

<p>Portugal is actively caring for her extensive African domain.
The Governor-General of Angola has been directed to organize a system
of colonization in that province, by selecting a region best adapted
for its salubrity, fertility of soil, abundance of water and facility 
of communication, and to prepare accommodations for one hundred 
colonists and their families, an emigration having begun from
Madeira. Lorenzo Marquez, the port of Delagoa Bay, has been ceded 
to Great Britain. It is the best harbor on the south-eastern coast, 
while its geographical relation to Natal, Zululand and the 
Transvaal makes its possession of importance to England. 
The latter guarantees to Portugal the exclusive right to the 
territory between the Ambriz and Congo rivers. The concession made 
by the Portuguese Government to the Andrada Land Company, extending 
from the Shire to the Kafrio, at Nyampanga Island, about 
seven hundred miles, is in course of examination by a party of French
mining engineers. The Commercial Association of Lisbon is raising 
funds by subscription to be offered to the Government to co-operate 
with it in the foundation of civilizing stations in the Portuguese African colonies.</p>

<p>Spain is meditating a protectorate of Morocco. Messers Bolliglia,
Mamoli and Pastori, of the "Italian Society for Promoting Commercial

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.003"/>

Exploration in Africa," have left Tripoli to examine the elevated
plain of Barka and to found trading posts at Bengasi, Derna and Tebreck,
and afterwards others on the oasis bordering the road to Uadai
and Bornu. The Italian Government has contributed generously to
outfit the expedition. The same Society has dispatched M. Demeitri
and M. Michieli from Khartoum for the Red Sea, with a caravan 
of seven hundred camels laden with various kinds of merchandise
for trade. The Egyptian Government has sent the learned Rohlfs to
the King of Abyssinia to arrange mutual relations on a friendly basis.
The Sultan of Zanzibar has engaged the intrepid Thomson to conduct 
a geographical investigation of the Rovouma.</p>

<p>THE SLAVE TRADE.&#8212;It is estimated that fifty thousand natives 
are annually conveyed to the Turkish and Egyptian ports of the Red
Sea, where they are disposed of to dealers. The Sultan of Zanzibar 
has dispatched an armed force of five hundred men, commanded by 
an officer detailed from the British Army, in the direction of Lake
Tanganyika, and the British Government is to establish consuls at
Suakin and Khartoum, with authority to travel in Egypt and on the Red
Sea, "to heal the open sore of the world." The French Government is 
to make earnest efforts and to co-operate with England in all measures
having in view the same humane object. The Khedive has appointed 
Comte Della Salla to the special office of repressing the 
slave traffic in lower Egypt. It is to be regretted that at the Berlin
Congress in 1878, which afforded an excellent opportunity for concerting
a treaty on slavery between the Powers of Europe, this good 
result was rendered impossible by the action of the English representatives.</p>

<p>EXPLORATIONS.&#8212;In the exploration of Africa the Germans keep
the lead, of which almost nothing is known until they appear after
an absence of a few years, with a fund of knowledge that is astonishing.
Witness, for instance, the apparition of Lenz from a journey 
from Morocco to Timbuctoo, and thence to Medina and St. Louis. 
This famous traveler reports passing through towns of from ten 
to thirty thousand inhabitants, and of having made discoveries which
explode the theory of converting the Sahara into an ocean. He states
that the most depressed portion of El Juff, the body of the desert, is
some five hundred feet above the level of the sea, and that there
exist in several oases points which promise to be of great utility for the proposed Sahara railway.</p>

<p>Dr. Pogge is penetrating the country inland from St. Paul de Loando,
the German Government having asked for him the protection 
of the Portuguese Government in its African jurisdiction. Dr. Holub,

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.004"/>

who has made interesting researches on the Zambesi, intends to cross 
the continent from south to north. Starting from the Cape of Good 
Hope he is to strike the Zambesi, thence the watershed district between
that river and the Congo, and on to Egypt through Darfur.</p>

<p>Dr. Stocker is exploring Lake Toana. M. Piaggia is traversing Soudan,
south of Khartoum, between the Blue and White Nile, M. Lombard, 
corresponding secretary of the Normandy Society of Geography, 
has entered on a scientific mission to Abyssinia. M. J. Chouver, 
a Hollander of fortune and experience as a traveler, has reached the
Galla country on his way to the Cape of Good Hope. Capt. Ferreira,
Governor of Benguela, and several officers of the army, have offered
their services to the Geographical Society of Lisbon for a Portuguese 
expedition across Africa, starting from the West Coast. M. Antusa 
is organizing a commercial station at Zomba, where he is to be joined 
by workmen whom the Portuguese Government has promised to furnish 
to erect buildings. The learned Dr. Schweinfurth has returned 
from a visit to the Island of Socotra, off the coast of Aden, and affirms
that it is very fertile, with a splendid and varied vegetation. One-fourth 
of its plants are peculiar to the locality.</p>

<p>M. Moustier, who in 1879, with M. Zweifel, discovered the source 
of the Niger, is again to start from Freetown on a trading venture and 
to fix the exact geographical position of "the rise of the mysterious river." 
Lieut. Dumbleton and Surgeon Browning, R. A., are in charge of
an expedition to penetrate, by the Gambia, into the valley of the
Niger to Timbuctoo. Dr. Gouldsbury lately led an exploring
party from the river Gambia, via Timbo and Port Lokko, to Sierra 
Leone, the outlay for which from the colonial treasury was 
£2,400, ($12,000.)</p>

<p>THE CONGO.&#8212;The illustrious Stanley has reached his second 
station on the Congo, Isangila, about 30 miles above Vivi, which point
was gained only after faithful but weary toil, and against every kind
of difficulty. He was obliged to throw bridges across the streams, 
open, hatchet in hand, a route across dense forests, blow up rocks;
leading the way with a group of pioneers, and after advancing a 
little, to make a halt, pitch a camp, then go back to bring by instalments 
the rest of the convoy, till all were united. Count de Brazza 
has ascended the Ogowe to its headwaters, reaching thereby
the sources of several of the affluents of the Congo. Descending
one of these, the Alima, partly along the shore and partly by 
boats, he struck the Congo below Stanley Pool, and coming down 
the river he met Stanley. It is suggested that a more practicable
route to the interior than that by the lower Congo may be opened by

<pb xml:id="p005" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.005"/>

the Ogowe and the streams which rise near its source. The Count is 
again to descend the Alima, this time in a transportable steam launch,
and then to make a thorough examination of the valley of the Congo
&#8212;the area of which is estimated to be four times that of France.</p>

<p>TELEGRAPHIC.&#8212;Telegraphic communication has been established
between Elmina and Cape Coast. The Portuguese Commissioner of 
Public Works has constructed in Angola a telegraphic line from St.
Paul de Loando to Dondo and Calcullo. Preparations are making
for its extension. The French Government proposes to connect Tunis
with Corsica by cable. A third cable has been laid from Marseilles to
Algiers. A second telegraphic line is in operation between Algeria 
and Tunis.</p>

<p>GOLD MINES.&#8212;Six companies are working on the Gold Coast
with encouraging prospects. Improved machinery has been shipped
by the African Company, and its mine is reported to be one of extraordinary 
richness. The success of the Gold Coast Company places it 
in the highest rank of gold mine enterprise. At meetings of the Effuenta
Company (July 7 and 21) resolutions were adopted to create an 
additional two thousand shares of £5 each, ($25,) to be distributed
among the existing shareholders proportional to their present holding.
The number of shares applied for was more than double the 
amount to be issued. The Akankoo Gold Coast Company&#8212;a new
organization&#8212;has acquired territory on the borders of the river Ancobra, 
and the celebrated Cameron has been engaged to open up the 
property. The British authorities have placed a civil commandant 
with a police force at Tacquah. Much of the delay experienced in 
the production of the precious metal is attributed in some cases to error
of management, perhaps unavoidable, and in all to the many difficulties
encountered in an almost unknown region, with the additional disadvantages of a very unhealthy climate for Europeans.</p>

<p>FINANCIAL.&#8212;A prospectus has appeared for the establishment of
"The Bank of West Africa," capital, £500,000, ($2,500,000,) in fifty
thousand shares of £10 each, ($50.) The chief office is to be in London,
with branches at Sierra Leone and Lagos. The shares of the 
Standard Bank of South Africa, £25, ($125,) paid, are quoted at 57, 
and the dividends paid for the last two years have been sixteen per
cent. Postal money order offices have been opened between Sierra 
Leone and the Gambia, at the rate of three shillings (75 cents) per
£10, ($50.)</p>

<p>COMMERCIAL.&#8212;Africa contains resources upon which large portions
of the enlightened world will in no very remote future be dependent, 
and it possesses the very highest capacity for the consumption

<pb xml:id="p006" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.006"/>

of many of the productions of civilization. One of the marked
developments is the numerous orders for utensils and simple machinery 
of various kinds, to be worked by hand or with light power, and 
for mechanical tools and agricultural implements. The business is 
already extensive and is likely to be of immense magnitude. Dr. Holub
describes Prince Sechele, chief of the Bechuanas, as living in a 
grand abode, which he had erected in European style, at a cost of $15,000. 
Khartoum is making astonishing progress. Magnificent stores 
have been built within the last three years, and everything in modern
civilization can now be had there. The Northwest Company is extending
commerce at Cape Juby. The security afforded since 
the "annexation" by England of Lagos has powerfully helped 
it to become the "Liverpool of Africa." The declared value of its exports
in 1878 was £577,346, ($2,886,730.) The number, tonnage, &amp;c, 
of steam vessels which entered Lagos in the same year is thus given:</p>

<table>
<row>
<cell>Nationality.</cell>
<cell>Steamers.</cell>
<cell>Tonnage.</cell>
<cell>Crews.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>British</cell>
<cell>144</cell>
<cell>141,590</cell>
<cell>5,746</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>German</cell>
<cell>72</cell>
<cell>4,251</cell>
<cell>1,177</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell>
<cell>216</cell>
<cell>145,841</cell>
<cell>6,293</cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>"The Lagos Warehouse and Commission Company," capital £50,000,
($250,000) in £5 ($25) shares, has been formed, for the purpose of
founding a wholesale warehouse at Lagos, and, when desirable, at other
important points on the West Coast. Thus a native merchant will
be put in possession of two thirds of the net value of his consignment
immediately the Company is in possession of his produce, and he will 
be enabled to have all his produce realized in the home market.</p>

<p>STEAMERS.&#8212;Twenty-five years ago it took a passenger from the
United States one hundred and thirty days to reach Corisco; now a
trip via Liverpool of about a month, in a palace compared with the
pent-up quarters of a sailing ship, and tables furnish with luxuries instead 
of ringing the changes of salt beef and hard bread from day to 
day. Twenty-eight steamships afford weekly communication between
Liverpool and the West Coast. The vessels of "the African Steamship
Company" are named as follows: Africa, Akassa, Ambriz, Benin, 
Biafra, Ethiopia, Landana, Mayumba, Nubia, Opobo, Whydah and 
Winnebah, and those of "the British and African Steam Navigation 
Company" bear the following names: Benguela, Bonny, Cameroon,
Congo, Corisco, Dodo, Forcades, Formoso, Gaboon, Kinsembo, Loando,
Lualaba, Ramos, Roquelle, Senegal and Volta. "The West African 
Steam Navigation Company" also employ a number of steamships

<!-- PAGE 7 IS A MAP -->

<pb xml:id="p008" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.008"/>

ships in the West African trade. Messrs. Rubattino &amp; Co. announce
their intention to put on several steamers between Genoa and Bengasi.
Not a steamer from the United States to Africa!</p>

<p>A company has been formed in New York for "the establishment
of a line of steamships for passengers, mail and freight, between New
York, Madeira, St. Thomas and Teneriffe, Cape de Verde, the Western
Islands, the Canary Islands, and the ports of the West Coast of
Africa." The capital stock is $100,000; and may be increased to $4,000,000;
shares $100. Such a line would open cheap and rapid communication
between the Liberian Republic and our own, furnishing
facilities for the thousands of people of color who desire to obtain an
expansive field for their energies, and bringing to our market the valuable
staples of its productive soil. In relation to this important project
an experienced missionary writes: "Often, during these twenty 
years, I have been surprised at the apparent indifference of American
capitalists and ship owners to the share that they might have obtained
in the profits of the African trade, other than slaves. I have 
seen two English lines of steamers (the South and the West, having 
their termini respectively at the Cape of Good Hope and the mouth 
of the Niger) develop by rich opposition to five, and the termini of
three of them extended from the Niger down to the Congo-Livingstone,
and literally every nation of Europe engaged in their profits, 
while America has scarcely a showing." A subsidy or liberal legislation
by Congress is counted upon before additional steps in this enterprise
are taken. And among other public action tending to success is the
creation and appointment of consuls at the Gold Coast, Lagos and
Bonny; and vice-consuls at smaller points between Monrovia and the 
Niger, to be under the supervision of the Minister Resident to Liberia.</p>

<p>RAILROAD SURVEY.&#8212;While the United States flagship Ticonderoga,
Commodore Shufeldt, was on the West African coast, two of her 
officers, Lieut. Drake and Master Vreeland, assisted by eleven men
from the ship and twenty-seven natives furnished by the Liberian
Government, made a survey of the St. Paul's river, and ran a line of
levels along its northern bank and some distance inland, to determine 
the feasibility of constructing a railroad to connect Monrovia with 
the Soudan Valley, via Boporo. This <sic>reconnoissance</sic> proved that the
engineering difficulties would be comparatively trifling. There is no
doubt that Monrovia would be the most available point for the
starting of such a road, as it would pass through an entirely virgin
country and penetrate to a salubrious region, whose resources for 
trade, known to be prodigious, are as yet untouched. Such a connection
with the interior, with the various appliances of civilization

<pb xml:id="p009" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.009"/>

which must follow would be one of the most effective agencies for
promoting vigorous colonization, of the immigrants, who would at 
once reach a healthy and fertile district, and would prove great
practical power in the advancement of missionary work, and immediately
become an important auxiliary in developing and <sic>controling</sic> an 
immense and valuable commerce.</p>

<p>This <sic>reconnoissance</sic> was the first made in that quarter, and it has 
done much toward bringing the interior tribes into commercial and
friendly relations with the Liberians. Other surveys were conducted 
by the same bold and public-spirited officers, including that of the
Sugaree and Marfa rivers. The presence of the Ticonderoga and Commodore
Shufeldt will long be pleasantly remembered, and good 
continue to result. This accomplished officer, in letter dated April
1881, remarks: "In view of the many failures which have been recorded 
in every age of the world, Liberia may be regarded as success. 
* * * This, the first effort of the African race to establish a
free government upon its own soil, merits and should receive the
sympathy and encouragement of every man, woman and child in America."</p>

<p>LIBERIA COFFEE.&#8212;The species of coffee which indigenous to
Liberia promises to have an important influence on the industry of 
those countries in which the coffee blight has almost extinguished the
Arabian coffee plant. In Dominica, W. I., the Liberia coffee, from 
seedings planted in 1874, has proved impervious to the ravages of the 
blight, and its productiveness matter of astonishment. The 
stranger described as "much larger than that of Arabia, being, indeed,
in its native state small tree, its leaves much larger the berries 
are twice the size of the ordinary coffee bean, and the
flavor is excellent." The Liberia coffee seed has been introduced
into Ceylon, and Liberian coffee from that isle commands much 
higher price than the Ceylon, (Arabian) coffee. The bark Elverton
took from Liberia to Rio Janerio some one hundred 
thousand coffee plants and fifty thousand pounds of coffee seed, 
and returning to Monrovia, readily obtained a similar cargo for the 
same parties in Brazil. A German trading firm extending the
coffee culture a short distance inland, near the Gaboon, with scions
procured in Liberia. The Republic in its infancy with regard to the
cultivation of the far-famed berry. The crop last year said to have
reached half million of pounds.</p>

<p>MOHAMMEDANISM.&#8212;Enthusiastic propagandists of Islam, without
commission or compensation of any kind, but trusting wholly to that
hospitality which the pride of the Oriental, pass from village to village

<pb xml:id="p010" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.010"/>

reading the Koran and giving instructions to wondering groups 
of natives. Whole tribes are stated to be converted to the Mahommedan
faith. The eminent scholar and writer, Rev. Dr. Blyden,* says: 
"Africans are continually going to and fro between the Atlantic Ocean 
and the Red Sea. I have met in Liberia and in its eastern frontiers,
Mohammedan Negroes born in Mecca, the holy city of Arabia, who thought 
they were telling of nothing extraordinary when they were detailing the
incidents of their journey, and of the journey of their friends, from the
banks of the Niger&#8212;from the neighborhood of Sierra Leone and Liberia&#8212;
across the continent to Egypt, Arabia and Jerusalem. I saw in Cairo 
and Jerusalem, some years ago, West Africans who had come on business 
and on religious pilgrimage from their distant homes in Senegambia." 
The promoters of Christianity are using these native travelers 
and missionaries of the false prophet. Copies of the Holy Scriptures 
in Arabic, printed at Beyrout, are sent to Egypt and for circulation 
in the Delta and along the valley of the Nile, and to Liberia, whence
they are distributed among the inhabitants of vast outstretching 
realms whose vernacular is the Arabic.</p>

<p>POPULATION.&#8212;The population of Africa, exclusive of its Islands,
is estimated by Dr. Behm, in Peterman's "Mittheilungun," at 201,787,000.
Of these the number of Protestant communicants in the various 
colonial and mission churches was reported in 1880 as 122,700; the 
number composing the communities connected with these churches 
506,966; the number of Jews, 350,000; of Coptic, Abyssinian and similar
Christians, 4,535,000; of Mohammedans, 51,170,000; of heathen,
145,225,000.</p>

<p>To carry the gospel to these millions, sixty four societies are at
work. In South Africa and the colonies and Sierra Leone and Liberia 
there are connected with colonial churches 468 ministers, evangelists 
and teachers, of whom 54 are natives. The other white missionaries 
and teachers on the continent, are reported as 662, with 1095 
natives, making 1757 mission workers proper, and 2,255 ministers,
missionaries and teachers of all kinds, engaged in religious labors.</p>

<p>The population of Liberia, including Medina, may be 1,400,000. 
The largest proportion of the natives are Mohammedans, perhaps 
1,000,000. There are 26 Baptist churches, reporting 24 ministers and
1,928 communicants. The Protestant Episcopal Church of the United 
States reports one bishop and 31 others, missionaries, teachers and
assistants, 361 communicants, 597 Sunday-school scholars and 415 in

<fw type="note">* Liberal use has been made of the writings of this gifted Negro, and of the pages of the Missionary Herald, of Boston; Foreign Missionary, of New York, African Times, of London, and L' Afrique, of Geneva.</fw>

<!-- PAGE 11 IS A MAP -->

<pb xml:id="p012" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.012"/>

day and boarding-schools. The report of the Methodist Episcopal 
Church of the United States, gives 25 ministers, 10 assistants, 4 native 
preachers and 47 local preachers and teachers, 2,200 members, 1,831
Sabbath-school scholars and 300 day scholars. The American Presbyterian 
Church (North) reports 9 <sic>misionaries</sic> and assistants, 270 communicants, 
and 65 pupils in schools. Total 104 ministers, assistants and 
teachers reported, 4,759 communicants, 2,428 Sabbath-school scholars 
and 780 day pupils.</p>

<p>It is a suggestive truth that a few only of the "104 ministers, assistants 
and teachers" laboring in Liberia were sent by missionary societies, 
but that nearly all of them were sent or are the children of men sent
by the American Colonization Society as emigrants, and established 
there with means of subsistence, This single fact teaches that in proportion 
as the emigrants from this country are multiplied, the Christian 
laborers are <sic>aiso</sic> multiplied.</p>

<p>MISSIONS.&#8212;The six European missions commenced in Central
Africa since the death of Dr. Livingstone have been constantly reinforced 
and strengthened, viz.: The Presbyterian stations on Lake 
Nyassa; the Church Missionary Society efforts on Lake Victoria Nyanza; 
the London Missionary Society operations on Lake Tanganyika; 
the French Bassuto extension to the Barotse Valley, and the Baptist 
Mission and the Livingstone Inland Mission, both on the Congo. The 
two latter named are pushing inland from the coast; the first on the
southern and the other on the northern side of the river. The Baptists 
are nearing the accomplishment of their first leading design, viz;
the establishment of a station at Stanley Pool, to be used as a base 
of operations beyond. A gentleman has given the £4,000 ($20,000)
necessary to procure a steel boat to be named the "Plymouth," to be 
used upon the Congo. The Livingstone Inland Mission (undenominational, 
begun in 1878,) has founded five stations and passed some
two hundred of the three hundred miles to overcome the cataracts, 
where the river stretches out in navigable waters for about one thousand 
miles. Here it is intended to locate an industrial mission station, 
and to make the work ultimately self-supporting and self-extending.</p>

<p>An offer of £4,000 ($20,000) has been made by James Stevenson,
Esq., of Glasgow, for the construction of a road between Lakes Nyassa 
and Tanganyika. The gift is based on the condition that the 
London Missionary Society and the Livingstonia Mission open and
maintain stations at Mambe and Maliwanda, on the line of the proposed 
road, and that the Central African Trading Company undertake 
to keep up regular communication between Lakes Tanganyika

<pb xml:id="p013" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.013"/>

and Quilimane. The distance between the lakes is about two hundred 
and twenty miles. The London Missionary Society has resolved 
to assume the conditions as far as it is concerned, and the Livingstonia 
Mission of the Scotch Free Church has sent a force to begin 
the station at Maliwanda.</p>

<p>Christendom knows not any other such mission as the Niger mission
of the Church Missionary Society, begun in 1867, to evangelize that 
portion of the continent by native Africans, headed by a native African, 
Bishop Crowther. Large and increasing Christian congregations 
exist at Bonny and Brass, and assemblies of varying sizes at Onitsha, 
Asumare and Lokoja. Sixteen hundred worshippers attended religious 
services at Bonny last Christmas. Kings and chieftains are 
erecting churches for themselves and their subjects. A cathedral is
to be built at Bonny at a cost of £2,000, ($10,000.)</p>

<p>The appointment of a Secretary by the American Board of Commissioners 
for Foreign Missions to superintend its operations in Africa, 
indicates an earnest purpose with respect to that land. Three pioneer 
missionaries have been cordially received by the King of Bailunda, 
and others are on their way to found a station at Bihe, which 
lies behind Benguela, some 250 miles from the Atlantic Ocean, an elevated 
region, inhabited by large and compact tribes.</p>

<p>The American Missionary Association has sent two commissioners 
to select a site for a station near the headwaters of the Nile, in aid 
of which Robert Arthington, Esq., of Leeds, has contributed £3,000, 
($15,000,) and English Christians have given a like sum. Two missionaries 
are under appointment to occupy this field. The American
Baptist Missionary Union is considering the Soudan as a theatre 
of labor, stimulated by an offer from Mr. Arthington of £7,000
($35,000) toward a mission on an extensive scale in that populous district. 
No man in this age has done so much to stimulate missionary 
enterprise as Mr. Arthington. The Southern Presbyterian Board of
Missions is contemplating the opening of a station at Kabenda, preparatory 
to an advance on the centre of the Kingdom of Loango.</p>

<p>AMERICAN COLONIZATION SOCIETY.&#8212;This association is quietly 
prosecuting its work of boundless scope and thrilling issues. An impartial 
observer of its progress in the United States, and who has personally 
seen its fruit on the coast of Africa lately declares: "This was the 
first and remains the only Society ever organized for the explicit purpose 
of giving the Negro perfect freedom, of promoting his education 
for his own good, of making him independent, of giving him a country 
he can call his own, and of elevating his race to the standard of a
Christian nation. * * * * * Liberia's flag is now honored by all

<pb xml:id="p014" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.014"/>

Christian nations, and none more deserves honor, for the cause over
which it floats is the grandest and holiest which ever gave birth to a
nation—the redemption of a whole race of mankind from heathenism 
and slavery."</p>

<p>The number of persons provided passage to and homes in Liberia 
by the Society in 1880 exceeded that in any one year since 1872. One 
of its recent proteges, Rev. James O. Hayes, a graduate of Shaw University, 
writes: "I have met many of the prominent citizens and
others, all of whom have extended to me the warm hand of fellowship 
and welcome. Hon. Beverly P. Yates, who has resided in this Republic 
fifty-two years, remarked to me that he would prefer Liberia to 
America, even if he were made President of the United States. I have 
two brothers and their families, with numerous friends residing at 
Brewerville, and they are prospering finely. The conviction is 
strengthened by all I see that persons who improve the advantages
afforded immigrants here could not be induced to exchange countries." 
The Society looks hopefully for that increase in gifts which
the broadening work imperatively demands.</p>

<p>CLIMATE.&#8212;Africa continues to be guarded by her malarious seaboard 
and poisonous fevers, and alien travelers, explorers, miners and 
missionaries still there find early graves. Statistics show the difference 
in the effects&#8212;of the climate upon the white, the mulatto and the 
black man. In the recent Ashantee campaign, out of the heavy death
list of forty-two English officers only six died of wounds. Four 
scientific explorers are known to have fallen in the last few months,
including the hardy Popelin, the leader of the second Belgian expedition. 
Each of the three first stations of the Livingstone Inland 
Mission has been consecrated by the call of one of its founders to 
higher spheres and grander activities. The Presbytery of West Africa 
has had during the past twenty-five years eleven members. Four were 
pure Negroes, the others mulattoes and quadroons. Of the mixed 
men six are dead, all comparatively young. Of the Negroes two are 
dead, both over sixty. Of the two who survive, one is nearly seventy 
and the other is fifty years of age. The Niger mission of the Church 
Missionary Society is manned wholly by native Africans, among whom 
the deaths in twenty-three years have been but eight, and that in a 
section which is mostly swampy and under water several months in 
the year. The Negro is the man of God's right hand in Africa.</p>

<p>WORKMEN.&#8212;A convention of colored delegates from twelve Southern 
States, held at Montgomery, Ala., organized the Baptist Foreign 
Mission Convention, the object of which "is to give the gospel to
the people of Africa." Three ministers have expressed their readiness

<!-- PAGE 15 IS A MAP -->

<pb xml:id="p016" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.016"/>

to enter upon labors in "fatherland." The African Civil and
Evangelical Association has for its purpose "the sending and supporting 
of missionaries and school teachers in Western and interior
Africa, a duty we owe as descendants of that continent to our kinsmen 
there." The Presbyterian Synod of the Atlantic, composed
largely of Freedmen, has inaugurated a movement looking to missionary 
efforts in the country of their ancestors.</p>
 
<p>There is a bright and cheering history of African enlightenment
to be written. The six millions of reserve force now drilling in 
America for the final victory are to be called out. They are now 
on the move. Thousands have already developed many of the proper 
qualifications for the work, and are waiting the means to go forward. 
And this mighty country has peculiar facilities for the introduction 
and extension of civilization. Europe has no population 
available. Entering on the West Coast, the people and Government 
of the United States may stretch a chain of settlements of her own 
citizens through the whole length of Soudan, from the Niger to the 
Nile&#8212;from the Atlantic to the Indian Ocean.</p>

<p>COLONIES.&#8212;A protracted experience convinces us that it may be 
laid down as a principle demonstrated by numerous examples, that 
if Western and Central Africa is ever to advance in civilization; if 
its inhabitants are ever to become not Europeanized, but intelligent,
competent and productive Africans; if they are ever to be brought 
into commercial relations mutually beneficial with Europe and America, 
it must be by establishing and fostering such colonies as Liberia. 
If it is the desire of Christians to abolish polygamy, to put a stop to 
domestic slavery, to encompass and vivify the people by civilizing influences, 
to elevate their thought, ennoble their action, and regenerate 
the continent, these things must be done by planting colonies of 
Christian and civilized Negroes along that coast and in the interior.</p>

<p>"Worthy the Lamb, for he was slain for us!<lb/> 
The dwellers in the vales and on the rocks<lb/>
Shout to each other, and the mountain tops <lb/>
From distant mountains catch the flying joy:<lb/>
Till, nation after nation taught the strain, <lb/> 
Earth rolls the rapturous hosanna round."</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p017" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.017"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>[Editorial from The Sun, of Baltimore, October 25, 1881.]</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Continent of the Future.&#8212;The Supplement of 
"The Sun" to-day contains an article by Mr. William Coppinger, Secretary 
of the American Colonization Society, upon Africa, its condition 
from various points of view, its trade, mines, agricultural products 
and increased closeness of relation with the civilized world, which 
cannot fail to prove of interest to all persons concerned in the future 
of the mysterious "dark continent." Americans can hardly conceive 
the importance attached by Europeans at present to the matters 
with which Mr. Coppinger so fully and entertainingly deals. The continental 
powers of Europe, perceiving the immense advantage possessed 
by England in having her Indian Empire and her colonies as 
outlets for her manufactures and excess of population, are seeking to 
imitate her example by founding claims to such territories yet unoccupied 
by Europeans as are unable to protect themselves from aggression 
backed by Krupp guns. After the pickings of Russia, England 
and France, there is little of Asia, besides, perhaps, the Corean peninsula,
left to appropriate. The jealousy of the United States has deterred 
the nations of the Eastern hemisphere from attempts, like that
of Maximilian in Mexico, to found claims upon territories in either 
North or South America. Africa remains, and is at their doors. 
Having an area of 9,858,000 square miles, and an estimated population, 
mostly barbarous, of about 201,787,000 souls, it offers, despite 
its unfavorable climate, great advantages to the European people 
who shall first appropriate its fertile interior, its trade in mineral 
and agricultural products, and open these up to European commerce
by means of lines of steamboat and railway communications. Africa 
will perhaps at no distant day become to Europe what North and 
South America have been for the last two hundred years, the recipient 
of their overflow of population and their chief producer of 
food. Its capabilities are untried, but we know they are enormous. 
Explorers within recent years have traversed the continent in every 
direction, and have brought back reports generally favorable. The 
Sahara is shown to be by no means the barren waste it has been 
represented, and the Soudan has had its vast capabilities exploited. 
Behind the explorer comes the military post and European civilization. 
As was shown in "The Sun" some time ago, France has 
since 1854 been extending her acquisitions from St. Louis, on the

<pb xml:id="p018" facs="teaa.en.book.0013.018"/>

West Coast, along the Senegal and Gambia rivers, eastwardly 
into the Soudan, until she now possesses a large area of country, and 
exerts a predominant influence over a territory comparable, it is said, 
in extent with that of England in India. It is to consolidate and 
strengthen her acquisitions that she proposes to add Tunis to Algeria, 
and it would be doing scant justice to her policy to suppose 
that the seizure of Tunis is a detached and insignificant incident. 
Mr. Coppinger narrates in detail the measures being taken to confirm 
her position in Africa, as against her various European competitors.
A notable fact in connection with the Islamic movement, 
of which so much is said, is the large hold the Mohammedan religion 
already has in Africa. There are 51,170,000 of this faith to 
145,225,000 heathen, 350,000 Jews and 4,535,000 Coptic and other 
Christians. Even in Liberia, out of a total population estimated by 
Mr. Coppinger at 1,400,000, fully 1,000,000 are Mohammedans, and 
of an aggressive character.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>