<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0053">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, "Forty-Sixth Annual Report of the American Colonization Society" (1863)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0053</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Forty-Sixth Annual Report of the American Colonization Society</title>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
<date when="1863-02">February 1863</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62601090">Banneker, Benjamin, 1731-1806</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51556067">Benson, Stephen Allen, 1816-1865</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term>Briggs, L., Jr.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/6453350">Caldwell, Elias Boudinot, 1776-1825</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32012452">Clay, Henry, 1777-1852</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76392240">Crummell, Alexander, 1819-1898</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/50036467">Cuffe, Paul, 1759-1817</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/101486675">Drayton, Boston J. (Boston Jenkins), 1817-1866</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39258883">Finley, Robert, 1772-1817</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54969088">Harper, Robert Goodloe, 1765-1825</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41866059">Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826</term>
<term>Johnson, J. D.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22144104">Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/59096754">Madison, James, 1751-1836</term>
<term>Maxwell, George</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27870303">Mercer, Charles Fenton, 1778-1858</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17226855">Milton, John, 1608-1674</term>
<term>Morris, Edward S.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/106963836">Park, Mungo, 1771-1806</term>
<term>Roberts, J. J.</term>
<term>Seys, John</term>
<term>Sibley, J. L.</term>
<term>Warner, D. B.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31432428">Washington, George, 1732-1799</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Baltimore (Maryland)</term>
<term>Ethiopia</term>
<term>Ganges River</term>
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Kentucky</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Maryland</term>
<term>Mississippi River</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Tennessee</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Caucasian</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christian</term>
<term>Episcopal</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-10-29" who="kln">reviewed encoding</change>
<change when="2019-04-11" who="pr">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p33" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.001"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>Forty-Sixth Annual Report
of the
American Colonization Society.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<p>Emigration.</p>

<p>The civil war, and the various questions which have divided
and distracted the minds of our free people of color, have prevented
any large emigration to Liberia during the year. But two small
expeditions have left Baltimore for that Republic&#8212;the bark Justina, 
which sailed on the 10th of June, with eighteen emigrants,
and the Mary Caroline Stevens with forty-seven emigrants on the
15th of November. A larger number had been expected from Tennessee 
and Kentucky, but the state of the times prevented their

<pb xml:id="p34" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.002"/>

departure. In the Justina supplies were sent out for the support of
emigrants, and some four thousand dollars for defraying expenses
and making improvements in Liberia, while the principal part of 
the cargo (the whole cost of which was $30,000) was shipped to 
fill orders sent out by citizens of Liberia.</p>

<p>In addition to the supplies for the emigrants, goods to the value
of several thousand dollars were sent out in the Stevens for expenses 
and trade. All the emigrants by this expedition, with the
exception of a single family from Maryland, were from free States;
and among the cabin passengers were the Rev. John Seys, United
States Agent for Recaptured Africans; Edward S. Morris, Esq.,
who visits Liberia with Philanthropic views, and to promote its
agricultural interests, with several individuals and families, under
the care of the Presbyterian and Episcopal Board of Missions.
Five emigrants have also sailed from New York during the year.</p>

<p>Commissioners sent from Liberia to the U.S.</p>

<p>The Legislature of Liberia, at its last session, authorized the
President of this Republic to appoint suitable commissioners, citizens
of Liberia, to the colored people in the United States, "to present
the cause of Liberia to the descendants of Africa in that country, and
to lay before them the claims that Africa has upon their sympathies,
and the paramount advantages that would accrue to them, their
children, and their race, by their return to their fatherland."</p>

<p>On the 18th of March, President Benson appointed as Commissioners 
for this service, Reverends Messrs. Alex. Crummell, and Edw.
W. Blyden, and J. D. Johnson, Esq., who early thereafter came
to the United States. The Executive Committee cordially approved
of this movement of the Liberian Government, and of the object proposed 
by the Commissioners, and cordially commended them to
the respectful and favorable regards of all the friends of this Society.
These Commissioners visited many of the Northern States, and
most of the principal cities, exchanged thoughts with many of their
colored brethren, conferred with them in their religious associations,
addressed them and their congregations, and both publicly and in
private, exhibited to them Liberia as opening to men of color advantages 
and prospects to be sought in vain in any other country. We are

<pb xml:id="p35" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.003"/>

well assured that these labors were not without good effect; and
the volumes mostly relating to Africa, published by Messrs. Crummell 
and Blyden while in this country, embody facts and arguments 
of great value, and will live as pious and eloquent memorials
of their concern for their Republic and their race.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<pb xml:id="p36" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.004"/>

<p>Liberia College</p>

<p>"Our last report," says the Secretary, "announced that the legal
difficulties which had for several years impeded the completion of
the college buildings had been removed, and the work on them
resumed. We are now happy to announce that the buildings
are completed and ready for use.</p>

<p>"The plans and specifications for the buildings were drawn by
L. Briggs, Jr., Esq., architect of Boston, under the direction of the
trustees, in consultation with President Roberts, with a careful
regard to economy, in view of the uses of the building, the nature
of the climate, and the probable necessity of future enlargement.
The main building is seventy feet long by forty-five feet wide, and
three stories in height, on a foundation of Liberia granite, and surrounded 
by a verandah, eight feet wide, on an iron frame, the
posts of which are inserted into blocks of granite. It contains
apartments for two members of the faculty and their families, who
will reside in the building and have the immediate oversight of the
students; a dining-room sufficient for these families and the students; 
a room for the library and philosophical apparatus; a hall
to be used for a chapel, lecture-room, or any other purpose for
which all the students need to be convened; rooms for recitation
and for study in classes; dormitories for students, and the necessary 
offices, store-rooms, and other accommodations. The kitchen
is a detached building, in easy communication with the dining-room. 
The eleven dormitories furnish all desirable accommodation 
for twenty-two members of the regular college classes,
which is as great a number as can be expected for some years.&#8212;
They may, without discomfort, receive twice that number; and
when it becomes necessary, more dormitories may be added with
little expense.</p>

<p>"The Legislature of the Republic has done liberally. It has
granted the site of twenty acres, on which the college stands, and
where it must remain till removed by the concurring votes of its
Trustees and the Legislature. It has granted, as an endowment,
one thousand acres of land in each of the four counties, to be
selected by the trustees. It has appropriated six hundred dollars,
to enable to professors to visit foreign institutions. It has given
the college a carefully revised charter, the result of the best
thinking in Liberia, aided by able counsel in the United States,
and satisfactory to both Boards of Trustees who are concerned in
its management. And it appears ready to grant any other favors
in its power which the best interests of the college may be found
to require.</p>

<p>"This delay has not been wholly useless. It has secured the
settlement, in the minds of Liberians generally, before opening

<pb xml:id="p37" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.005"/>

the college, of questions which otherwise would almost certainly
have come up, and might have made trouble, at some future time. 
It has also enabled the Trustees of Donations, to whom the appointment 
for the present belongs, to find a Faculty in Liberia,
and thus to avoid the most formidable obstacle to the successful
establishment of the College, viz: the difficulty of finding suitable men 
elsewhere; including them to accept the appointment;
securing their sage acclimation; and above all, making them
acceptable after their arrival.</p>

<p>"The college had already an able president, the Hon. J.J.
Roberts, under whose superintendence the buildings were erected.
The following appointments were made August 9, 1861, viz:</p>

<p>"Hon. J.J. Roberts, Professor of Jurisprudence and International Law.</p>

<p>"Rev. Alexander Crummell, Professor of Intellectual and Moral
Philosophy, and of the English Language and Literature.</p>

<p>"Rev. Edward W. Blyden, Professor of the Greek and Latin
Languages and Literature.</p>

<p>"Till other arrangements are made, Prof. Crummell is to give
instructions in Logic and Rhetoric, and in History; Prof. Blyden
in the Hebrew and French Languages; and the two, conjointly,
in Mathematics and Natural Philosophy.</p>

<p>"Professor Crummell, being necessarily detained for a time in
the United States, engaged in procuring books for the library.
He is understood to have procured about four thousand volumes,
many of them very valuable and difficult to be obtained. A list
of these, with the donors, will probably appear, from the proper
source, in due time; but it seems a duty now to mention the gift
of about six hundred volumes by the corporation of Harvard
College, through J. L. Sibley, Esq., librarian.</p>

<p>"A part of these books have been sent out, and have arrived.
With them have been sent about seven hundred specimens for the
cabinet of mineralogy, gathered from most parts of the world
between the Mississippi and the Ganges, and wanting only two
or three specimens, which are already promised, for a complete
elementary cabinet. A small but well-selected box of specimens
in conchology accompanied them.</p>

<p>"For the inauguration of the college,. January 23, 1862, was
selected, as a time near the close of the session of the Legislature
when the attendance of the proper persons would be most convenient. 
On that day a procession was formed in front of the
house of President Roberts, and marched, led by a band of music,
to the college buildings. The exercises were sacred music,
reading the scriptures, prayer, music by the band, addresses by
Chief Justice Drayton, President Roberts, and Professor Blyden,
appropriate resolutions moved by Hon. D. B. Warner, and
adopted by the Trustees, and a closing Doxology. The Legislature 
ordered the addresses to be printed at the public expense.</p>

<p>"The way seemed now fully prepared for the formation of
college classes and regular recitations; but the appointment of

<pb xml:id="p38" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.006"/>

two professors as commissioners from the Republic to the colored
people of the United States, compelled its postponement for a few
months.</p>

<p>"The endowment of this college, and its support till endowed,
will demand the earnest consideration of the friends of Christian
civilization in Africa. The funds remaining in the hands of the
Trustees of Donations, after erecting the college buildings, are
well invested, yielding a satisfactory income. But their income
is altogether inadequate to the support of the college, and no good
financier would willingly encroach upon or disturb the principal.
The New York Colonization Society has assumed the payment
of Professor Blyden's salary, from the income of its Fulton fund,
and will support several beneficiaries from its Bloomfield fund.</p>

<p>"If more than a very few scholars are to be educated in this
college for many years to come, it is plain that some of them
must receive pecuniary aid, as few Liberians are able to spare the
services of their sons, and support them in college, without aid.
The best form of rendering such aid is doubtless by establishing
scholarships yielding a certain sum annually, to be used in
assisting students who show that they deserve it. The annual
amount should be from half to the whole of a student's necessary
expenses.</p>

<p>"The New York Colonization Society, in its late annual report,
says: 'Perhaps in no more certain way can perennial blessings
be assured to the race in Africa than by the adequate endowment
of professorships and scholarships in this college.' "Twenty
scholarships, founded this year, would do much to insure permanence 
and freedom to the future population of Liberia; while
their prosperity would attract thousands of our aspiring colored
population to become participators by emigrating thither."</p>

<p>And that Society, at its annual meeting:</p>

<p>"Resolved, That to aid a thorough education among the people of Liberia
endowments of scholarships in the Liberia College are urgently needed, and
this Society will thankfully receive, and faithfully apply, gifts intrusted to it
for that object."</p>

<p>The Executive Committee, at the suggestion of Professor Blyden,
presented to the college of Liberia an entire well bound set of the
Annual Reports of the Society, with the African Repository, making
in all more than fifty volumes. They were sent out in the Mary
Caroline Stevens.</p>

<p>Independence of Liberia Acknowledged.</p>

<p>To Liberia and her friends the most cheering event of the year
is the establishment of diplomatic intercourse between our Government 

<pb xml:id="p39" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.007"/>

and that Republic. "A bill authorizing the President of the 
United States to appoint diplomatic representatives to the Republic
of Hayti and Liberia respectively passed the United States Senate
by a vote of 32 ayes and 7 nays, and subsequently the House of
Representatives by that of 86 ayes and 37 nays, and was approved
by the President." While it has been truly said "that the Government 
of the United States has never regarded Liberia otherwise
than as an independent State," and while by the new Constitution
and declaration, issued by Liberia, (in 1847), setting forth her true
character as an independent State, she stood prepared to negotiate
treaties with foreign nations, yet this recent act of our Government
announces our views of her importance, and places her on commercial 
equality with the most favored nations.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<pb xml:id="p50" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.008"/>

<p>The African Question.</p>

<p>It is to this country what the Roman question is to Europe, only
more important, more imminent. The problem presented to the
founders of your Society a half century ago, before railroads, before 
telegraphs, before ocean steamers, remains still the problem of
to-day. Notwithstanding the demonstration of Euclid, some mathematicians 
still announce the discovery of a rule for squaring the
circle. So, now, notwithstanding the demonstrations of the Almighty,
inventive politicians announce extraordinary solutions of this problem. 
One says bind the African on this continent in indissoluble
bonds. Give him no means; if possible, extinguish the desire for
development and progress in the scale of civilization; teach him
no letters; give him no books; rivet him like Prometheus to the
eternal rock of servitude; deny him all legal rights of marriage
and of parentage; deprive him of free will; subject him to the will
of another. Direct what faculties he has to physical production, for
the benefit of another. Let his merit or his extraordinary diligence
go to the emolument of the master, but in no case to the elevation
of the slave. Contempt for the color, without respect for the
quality, is the maxim. Build the foundation of society from this
quarry; but whatever the grain of any slab, however fine the polish
it might take, whatever the demands of the edifice, let none of this 
marble rose in the superstructure. Let the African in America be
either a perpetual slave, or an outcast, an outlaw.</p>

<p>This, in the plain language of results, is the solution presented
by one very large class of people, extending more or less over all 
parts of the United States at this moment.</p>

<p>Elsewhere we hear another solution. Its current runs thus:
The African is here without his fault. Give back to him, here, at
once, the physical freedom, at least, to which he would have
been entitled on his original continent. Give him a status in the
courts which shall recognize the humanity of his race, rather than
its vendibility. Guarantee to him that primary element of civilization, 
the family relation with all its rights. Give him the alphabet
and all its combinations to which his capacity shall be found equal.
Give him wages adequate to his labor. Impose no other restraints

<pb xml:id="p51" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.009"/>

upon him than are imposed on other laborers. Then let him stay
forever, as a race, upon the same soil, and in the same climate
with the Caucasian, and develop as he may in the progress of
events. These views are also entertained by very large numbers
of people, and usually prevail most where this questionable race
prevails the least. Those who entertain them are mainly guided
by the light of Christian sentiment, and by the political principles
established at our independence, but they do not solve the question. 
They only shift the difficulty. They reach the question of
the African slave, but not the question of the African, which is by
far the most difficult.</p>

<p>The former solution, which is directly antagonistic to this, also
ends the question of the slave; but stops at that of the African. I
only follow the path of the great men whose names grace the
records of your society, when I declare the first solution untenable,
unsound in principle and policy; and that both solutions involve
serious injury, if not ruin, to our national interests. Ideas constitute 
the true life of moral and political organizations. They are
to these what the blood is to the human system, what the will is to
our other faculties; they are the motors, more or less comprehended,
of all the vast machinery which creates history. The most powerful 
thing in the universe is an idea. The wind, the earthquake,
the storm, the lightning may inflict their local devastation; but
man will retrieve it. An idea possessing the mind of man or a
nation may elevate, degrade, or destroy man himself, or an entire
nation. It nobly moves martyrs to the stake, patriots to the scaffold, 
whole armies to the blazing muzzles of deadly artillery. It
may also move religion to inflict the cruelties of torture, the criminal
to the dungeon, and a nation to infidelity, the guillotine, and
civil war. How fatal, then, is such a conflict! How much to be
avoided, if possible. A nation may fight for a boundary, or a fact;
nay acquire it, relinquish it, adjust it, and the contest is ended.
But let the contest be for conflicting ideas&#8212;there may be truces,
cartels of suspension, hospital neutralities, and humane courtesies;
but the contest is never ended save by the suppression of one idea
under the acknowledged dominion of the other. History is full of
illustrations of this truth; but our own country, perhaps, furnishes
the most complete example of the moral necessity of harmony in
its controlling ideas.</p>

<p>Thus, one idea which animated our fathers on this continent, and
which permeated the Declaration of Independence, was personal
freedom as the natural, rightful status of all men. The gate of
progress must stand open to every branch of the human race. All 
obstructions to the universality of this idea were to be removed at
some time more or less quickly; but were to disappear in the future.
Bondage was inherently wrong, but might be endured for a while,
so the conflict should end by its gradual disappearance. The papers
of Washington, Jefferson, Madison, Lafayette, verify this statement;
and, indeed, it is admitted within the last two years by the leading

<pb xml:id="p52" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.010"/>

advocates of the theory which I am examining. While the universality 
of the right of personal freedom, the transiency of personal
bondage, continue to be animating ideas in the administration of
our institutions, the wheels of the Republic moved as harmoniously
as the doors of Heaven&#8212;</p>

<p>"On golden hinges turning."</p>

<p>But in proportion as antagonistic and despotic ideas grew in magnitude, 
organizing the perpetuity of personal bondage, with the right
to dispose of an entire race at public vendue, a necessary conflict
arose. Both ideas could not expand in the same jurisdiction. They
asserted a conflicting dominion. Our present generation of public
men has been education under the influences of this conflict. They
are not, properly speaking, ruled by leading men, nor by a party,
but by ideas. No Christian doubts that the one of these ideas
which God supports will prevail, be it sooner or later, Most disastrously 
for the country, the contest has at this moment ceased to
be visibly influenced by the prayers of the good, the plans of the
wise, and the arguments of the logician. In a similar contest of
ideas became a contest of arms, in England. John Milton, said: "I
care not what error is let into the field, so truth be left free to combat 
it." Far happier for us had this maxim controlled our great debate,
and prevented the gathering of the first stack of muskets.</p>

<p>The census furnishes some interesting facts which indicate the
gradual retogression of the old ideas. In the first decennial period
from 1790 to 1800, the increase per cent of free blacks was 82.
The decade from 1820 to 1830, shows 36 per cent. That from
1850 to 1860, gives only 10 per cent, showing a decreasing range of
variation of 72 per cent. In the same time, the per centage increase
of slaves, including the decade ending in 1810, when the increase 
was stimulated by the last year of a tolerated slave trade, varied upon
a decreasing range of only 10 per cent. Manumission diminished
as our fathers departed from their labors.</p>

<p>The records of your own Society, sir, confirm my representations
of the early ideas and policy, and show that itself was established
under the influence of the humane and progressive doctrines of our
fathers. Judge Washington, your first President, in his first annual 
address, speaks of your purpose as "that enlarged and beneficent
plan, which associates the political emancipation and future comfort
of an unfortunate class of men with the civilization of happiness of 
an afflicted, oppressed and degraded quarter of our globe." * *</p>
 
<p>* * * "Should it lead, as we may fairly hope it will, to the
slow but gradual abolition of slavery, it will wipe from our political 
institutions the only blow which stains them."</p>

<p>Just before the same anniversary, General Harper wrote you
from Baltimore in aid of your plan, and said: "It tends, and may
powerfully tend, to rid us, gradually and entirely, in the United
States, of slaves and slavery: a great moral and political evil, of increasing 

<pb xml:id="p53" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.011"/>

virulence and extent, from which much mischief is now
felt, and very great calamity in future is justly apprehended." * *</p>

<p>In the same letter he says further:</p>

<p>* * "The alarming danger of cherishing in our bosom a distinct
nation, which can never become incorporated with us, while it
rapidly increases in numbers, and improves in intelligence; learning
from us the arts of peace and war, the secret of its own strength,
and the talent of combining and directing its force&#8212;a nation which
must ever be hostile to us, from feeling and interest, because it can
never incorporate with us, nor participate in the advantages we enjoy; 
the danger of such a nation in our bosom need not be pointed
out to any reflecting mind. It speaks not only to our understandings,
but to our very senses; and, however it may be derided by some, or
overlooked by others, who have not the ability or the time, or do not
give themselves the trouble to reflect on and estimate properly the
the force and extent of those great moral and physical causes which
prepare gradually, and at length bring forth the most terrible convulsions 
in civil society, it will not be viewed without deep and
awful apprehension by any who shall bring sound minds and some
share of political knowledge and sagacity to the serious consideration
of the subject. Such persons will give their most serious attention
to any proposition which has for its object the eradication of this
terrible mischief lurking in our vitals."</p>

<p>While General Harper so powerfully portrayed this cause of alarm,
he failed to forsee the danger then springing from another cause,
which this unhappy epoch so effectually illustrates. He forgot the
ethnological characteristic of the Caucasian himself, that he will
fight for a grand idea of humanity, or of God, even when he finds no
personal interest involved. He will fight to preserve, as well as to
establish, certain traditional ideas of social or political organization.
He will do this before the duller African mind has comprehended
the same idea, although aided by his greatest personal interest.
Had he been gifted with prophetic vision, he would have seen new
ideas then organizing the perpetual bondage of a foreign race in our
midst; organizing resistance to the spirit of our political institutions,
and to the spirit of our fathers breathing through them; marshalling
to their aid the powers of the press, the party, of prejudice and self-interest; 
and restricting the freedom of the press, the voice, and the
vote on this subject. On the other side, he would have seen the
original ideas of the ultimate universality of freedom organizing the
battle for their own perpetuation more slowly, but equally surely;
gathering to their aid, also, press, party, pulpit, and all other auxiliaries,
whether of generosity or of interest. His country's heaven
would have appeared dark with these gathering hosts, flashing
mutual threatenings athwart the blue union which still embraced
them both; until at last the lurid thunderbolt should burst upon the
earth, the vision dissolving in the terrors of reality.</p>

<p>Although the grounds of alarm suggested by Jefferson, by Harper,
and by many others, did then, and do still beyond doubt exist, yet

<pb xml:id="p54" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.012"/>

the greater cause of alarm has been found in the influence of this
population upon the political and social temper of the white race.
So long as liberty and despotism are hostile elements in the world,
and man's aspirations go forth to the one or the other, so long will
this black ingredient in our national cup stir up adversities among
our people, upon varying grounds of principle, or morality, of religion,
of policy, or of humanity. Free thought must itself be fettered, and
some of the grandest ideas and aspirations which it ever pleased
the Almighty to plant in the breast of man, must become extinct,
before the American people will rest content without progress in one
direction or the other. With the fundamental relations of our political
institutions to this question, what I have shown them to have been,
what your own records prove them to be; with a revolutionary antagonism 
of ideas operating logically, to reverse them, during thirty
years; next a popular decree in 1860 for the perpetuity of the ideas
of '76 and '89, followed by resistance to this determination by arms;
in this sentence is the whole significance of the present crisis, so far
as the two races are concerned. It is a war involving the perpetuation 
of the ideas of '76 and '89, against the ideas of '32 and '54.
The calamity anticipated by the wisest and best of our patriot sires
has fallen upon the country though in a different form from that predicted. 
The dominant race which once introduced this element of
discord into the country almost exclusively suffers from the contest;
while the subject race, by a species of Divine Justice, instead of
finding its bondage made perpetual, avails itself of the general disorder 
of its own relations to escape from its bondage. Such appears
to me to be the condensed philosophy of the past, in the midst of
which, your Society has stood&#8212;</p>

<p>&#8212;"Like Atlas firm,<lb/>
Though storms and tempests beat upon his brow,<lb/>
And oceans break their billows at his feet."</p>

<p>As the result of this disorder, precipitated by the interest which
professed above all other fears to dread such disorder, many thousands 
of freedmen are thrown upon the country, and in no contingency 
can be reclaimed to servitude. Many of these freedmen will 
become acquainted with the use of arms, and with military evolutions;
many of them will constitute military organizations for exceptional
service.</p>

<p>Now, sir, when this war is ended, and however ended, what a
magnificent preparation is made for the separate progress of this
race and for the progress of colonization! Whether slavery remains
to perpetuate the struggle against the imperishable ideas of the
founders of our nationality, or itself presently or prospectively
perishes, restoring harmony to all our institutions, in either event
a new vigor and a new support should be given to the operations of
colonization.</p>

<p>Take, if you please, the hypothesis that personal servitude continues. 

<pb xml:id="p55" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.013"/>

Here are thousands of Africans, freedmen, who to remain
free must extricate themselves form the scenes, the climate, the ties
to which they have been accustomed, and must labor among
strangers, deprived of the society of their own race in many cases,
and of the means of gratifying the social instinct so strong with that
people. While enjoying his natural rights, he will not be admitted
to, nor fitted for, the regulated civil rights which would imply the
equality of the races. What road to the pursuit of happiness is
open to him as a freedman, other than migration to a colony where
his own race legitimately opens to him all the privileges of social
and political equality? There he may use all the agricultural
and mechanical arts he has acquired in America, and make them
the instruments of personal independence, civil elevation, and
wealth.</p>

<p>Then take your military organizations of that race; no use for them
remains after the special emergency has passed, which called them
into existence. They will not be retained in a reduced military
establishment, not disposed to return to the dull routine of labor,
forced among strangers, and possessed of the advanced ideas which
would be inculcated by their military training; what shall they do
but emigrate to a congenial climate, where they may the more effectually 
for their new training, serve to extend civilization by increasing
both the civil and military power of the colony. They should be
the explorers of the interior of that great continent to which your
eyes have been so long directed. Livingstone's explorations have
not only disclosed the existence in that interior of animal wealth,
but also of mineral wealth, and of high and healthy plains and valleys.
These military colonists, accustomed to discipline and hardy exercises, 
and capable of fighting their way, if necessary, should in the
course of a few years crown and surpass the labors of Park and
Maxwell, and Livingstone, and of others who have painfully sought
the course of the Niger, and the sources of the Nile. That almost
fabulous mineral wealth exists in the interior of Africa, no geographer
can doubt. The domestic African lacks the intelligence to discover
or develop it. The Caucasian lacks the physical characteristics to
endure the climate. What remains but a loud call to the more intelligent 
African race in America, which has produced an astronomer
like Banneker, a philanthropic voyager like Captain Paul Cuffee, to
assume the discovery, and if necessary, the conquest of Ethiopia
and its geological treasures, hidden for ages. The earth there awaits
the arrival of this more intelligent part of the race to return to us
an exuberance of such staples as coffee, cotton, and other tropical
products which insure wealth to intelligent labor. Sir, there are
two thoughts we must banish from our minds, that Ethiopia is
the blank represented on the maps of our boyhood; and that the
Almighty intended to exclude forever the African race from all
participation in the progress of the human race in knowledge and
enterprise.</p>

<pb xml:id="p56" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.014"/>

<p>If, on the other hand, this personal servitude is ended by the war,
the foregoing views receive additional force.</p>

<p>I am not reckoned with those who think the African here is
useless unless a slave. It is true that America does not belong
to him, but to the Caucasian; Africa is his heritage; America is
ours.</p>

<p>But his sudden removal would not only be impractical, but inexpedient. 
Let him go gradually, and the white race gradually
occupies the lands vacated. He is not welcome as a freedman to the
colder Stats. He will not go there when he can remain, as a freedman, 
in the warmer States, and among his own people.</p>

<p>This reduces the question to his condition in the States where he
has been a slave. In cases where his treatment has been controlled
by the law of kindness, which I believe will embrace the majority of
cases, the change would hardly be sensible. The master calls his
servants and says to them, "you are freemen; you are entitled to 
wages for so much labor as you do for me; I can't sell you now if I
wish to, nor can anybody buy you; but I can turn you off my plantation 
if you do not work well, and behave well. If you stay with
me, you must do both; I will feed you and your families, and clothe
you, and give you what more you may earn. When you show me
what you will do, I can tell you what I will pay you beside. If you
don't earn your living, because you won't work, I will drive you off."</p>

<p>Who has lived in the midst of this race and does not know that
no other law or regulation would be needed by the great majority of
the race, when governed by one who understood their character.</p>

<p>But while this would serve the purpose with the greater number,
there would inevitably be some whose vicious and wasteful qualities
would subject them to banishment.</p>

<p>Leaving without a character, they would be rejected when applying 
for employment elsewhere. Others would be arrested, as whites
are, for infractions of the penal law. The objections to voluntary
and compulsory emancipation have always been that freedmen would
become vicious, and would corrupt the slaves. It may at first appear
paradoxical, but it is true nevertheless, that this apprehension was
more justifiable when freedmen were the exceptions than it would be
when all are freedmen. In the former case, he was regarded with
suspicion by the master, and perhaps with envy by the slave. He
had a status between the two, and admitted to an equality with
neither. When all are free the master fears nothing but positive
vices. He fears no loss of property. The late slave and the former
freedman are then equal, and subject to the same laws and rules of
humanity.</p>

<p>Still there would be a necessity to provide for the only two evils
which the white race, living in the midst of freedmen, would fear&#8212;vagrancy
and crime. All other ills would be corrected by the common 
law of kindness extended by the superior to the inferior, by the
laws of society and of self-interest. In other respects, the hypothetical 
change of institutions would be effected with hardly a ripple

<pb xml:id="p57" n="teaa.en.periodical.0053.015"/>

upon the surface of daily duties on the plantation of an upright
master. * * * * * * </p>

<p>I propose the subject for the consideration of a Society which
has always been characterized by a regard for the best interest of
both races; and upon which it is possible new duties may be imposed 
by the extraordinary events now transpiring, and by the
prospective legislation of the several States, or of the United States,
opening the way. If they make special provision for the unproductive 
and vicious portions of the race, the country would wait
more patiently for such enlargement of the means of colonization
as shall induce an emigration equal to the annual increase of that
race within the United States. This rate of increase may be estimated 
for the future at about two per cent., or about 80,000 per
annum. During the last census decade the ordinary commercial
facilities afforded means for introducing, on the average, about
270,000 immigrants into the United States annually. With the
removal of the increase, therefore, which is practicable, time would
terminate the domestic contact of the races in the United States.</p>

<p>In any event, your Liberian colony will continue the honorable
and progressive home of the voluntary emigrant. I would not propose 
to change its character a hair's breadth. It is a splendid memorial 
to the memory of Finley and Mercer, of Washington and
Harper, of Caldwell and Clay, and of the early patriots and philanthropists 
of this country. With its many thousands of civilized
Africans, its fifty churches, its college and schools, its organized
and independent Government, let it kindle new beacon lights of
Christianity and education along the headlands of the Atlantic
coast, and upon the hill tops of the interior, until Ethiopia receives 
the baptism, and rises from her knees regenerated and dis-enthralled.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

