<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0900">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward, December 26, 1862</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0900</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Abraham Hanson to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 2</biblScope>
<date when="1862-12-26">December 26, 1862</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Haiti</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Stockton Creek</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hanson, Abraham</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1862-12-26"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-02-27"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-05" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll2-0066.jpg"/>

<p>No. 4.</p>

<p>U.S. Commercial Agency,<lb/>
Monrovia, Decr 26, 1862.</p>

<p>To the Honorable Wm. H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State, U.S. of A.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I would respectfully beg leave to
call the attention of the Department of State a few
matters of personal interest, connected with this Commercial
Agency. I have delayed until now, under an
impression that the Act of June 5th., 1862, "to authorize
the President to appoint Diplomatic Representatives to
the Republics of Hayti and Liberia, respectively", would
render a change in our representation here, more than
probable.</p>

<note place="right">Inadequacy of Salary</note>

<p>I suggest for the consideration of the Department,
that the present Salary of this Commercial
Agency is inadequate for the officer's support.</p>

<note place="right">Privilege of engaging in trade not available</note>

<p>The privilege of engaging in trade has hither
to been surrounded by so many embarrassing restrictions,
as to rending it of no practical value to a person

<pb n="Roll2-0067.jpg"/>

confined exclusively to one place. Moreover, I am
now deterred from engaging in business from a deep
conviction that it would seriously interfere with the
efficient discharge of my legitimate duties, &amp; from
an apprehension that this Commercial Agency
will, ere long, be placed in that Schedule which prohibits the incumbent from trading.</p>

<note place="left">Unavoidable expenses and the claims of Hospitality &amp; Reciprocal intercourse</note>

<p>Under these circumstances the expenses will
far exceed the income. I have a family,
and, besides this, the claims of hospitality from
citizens of the United States, and of reciprocal
intercourse with the Officers of the Liberian Government, (exercised even with an
economy so rigid, that it is but little above seeming
parsimony) are such, as have already
convinced me that I shall not be able to meet
the obligations long, from present resources.</p>

<note place="left">The only established Representative of our Governt to this Republic and hence the calls numerous</note>

<p>I beg leave to refer to the fact that as I am
the only established representative of our Government
here, (and indeed the only foreigner from
any government) and as this is the Capital
of this Republic, the draft upon my resources
is much more heavy, and frequent, than it
would be under another state of things, which

<pb n="Roll2-0068.jpg"/>

may be readily conceived.</p>

<note place="right">Intercourse with this government &amp; people subservient to our commerce and beneficial to persons of African descent now in the United States</note>

<p>Confiding in the judgment &amp; justice 
by which the Department is governed, I am 
endeavoring to surround myself with those influences
and facilities which will be conducive to the 
successful prosecution of my labors. I am fully convinced
that, by constant vigilance, discretion, to
prompt, energetic action, our intimate intercourse,
with the government and people of Liberia, may
be rendered eminently subservient to the interests
of our general commerce; and of high practical value
in the emergencies which have arisen, and
which are likely yet to arise, in connection with
persons of African descent, now in the United
States.</p>

<note place="right">Favorable indications of constitutional adaptation to this climate <unclear>ie</unclear> physically</note>

<p>Permit me to say that the indications,
thus far, in reference to my constitutional adaptation 
to this climate, are all favorable. My health is excellent. 
While every white person who came with,
or after me, has had dangerous sickness of the
"African fever", and one amiable and intelligent
German gentleman has died, I am permitted
to record, gratefully, that I have no symptoms of
any disease whatever, though I do not omit

<pb n="Roll2-0069.jpg"/>

or evade, any necessary exercise or labor, and
have been exposed by night, as well as by day,
to those elements which usually engender fever.</p>

<note place="left">Acquaintance with officers, people, and country</note>

<p>It has been my privilege already to form
an extensive acquaintance with the officers of this Republic,
with the Senators and Representatives, (now in
session) and with the citizens generally. On my
journey hither I called at several settlements along
the coast, and have, subsequently, been eighteen
(18) miles up the Stockton and St. Paul's
rivers, and the result of my observations is, a
deep conviction that Liberia has, in the productions
of her soil, (independent of her
mineral treasures) an inexhaustible source of
wealth.</p>

<note place="left">Suggests that one person, with proper functions, can manage, for some time, all our business here–and could then have compensation on a scale of reasonable indemnity</note>

<p>I approach with delicacy, the following
suggestion, viz: That one intelligent &amp; industrious
person, invested with the necessary functions, can,
for some time yet, represent our government at
this court, promote, and protect our commercial 
interests, and perform all the labor at the Consulate:
and thus he might be placed upon
a scale of compensation which would, in
some measure, indemnify him for risk &amp;

<pb n="Roll2-0070.jpg"/>

expenses.</p>

<note place="right">Many weighty arguments omitted, and the question submitted.</note>

<p>I would not be becoming in me
to urge this matter upon your attention in
terms more explicit than the foregoing.
I am aware that you will at once discover
my principle design, and, without
exhausting the arguments that bear forcibly
upon the subject, I submit it cheerfully,
and very respectfully, to your consideration.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, with the
highest considerations of respect &amp; esteem,</p>

<p>Your Obedient Servant,<lb/>
Abraham Hanson,<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent.</p>

<pb n="Roll2-0071.jpg"/>

<note>Monrovia, Liberia<lb/>
December 26th A.D. 1862</note>

<note>Abraham Hanson<lb/>
Com Agent</note>

<note>No. 4</note>

<note>Not any enclosures.</note>

<note>Received</note>

<note>Salary inadequate. Privilege
of trading not safely available
virtually requesting additional
duties and compensation.</note>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>