<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0583">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton, June 28, 1892</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0583</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date from="1892-06-28">June 28, 1892</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Kalamba, Mukonga</term>
<term>King Mushidi of Katanga</term>
<term>Le Marinal</term>
<term>Sharpe</term>
<term>Stairs</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Ambriz (Angola)</term>
<term>Ambuela (Angola)</term><!-- not sure if Angola -->
<term>Angola</term>
<term>Bihé (Angola)</term>
<term>Cassoalala (Angola)</term>
<term>Cazengo (Angola)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Dondo (Angola)</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Gangda (Angola)</term><!-- not sure if Angola -->
<term>Kasanji (Congo)</term>
<term>Kasai River</term>
<term>Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>Lucala River</term>
<term>Lulua River</term>
<term>Mossamedes (Angola)</term>
<term>Oporto (Portugal)</term>
<term>St. Thomas and Prince</term>
<term>Transvaal</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>France</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Bashilange</term>
<term>Boer</term>
<term>Makioko</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68793274">Chatelain, Héli, 1859-1908</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent at Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1892-06-28"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70343272">Wharton, William Fisher, 1847-1919</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2020-01-30" who="kln">Reviewed transcription and encoded</change>
<change when="2019" who="caa">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.001"/>

<note>No. 27</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, Africa, June 28, 1892</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Miscellaneous News</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>Evasion of the Oporto Rebels; the leading men,
from Mossamedes, Loanda, and Principe. Pardon of the
common soldiers.</p>

<p>Public opinion and feeling in Angola has quieted
down into discouragement, politically as well as
commercially.</p>

<p>Principal features of the new tariff, which was intended 
to favor national industries but is really threatening
the prosperous commerce of Angola with reason.</p>

<p>A new trek of Boers into Southern Angola may be
the starting point of a new African Republic.</p>

<p>King Mushidi of Garenganze is shot by one of Capt
<unclear>Stairs'</unclear> officers, and anarchy in parts of the Kongo State.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.002"/>

<note>No. 27</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Loanda, Africa, June 28, 1892.</p>

<p>Honorable Wm. F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Since my despatch No. 20, dated February
13, 1892, no material changes have taken place
in the political and commercial situation of this 
Province. Still some events may be of interest
to the Department.</p>

<p>Evasion of the Oports Rebels: Most of the
common soldiers who took part in the Oporto Rebellion
of January 31, 1891, and who had been exiled to
this Province and that of S. Thomé have been 
pardoned in the early part of this year and have
returned to Portugal. Of the chiefs of the rebellion
only one is still here, and for the simple reason
that he has no desire at all to leave Loanda.
All the other leaders of the Rebellion have contrived
to escape to France. One embarked at Mossamedes
on a sailing vessel bound for Gaboon and reached 
his destination without difficulty. The Director of

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.003"/>

the Custom-House at Mossamedes was censured and
the "Official Bulletin" for conniving with the evasion,
but was not otherwise punished. Two other leading
rebels were at Loanda, put in boxes and embarked on French
steamer bound for the North. At Ambriz, however,
sea-sickness caused by the usual heavy rollers of
that coast compelled one of the secret passengers
to open the wicket of his box, and led to the discovery,
of the two fugitives. The captain of the steamer had 
them bound with chains and delivered them to the
Portuguese authorities of Ambriz. Here they were accompanied
to the fort by a detachment of soldiers and by a chasing
crowd who hailed in them the martyrs of the Republic.
After a few days of banqueting with their Republican
friends of Ambriz and receiving 300 dollars subscribed
in a few hours by all the leading traders, the rebels 
again escaped on a sailing-vessel bound for 
Gaboon, when they met their comrade from Mossamedes
and whence all embarked for France. After 
leading men of Ambriz were arrested and brought
to Loanda in a man of war; but as the whole population
of Ambriz had openly taken part in the envasion,
and the population of Loanda too was favoring
it, the men were again sent home unmolested.</p>

<p>A fourth leader of the Rebellion escaped in the same

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.004"/>

manner - with the secret assistance of Republican Government 
officials from Principe (Prince's Island) and the accomplices were not more seriously
prosecuted.</p>

<p>Public feeling. The public opinion of Angola which for
a time leaned strongly towards separation from the metropolis,
ceased agitating this question, when the Dias Ferreira ministry
took the helm of government, because many hoped it would
by a coup d'etat establish the Republic. Then the tariff
question called public attention to another side, and now 
the presiding feeling is one of discouragement. "Everything
is lost; Portugal is dead" is now a frequent expression.</p>

<p>Commercial situation and the new tariff. The main provisions
of the new tariff are: (1) Most duties are charged according to the
weight of the merchandise (2) Portuguese goods are free or
well-nigh so (3) All foreign imports pay much higher duties,
(4) The duty in foreign alcohol is prohibition, (5) The Governor
has no longer the power to exempt any goods from paying
duties, (6) The Kongo District, which enjoyed free-trade
is now, by an agreement between Portugal and the Kongo
State, subjected to a tariff more moderate than that
of the Kongo State. This new tariff does not interfere
much with American imports: machines continue to be free;
kerosene and flour are necessities and Portugal can not
compete in them, and timber pays little more than previously
as to the general effect of the new tariff, everybody is now
agreed that it was a mistake, that its only result will
be a rise in the prices of all necessities and hence
of labor, and the final desertion of these markets by

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.005"/>

the native trade of this far interior (rubber-trade)
which will prefer the Kongo-route. Of all events,
Angola which had enjoyed unusual prosperity during
the terrible crisis of Portugal is beginning to lose confidence 
since the new tariff has come; credit is being
withheld and the air is full of fears for the future</p>

<p>Railroad extension. On the 17th of May the fifth section of the Loanda
railroad was opened to the public. The daily up and 
down trains run now over 220 kilometres. The territories,
Cassoalala, is on the Lucalla river, near Dondo. The
coffee district of Cazengo, which is the main object of
the railroad, is not yet reached, but every new section
of 20 kilometres will already help the planters to bring
their coffee to the terminus of river navigation. The <unclear extent="one word"/>
rates are still too high to compete with the river boats
or to induce the native trader of the interior to make use 
of the railroad. Most of the Angolan natives, too, prefer to walk
over the track rather than pay the fare. The railroad
as far as opened, is still far from paying; but the Government 
guarantees the interest on all the capital actually
spent by the company on the road. This is the reason
why the company does not care to increase either the
passengers or the freight traffic; which could easily be 
done by a general reduction. Poorly built and managed
as this railroad is, it is a decided blessing to the country
and is sure to pay a good dividend when the coffee
region is fully tapped, that is in three to six years

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.006"/>

The new trek of Boers. When, last year, the Boers of
Humpeta, in the district of Mossamedes, helped the
Portuguese government to subdue Bihe, they were so
pleased with that cool and salubrious high plateau
that they wrote to the Transvaal inviting their countrymen,
to come and join them. Now this new trek of Boers, estimated 
at about 200 <sic>waggons</sic> is daily expected in the south.
The Portuguese government has sent there the officer who
knows best how to deal with the Boers, having married
one of their daughters, and the people and government
hope he will be able to settle the new corners without
conflict. Hitherto the colony of Boers has been a State
within the State, jealously maintaining their own religion,
customs, administration, language and race. They elect their
own commandants, carefully and intermarriage with the Portuguese, 
and only go to war for the Portuguese government
when the latter agrees to pay them what they ask. Nor,
have they ever paid taxes. If, on the arrival of the new
trek, the Boers should decide to found a new Republic,
there is no military power in Angola that could prevent it;
and if the Portuguese government should try to subject the
Boers to the common administration, there is no doubt but
that it would hasten the formation of a Boer State.</p>

<p>It does not take a prophet to foresee the loss to Portugal
of the highlands of Bihe, Gangda and Ambuela, and
the formation in the near future of a State which European
statesmen never dreamt of, when they partitioned Africa.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0583.007"/>

<p>King Mushidi of Katanga shot. According to a letter
from Captain Stairs to a missionary in Bihe, King 
Mushidi of Katanga (Garenganze) was shot by an
officer of Stairs, as he was ordering his soldiers to
<del>make</del> fire on the approaching column of Stairs' expedition
I already informed the Department of how Mushidi <unclear>has</unclear>
coolly rejected the British Protectorate offered him by Mr.
Sharpe of the South Africa Company. It appears he was
going to do the same with the expedition of the Kongo
State; but the latter felt strong enough to fight, and
so made short work with the King's resistance. <unclear>Previous</unclear>
to Stairs' expedition, the King had kindly "received the
Kongo-State expedition under Lieut. Le Marinal, whom
I had the pleasure of meeting here in Loanda on his
way to Europe. Though Le Marinal, missionaries on 
the spot, and nation just come from there, I learn that
the country between Kasangi (Cassange) and <unclear extent="one word"/>
at the confluence of the Lulua and Kassai, is in a state of anarchy.
The Kongo State has destroyed the town of their <unclear extent="one word"/>
<unclear extent="one word"/>. Mukonga Kalamba, King of the Bashilange
and the Makioko slave-raiders are carrying as 
many human herds as they can manage, to be sold
as slaves to the middle men who bring the survivors
to the coast, where they are "redeemed" as contract
laborers.</p>

<p>Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>