<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0079">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Southern Workman, "Hampton in Africa" (1897)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0079</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Hampton in Africa</title>
<title level="j">Southern Workman</title>
<date when="1897-06">June 1897</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Clement, Claudius A.</term>
<term>Cleveland</term>
<term>Schofield, William</term>
<term>White, Ackrell</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/247013963">Wilberforce, Daniel F. (Daniel Flickinger), 1857?-1927</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Mount (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Sherbro Island (Sierra Leone)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-18" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">Hampton in Africa.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>News from Hamptonians in Africa is always welcome and we print almost in full, a communication from Claudius Clement of the Class of '84, who has been at work as a missionary on the West Coast of Africa now for twelve years. Clement was himself a pupil of Ackrell White, Hampton's first African missionary, and was brought to this country from Sierra

<pb n="p2"/>

Leone and placed at Hampton by his teacher. Mr. Clement's reference to another of our Hampton boys. Rev. Wm. Schofield, is pleasant to us who remember our wheelwright-blacksmith-preacher, who went out from Hampton after completing his course in the Pastor's Class and who has been working with head, heart and hand ever since in Liberia.</p>

<p>Danville Station,<lb/>
Imperreh Mission,<lb/>
Sherbro, W. C. Africa, Oct. 3, 1896.</p>

<p>Dear Miss Cleveland,&#8212;</p>

<p>Your very kind letter of the 30th June was received with thanks and joy.</p>

<p>In reply I am sorry to have been so remiss in writing, which is due to nothing else but pressure of work in one way and another that kept putting off the idea till the moment I wrote you last.</p>

<p>I left the Shaingay Mission over five years ago during which time I have been teaching at York, a successful school on the whole, 120 pupils. My reason for leaving them for this place is the fact of Dr. Hickinger, a returned American missionary, having come here this January to arrange with the Rev. Mr. Wilberforce of Imperreh to extend the missionary line, and they both had to come for me at York where I was teaching stating that it was but right for us (wife and myself) to join this mission of American United Brethren in Christ and hence our being here.</p>

<p>For the present the school is not so large, having 38 pupils whom we mean to teach how to use their hearts, heads and hands wisely to the glory of our Lord. For such purpose we want means, especially suitable tools etc., for teaching the boys trades.</p>

<p>I am a great way from Cape Mount and as much as we have been informed, Liberia is making progress through her missionaries, among whom we can happily name Rev. Wm. Schofield. It is no easy task to labor for the Lord and our country. Many sometime, are the inconveniences, but when one sees the inconveniences, shame and ridicule that met our Saviour, personal troubles used to give way and the troubles become inspirations to work heart and all for the master.</p>

<p>I shall be happy to receive the certificate of membership to the League.</p>

<p>With hopes you are very well and many thanks for papers and best regards from us.</p>

<p>I am yours truly,<lb/>
Claudius A. Clement.</p>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
