<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0286">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. M. Preston to William H. Seward, August 12, 1865</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0286</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. M. Preston to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gaboon, 1856-1888 T-466</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-466, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1865-08-12">August 12, 1865</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Lopez (Gaboon)</term>
<term>Fernan Vaz River</term>
<term>Fernando Po (Spanish Guinea)</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>St. Thomas and Prince</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Preston, J. M.</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Gaboon</placeName>
<date when="1865-08-12"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02-24" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170615_111937"/>

<note>No 1.</note>

<p>Comcl Agency of U.S.A.<lb/>
at Gaboon Augt 12th 1865.</p>

<p>To the Hon. Wm H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>There is, and 
long has been, an active trade in Slaves, amounting 
to several hundreds a year. (I can not give 
exact figures) Carried on between Princes and 
St. Thomé, (Portuguese islands 150 miles west 
of Gaboon) and Gaboon &amp; Coast South.
Last year I coasted as far as 2°40' South. On
the way I saw a schooner of about 100 tons 
burden, which had been boarded by the agent 
of an English factory the day before, and found 
to be "full of slaves" I also saw a boat, capable 
of carrying 30 or 40 persons, but darkness
prevented our distinguishing what it contained.
On a previous voyage our vessel saw 
three such slave-boats. We have children 
in our school taken from such boats, and 
given to our Mission to be free and educated.
At Cape Lopez I learned there were 
two slave factories (one of which I saw) whence

<pb n="20170615_111946"/>

Slaves were carried to the islands in boats 
and larger Canoes.</p>

<p>During the present voyage I heard 
of a slave factory in Fernan Vas river, of 
another large one at Cape Lopez, &amp; I saw 
at the latter place a schooner at anchor 
in the <unclear extent="one word"/>.</p>

<p>I had with me a son of the late King 
of Cape Lopez, who was very communicative 
on the subject of the slave trade. He knew 
all about the movements of the schooner which 
I saw at anchor. He said she seldom carried
slaves; is engaged in taking cargoes of Fariña 
&amp;c.; it has a bundle of certificates of good 
characters received from Eng. Cruisers; is owned at 
Princes; is recognized at Gaboon as a lawful trade &amp;c.</p>

<p>This is no doubt the same schooner I saw 
last year a little further south.</p>

<p>A few months ago a Portuguese schooner from St.
Paul de Loanda, bound for Princes or St. Thomé put 
into Gaboon leaking very badly. It had a great 
many blacks aboard, servants to the officers &amp; crew of
the schooner, for whom regular passports had been 
made out at St. P. de L. I learned that each 
citizen may taken 10 such servants. according 

<pb n="20170615_111951"/>

to Portuguese law.</p>

<p>The question arises, What becomes of all 
these slaves?  Whence the Cash and Merchandise 
that pay for them? Agriculture on these islands
is at a very low ebb. Only small quantities of Coffee
&amp; Cacao are raised for exportation and nothing
else. No kind of manufactures is carried on.
Whence then the demand for so many slaves?
Are they reshipped to another market? This would 
seem probable. An American supercargo, an 
acquaintance of mine, was told, when there a few
years ago that they could furnish him with 200
slaves in ten days time. The schooner in which 
I coasted south last year, was at the islands a short 
time before, when the Capt. saw there a brig, with hatches
down and no appearance of trade day after day.
When her Capt. was questioned about his trade his 
answers were very evasive. At the same time the 
Portuguese schooner above mentioned "was absent 
at Cape Lopez, for a cargo of Pea-nuts"
Our captain had no doubt the brig was there 
for a cargo of Slaves. I have heard of there 
being no slaves on the island to gather the little
Coffee that grows there, but heard nothing 
of any epidemic that swept them off.</p>

<pb n="20170615_112003"/>

<p>The trade is contrary to the laws of Portugal, and
I have heard of persons imprisoned at these stands for
engaging in it, or was it that they had not paid the
governor a bonus on the importation?</p>

<p>The French claim Cape Lopez as well as Gaboon,
yet slave trading is carried on at both places almost 
continually. There is now a trader in Gaboon, but 
probably not known to the Authorities. Occasionally the 
Authorities here make some effort to stop it, and I 
have, once, in the last 5 years, taken a canoe and slaves.
They freed the slaves &amp; released the traders.</p>

<p>Such is about the sum of the information 
I have. I have communicated it, unofficially of course,
to the British Consul of Fernando Po.</p>

<p>I am sir your obedient servant<lb/> 
J. M. Preston</p>

<ab>Enclosure.<lb/>
Comcl Agency at Gaboon.<lb/>
With despatch No 4.</ab>

<ab>Slave trade between Princes &amp; St. Thomé and Gaboon and region south</ab>

<ab>No 1<lb/>
Augt 12th 1865.</ab>

<pb n="20170615_111932"/>

<ab>U.S. Comcl Agency<lb/>
Gaboon Augt 12th 1865.<lb/>
J. M. Preston<lb/>
No 4.</ab>

<ab>One Enclosure.<lb/>
Received</ab>

<ab>Documents recd at Comcl Agency.<lb/>
Absence reported &amp; defended
Objects &amp; duration of Absence.</ab>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
