<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0089">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Missionary Review of the World, "Sierra Leone vs. Liberia" (1882)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0089</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Sierra Leone vs. Liberia</title>
<title level="j">The Missionary Review of the World</title>
<date when="1882-07">July 1882</date>
<biblScope unit="page">315-316</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Sharp</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Mount (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Methodist Episcopal</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-22" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p315"/>

<p>Sierra Leone vs. Liberia.&#8212;The political status between these African neighbors is far from pleasant. Miss Sharp, one of the most intrepid workers of the M. E. Missionary Society, writes (March 22) to the <hi rend="italics">Missionary Editor</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">Northern</hi>:</p>

<p>"Monday of this week a steam yacht came in, followed by the <hi rend="italics">Algerine</hi> 'Man o' war.' The yacht bore the governor of Sierra Leone, who makes a demand for an indemnity of $90,000 for the burning, a few years ago, of two small factories (i. e. country stores) on the disputed territory. It, or they, were burned during the native war at or above Cape Mount. (Cape Mount is 40 miles north of Monrovia.) The Liberia government refuses to pay. It would be utterly impossible. They also refuse to surrender the territory. The governor of Sierra Leone says it is not left with him to arbitrate, nor has he any discretionary powers; that, if payment is refused, he is authorized to collect it. I suppose that means to bombard Monrovia. Once before they gave them so many hours to pay a claim under threat of bombardment. The claim was paid; but the Liberians are poorer now. Besides, they strained every nerve to pay the Germans $5,000 lately. I'll put up the American flag on the old seminary! The United States <hi rend="italics">Essex</hi> has been looked for several days, but not heard from yet. Not daylight, but the steamer is in."</p>

<pb n="p316"/>

<p>The editor adds:</p>

<p>"We do wish the robust, manly Christian sentiment of Great Britain could be brought to bear on this "squeezing" of Liberia. Our own impression is that in this case she is being greatly wronged, and we ask the Christian people of England to look into it."</p>

<p>And has our own U. S. Government no duty to perform in case of unjust demands and inflictions on Liberia?</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
