<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0566">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton, October 19, 1891</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0566</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date from="1891-10-19">October 19, 1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/255734976">Amaral, Francisco Ferreira do, 1844-1923</term>
<term>Bannister, Edward</term>
<term>Baracho, Dantes</term>
<term>Chagas, João</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/315533938 ">Downing, Henry Francis, 1846-1928</term>
<term>Verge, Louis Astyanax de Rathier du</term>
<term>Jackson, Joseph E.</term>
<term>Judson, Julius Leroy</term>
<term>Newton, Robert Scott</term>
<term>Silva, Augustus Archer</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Ambriz (Angola)</term>
<term>Angola</term>
<term>Banana (Congo)</term>
<term>Bihé (Angola)</term>
<term>Cabinda (Angola)</term>
<term>Caconda (Angola)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Dondo (Angola)</term>
<term>Kasanji (Congo)</term>
<term>Kingdom of Lunda</term>
<term>Kunene River</term>
<term>Mossamedes (Angola)</term>
<term>Oporto (Portugal)</term>
<term>Pengo Andongo (Angola)</term>
<term>Portuguese Guinea</term>
<term>Prince (St. Thomas and Prince)</term>
<term>St. Antonio (Congo)</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>St. Thomas (St. Thomas and Prince)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Brazil</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Netherlands</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Lunda</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68793274">Chatelain, Héli, 1859-1908</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent at Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1891-10-19"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70343272">Wharton, William Fisher, 1847-1919</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2020-01-28" who="kln">Reviewed transcription and encoded</change>
<change when="2019" who="caa">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.001"/>

<note>No. 12</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
at Loanda October 19, 1891</p>

<p>Honorable William F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have to acknowledge the receipt of
your Circular dated July 17, 20, &amp; 27
whose intents were duly noted.</p>

<p>Enclosed I have the honor to transmit 
to the Department:</p>

<p>1) A Report of the present State and
needs of this Consulate</p>

<p>2) A Report on the present political
situation of Portugal and Angola.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

<p>Enclosures:</p>

<p>1) Report on Present State of Consulate at
Loanda</p>

<p>2) Report on Present Political Condition of
Portugal and Angola, with annexed
printed documents</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.002"/>

<p>Report on present State
and Needs of U.S. Consulate at
St. Paul de Loanda</p>

<p>From the Inventory sent last march, The Department, 
could infer, to some extent, what this
Consulate has and what it lacks; but a detailed 
report on the present state and needs
of the Consulate is surely not out of place.</p>

<p>1) The Office</p>

<p>This used to be in Mr. Newton's office, in 
a corner partitioned off by a common wall about
8 feet high, and when I took charge, that corner
had been evacuated in favor of the British
Consul (newly appointed) and the U.S. archives
were piled up in Mr. Newton's business office.</p>

<p>As the Department probably known, Mr.
Newton has retired to Europe and his business
here is in charge of clerk. Mr. Ed Bannister 
is no longer connected with Mr. Newton's
firm. Whether the two consular archives, American
and British, and to be kept in the same room
or partition, I am not sure of, but think they
were.</p>

<p>Until a better place can be found, I
have hired two rooms as the American 
Mission, one for myself, the other for office</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.003"/>

<p>The latter is on the ground-floor, has a door
to the front of the house, and another door opening 
into the schoolroom which is only used on Sundays.
A partition wall reaching to the ceiling, separates
the office from the store-room of the mission.
My bed-room is up-stairs.</p>

<p>2) The furniture</p>

<p>As appears from the Inventory, nothing was 
turned over to me but the <unclear extent="one word"/> remains of
a few chairs, and two ruined book-cases, which
latter Mr. Bannister was not sure belonged to
the Consulate.</p>

<p>I furnished the office with some of my own,
and borrowed chairs, table, and repaired one
small book-case. To these I added a table
and book shelves, which I made myself
from old boxes. The walls I adorned with
African and other maps of my own, so
that the office, tho poorly furnished,
looks pretty decent and comfortable.
Considering, however, the rapidly growing 
importance of this port and the 
nation represented at this Consulate, its 
office should, in justice, be properly furnished. 
Furniture is very dear at Loanda;
so I propose to the Department to either
appropriate a sufficient seem to buy said

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.004"/>

furniture here (counting the cost here to be
at least 100% more than it would be in the 
States) or to send a full supply of office 
furniture from the States.</p>

<p>If this Consulate be henceforth part in 
charge of decent men, and detailed inventories 
required of them, the Department may
be sure that the furniture will be properly
cared for.</p>

<p>3) Office paraphernalia</p>
 
<p>Of these nothing was turned over except what
is mentioned in the Inventory (Two stamps,
a few waifers, sheets of paper and envelopes).
The stamp mentioned as "hand stamp" bears
the inscription "Commercial Agency" and is
therefore no longer correct, nor is it in good condition. 
Letter-files needed.</p>

<p>Just now I have received from the Department 
a supply of forms and stationary, but 
no ink nor string. These I shall have to buy
The press, mentioned in former inventories,
has not been transferred and may have
disappeared in Judson's time. One ought
to be sent by first opportunity. As there is 
no bookbinder in this place, it would seem
advisable for the Department to send some
material wherewith the officer might find

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.005"/>

himself what things require binding (and there
are some). Packing-paper, too, which, here, is
rather high, should be not but not with myself lot.</p>

<p>4) The Archives</p>

<p>a) Forms. Of these, more than
half were obsolete, but no mixed up, that 
it took me several days' hard work to
sort the antiquated from the good and
to sort and arrange the latter.</p>

<p>The result in that the Forms lacking, even 
after arrival of those sent with stationary to
me, are Nos:</p> 

<table>
<row>
<cell>1 to 12 incl.</cell>
<cell>88 &amp; 89</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>15</cell>
<cell>93 <del>&amp; 94</del></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>19</cell>
<cell>97-99 incl.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>26-32 incl.</cell>
<cell>104</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>34 &amp; 35 " </cell>
<cell>106-11</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>40-67 " </cell>
<cell>114 &amp; 115</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>69-78 " </cell>
<cell>125</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>80 &amp; 81</cell>
<cell>131-137</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>143 &amp; 144</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>146-152 incl.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>155-158 " </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>160-166 " </cell>
</row>
</table>

<p>Any of these that are deemed by the Department 
to be of sufficient importance shall be
sent, in moderate numbers, by first opportunity.</p>


<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.006"/>

<p>b) Books. The list of those extant is found 
in the Inventory.</p>

<p>The set of books pertaining to the S. Thomé
Consulate is all blank. It might serve for 
a Consular Agency in that island when one
be established. That one will have to be established 
there is sure as soon as direct communication 
between W. Africa and the States 
be a fact. S. Thomé &amp; Principe are <unclear extent="one word"/>
for the production for coffee, cocoa and fine timber.
They also offer a good market for higher clan
goods, such as are produced by America.
An American firm beginning modestly, would 
do a good business</p>

<p>Of the Loanda Consulate book.</p>

<p>The Register of Landing Certificates is blank</p>

<p>The Marine Extended Protests has but one page filled 
by Judson</p>

<p>The Invoice Book has only two entries (1879 &amp; 1883)</p>

<p>The Seamen's Registrar was only used from (1881-1883)</p>

<p>The Passports used only since 1889</p>

<p>The Ship's Daily Journal has record from 1881-1891</p>

<p>The Marine Note of Protect has one entry by du Verge
&amp; one by Bannister</p>

<p>The American Seamen <unclear>Relieved</unclear> has entries from 1881-1884
&amp; one in 1889</p>

<p>The Treasury Fee Book regularly kept, by Newton's
firm, from 1881-1891</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.007"/>

<p>The Record-Book was used by Downing to copy some
extravagant letters to high personages, and since, by
Newton's clerks and Bannister to copy letters and
documents aside from Dispatches to Departments
There is nothing in it previous to Downing &amp; 1888.</p>

<p>The Letters Sent has a few entries in 1883, a few
in 1888 and regular ones since 1889</p>

<p>The Letters Received contains entries since end
of 1888</p>

<p>The Two old Despatch Books mentioned in Inventory
contain one; Archer Silva's &amp; Newton's despatches
between Oct. 1864 and March 1878, Jackson's 
from <unclear>later</unclear> date to April 1878, the Newton's
to March 1879.</p>

<p>The other: Newton's despatches from April
1879 to Dec. 1879 and after a gap 
of 3 years, those from June 1883 to
June 1885</p>

<p>In a third, unbound, volume are despatches
and letters from Sept. 1885 to Oct. 1887
The Despatch-Book proper contains despatches
and official letters from Jan. 1880 to June 1882 
(Newton) and from then to Jan. 1884 (Du
Verge). After gap, Downing's letters &amp;
copies of documents from Nov. 1887 to
March 1888. After another gap, Newton's
Inventory of things taken over by him

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.008"/>

on Judson's death, and subsequent dispatches
and letters from <unclear>Nov.</unclear> 1888 to Bannister's correspondence
the whole of this and beginning of mine.</p>

<p>Record-Books Lacking:</p>

<p>A Letter Book, into which to copy official letters
apart from Despatches to U.S. Departments.</p>

<p>A Miscellaneous Record-book, though the
old one, mixed as its contents are, might
continue to be used for its proper purpose.</p>

<p>A Record of Commercial Returns</p>

<p>A Quarterly Account-Current Book</p>

<p>An Index-Book.</p>

<p>As may be inferred from the above, the
two latter Records were never kept, which 
made it next to impossible to find anything
dating book to a predecessor.</p>

<p>The Inventory tells what printed
books there are, and in what condition. from
it can be inferred what books may be
lacking</p>

<p>The Consular Reports were never taken
care of; so the collection is most important</p>

<p>c) Correspondence</p>

<p>This I found in utmost confusion except
the latest, sent to Bannister since he had 
sole charge.</p>

<p>It took me a long time to sort what

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.009"/>

there is, and now all the letters are chronologically 
arranged in different packages, awaiting
binding.</p>

<p>The division is:</p>

<p>Package (1) Instruction from State Dept.
(incomplete but beginning with a few
addressed to Archer Silva)</p>

<p>(2) Circular from State Dept.
(same remarks)</p>

<p>(3) Letters from Treasury Dept.</p>

<p>(4) Official letters from other 
Consulates</p>

<p>(5) Official letters from Portuguese
authorities (such as on left)</p>

<p>(6) Letters and documents concerning
crews and ships</p>

<p>(7) Letters and documents concerning 
missions</p>

<p>(8) Judson's private letters &amp;
accounts (a most disreputable
bundle).</p>

<p>Excepting Newton's and Du Verge's, though
both incomplete, scarcely any correspondence
has escaped.</p>

<p>It is high time to bind what is left.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.010"/>

<p>5) Flagstaff and flags.</p>

<p>As stated in last mail, Newton's clerk
said they were not sure whether the flagstaff
belonged to Consulate or not. I showed
them since the letter of the Department
authorizing Mr. Newton to spend $25.-
on purchases and erection of one and they
said that did not prove that Mr. Newton
actually got the money, and that I should
get Mr. Bannister (now disconnected from
Newton, Carnegie's) to declare whether the
money was received or not. I have not
yet been able to find Mr. Bannister 
since that time, and so the matter is
standing, until I see Mr. Bannister,
when, no doubt, the matter will be satisfactorily 
decided.</p>

<p>Still, for either the removal and erection
of the old, or the purchase of a new staff, I beg
the Department to allow me to spend,
in first case not more than five dollars,
and in the latter case the maximum of
twenty five dollars.</p>

<p><del>Hitherto</del> Meanwhile, I have, on convenient occasions
hoisted the flag on the flagstaff of the 
Mission House where the Consular office is
temporarily located</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.011"/>

<p>As to the flags, the boat-flag, though some
what moth-eaten will yet do for the rare occasions
of this port; but the large flag, already
torn at the corners, needs being superseded
as fast as another box comes from the Department. 
It would be wise to send with 
the flag some tones of naphthalene to ward off
insects.</p>

<p>6) Consular Officers</p>

<p>The arranging of the consular correspondence 
and its <unclear extent="one word"/> have given me, together 
with what I gathered here from conversations, 
a very fair idea of the history and 
work of each successive consular officer.</p>

<p>The impression, that history leaves, is most painful 
for an America. Excepting Archer Silva,
who was the most popular and generous
trader Loanda had in this century, all the
Americans who have held this post were fit
for the penitentiary and the gallows rather
than for the office of representatives of the
United States. Of Jackson I know nothing
as he was here but as a passenger.</p>

<p>That the only one to maintain the dignity
of the office in all that line, should have
been an Englishman, Mr Newton, is rather
humiliating; and not less humiliating

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.012"/>

is the fact that he used to give the American
Consulate openly or <unclear extent="one word"/> as part-salary to
one of his clerks.</p>

<p>Now, as Angola is being more and more 
occupied by American Missions, as its commercial importance 
is fast growing, and as there is no
doubt that are long it will form a powerful 
independent state with strong sympathies 
for the United States, it is of the 
highest importance, that, should I be replaced
from decision any other cause, the standard
of this Consulate, which I shall have raised
out of the mud, be never again lowered
by sending here men who are a disgrace
to their country and to mankind, even in darkest
Africa.</p>

<p>But this improvement in the personel
of the Consulate depends chiefly on the
Salary. While I, who have got a reputation 
as a philanthropic Diogenes, can
manage to live and do some good with my
salary, there is no doubt but that an
ordinary man, frequenting the society of the
other consuls and Consular agents can impossibly
get along with the salary of the post.
The price for a poorly furnished room
and board (two meals a day) at any one
of the two or three better hotels of the place is

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.013"/>

2.75 per day, if taken by the week or month,
and the extras entailed by living in such a hotel
make the expense of an additional 50¢ to one dollar
per day necessary.</p>

<p>The only way for a Consul to keep out of debt
would be to accept a situation as clerk or to 
go into business with some capital. Thus the
Department in confronted with this dilemma; 
either have a trading Consul who will take care
not to have American competition in the Province
&amp; thus hinder rather than advance the commercial
interests he is supposed to promote, or have
a consul, who will give his time and talents
to the consular business, and pay him enough
to enable him to do so. Angola, with its 600,000
square miles of the best land in the world, and Loanda, 
whose custom house cleared last year, in
spite of all struggling 550,000$00, deserve something 
better than a last-class Consulate.</p>

<p>In a city like Loanda a salary of two 
thousand dollars should be the minimum for
a Consul for Schedule B.</p>

<p>Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Cml Agent</p>

<p>P.S. I would also beg the Department to allow
me 5 milreis (=5$40) for subscription to the "Futuro d'Angola"
and the same for the "Mercantil" another leading papers of Loanda.</p>

<p>Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>
 
<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.014"/>

<p>Report
on Present Political Situation
of Portugal &amp; Angola.</p>

<p>As promised in my first despatch
from Angola, I now lay before the Department a
detailed account of political movements within
my Consular District. And first of all, allow
me to state what I noticed on the way from
Lisbon to Loanda.</p>

<p>1) Voyage on S.S. Ambaca</p>

<p>We had on board over 300 Portuguese emigrants,
sent in Government expense to Portuguese West-Africa,
but chiefly to Angola. This was only the first batch 
of the crowd to follow on the by-weekly steamers
of the "Empreza Nacional". The lot of the "Ambaca"
hailed from OPorto and consisted of hungry workingmen 
all revolutionary Republicans, of whom the 
Portuguese Government was more or less afraid. As soon
as they were on board these men showed what could
be expected of them. The municipality of OPorto had 
promised all the residents of OPorto a present of
5 milreis = $5.40, but when the agent began to
distribute the money, on board the "Ambaca" and
returned to give that amount to those who were not
on his list of OPorto men, the whole crowd resolved
&amp; declared, they would not sail unless all got

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.015"/>

the same amount. The minister of Marine ordered
to delay the departures of the ship, as company of <del>4</del>
Marines was sent on board and the steamer was
surrounded by tugs and launchers from the Marine
Arsenal. On the seventh however, the Government decided 
to give all men equally the 5 milreis and
the "Ambaca" was allowed to sail, after a new
company of marines had been put on board with
a lot of ammunition.</p>

<p>On the way out, however, it soon became evident
that the missions were worse than the emigrants
and during the whole voyage the steerage passengers
practically ruled the ship. Every time launches went
ashore with cargo those emigrants would simply 
find the ship's officers aside and jump into the
boats and have a jolly time ashore. If no <unclear extent="one word"/>
happened, it is due to the Captain and first class
passengers, who being all Republicans, let the 
poor fellows have their own way.</p>

<p>At Principe (Prince's Isld.), some of the
emigrants walked up to a plantation where one
of the exiled OPorts rebels is working and made 
him an <unclear extent="one word"/>. There, as at other places, when the
boats would bring the passengers back in the coming
a red flag would fly on the first launch &amp; the
crowd would sing the "Portugueza" the new
Portuguese <unclear extent="one Portuguese word"/> which the government

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.016"/>

tried in vain to prohibit in Portugal. Before the ship
sailed from Principe, a big bon-fire was lit on the
hill where the exile's plantation <unclear>lais</unclear>, and the immigrants 
answered with land <unclear>"vivas"</unclear> for the exile,
pistol-shots and the singing of the Portugueza.</p>

<p>S. Thomé</p>

<p>Here the whole white population was highly
indignant against the Portuguese Government, and
had just held an excited meeting to protest
against following manners of the Government</p>

<p>1) The change in the export duties by which it
becomes almost impossible to export coffee and cocoa 
direct to foreign ports, and in the import
duties, which by forcing all foreign goods to pass
through the hands of Lisbon agents creates a
rise in the prices of next to all goods.</p>

<p>2) The premium granted to the Congo State
to contract (i.e to buy) 500 natives of Angola,
at a time when S. Thomé &amp; Principe cannot
get a sufficient number of (slave) laborers for
its coffee plantations.</p>

<p>3) The <unclear>Cession</unclear> (as it is called) of part of the
Lunda empire to the same Congo State.</p>

<p>The population of S. Thomé &amp; Principe whose 
black workers are Angolans and whose white
population is intimately connected with that of
Angola is now one with the latter in the opinion

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.017"/>

that the home government is the worst <unclear extent="one word"/> of the
colonies and that the time is come for the latter
to free themselves from the Lisbon magnates.</p>

<p>Kabinda</p>

<p>Here I saw no sign of political excitement,
but admired the magnificent barracks of the 
battalions statement here and the beautiful palace
of the governor. I talked with some of the soldiers
and found that most of them are from the District 
of Loanda; as for back to the interior as
Kasanji (600 miles), who were pressed into the
service. At Kabinda they take native women,
&amp; so the Kabinda race is being rapidly mixed
with the Angolan. Soon all the Kabinda women 
(who hitherto only <unclear extent="one word"/> Fiote or Kongo) will
know Kimbundu (or Angolan) which most men
already learnt is Loanda or other ports, and vice
versa a great number of Angolans are learning 
Kongo so that when the day of independence
comes, the people of Portuguese Kongo will feel
one with those of Angola, south of them. Unwittingly, 
the Portuguese Government is doing everything
to mould the greatest of modern black nations</p>

<p>Commercially, I noticed that the great Dutch
firm (Nieuwe Afrikaanse Handels vennootschap)
in building three new homes in Kabinda with
a view to transferring here the bulk of their

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.018"/>

Banana business, and thus escape to some extent the
vexation taxation and regulation of the Kongo State</p>

<p>As the Portuguese steamers no longer call at
Banana and the Portuguese port at S. Antonio
has no great importance, I saw little of the state
of affairs on the Congo, and what I heard the
Department may know from its agent out there (?).</p>

<p>Ambiz</p>

<p>This place lives entirely from the coffee which
the<del>y</del> natives bring from the interior, and owes its
importance and prosperity to the fact that its tariff
is very moderate compared to that of Loanda.
I heard that Mr. Newton has obtained a concession
for a company to work again the old and rich
copper-mines of Bemba, back of Ambiz</p>

<p>Loanda.</p>

<p>Here I noticed immediately that a new
life has come into the old city and that it
will soon count among the great harbors of the
world. The change that has taken place in the
18 months of my absence is wonderful. Politically,
the spirit of independence has <unclear extent="one word"/> from the
natives to the whites and the question is solved
in the minds of the leading men. Be it sufficient
to state that the first thing, on meeting me
again, which the two first men of Loanda
(the first lawyer &amp; the director of the Bank) told

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.019"/>

me in a whisper was: Things are in bad shape
in Portugal, are they not? The Republic and
the independence of this are not far. Both these
men have about 20 years residence in Loanda, &amp;
have made up their minds to finish their careers
in these parts. One of them is already limited as
is the future President.</p>

<p>Shortly before my arrival, all the leading traders
of Loanda, at the call of native leader, had held
a great indignation-masking and resolved to protest
against the cession of Loanda and the contracts
allowing the Congo State to buy 500 natives
of Angola. As I already wrote to the Department, 
they also effectually hindered the
purchase of any natives for Kongo State service,
and the agent of the Kongo State, after losing
his reason from the shock &amp; the abuse of morphine, 
had to return to the Kongo without having
obtained anything. It must also be noticed
that the people of Loanda solemnly declared,
and stick to it, that they maintain their rights
to the part of the Lunda country allowed to the
Kongo State, and they intend to enforce it as
soon as they see an opportunity.</p>

<p>Annexed to this are 1) The protest
of the capital (Loanda) against the two
contracts with the Congo State, in which

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.020"/>

protest they declare that for them the Portuguese
parliament does not represent the nation, but is 
only a body of mercenaries, 2) The letter of 
thanks of the same meeting to Ex-Governor
Ferreira do Amaral for his speech against those
contracts with the Kongo-State 3) The protest
of the Commercial Association of Loanda, to which
all the leading firms belong.</p>

<p>These three documents have been largely signed 
by all the whites and natives who are not in the
employ of the government.</p>

<p>I have not the time to translate them; but as
the Department has a translator who knows Portuguese 
I advise that those important documents
the precursors of the declaration of independence
be translated by him and duly noticed</p>

<p>Gringo Andongo</p>

<p>I also enclose a no. of the "Futuro &amp; Angola"
containing an important article "Ao paiz" &amp;
the protest of the municipality of Pengo Andongo,
a large town some 300 miles in the interior. 
It is remarkable that the four of the 
five members of the municipal board are
natives and the fifth, the President, declares that
his wife and children being born Angolans, his
sympathies are with them. The protest of the
municipality though <unclear extent="one word"/> in the most rebellious

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.021"/>

<unclear extent="one or two words"/> was signed by most of the whites of
Pengo Andongo. On sending the protest of the
Loanda papers for publication the president of
the municipality states that of the Governor
dissolve the municipality, all is ready to reelect
it.</p>

<p>Dondo</p>

<p>Not long ago,the exiled journalist João Chagas
(of the Oporto Rebellion) was invited to visit Dondo
(about 6000 population) &amp; get from the Governor
General the permission to go. On his arrival, the 
municipality went in a body to receive him at
the steamer; a grand reception was given him in
the town, Republican speeches were made and 
a street was given the name of João Chagas.
The Governor treatment to dissolve the municipality, 
but on learning that it was sure to be
re-elected, he contended himself with suspending
the government "Chefe" for not suppressing that
manifestation. As to João Chagas he was sent,
for punishment to the delicious climate of Mossamedes 
where he continues his propaganda.</p>

<p>Mossamedes</p>

<p>What happened or was going to happen here
is still somewhat mysterious; but one thing is
known, namely that a <unclear>sergeant</unclear> &amp; some of the
new immigrants had made a plot to seize <unclear>the</unclear>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.022"/>

<unclear extent="one word"/> Governor and make a revolution. One betrayed
his companions and these were shipped to Portuguese
Guinea.</p>

<p>The annual war with the natives in the interior
of Mossamedes, on the Kunene River has, it appears,
<unclear>turned</unclear> out a failure for the Portuguese, this year. After
an initial success in which more than 6000 heads
of cattle were <unclear extent="one word"/> from the natives, the Portuguese 
(black) troops have had to withdraw and
have arrived in Mossamedes in great disorder.
The Governor General has gone there by last steamer,
in order to investigate the two questions.</p>

<p>Sr. Dantes Baracho the delegate of the Portuguese
Government for the delimitation of the Lunda, who
has been here more than two months doing nothing
was also to go with the Governor but at last moment
a telegram came and he returned ashore 
with his baggage.</p>

<p>People here say that if the Delegate of the Congo
State comes, they will not let the two delegates
go to the interior.</p>

<p>The Spanish man of war "Isabel II"</p>

<p>Though less important, the following fact has its
significance. The "Isabel II" has been here for some
time, and for a few days, had the company of
an English flagship and of a German cruiser.
After the departure of the latter, the <unclear extent="one word"/> men

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.023"/>

of Loanda gave a grand reception to the Spanish
officers, and, ironically, also invited the English.
The answer of them was that they had to sail next
morning early, and no they did. As to the Spaniards
and Portuguese, though they said it was no political
manifestation, they could not help letting it out
as the return <unclear extent="one world"/> offered on board by the Spaniards, 
when one of the officers forgot himself &amp;
added to his "vivas" for Portugal &amp; Spain, the contrary 
for England. The "Isabel II" sails to day
for the Cape.</p>

<p>Summing up, I wish to state that in
Portugal the general feeling is, that the independence 
of Angola is a thing to rejoice in
rather than anything else, provided the Portuguese 
element remains permanent, and educated
natives who speak &amp; write Portuguese an not yet
separated from the Portuguese shock, in the Portuguese
mind. So the Portuguese Government has a
twofold object in view, in sending out thousands
of immigrants to Angola: 1) to export the revolutionaries 
of the worst type, and thus to prevent
an immediate popular attack at home, 2)
to introduce so many Portuguese into Angola,
before, by independence, it opens with it doors
to all nations, and thus secure the predominance
of the Portuguese language and tradition as

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.024"/>

in Brazil. As in all other things, honour, the
Portuguese Government goes against its own interests,
for it sends out men, and so few white women,
that these immigrants are going to raise a lot
of mulattoes who are more opposed to Portuguese
rule than the blacks.</p>

<p>A hundred thousand hectacres of the best land
on the high and healthy plateau of Caconda
and Bihe have been granted to a Portuguese
Company who is to establish there a colony
with the hundreds of <unclear>imports</unclear> <unclear extent="one word"/>
by the Government.</p>

<p>As to trade with the United States and
opportunities for American Capitalists to make
grand <unclear extent="one word"/> this is one of the most
promising fields. The people have feel
instinctively that for the building up of
a great nation in this land no nation
can be more helpful to them than our
United States who are the model and
ideal after which they are striving.</p>

<p>Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.025"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.026"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.027"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.028"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.029"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.030"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.031"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.032"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.033"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.034"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.035"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.036"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0566.037"/>
<!-- in Portuguese -->

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>