<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0248">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Memorandum of Liberian Government to U.S. Secretary of State, May 6, 1891</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0248</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Memorandum of Liberian Government to U.S. Secretary of State</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1891-05-06">May 6, 1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12670525">Anderson, Benjamin J.K., 1834-1910</term>
<term>Sun, Momoru</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Cavalla River</term>
<term>Condo Country</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Mannah River</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>San Pedro River</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Barclay, E. A.</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1891-05-06"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/15566890">Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-09-07" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170616_150640"/>

<p>Memorandum of the Liberian Government 
on the Anglo-French Agreement concerning 
the delimitation of their respective boundaries on
the West Coast of Africa and the Soudan.</p>

<p>The Liberian Government having been made 
cognisant of the said agreement, submits the 
following propositions thereon:</p>

<p>Considering that the districts comprising its 
south eastern territory situated between Cape Palmas 
and the San Pedro River were included within 
the limits of the State of Maryland in Liberia 
as far back as the years 1835-50, and that no 
counter claim was set up at that time by any
European State.</p>

<p>Considering also that the State of Maryland 
in Liberia was peacefully incorporated with the 
Republic of Liberia in the year 1857, that said 
incorporation was then and there published to 
the world, and that no protest against it was made
by any European State, that therefore said 
incorporation has had the sanction and acknowledgment 
of the civilized world for nearly half a century,
and that it is only within the last six years that 
<catchwords>any</catchwords>

<pb n="20170616_150646"/>

any claim to said territory have been preferred 
by the Government of France.</p>

<p>Considering also that these territories are 
responsible for a portion of the Foreign debt of the 
Republic.</p>

<p>Considering also that <sic>Americs</sic> Liberian 
missions and schools have in the past and are 
at present established in the said districts 
and up the Cavalla River.</p>

<p>Considering also that the Map of Africa recently
published by the Royal Geographical Society of Belgium
shows the proposed interior boundary of the 
Republic at its greatest width at Roporo, in 
the Condo country, which would only give 
the Republic an interior extent of about 40
miles; and that the whole of the Condo 
Country was formally ceded to the Republic 
by King Momoru Son in the years 1868-69.</p>

<p>Considering also that the countries between 
Monrovia and the interior slope of the Western 
Mandingo plateau were explored by 
Benjamin Anderson at the instance of the 
Liberian Government during the years 1868, 1873
and 1874 and confirmed to the Republic by 
Special Treaties, and are now set down in 
<catchwords>the</catchwords> 

<pb n="20170616_150652"/>

the French map of that region as "unexplored" and 
therefore liable to become a protectorate of France.</p>

<p>Considering also that the present or prospective 
<unclear>delimitation</unclear> according to the Map referred to, 
would cut off or separate from the Republic, populations 
that have been peacefully under its 
sphere of influence for the last 40 years, and 
would also deprive the Republic of all access to 
the River Niger, contrary to the Hinterland doctrine 
now acknowledged in Europe as binding with 
respect to European acquisitions on the African 
Continent.</p>

<p>Considering also, that the Republic of Liberia 
is not a European State, but was an Independent 
African Government in existence long 
before the era of the Berlin Conference, and 
was in possession of said territory at a period 
considerably anterior to the convening of said 
Conference, and was not invited to participate 
in its deliberations, and ought not therefore to 
be bound by the rules thereat prescribed for the 
conduct of European Powers in making fresh 
acquisitions of territory in Africa, and that 
Republic seeks only that territory which 
has, for so long a period been acknowledged to 
<catchwords>rightfully</catchwords>

<pb n="20170616_150659"/>

rightfully belong to her, and the right of 
her Hinterland.</p>

<p>For the above reasons the Republic 
considers that her boundaries ought in 
all right and justice to extend from the 
Mannah River, on the North to the San 
Pedro River on the South, and interior wards,
from the Sea coast to the River Niger in
accordance with the Hinterland law. This 
regulation of her boundaries would be of
very little moment to the European States
who have acquired such extensive Empires 
in Africa, but is of vital importance to 
the Republic of Liberia and would further 
more sufficiently meet her just aspirations.</p>

<p>The Republic therefore protests against 
the conclusion of the said Agreement, so 
far as the deprivation of Liberian territory 
by France is concerned, and solicits 
the good offices of the United States 
Government to avert her impending loss of 
territory on her sea board and inferior.</p>

<p>E. A. Barclay.</p>

<p>Monrovia<lb/>
May 6 1891.</p>

<p>Secretary of State</p>
   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
