<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0285">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. M. Preston to William H. Seward, June 23, 1865</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0285</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. M. Preston to William H. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gaboon, 1856-1888 T-466</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-466, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1865-06-23">June 23, 1865</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>May, Henry</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Bight of Benin</term>
<term>Corisco (Spanish Guinea)</term>
<term>Fernando Po (Spanish Guinea)</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>St. Thomas and Prince</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Preston, J. M.</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Gaboon</placeName>
<date when="1865-06-23"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1865-08-24"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02-24" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170615_111817"/>

<note>Consular Bureau Received Aug 24 1865</note>

<note>No 3</note>

<p>U.S. Comcl Agency<lb/>
Gaboon, June 23d 1865.</p>

<p>Wm H. Seward,<lb/>
Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>The 
vacancy in this Comcl Agency, caused by the 
resignation of H. May Esqr., which I mentioned 
in despatch No. 2, gives me an opportunity,
without infringing the rights of any one, of saying 
a few words on the U.S. commerce with this port, 
and the small need there is for a consular officer.</p>

<p>The trade has been gradually decreasing for 
a number of years. For the last three years, on an 
average three vessels (about 600 tons in all) a year 
have come this way from the Bight of Benin,
to land a few passengers &amp; a little freight, and 
to buy a few thousand billets of Barwood (an 
article, I believe, not dutiable, and of which a few 
cargoes would glut the market) to complete their 
cargoes of Coffee, Camwood, Palm-oil &amp;c. bought 
along the coast from Monrovia to Fernando Po.</p>

<p>There is no prospect of the Trade reviving. 
The Ivory trade is pushed to its utmost extent.
It is in the hands of the English, who can 

<pb n="20170615_111823"/>

produce the Articles bartered for it cheaper, &amp;
more inferior in quality than the Americans can.</p>

<p>The India-rubber id being rapidly exhausted. 
Barwood is still plenty; but the French 
authorities here prevent all vessels from going 
up the river to trade, &amp; thus getting near the 
Barwood, and even small boats must procure 
&amp; pay for permission to ascend the river,
and carry the French flag. This causes delay 
and increases the price.</p>

<p>American vessels of late, for the sake of 
despatch, buy of the English factories here.</p> 

<ab>Thus Trade does not require the presence 
of a Consul here.</ab>

<p>The officer at Gaboon can not know about
cargoes, taken aboard at ports North of 
this, so as to prevent frauds on the revenue.
Besides the greater number of vessels return
to the States from ports North of this, at which 
no consular officers reside; and thus the officer
here has not the opportunity of certifying, 
even to the best of his knowledge, to the 
cargoes shipped.</p> 

<p>The number of American Citizen residents
here has also decreased. Their relations with the 
authorities have been for the last fifteen years 

<pb n="20170615_111828"/>

of the most friendly character, and are likely so 
to remain. On their part there has never been a 
desire for a consular officer at Gaboon.</p>

<p>There are a few Americans at Corisco, but 
they are under Spanish rule. They may be 
interfered with; but they could not be much 
assisted by a consul in a French port, if they 
are.</p>

<p>Should the United State again send a squadron
to the West Coast of Africa to cooperate with 
England in supporting the Slave trade, a consul 
at Gaboon would be of very little use. For several
degrees north &amp; south of this port there is 
no foreign slave trade, except what is carried 
on in small schooners &amp; boats from the Portuguese 
islands of Prince and St. Thomas. The 
squadron could have no business in a French
port, whence the trade is prohibited.</p>

<p>Fernando Po, as being already a depot
for coals, and the Southern terminus of the 
line of Mail Steamer, and also near the 
ports in the Bight of Benin, whence the 
trade is carried on, would become a 
rendezvous for our vessels.</p>

<p>In fine I do not see what American interest
can be advanced by the U.S. Comcl Agency

<pb n="20170615_111835"/>
 
at Gaboon; nor what interest would be in
any way prejudiced by its discontinuance.</p>

<p>I have done only what I consider my duty 
to my Country in communicating the above. 
If, notwithstanding these representations, you wish 
to continue it, I am ready to welcome and 
assist your appointed as far as I can; or 
I should feel myself honored in subserving 
the interests of the United States here, and 
would, if appointed Commercial Agent, discharge 
the duties of the office to the best of 
my ability. I am free to confess that I 
desire the appointment, but I have no 
claims to urge why it should be conferred 
upon me rather than another.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,<lb/>
J. M. Preston.</p>

<ab>U.S. Comcl Agency.<lb/>
Gaboon June 23d 1865.<lb/>
J. M. Preston.<lb/>
No 3.</ab>

<ab>Advising the Agency to be discontinued, with reasons.</ab>

<ab>1st Very little trade</ab>

<ab>2nd Trade can not be increased</ab>

<ab>3d Obstacle to trade.</ab>

<ab>4th Consul  can not know about trade from other ports</ab>

<ab>5th Few residents, they do not desire it.</ab>

<ab>6th Could not assist in suppressing the Slave trade, should U.S. vessel be sent</ab>

<ab>But if continued, present occupant desires to be appointed</ab>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
