<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0021">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>New York Freeman, "England on the Congo River" (April 26, 1884)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0021</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">England on the Congo River.</title>
<title level="j">New York Freeman</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date when="1884-04-26">April 26, 1884</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>    

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22148544">Brazza, Pierre Savorgnan de, 1852-1905</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/49228150">Leo XIII, Pope, 1810-1903</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry Morton, 1841-1904</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Atlantic Ocean</term>
<term>International Congo Society</term>
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>West Africa</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>England</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-27" who="#kln">edited tei header</change>
<change when="2015-06-08" who="#kln">added places</change>
<change when="2014-11-13" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-07-21" who="#kln">encoded transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<div2 type="titles">

<head type="main">England on the Congo River.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>The discovery and explorations of Stanley and De Brazza have interested all nations in the Congo River. This broad, deep, and powerful body of water flows into the Atlantic Ocean on the west coast of Africa about six degrees south of the equator. It is destined to become the gate way to the heart of equatorial Africa. Hence the interest of Europe and the United States.</p>

<p>Portugal claims this great river and the surrounding territory. The Pope gave it to her several centuries ago. Who gave or sold it to his Holiness? Portugal has done nothing for the people or the country. She has no right to be there as owner. She ought not to be permitted to doom millions of people, now on the way to a new civilization, to poverty, ignorance and degradation.</p>

<p>England, in her foreign policy, is a sly, grasping, avaricious bully. Her policy is dictated by her selfish, money-getting merchants ands manufacturers. These have put their covetous eyes on the Congo river and territory. They send there every year out of Liverpool alone goods to the value of five million dollars. It would arouse the other great powers of the world if England were to establish an open protectorate over the Congo. She has with the slyness of a fox entered into a treaty with Portugal, recognizing the claim of this stagnant nation to the ownership of the great West African river. That is simply an outrageous blind, an infamous subterfuge. It simply means that England will play the monkey and Portugal the cat's paw. One will be, to all appearances, the throne, but the other the power behind he throne.</p> 

<p>Deeply interested in the auspicious events daily transpiring in Africa, we protest against this arrangement. we want to see the flag of the International Association planted upon every part of the Congo territory. England must not dominate, France must not control, Portugal must not be sovereign on the Congo river. Let this key and gate-way to equatorial Africa be free and open to all nations alike. Let it be international ground. The country will develop the more rapidly. The people will receive speedier and greater benefits from our civilization and Christianity.</p>

<p>We applaud the action of the United States Senate in recognizing the claims of the International Association and in declining to recognize the treaty concluded between England and Portugal; and we hope that the President will store up all the great powers of the world the resist unitedly this unholy and infamous scheme, and establish over the Congo Valley de jure and de facto international jurisdiction.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
