<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0506">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Julius Leroy Judson to George L. Rives, June 30, 1888</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0506</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Julius Leroy Judson to George L. Rives</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from U.S. Consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, Portuguese Africa, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date from="1888-06-30">June 30, 1888</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/315533938 ">Downing, Henry Francis, 1846-1928</term>
<term>Newton, Robert Scott</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cabinda (Angola)</term>
<term>Madeira</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Judson, Julius Leroy</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul at Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1888-06-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29909070">Rives, George Lockhart, 1849-1917</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-01-13" who="kln">Reviewed transcription and encoded</change>
<change when="2019" who="caa">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0506.001"/>

<p>Consulate of the United States<lb/>
of America at St. Paul de Loanda<lb/>
June 30, 1888</p>

<p>To the Honorable<lb/>
G. L. Rives<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I beg leave to make the following
statement to the department viz
I have been for several weeks very sick
with rheumatic fever, have had the doctor 
nearly every day for the past three weeks.
Most of the returns and Consular Correspondence 
for this quarter I have had to arrange
while in bed suffering most excruciating
pains, and only getting a little help occasionally 
when visited by an English friend
Mr. Downing's disgraceful career here has also
rendered it very hard here for me as I can
find no one here willing to honor a draft
on the U.S. government. I have consequently
exhausted all the means I brought to Loanda and
have drawn on all the ready money I had in
Cabinda to meet the expenses of this quarter, to say 
nothing of my own doctors bill and medicine.
The disorder from which I am suffering is very
prevalent here and seems to beyond the power
of the Portuguese doctors.</p>

<p>I have the honor also to beg the department to
excuse this paper and that upon which most
of my returns are made as it was impossible to
procure other of the proper page. All the Consular
visiting material being still in the hands of Mr.
Downing's creditors. I promise the department
<catchwords>that</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0506.002"/> 

that 
as soon as I am furnished with proper forms and
instructions I will endeavor to render my accounts
as neatly and as accurately as possible.</p>

<p>I note the Governor General a second time concerning 
the Consular effects held by Mr. Downing's
creditors referring him to the treaty between the U.S.
and Portugal, he immediately advised me to <unclear extent="one word"/>
legal proceedings in the local courts for their recovery.
This will of course entail expenses which 
have no authority to make, which expenses may 
amount to several times the value of the 
effects in question, please advise me as to this.</p>

<p>Mr. Downing carried with him
all the forms for making out drafts except two
or three which he had partially spoiled.
Consequently two of mine made out on unofficial
paper as I could do no better notwithstanding
this, I hope you will honor or pay them, if you
dont, and force me to wait until I can get
forms, etc. I will starve here in Loanda.</p>

<p>Mr. Newton the English Vice Consul and former
U.S. Vice Consul returned here a few days since from
Madeira where he has gone for his health and to meet
his wife upon his ascertaining that Mr. Downing had
also defrauded him off a large amount, he told me
that he intended to let the next Consul sent here
starve as they would all have done had he not
cared for them</p>

<p>I write this <del>by</del> in bed on board the Portuguese
mail steamer on route for Cabinda where I will remain
three or four days to see if I shall not get better.
Of course I would not dare forward the department
such a mutilated dispatch under ordinary circumstances
but I have not walked in a month. begging your leniency</p>

<p>I have the honor to be
<catchwords>your</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0506.003"/>

Your humble servant<lb/>
Julius Leroy Judson<lb/>
U.S. Consul</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>