<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0105">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Afro-American, "Commissioners Highly Honored by Liberians" (1909)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0105</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Commissioners Highly Honored by Liberians</title>
<title level="j">Afro-American</title>
<date when="1909-07-31">July 31, 1909</date>
<note>Typographical errors have been corrected by transcriber.</note>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/33280630">Ashburn, P. M. (Percy Moreau), 1872-1940</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9398147">Cloman, Sydney A. (Sydney Amos), 1867-1923</term>
<term>Davis</term>
<term>Doyle</term>
<term>Emerson</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/69293642">Falkner, Roland Post, 1866-1940</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43004374">Finch, George Augustus, 1884-1957</term>
<term>Flower, Frank Abial</term>
<term>Howard, William L.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/56447042">Latrobe, Ferdinand Claiborne, 1833-191</term>
<term>Lyon, Ernest</term>
<term>Sale, George</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27443582">Scott, Emmett J. (Emmett Jay), 1873-1957</term>
<term>Wilson, H. B.</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Cavalla River</term>
<term>Half Cavalla (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Grebo</term>
<term>Negro</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.analysis.0006">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<head type="main">Commissioners Highly Honored by Liberians.</head>

<head type="sub">United States Minister Praised For His Courteous Treatment of the Visitors</head>

<head type="sub">Disfranchisement Amendment Must be Defeated by United Effort On The Part Of the Colored People Assisted By Members Of The Other Race&#8212;Commissioner Scott Highly Praised For The Part He Took In The Proceedings&#8212;Was a Good Appointment.</head>

<p>(Special Correspondence.)</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, June 26</p>

<p>My dear Editor:</p>

<p>I have noted with pleasure the fight you are making against the adoption of Disfranchising amendment to the Constitution and I am satisfied that you, with our good friends Collector Stone and Councilman Cummings, must have the unqualified support of all patriotic and race loving Negroes, not only in the State of Maryland, but thruout the length and breadth of the country.</p>

<p>The measure is undoubtedly directed at the liberty of the colored voter in the State. It has in it the tinge of race prejudice, and for that reason, if for no other, it should be defeated. I believe that there are enough patriotic and fair-minded people in the State, if aroused to the significance and far-reaching effects of the measure, if adopted, who would rise in their might, regardless of race, and defeat it for the honor of the State. We must remember, however, that no political measure of this character which means so much to the opposite party, is defeated on its merits. The history of other measures in other States is proof positive against that belief. The hurtful measure can only be defeated by the united effort of the colored voter himself, who is directly concerned, and patriotic appeals to members of the other race, without whose assistance we can hope to accomplish nothing. This seems to be the work that your journal is doing for Maryland and I bid you and the friends with you, God speed in your patriotic endeavors.</p>

<p>By this time no doubt you have with again the American Commissioners who have returned home from their important mission. Their presence, accompanied by two warships, in Liberian waters was a benediction to all concerned and must in the ultimate exert a good effect upon the international policy of the little Republic.</p>

<p>The people received them well. Enthusiasm ran high, and never in the recollection of the oldest inhabitant, were such scenes witnessed before&#8212;not even during inauguration periods. These manifestations simply emphasized the deep feeling and regard the Liberian Government and people have for the American Government and people, from whose loins they naturally sprang.</p>

<p>The personnel of the Commission Attaches was all that could be expected. "A finer set of men never came to use before," is the universal expression of Liberians. They measured up grandly to our expectation. They were sincere, methodic and sympathetic and yet  firm and honest in their inquiries&#8212;this won for them universal praise.</p>

<p>At Monrovia, the Commission was divided&#8212;Chairman Faulkner, Commissioners Sale and Scott and Secretary Finch were assigned to magnificent headquarters provided for them and Major Ashburn, Captain Cloman and Attache Flower became the guests of the American Legation. Major Ashburn and Captain Cloman occupy first rank in their professions. The former is a medical expert on the tropical diseases and the latter is the Military Attache at our Embassy at London. While there he entertains like a prince and has Royalty for his companions. Mr. Flower is a man of literary experience and wide knowledge of the colored people.</p>

<p>Our association was of mutual benefit. At no time during their stay did they consider it a condensation to be under our roof of did we consider it any special honor to have them. The association was of special pleasure and mutual enjoyment as fellow-officers of the same great Government. As evidence of the fact I here append two communications which were left with me on their departure which will be of interest to my fellow-citizens:</p>

<p>Commission of the United States of America to the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, May 28, 1909</p>

<p>Dear Dr. Lyon:</p>

<p>Before leaving Monrovia, I desire to express to you the gratitude of the Commission for the valuable assistance rendered us by your Legation in the prosecution of our labors in this country. The elaborate memorandum which you had the kindness to present to us, dealing with the questions which are the subject of our inquiries, has been particularly useful, and your courtesy in arranging our trips into the country and providing for our comfort in Monrovia, has greatly facilitated our work and is sincerely appreciated by every one connected with the Commission.</p>

<pb n="p5"/>

<p>With many thanks for your kindness in these matters, I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,<lb/>
Roland P. Faulkner,<lb/>
Chairman.</p>

<p>Dr. Ernest Lyon,<lb/>
Minister Resident of the United States, Monrovia, Liberia.</p>

<p>Commission of the United States of America to the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>Monrovia, Liberia, May 28, 1909</p>

<p>To His Excellency Ernest Lyon,</p>

<p>American Minister Resident and Consul-General, Monrovia.</p>

<p>Sir:&#8212;</p>

<p>The Attaches of the Commission of the United States of America to the Republic of Liberia, take particular pleasure in making an acknowledgement of the kind and courteous treatment they have received under your hospitable roof from you and your pleasant family, in ministering to their personal comfort, and from yourself individually in facilitating the performance of their official duties.</p>

<p>They will never cease to treasure the memory of their stay with you, and sincerely hope that our Nation may long continue to be represented by officials as tactful, patriotic and generous as yourself.</p>
<p>With kindness regards,<lb/>
P. M. Ashburn, Major M. C., U.S.A.<lb/>
S. A. Cloman, Capt. 23d Inf'y Mil. Attache.<lb/>
Frank Abial Flower.</p>

<p>The spectacle presented at Monrovia by this historic mission was a pleasing and inspiring one so far as the race was concerned. I speak now in reference to Mr. Scott, the Negro member of the Commission. The Government is to be congratulated for his appointment and the race must congratulate itself for the honor his appointment brought to it. This is the only case, I think, in modern diplomacy, when a Negro has been appointed by a Government so dominated as the American Government to membership on a Commission, which for far-reaching effects in international politics none can forsee. Mr. Scott was the cynosure of every eye. His presence in a gathering was the signal for applause. His popularity among both white and colored was marked. To say that he bore himself with becoming dignity but faintly expresses his conduct, under circumstances which would have tried the pride of other men differently constituted. As an American, I was proud of Mr. Scott, but became still prouder when he was praised by English and Germans who happened to get in touch with him.</p>

<p>Upon the consummation of their work in Monrovia, the party left on board the two cruisers which were waiting in the harbor. Chairman Falkner, Captain Cloman and Secretary Finch, going to Sierra Leone by the "Chester" to inquire into conditions in the Kanre Lahun district; and Commissioners Sale, Scott, and Attaches Ashburn and Flower, and the American Minister as their guest, left in the "Birmingham" for parts on the Liberian seacoast. Our first stop was at Bassa, the commercial centre of the Republic, and then at Cape Palmas, formerly known as Maryland in Liberia, in the settlement of which the late John Latrobe, the father of our good friend Ferdinand C. Latrobe ex-Mayor of Baltimore, did so much to bring about in the early colonization period. From here we went up the Cavilla River, the southeastern boundary of the Republic, visited Bleiron, the cable station on the French territory opposite to Kablake, the Liberian town at the mouth of the river. Our party returning from our trip up the Cavalla, landed at Dimalu and walked across the country, a distance of three miles, to Half Cavalla, a Grebo town of about 5000 inhabitants. Here we slept for the night and returned next morning to Harper, where he embarked for the homeward trip.</p>

<p>Our party up the Cavalla beside those already mentioned, thru the courtesy of Commander Howard, was enforced by the addition of three Naval Attaches, Chief Engineer Doyle of South Carolina, and Officers Davis and Emerson, three splendid fellows. It fell to my lot to "roost" with them at the house in Half Cavalla, and they all declared that the party was as jolly and happy under the circumstances as could be.</p>

<p>The cruiser stopped at Monrovia to put the Minister off and it fell to the lot of Chief Engineer Doyle to accompany him ashore. The Commander kindly sent us ashore in his own gig, and as it left the side of the ship the customary salute of 13 guns were fired from the ship's battery in honor of the American Representative; thus making 39 guns fired in his honor during the stay of Commissioners.</p>

<p>I cannot end this account which I know will be interesting to you, without testifying to the splendid conduct of both the Commander and his officers all thru their stay in Monrovia, and especially down the coast when I became the guest of the ship. It was indeed a pleasure to be in company with such gentlemen, who without regard to race or color discharged the functions of their office with ease and satisfaction. Both Commanders Wilson of the "Chester" and Howard of the "Birmingham" were present at the functions given at the Legation and by the Secretary of State. This account sounds so entirely different for many of the newspaper accounts which reached us from the United States when the Commissioners were leaving Liberia.</p>

<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
Ernest Lyon.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
