<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0091">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from D. L. Marsins to Hamilton Fish, March 29, 1870</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Sims, Lee-Ann L." xml:id="ls">Lee-Ann L. Sims</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0091</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from D. L. Marsins to Hamilton Fish</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">3</biblScope>
<date when="1870-03-29">March 29, 1870</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Marsins, D. L.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul for St. Thomas</roleName>
<placeName>Saint Thomas and Prince</placeName>
<date when="1870-03-29"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/232585893">Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
<date when="1870-05-31"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-06-25" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and addition encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="ls">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0091.001"/>

<note>Received May 31 1879 Department of State</note>

<p>United States Consulate at S' Thome and Prince's, West Africa<lb/>
St Thome March the 29th 1870</p>

<p>Honoble Sir,</p>

<p>The <sic>continuos</sic> fevers of
the African Coast have not allowed me
so far to send the report of the trade of the
Province, as <sic>reccomended</sic> by the Consular Regulations
I will do so however as soon as I am able, and I
hope that will be sometime next month. I will
also send by the same mail a draft for authorized
expenses, such as relief of destitute seamen,
freight on parcels from Lisbon, <gap extent="one word"/> 
etc, amounting in all to somewhere about 50
Dollars more or less.</p>

<p>I have to <sic>aknowledge</sic> the receipt of Coat of Arms
Commercial Relations, and Diplomatic Correspondence
part 1th and 2d 1868. I must beg to remind the 
Department that as yet I have not received any
book containing the Treaty, between the United States
and Portugal, and that I think it would
be advisable to send it, as well as a letter press
and Books and Blanks, for the use of this Consulate.
There has been a new tariff published

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0091.002"/>

here, but not to go in operation. I believe
untill the first of August next. I have not had
time yet to look it all over, but as far as I have
seen, it is somewhat more moderate than the one
in force now, and has the advantage of putting foreign
vessels, on a par with Portuguese, regarding goods
of foreign growth, or manufacture This ought to encourage
American Vessels to come back to this Province
and trade. The Rotterdam house of Kerdyke and Pinkoff 
have just opened a branch here in St Thomas
and in time opening another in Prince's, with very fine
prospects. I don't see any reason, why enterprising Americans
should not do the same to a good advantage.
Formerly the American trade in these Islands was
of considerable importance, and apparently on the increase.
Our domestic difficulties, and the high import duties 
charged here, have put a stop to a trade that ought
to have been very profitable to all parties. To <sic>wich</sic>
may be added the low price that the St Thomé coffee,
really a very good kind, fetches in the states. The coffee
is bought here now for cash, at about 5 cent p pound
subject to export duties (about 3/4 of a cent a pound both
in Portuguese and Foreign vessels. This is about also
the Price of cocoa, with a lower duty however, a fraction 
less than 1/2 cent a pound. The Port charges are moderate, and

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0091.003"/>

the Custom's House authorities very obliging. The
Prices of both coffee and cocoa are such, that a
good profit could be made, on both articles of produce.
No large trade however could be done, but it
could be reasonably expected, that it would increase
yearly. The Exportation of this Island for the 
year 1860 at this market price amounted in round
numbers to $200,000 and The Importation to about
$170,000. In Prince's Island (within 70 miles distance) Importations
amounted to $40,000, and the Exportation
to about $20,000. This year (1869) will probably be the same.
With the influence of trading vessels, these numbers
would steadily increase. The only chances to
import or export now are through the monthly line
of steamers, whose high rates of freight, added to
the frightfull overcharges of the Portuguese Consignee's
in Lisbon, take about 50/00 from the
Profits that the traders would be making.</p>

<p>Hoping these few remark's on
the trade of this province will be acceptable 
I have the honor to remain with the greatest
consideration</p>

<p>Your Most Rest and Obet Servant<lb/>
D. L. Marsins<lb/>
Consul.</p>

<fw type="address">To the Honble<lb/>
Hamilton Fish<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington
D.C.</fw>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
