<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0031">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The A.M.E. Zion Quarterly Review, Rev. F. M. Jacobs, "The Work of Missions in the A.M.E. Zion Church"</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Reynolds, Peyton" xml:id="pr">Peyton Reynolds</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0031</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Work of Missions in the A.M.E. Zion Church</title>
<author>Jacobs, F. M.</author>
<title level="j">The A.M.E. Zion Quarterly Review</title>
<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">286-294</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>        
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/90631825">Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564</term>
<term>Cartwright, Andrew</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14773105">Jacobs, F. M.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14773105">Luther, Martin, 1483-1546</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/38555521">Varick, James, approximately 1750-1827</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/19686646">Wesley, John, 1703-1791</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71399367">Zwingli, Ulrich, 1484-1531</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Ethiopia</term>
<term>Knoxville (Tennessee)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>African Methodist Episcopal</term>
<term>Episcopal</term>
<term>Pietism</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
<term>Wesleyan</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-10-23" who="#kln">reviewed and edited</change>
<change when="2019-04-04" who="pr">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p286"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<head type="main">The Work of Missions in the A.M.E. Zion
Church.</head>

<head type="sub">By Rev. F. M. Jacobs</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Knoxville, Tenn.</p>

<p>To me has been assigned the subject of Missions in the
church. It, when put in the most pleasing language, still retains
its dryness. But, it shall be my purpose to eliminate that dryness 
by interlocuting such other discussions as will tend to elevate
the subject beyond the monotonous.</p>

<p>That we may the better see the subject before us, let us 
look backward. Man, we are told in the good book of God, is
wonderfully and fearfully constructed. This is true not only of 
the tenement of clay, which we inhabit, but far more illustriously
true of the immortal mind which mainly constitutes our self.
Possessed of powers of cognition, of feeling and action, man is
adapted for the high destiny marked out by the Almighty, for a
sphere little lower than that of angels, encircled with honor and
glory. As he journeys through life, he is surrounded upon all
sides by an intellectual vision, which like the torch of the 
benighted traveller, forms a circle of illumination by which he
can safely direct his steps. His powers of cognition embrace a
knowledge of the present, some certainties commingled with
many probabilities of the future, and copious reminiscences of
the past. The past is our richest and most instructive teacher,
and it was justly said by one of the most brilliant intellects of
heathen antiquity, that to know what happened before we were
born is to remain always a child.</p>

<p>This power of retrospection sheds its influence upon every
department of human life, upon our social, our intellectual, and
our religious interests.</p>

<p>It is in this field of retrospection that the Christian finds
many of his dearest social enjoyments. Fond memory delights 
to dwell upon the pleasing and interesting associations of our

<pb n="p287"/>

early years, especially associations of effort in the cause of the
Redeemer. "And it is here too, that pensive memory retraces
scenes of bliss forever fled, it is here she dwells in former times
and places; it is here she holds communion with the dead." On
this occasion these feelings rise commingled in my breast, as I
see around me some who have shared the toils of early ministerial
life, and where I see others, who 20 or 50 years ago, in times of
slavery and servitude, were co-laborers with and for you, are no
more, but gone to rest.</p>

<p>It is in the wide field of retrospection, that we gather our
richest treasures of wisdom and experience. It is memory that
enables us, to appropriate to ourselves the knowledge and experience
of past ages; to hold communion with apostles and prophets 
and patriarchs, and virtually to extend our life from three-
score to a thousand years. It is in the rich fields of retrospection
too, that the Christian finds two incidents, the principles and
many of the evidences of his holy religion; the glorious displays
of Divine Providence, and the heavenly, the expansive
power of that gospel, which, aided by the Spirit, serves in every
age as the conductor of saving influence from heaven to man.
Not only is it in the Old Testament dispensation, that the hand
of providence and the power of God's word may be recognized,
pulling down earthly kingdoms, persuading paganism that her
creeds and rites are unholy, but they are displayed with increasing
lustre in the development of the New Testament Church
throughout her history. They are seen in the reformation of the
sixteenth century, when after ages of concealment beneath the
dust of ignorance and superstition, the seen of the Word were
brought to light and scattered among the people. They are seen
in the history of Pietism in Germany, the Presbyterian Church,
the Episcopal and other Churches, and we may add, in the
development of the history of our Zion Church from its earliest
mission efforts by Bishop Varrick, the preacher and layman
down to these its proudest days. Here too the precious seed
scattered abroad by a few able and faithful servants of Christ,
was richly watered by the Spirit, and produced abundant fruit to
the praise of his grace and the permanent establishment of the

<pb n="p288"/>

Zion Church. All of these successes, through a century of
prosecution of the cause of the kingdom by these mission
laborers, have not come spontaneously, have not arisen in a day
to luxuriant beauty, were not born in the full bloom of manhood
and organized perfection, but by long toils, desperate privations,
of self-sacrificing and consecrated Christian manhood.</p>

<p>One hundred years have rolled away, have written diversified statements upon the pages of eternal memory, have settled
the destiny of thousands, have seen nations bloom, and nations
decay; have witnessed the elevation of principalities and powers,
have seen them drop like a fiery meteor to ruin, since the first
disciples of Christ bearing the name of the A. M. E. Zion
Church, traversed the mighty mountains and low valleys of the
United States, of the Islands of the sea, and crossed the mighty
deep to Africa, to find a resting place for their insulted Christian
manhood, where the emoluments in grace and peace with and
from God, could be enjoyed at ease and with satisfaction.</p>

<p>For one century an uninterrupted stream of devotedly race
loving, Christian emigration continued to swell its numbers, till
to-day. From these primitive mission efforts of the fathers of
Zion, in America, Africa and the Bahamas, thousands enjoy its
freedom and are led by her shepherds.</p>

<p>Various and interesting and instructive are the incidents
which have through this long period transpired; and as the improvement 
of such incidents is often enjoined in scripture, it
may be well for us to adopt the language of Moses, when about
to bid adieu to his brethren. "Remember the days of old, the
years of many generations, ask thy fathers and they will show
thee; thy elders and they will tell thee." This will be the more
appropriate as we are assembled to herald to the world the prosperity
of the church, and as we are on the eve of a century
celebration. It would indeed be more joyful to the speaker if the
contemplated celebration pertained to the body of Christ at large,
yet if invidious comparisons be avoided, if with our reminiscences
of the goodness of God to Zion, we forget not his mercies to
others, and cherish a deep sense of our unprofitableness, it will
tend to the glory of that Redeemer, who would have all of his

<pb n="p289"/>

disciples regard each other as brethren, while they acknowledge
as their one and only Master, neither Calvin, nor Wesley, nor
Luther, nor Zwingle, but Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>The period selected as the beginning of the Spirit of Missions 
in the A.M.E. Zion Church, is one illustrious in the
annals of the world. It separates between the reign of different
political theories, the divine right of kings to govern the people
and the people's right to govern themselves, between the principles 
of liberty and slavery. Christianity is a religion of peace,
and the tempests of war never fail to blast and scatter the leaves
that are for the healing of the nations.</p>

<p>The particular circumstances attending the formation and
growth of this blessed institution, the Missionary cause, are
known to the most of you, and our time will not allow us to
narrate them.</p>

<p>We pause to consider that the genius of the Gospel is essentially
diffusive in Mission work.</p>

<p>The genius of the Gospel is essentially diffusive. It is
adpated and was designed to be the religion of man. And if any
future event can be rendered absolutely certain, it is in the ultimate 
spread and intelligible proclamation of the gospel to the
whole world. Independent of express prediction, this might be
argued, from the adaptation of the gospel to the condition of the
entire human race, and the kind of witness it is intended to bear
for God to the whole world. Its ample provisions are suited to
the needs of all and sufficiently manifest to meet the direct
exigencies of ruined human nature everywhere. The administration 
of the Holy Spirit is efficient and glorious, adapted to
gather all the nations under its unseen yet almighty energies.
The power and grace of Christ is illimitable. The change of
moral character which the gospel effects, the tragic woes which
it relieves, the joys it confers, and the hopes it inspires, are
equally interesting to human nature, in every variety of physical
condition, or in any possible locality on the face of the globe.
Why then should it not be preached in all the world. Now if it
is important that this august disclosure of God's character in the
Gospel be made to any, it is not equally as important that ultimately

<pb n="p290"/>

it should be made to all the human race? If this witness
which the gospel bears to the eternal love of God in the gift of
his Son, to his holiness, justice and truth, to his compassion for
the guilty and miserable, to the provisions he has made for their
rescue, from all the ills of their <sic>apostacy</sic>, and their elevation to
all the joys and exalted destinies of the redeemed in heaven, if it
be important that such a testimony be borne for God, to any
nation under heaven, is it not equally important that it should be
borne in behalf of their common Sovereign and Proprietor to all
nations?</p>

<p>Now as God has indicated his purpose to accomplish this
stupendous result mainly by human instrumentality, and as the
command to go into all the world and preach the gospel to
every creature, rests imperatively on the church at present, it
becomes us to look carefully over the whole field, and see if any
of it has been hitherto in any considerable portion almost
entirely neglected.</p>

<p>With the moral map of this apostate world, in its lights and
shadows of life and death before us, let us contain our eyes upon
the vast continent of Africa, and survey with Christian compassion
its horrors of great darkness.</p>

<p>Thirty years ago our eyes were fixed upon it. We saw that
if Ethiopia would ever stretch forth her wings and come forth to
the praise of God, it must be accomplished largely through the
instrumentalities of the race. Thus a mission station was put at
the seat of the government of the Republic of Liberia, with Elder
Cartwright at its head. To him was given the superintendency
of that work. It is needless to remark that the efforts put forth
by this sacrificing Christian man, were not at all times successful,
at one time tidings would come of the abundant success of the
work and spread of the kingdom. Again would come the intelligence 
of the return of a hostile spirit of the natives, sufferings of
the missionary, calls for monetary aid. But under the guidance
of an allwise God the church has been able to continue work
among the millions of souls in that benighted land not only
resulting in the planting of congregations, but schools as well.</p>

<pb n="p291"/>

<p>That Africa has claims upon the sympathies, the charities
and evangelical efforts of Christendom, is manifest.</p>

<p>For centuries the history of the African race has been one
of mournful and tragic interest, and their sad destinies a profound
mystery, in righteous providence of God over the world.
The slave trade, with all its direct and collateral miseries and
devastations, with fiendish rapacity, piracy and enormous vices,
has been plied on the devoted inhabitants of Africa with an
industry that has never tired nor paused, and a cruel cupidity
that has never relented, for the last four or five hundred years.
Millions of her unoffending children have been torn from her
bosom amid circumstances that give to separation its most
poignant agony. They have been made the servant of servants
in every land of their dispersion. Doomed to returnless exile,
and bound to perpetual servitude, have worn out their lives in 
unrequited toil in an unwearied and joyless industry, for the
interest of those who originally stole them, and the accomplices
who imposed <sic>npon</sic> them the galling and permanent bands of 
their slavery.</p>

<p>And who has inflicted this overgrown and outrageous
aggregate of injuries on Africa? Professedly Christian Nations.
Yes the Lion of Great Britain, and the Eagle of America, formally
crouching and perching over the deck of the slave ships as
they bore away Africa's sons and daughters to hopeless bondage. 
Does not Christendom owe a mighty debt to that despoiled,
bereaved land? "Like Rachel weeping for her children, and
refusing to be comforted, because they are not;" does not
Africa's voice of lamentation cry to heaven against the civilized
world? and call upon our common humanity for redress? Now,
what adequate reparation can we make for wrongs, violence, and
havoc of centuries, without parallel, and 'in some' respects irretrievable? 
We must send them the glorious gospel of the
blessed God. Thus we see that the genius of the gospel is
essentially diffusive in the work of missions. Not only is it true
but it is the obligation of christianity to foster the cause of missions 
by this diffusion. There is a very prevalent idea, that it is
a matter left to our option how far we shall exert an influence

<pb n="p292"/>

in the spread of missions, to what degree we shall allow the
spirit and principles of Christianity to control that influence. It
is thought that so long as we do not choose to make that control
supreme over us, we may disregard it with impunity. No
church can prosper, that does not make advances upon the
world both at home and abroad. This is the plain object of its
existence, and when it ceases to keep this view it becomes stagnant,
breeds internal strife and external obloquy. But how to be
most effectively aggressive must be gained by experience and by
varied readjustments of the methods pursued, one church will be
more successful working along certain lines of effort, another
will accomplish more while pursuing a line running a different
direction. Each should study its own agency and its own field,
and adapt its methods to its means and the character of its
sphere. If these are governed by this controlling spirit of the
religion the Bible teaches, the plaudits of the matter of the work
in the world will fall upon all. It is the business of the Christian
church to make a market and not to wait for one. An iron post
placed in a public park does not disperse darkness, something to be bruised
against when you find it at night, to be avoided and shunned by
day. String the electric light across it, fix the carbon points,
now it is a fountain of light. The past added to the darkness,
making its own market. Light compels recognition; this is as
true of missions as it is of electricity. It compels recognition.
Plant one here, adjust the carbon points of the gospel of Christ
Jesus and it will find its market in the gathering in of precious
souls to God and his Christ.</p>

<p>In a Wesleyan Mission not long since, a mighty revival was
in progress. The rector of the Established Church dropped in
one evening, as he was bound to do. Scandalized by the excitement, 
he rebuked the zealous missionary, saying, this is all
wrong, all wrong. You make too much noise here. The missionary 
only replied, "Oh! but that's all right, we are not
erecting a house here, we are just blasting, getting out lively
stones for the temple." Friends, this is what the Christianity of

<pb n="p293"/>

today needs in the spread of missions into all the world, dynamic
energy.</p>

<p>Again, in the spread of the Master's kingdom by the instrumentality 
of missions, there have been, and are, mighty foes
with which to contend. There are many who begin to view the
actual condition of our country, in its religious and moral aspect,
with alarm. A vast increase of territory and of population has
made the problem of evangelization a very perplexing one. The
profligate waste of christian resources, spiritual and material, implied 
in the perpetuation of sects, calling for five or six men in a
village where one man would suit. We are not fulfilling the
conditions of our social life as christians. Till now there has
existed among us a recognized standard. But already the Bible
is banished from our schools with indignity and contempt. The
Gospels are flippantly classed with the Koran and Zeud Avesta,
as equally imperfect and equally useful; nay sentimentalists in
pulpits and on platforms are applauded when they contend that
the Bible is not more the light of the world than the monstrous
fables of the Bramin and Buddhist. Materialism and mammon-worship
predominate in many of our great cities, while mere
indifference lends itself to their controlling influence. The gallios
of the market, the masters of trade, and the tacticians of
politics care for none of these things. All of these forces the
mission cause has to combat.</p>

<p>What is christianity doing with its immense resources and
gigantic energies to stay this plague and <sic>fostor</sic> this influence
laboring to establish the Church in all parts of the world?
<hi rend="italics">Much</hi> is the word that answers this query.</p>

<p>But what is the plan? The plan of missions is indeed
dependent upon the agency of the Holy Spirit for its success.
This is the plan of St. Paul, outlined as the scheme for redemption.
The preaching of the gospel to all nations as a witness.
To witness to world and to win the world are not co-extensive
undertakings, and when the church shall have testified the gospel
of the grace of God to the world and among all nations, it may
be that multitudes will yet remain disobedient to the heavenly
message. The theology of missions is christo-centric; that is to

<pb n="p294"/>

say, we take our standard at the cross and move out to the uttermost
parts of the earth, instead of grasping the uttermost parts
of the earth that we may move them to Christ. Here is the
point of our activity. If we place before ourselves the task of
bringing the world to Christ, we have all the unbelief and all of
the inertia and all the hostility of the world to resist us. If we
do as we are bidden, carry Christ to all the world, we have all
the impulse and might of his life and love to carry us forward in
our work. Here the principle holds true, <hi rend="italics">Teneo et teneor,"</hi>
bear Christ to the heathen and we will be borne to Christ. I
pray you that I shall be pardoned for bearing upon your patience
in this, and that a short review of the mission operations of Zion
Church at home and abroad will not prove burdensome to your
patience.</p>

<p>The Women's Home and Foreign Mission Society at the
head of which was the lamented Mrs. Bishop Jones; and now
Mrs. Bishop Hood, has and is still accomplishing a work that
has been of incalculable assistance to the spread of the Master's
kingdom and the development of the church. By them hundreds 
of dollars are raised for the aid of our missions. In their
report to the General Conference last held showed a decided
increase upon work accomplished in years previous.</p>

<p>Missions in the United States have been very fruitful.
Though silently prosecuted, yet they have wonderfully progressed. 
A few years ago the Church in the West and extreme
South-west had developed only moderately; but by the energy of
sacrificing men, consecrated to God and the cause of the Church,
to-day witnesses a blooming condition of the Church. Conferences 
have sprung up- grown into prominence and numbers.
Louisiana, Texas, Oregon and Canada are specimens of the
labors of the home mission workers in the church. A few years
ago these conferences were not self-supporting; to-day they
represent some of the best brain among the people of color and
are here and there blessed with fine churches and flourishing
congregations.</p>

<p>In the Bahama Islands many years ago the church established
mission stations that have grown as the condition of the
people would admit.</p>

<p>In Africa, for twenty years, Rev. A. Cartwright has been
laboring with flattering success among the heathen. He went
early among the people of the West coast and it can be said that
the church has in him and his assistants contributed much to
the Christian civilization the people there now enjoy.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

