<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0063">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, "The New Africa" (1887)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0063</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The New Africa</title>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<date when="1887-01">January 1887</date>
<biblScope unit="page">7-8</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>International Conferences</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/22935395">Bismarck, Herbert, Fürst von, 1849-1904</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Berlin (Germany)</term>
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-01" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p7"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The New Africa.*</p>

<p>* Thanks are cordially expressed to the <hi rend="italics">Missionary Herald</hi> of Boston; <hi rend="italics">Foreign Missionary</hi> of New York; <hi rend="italics">African Times</hi> of London, and <hi rend="italics">L'Africque</hi> of Geneva, for facts and figures freely incorporated in this paper.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<p>The Berlin Conference.</p>

<p>The representatives of the Powers who attended the Congo Conference 
last year met at the Berlin Foreign Office on April 19, under
the presidency of Count Herbert Bismarck, in conformity with article 
38 of the General Act, for the purpose of drawing up a protocol
as to the delivery of the ratifications, when Count Bismarck announced 
that the General Act had been ratified by all the Conference
Powers, with the exception of the United States. instead of exchanging 
ratifications, as is customary in the case of most treaties,
the Powers in the present instance deposited their respective ratifications 
in the archives of the Imperial Government.</p>

<p>Why the Government of the United States has not imitated the
example of its co-signatories of the Congo General Act is not stated
in the official announcement of the results of the meeting, but its omission 
to do so is the more singular, as this Government was the first that
recognized the flag of the <sic>Internatial</sic> Association, sometime before
this <sic>enterprize</sic> had developed into the Congo Free State. But the
United States Government was not satisfied with the tenor of certain
clauses in the General Act, which had been signed by its representative 
at the Conference, and the subsequent message of the President
to Congress contained the following allusion to the subject: "A
conference of delegates of the principal commercial nations was held

<pb n="p8"/>

at Berlin last winter to discuss methods whereby the Congo basin
might be kept open to the world's trade. Delegates attended on
behalf of the United States on the understanding that their part
should be merely deliberative, without imparting to the results any
binding character, as far as the United States were concerned. This
reserve was due to the indisposition of this Government to share in
any disposal, by an international congress, of jurisdictional questions
in remote foreign territories. The results of the Conference were
embodied in a formal Act, of the nature of an international convention, 
which laid down certain obligations purporting to be binding on
the signatories, subject to ratification within one year."</p>

<p>The Government of the United States has later declined to ratify
the General Act which embodies the results of the Berlin Conference, 
on the ground that the document would impose obligations on
the American Government at variance with its traditional foreign
policy. The attitude of the Government of Washington was defined
by the President in his message of December last, as follows: "Notwithstanding 
the reservation under which the delegates of the United
States attended, their signatures were attached to the General Act in
the same manner as those of the other Governments, thus making
the United States appear without reserve or qualification as signatories 
to a joint international engagement, imposing on the signers the
conservation of the territorial integrity of distant regions where we
have no established interests or control. This Government does not,
however, regard its reservation of liberty of action in the premises at
all impaired; and, holding that an engagement to share in the obligation 
of enforcing neutrality in the remote valley of the Congo would
be an alliance the responsibilities of which we are not in a position
to assume, I abstain from asking the sanction of the Senate to that
General Act."</p>

<p>The question is, whether the President was right in his interpretation 
of the meaning of the General Act as regards the assumption
of an obligation on the part of the American Government to enforce
the neutrality of the Congo State instead of merely respecting it.
Meanwhile the fact is, America has ceased to be a party to the instrument
known as the Acte Generale.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
