<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0615">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John A. Parm to Frederick W. Seward, October 26, 1878</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Sherrod, C'yera" xml:id="csls">C'yera Sherrod</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0615</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John A. Parm to Frederick W. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Sierra Leone, 1858-1906 T-438</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-438, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1878-10-26">October 26, 1878</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Broadhurst, John</term>
<term>O'Brien, Thomas</term>
<term>Grey, Julian, Mrs.</term>
<term>Griffith, John</term>
<term>Hynderson, Edward</term>
<term>Miller, Hnery</term>
<term>Thompson, Charles</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Boston (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Parm, John A.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consular Agent</roleName>
<placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
<date when="1878-10-26"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Acting U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-03" who="#kln">Encoding, transcription edits, and review</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#csls">Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="318"/>

<note>No 3</note>

<p>U.S. Consulate at<lb/>
Sierra Leone Oct 26th 1878</p>

<p>John A. Parm<lb/>
To Department of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

<p>Subject.<lb/>
The Arrival at this consulate of 
three destitute American Seamen &amp;c.</p> 

<p>Abstract of Contents.<lb/>
To inform the Department that I have Sent 
Edward Hynderson one of the Seamen to 
Liverpool, &amp; have drawn a Draft for his 
passage; Also to acquaint the Department 
of the refusal of Thomas O. Brine (Master of Brig "Annie &amp; Lily.") to take the two remaining 
Seamen, and the correspondences connected
 therewith.</p>

<p>Inclosures.<lb/>
<sic>Copys</sic> of correspondence from Messers 
Randall &amp; Fisher. And my Reply's.</p>

<pb n="319"/>

<note>No 3</note>

<p>United States Consulate at 
Sierra Leone<lb/>
Octb 26th 1878.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to inform you that there
arrived at this Consulate on the 6th of October
from Monrovia Liberia, Henry Miller &amp; Charles 
Thompson, two destitute American Seamen, belonging 
to the Schooner "Cupid" of Boston Mass. Said
Schooner having been seized by the Liberian 
Government and afterwards burnt; There being no 
American Vessel at that port, they were sent 
to this Consulate, by the American Consul at 
Liberia to be forwarded to America. On the 12th
inst there arrived Edward Hynderson another
destitute American seamen (belonging to the same 
schooner "Cupid") to be forwarded to the U.S.</p>

<p>There was then in this port one 
American Vessel the Brig "Annie &amp; Lily" of Boston 
consigned to Messrs Randall &amp; Fisher, Thomas O'Brine
Master, <sic>Tonage</sic> 291; Which was to have sailed for
Boston in a few days. I had intended to send the men 
by her, but on the 18th inst Edward Hynderson
shewed slight symptoms of fever and as the steamer 
"Gaboon" arrived that day from the <sic>Leward</sic>, I thought
it best to send him in her. I therefore arranged with 
Capt John Griffith of said steamer for his passage 
to Liverpool, giving the Captain a Draft on the 
secretary of state for Ten Pounds sterling, and sent by 
the same steamer a letter to the Consul at Liverpool, 
requesting him to forward the seamen to some port in 
the United States. I am sorry to inform the Department
that in drawing the Draft, I was compelled to Omit 
<catchwords>the</catchwords> 

<pb n="320"/>

the clause in the regulations, paragraph 169. "referring 
to Drafts drawn for transportation of destitute
American seamen to intermediate ports". The Captain
refused to take the man unless that clause was <sic>omited</sic>.</p>

<p>On the morning of the 21st inst the master of the 
American Brig "Annie &amp; Lily" applied to this Consulate 
for his clearance and ships papers, I requested 
the Captain to take on board of his Brig Henry 
Miller &amp; Charles Thompson on the two destitute Seamen 
remaining, to be landed at the port of Boston U.S.A. 
he after some hesitancy agreed to do so, and 
requested me to have the seamen meet him at 
this Consulate, prior to their going on board. I 
immediately sent to the seaman's boarding place 
(a distance of a quarter of a mile from this 
Consulate) requesting them to be present at 12 Oclock noon. 
they accordingly came; one of them Charles Thompson 
looking weak from an attack of <unclear extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> the night
previous. I informed them of the nature of the 
call, and asked them if they were ready, and 
felt well enough to go to sea? They said "they 
were, provided they were not compelled to 
work until they felt stronger." On the 
Captains return he refused to take them, saying 
they were sick and unable to work at Sea; Not 
finding any law where Masters of American <sic>vessel's</sic> are privileged to refuse taking destitute 
American Seamen because they are not able to 
work on their passage home. But finding a law 
which <sic>compells</sic> them to take destitute American 
seamen, when requested to do so by the Consul, 
I refused to give up the ships papers <sic>unles</sic> he 
would take them, or make a declaration in
<catchwords>writing</catchwords>

<pb n="321"/>

writing, <sic>stateing</sic> the <sic>cause</sic> of his refusal.</p>

<p>Neither of the men had applied to me to be sent 
to the Hospital, and in my opinion they were 
not really sick enough to be sent there, though 
they had asked once for a dose of salts, which I
gave them gratuitously. climate and change of diet 
have caused them to look a little <sic>amacipated</sic> but they 
would in a few days improve by being at sea.
Captain O Brine left the Consulate and in a few 
moments after I received letter No 1 which I inclosed with my reply.</p> 

<p>I beg also to inclose <sic>correspondence's</sic> No 2. &amp; 3. from
Messrs Randall &amp; Fisher on the same subject, with my
reply.</p>

<p>On the 22nd Captain O'Brien called at this Consulate 
the second time for the ships papers, stating that the 
seamen <unclear>refered</unclear> to, had themselves informed him that 
morning, that they were not well enough to go to 
sea. I immediately called at their boarding place 
and inquired of them, had they made such a
statement? They <sic>acknowledge</sic> to me that they had. 
I requested them to make it in writing which they did.
I then delivered to Captain O'Brine the Brig "Annie &amp; 
Lily's" papers, and he sailed the next day.</p>

<p>Acting upon the statement of the seamen relative to 
their not being well enough to go to sea, I wrote to the 
Colonial Surgeon of this place on the 23rd, requesting 
their admission into the Colonial Hospital for 
account of this Consulate.</p>

<p>I beg to state for the information of the Department 
that Mrs Julian Grey the seamen's boarding mistress, 
informed me that Captain O'Brine visited the 
seamen at her boarding house on the morning of the 
22nd and said to them that if they would make <catchwords>above </catchwords>

<pb n="322"/>

above mentioned statement, the Consul would be 
obliged to send them by first steamer via
Liverpool which would enable them to reach 
home much sooner, and they would not have to
work on the passage."</p>

<p>In conclusion I beg to say that Thomas O'Brine 
Master of the Brig "Annie &amp; Lily" of Boston, Seemed
to be entirely devoid of sympathy for the destitute 
American Seamen, and expressed himself very 
unbecomingly in my presence, as Master of an 
American Vessel, in regard to the laws governing 
merchant ship's.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir <lb/>
Your Obedient Servant<lb/>
John A. Parm<lb/>
U.S. Consul</p>

<p>To<lb/>
The Honorable<lb/>
F. W. Seward<lb/>
Acting Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="323"/>

<note>copy of reply<lb/>
No 1</note>

<p>U.S. Consulate at<lb/>
Sierra Leone Oct 21st 1878</p>

<p>Mr John Broadhurst</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Yours of the 21st inst was 
received, I beg to say that the papers of 
the Brig "Annie &amp; Lily" are ready to be 
delivered to the Master of said vessel 
when he applies for them, provided he 
conforms with the regulations paragraph 
163.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your obt Servant<lb/>
Jno A. Parm<lb/>
U.S. Consul</p>  

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="324"/>

<note>Copy of reply<lb/>
No 2</note>

<p>U.S. Consulate at
Sierra Leone<lb/>
Oct 20 1878</p>

<p>Messers Randall &amp; Fisher</p>

<p>Sirs,</p>

<p>Your letter of the 21st October informing me 
that you will instruct the Captain 
of the Brig "Annie and Lily" to proceed to sea 
without her papers, have been received. 
on that point I have nothing to say.</p>

<p>In reference to my having attended the sick
seamen contrary to regulations, remains to be 
proven. your statement to the contrary 
notwithstanding.</p>

<p>I will communicate to the state 
Department at Washington D.C. on this subject
and hold myself subject to its decision.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your Obt Sevt<lb/>
Jno. A Parm<lb/>
U.S. Consul</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="325"/>

<note>Copy of Reply<lb/>
No 3</note>

<p>U.S. Consulate at 
Sierra Leone<lb/>
Oct 22 1878</p>

<p>Messers Randall &amp; Fisher.</p>

<p>Sirs,</p>

<p>I am in receipt of yours of the 22 inst, 
and in reply I beg to say that I am ready 
&amp; willing at my moment to sign <unclear>Hide</unclear> 
Certificate, Certify to Invoice, or give my 
signature to any paper connected with 
your vessel as far as it is in my power; 
I have no desire to detain the vessel, or to 
prevent the Master of the Brig "Annie &amp; Lily" 
from having all of her papers, provided he 
take the two destitute America seamen, or
enters a protest or declaration in writing that 
he <unclear>declined</unclear> to do so.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your obdt servant<lb/>
Jno. A. Parm<lb/>
U.S. Consul</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>