<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0069">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Augustus Archer Silva to William H. Seward, November 25, 1865</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0069</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Augustus Archer Silva to William H. Seward, November 30, 1865</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from U.S. Consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, Portuguese Africa, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">T430</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="roll">2</biblScope>
<date when="1865-11-25">November 25, 1865</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Affonso, Luis José Mendes</term>
<term>Barnett, Isaac</term>
<term>Baxter, Edward</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/99317554">Bettencourt, Carlos Pacheco de</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/99730548">Leal, Fernando da Costa, 1825-1869</term>
<term>da Silva Marquis Porto, Francisco</term>
<term>de Espirito Santo e Cinsha, Feliciano Gonçales</term>
<term>de Lewis Perveira Batalha, José Solomão</term>
<term>de Mello Varajãs, Antonio</term>
<term>de Santos, José Antonio</term>
<term>de Viagas de O., Joaquim</term>
<term>Ferreira, Luis Pedro</term>
<term>Finlay, Kirkman</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9835147270628635700003">Govea, Augustus E. B. (Augustus Edward Bothelho), approximately 1826-1890</term>
<term>Mason, Charles</term>
<term>Vredenburg, Watson</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Angola</term>
<term>Bahia (Brazil)</term>
<term>Boston (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>Glasgow (Scotland)</term>
<term>Hong Kong</term>
<term>Isle of Wight (England)</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Mossamedes (Angola)</term>
<term>Nantucket (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>New London (Connecticut)</term>
<term>New York (New York)</term>
<term>Salem (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>San Francisco (California)</term>
<term>Shanghai (China)</term>
<term>St. Helena</term>
<term>Westport (Rhode Island)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>England</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Silva, Augustus Archer</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent for Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1865-11-25"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1866-03-05"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-05" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and addition encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.001"/>

<note>Recd Mch 5</note>

<note>No 15.</note>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda 25th November 1865.</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>In my despatch No 13, I had the honor of informing the 
Department that an American Seaman calling himself Edward
Baxter, presented himself to me, on the 24th of September, requesting
protection as a destitute seaman. He represented to me that he
departed from the American Barque "Governor Carver" <unclear>Captain</unclear>
Charles Mason of Westport, R.I. at Mossamedes (Little Fish Bay)
for the reason that said Barque had taken in at that place slaves
and that he assisted taking on board the first seventy five and on
returning for more, ran away and after the Barque had proceeded to
sea, he came down to the town and made arrangements with Captain
<unclear/> of the British Mail Steamer "Lincolnshire" and came to
this place and presented himself to me, as stated. I listened to 
<catchwords>his</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon William H Seward<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
Washington,
D.C.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.002"/>

his story with apprehension and doubt, but not wishing to show, that 
I entertained such a feeling, I treated the subject, for a time with
seeming indifference, and set Baxter to work, about my house
with some light jobs. My anxiety to sift out the truth of this case
increased from day to day and I questioned and cross-questioned
him frequently on the subject with a view to compare one statement
with another and I was surprised to find them always correspond.
On one of these days, I met at the house of a friend, Watson
Vredenburg Esquire, H B M's Commissioner for the Slave trade. 
We conversed together and I promised to send Baxter to him,
that he might take his deposition, with an object to compare with
the one that I should require of him, when I should consider it 
proper to take a formal one, before me. I sent Baxter to Mr
Vredenburg, and to my surprise, two days after, I learned at
a late hour that Baxter had been sent on board the British 
Brig "Elizabeth," as a British subject, and which vessel was that
day sail for England. I was still under excitement on account
of this extraordinary occurrence. Captain <unclear/>
<catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.003"/>

of the Portuguese Corvette "Infante D. João" came into
my office, and in a few words I explained to him the course of
my <unclear/>. He made a remark of dissatisfaction and said
he could not imagine what motive could have caused Mr Vredenburg
to act so, and doubted very much if Baxter had been properly 
cleared by the Police Authorities, according to the local laws of 
this Province. I <unclear/> that same evening to learn that through 
Commander de <unclear>O's</unclear> influence Baxter was taken out of the  
vessel by order of the Police Authorities for not having been 
cleared from that department and sent on board of the Portuguese
Corvette "Infante D. João." Two days afterwards Baxter 
was sent to the British Consul (Mr Vredenburg is also Consul) 
on the 9th ult. I addressed a note to Mr Vredenburg, who
immediately sent Baxter to my office with a despatch and a 
certified copy of the deposition of Baxter, taken before him. In
the mean time the Portuguese Government had heard of the report
made by Baxter of an <sic>embarcation</sic> of slaves in a Portuguese 
port, and addressed me a note requesting me the kindness to 
<catchwords>inform</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.004"/>

inform them fully on the subject. The following evening, I 
invited three witnesses to my house and before them, took the 
deposition of Baxter and the same day sent a despatch 
to the Colonial Secretary General <unclear>&amp;</unclear> <unclear>other</unclear> certified copies of both 
depositions. I also addressed Mr Vredenburg again. You will 
observe by inclosure No 6 that I requested of the Provincial Government
to send Baxter to Mossamedes, as I thought that on the <unclear>very</unclear> <unclear>spot</unclear>
they would be better able to get at the truth of this <unclear/> subject.
I received a reply in the affirmative and on the 12th ult. I sent
Baxter with a despatch, on board of the Portuguese Corvette
"Infante D. João". On the 14th ulto I received a despatch from 
the British Consul. On the 30th ulto the Corvette returned, and 
on that day I received a communication from Commander de <unclear>O</unclear>
and on the 3rd inst a despatch from the acting Governor General 
both informing me that the evidence obtained at Mossamedes found
Baxter guilty of basest falsehood and that he had been committed
to Prison by order of the Government, to be tried on 
the charge of the false <unclear/>. I replied on the 3rd inst 
<catchwords>requesting</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.005"/>

requesting copies of the depositions taken at Mossamedes. In 
the meantime Baxter was brought up before the Judicial 
Authorities for indictment, when he confessed, voluntarily that 
everything he had said was false and a <unclear/> mention of his <unclear/>
I was officially informed of this fact on the 9th inst, enclosing
<unclear/> a certified copy of the confession taken before the Chief 
Justice of the City in open court. His Excellency in reply to my 
despatch (enclosure No 18) regretted that the original deposition 
taken at Mossamedes had been sent to the Judicial Authorities
to enable them to find a bill of indictment against Baxter 
which prevented him sending me copies at present, adding
that they were very voluminous and not of much importance 
after the declaration of falsehood made by him. I was satisfied 
that the evidence was quite sufficient and on the 11th inst. I 
addressed a note to the President of the Government Council
expressing my approval in complimentary terms on the favorable 
termination of this case, which at one time indicated serious
alarm, on the probable revival of the slave trade in American
<catchwords>vessels</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.006"/>

vessels and in Portuguese waters. On the 20th inst I addressed 
a note of congratulations  and thanks to Commander <unclear>Viagas de O.</unclear>
of the Portuguese Corvette Infante de João and also to Fernando 
da Costa Leal Governor of Mossamedes. I also wrote on the same 
date to Charles Mason, Master of the Barque "Governor Carver"
requesting him when he visited Mossamedes to call at this port.
Throughout the case a spirited correspondence has been carried on 
between the British Consul and the President of the Government 
Council, on account of the Authorities having taken Baxter 
from on board the Brig "Elizabeth" and question their authority 
to do so, alleging that they interfered with his Consular functions. 
The Government has endeavoured to convince him that they acted in 
accordance with the local laws of this Province. The President 
of the Government Council told me, he had censured him for 
not regarding in a more serious manner the responsibility 
which the accusation of Baxter inflicted upon the reputation of 
Portugal and the United States and without entertaining the 
least consideration would have sent Baxter to the Foreign 
<catchwords>Office</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.007"/>

Office in England and thereby compromise this Provincial 
Government and the Commercial Agency of the United States.
The Provincial Government has also been informed by the 
British Consul, that Baxter was a British subject and 
professes to have delivered him over to me as a deserter from an 
American Barque. The Department will observe by the
several depositions, that Baxter declared himself, on oath, 
to be an American naturalized citizen. In his confession 
which can be taken as a "bona fide" evidence, he further 
declares that he is a naturalized citizen of the United States. 
He claimed protection at this Commercial Agency, when he 
could have applied to the British Consulate and being also 
a deserter from the American Barque "Governor Carver". I felt 
fully authorized with all these facts to <unclear>use</unclear> upon him my 
Consular authority. By enclosure No 1 you will perceive that 
I expressed my surprise to the British Consul at his attempting 
to send Baxter to England, when he had no reason to
suppose that I had done with him. Baxter was commanded 
<catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.008"/>

to present himself to the Foreign Office, on his arrival on  
England, to be there questioned on the subject and the 
consequences of such a step, without the possibility of contra-evidence, 
would have been extremely serious. He offered me 
an apology for acting thus, alleging that he supposed I 
had done with him, but which I had never thought a 
justifiable excuse; Nevertheless I considered it proper to 
let the subject stop with him, after this apology.</p>

<p>You will perceive by the numerous enclosures 
that I have enclosed to do this <unclear extent="two words"/> upon me 
and throughout the proceedings have been anxious to discover if
the abominable traffic of slave trade had been revived, in
American vessels which, since the capital punishment of 
Captain Gordon by the United States Government, I have 
not heard of a single shipment of slaves, from this part of the 
Coast and which previous to that event was almost exclusively
carried on, most disgracefully, under the American Flag. 
I learn from the President of the Government Council that 
<catchwords>Baxter's</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.009"/>

Baxter's trial will soon take place. I was surprised to hear 
him say that the penalty applicable to him by the Criminal 
laws of Portugal is very slight, and very probably he will only 
receive a reprimand and be set at liberty. Should this take place 
I shall order him back to Prison, and keep him there four 
months for desertion, unless claimed in the meantime by 
the Master of the Barque "Governor Carver". I never met 
in all my life a more curt and consummate <sic>rouge</sic> than the 
said Edward Baxter. A man so regardless of himself and 
his Creator as to make several false <unclear/> only to injure
Captain Mason of the "Governor Carver", who he himself 
has wronged by receiving advance money at St Helena  
and in a few days afterwards deserted at Mossamedes.</p>

<p>I would do an act of injustice if I closed this 
despatch without mentioning in an honorable manner, the 
able, prompt and willing cooperation, I received from the 
Government in assisting me to penetrate the truth of Baxter's 
representation, and it is worthy of commendable honor to the 
<catchwords>Authorities</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.010"/>

Authorities here to note the indignation which the story of 
Baxter aroused within them, when their National honor was 
in danger of being stigmatized with the revival of the slave 
trade in their waters.</p>

<p>I have the Honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your most obedt Servant,<lb/>
Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.011"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda Octob 9th 1865.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>The Seaman who claimed the protection of 
this Commercial Agency as a destitute American 
Citizen, &amp; who ran away from the American Barque 
"Governor Carver" at Mossamedes, for the alleged 
reason that said vessel was a slaver, &amp; who 
afterwards was shipped by you as a British 
Subject, on board of the British Brig "Elizabeth" 
but detained on account of some irregularity; You 
will please send said Seaman to this office, that 
he may explain to me, why he claimed &amp; received 
protection as an American Citizen, when he was 
not such &amp; likewise to prove the charge made 
<catchwords>by</catchwords>

<fw type="address">M Vredenburg Esqr<lb/>
British Consul<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.012"/>

by him, against the character of the American  
Barque Governor Carver.</p>

<p>I have the honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your Most Obedt Servant<lb/>
(Signed) Augustus Archer Silva.<lb/>
Commercial Agent.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.013"/>

<p>British Consulate Loanda<lb/>
9th October 1865.</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>In accordance with the request contained 
in your despatch of Today's date, I have the 
honor to send to your Office the Seaman Edward
Baxter, who left the American Barque "Governor 
Carver" at Mossamedes, on the ground, as he 
alleges, that she was engaged in the slave trade.</p>

<p>When Baxter by your desire presented 
himself to me, a few days ago, I was under 
the impression that you had satisfied yourself 
that he was a British Subject and intended to 
place him at my disposal with a view to 
my receiving his deposition. If I misunderstood 
your intentions and object you will I 
<catchwords>hope</catchwords>

<fw type="address">A A Silva Esqr<lb/>
United States Commercial Agent.<lb/>
&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.014"/>

hope accept the above explanation as an excuse.</p>

<p>I enclose the declaration made 
by Baxter before me to enable you to ascertain 
whether the circumstances that he may relate to 
you coincide with those that he told to me, 
and you are at liberty, if you think proper, to 
take and use a copy of this statement.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your most obedient<lb/>
humble Servant,<lb/>
(Signed) W. Vredenburg<lb/>
Consul.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.015"/>

<p>I, Edward Baxter, a native of Liverpool, 
twenty-five years of age, do solemnly declare, and 
state as follows&#8212;</p>

<p>Towards the end of July, I shipped 
at St Helena, on board the Barque "Governor 
Carver" belonging to Westport, United States of 
America, of which vessel, Charles Mason, a 
native of Nantucket, is master. The first port
at which the ship touched, after leaving St Helena, 
was Little Fish Bay, the arrival there on a 
Friday afternoon about three weeks ago. At about 
twelve Oclock that night, four boats, in one of 
which I was employed, were sent ashore to the 
North Point of the Bay, and there embarked seventy 
five Blacks, whom they conveyed on board. The boats 
were then sent a second time to the same place, 
and as I was afraid of what they were doing, I 
ran away in the dark, as I shipped to go 
<catchwords>on</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.016"/>

on a whaling voyage, and not to run slaves; I 
cannot say what number of Blacks, they took the 
second time. The ship was fitted out like a 
whaler, but when we were three days out from 
St Helena, I saw Sperm whales, all round the ship 
and said to the second Mate "how is it we are not
lowering after those whales." "Oh", said he, "we are 
not after these kind of whales." I then asked him 
what kind of whales we were after; he answered 
"We are after two or three hundred Black birds if 
we can catch them." Then the fourth day they lifted 
out the bodies. The Americans call them "Tripods",
and there was a kind of Bulk head. They knocked 
the bulkhead away and I saw an iron rod,
nailed down to the deck, with footcuffs, a sort of
handcuffs worn on the feet. Then the Captain
said Boatswain do you know what these things 
are for? "this is where we shall put the first 
<catchwords>seventy</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.017"/>

seventy niggers we get." and it was there they put 
the seventy-five they brought on board that Friday
night. After leaving the boat, I remained all 
night in the mountains, the Barque went away 
the following morning, steering towards the north.
I then went down into the town, and saw the Captain 
of the steamer "Lincolnshire" whom I asked to 
give me a passage to Loanda; He told me to 
help to get the Bullocks on board, and then 
to go on board myself; I did so, and arrived 
at this port on the 24th of September.</p>

<p>(Signed) Edward Baxter<lb/>
His X Mark.</p>

<p>Thus solemnly declared and stated 
before me at the British Consulate, Loanda 
this 6th Day of October 1865.</p>

<p>(Signed) W. Vredenburg<lb/>
Consul.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.018"/>

<p>This is to certify that the above 
named Edward Baxter, being an illiterate
person, the foregoing Statement was carefully 
read over to him; he appeared perfectly to understand 
the same and affixed his mark thereto 
in my presence.</p>

<p>(Signed) W. Vredenburg<lb/>
Consul</p>

<p>A true copy of the original of record in this 
Consulate.</p>

<p>British Consulate Loanda<lb/>
14th October 1865.<lb/>
W Vredenburg.<lb/>
Consul.</p>

<p>(Signed &amp; officially stamped)</p>

<note type="label">with Despatch No. 15.<lb/>
Deposition of Seaman
Edward Baxter, taken
before the British 
Consul.<lb/>
No. 3.<lb/>
October 6th 1865.</note>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.019"/>

<p>Translation</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>This Honorable Consul of Government 
desires me to request of you, all the possible information 
respecting a seaman named Edward
Baxter, who was found on board the English Brig
"Elizabeth", when about to sail from this port, without 
the legal and indispensable documents to enable him 
to leave this city. The said seaman states that 
he deserted from an American Barque that had 
taken in a cargo of slaves at Mossamedes, and 
that he, unwilling to run such a risk, ran
away in that place and obtained a passage to
this city on board the Steamer "Lincolnshire".</p>

<p>The Honorable Council of Government 
expects that you will kindly be pleased to furnish 
as much information as possible regarding said 
<catchwords>seaman</catchwords>

<fw type="address"><address>
<addrLine>To the</addrLine>
<addrLine>United States Commercial Agency</addrLine>
</address></fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.020"/>

seaman and all particulars bearing on this subject.</p>

<p>God preserve you!</p>

<p>Secretary General's office at Loanda October 9th 1865.</p>

<p>(Signed) <unclear>Antonio de Mello Varajãs</unclear><lb/>
Government Secretary General</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.021"/>

<p>I, Edward Baxter; a native of
Liverpool, employed in the commerce of the United
States during the past five years, as an American
Seaman; do solemnly declare and state 
as follows;</p>

<p>About three years ago I left
Boston, Mass. United States of America, on
board the American Ship "Eliza and Nell" bound
for San <sic>Franchisco</sic>; Arrived there and shipped
on board the American Ship "<unclear>Live Yankees</unclear>"
bound for Hong Kong and for <unclear/>. On
arrival there re entered said ship bound
back to San <sic>Franshisco</sic>. and on said
passage was captured by the Confederate
Privateer "Alabama"; was landed by said
privateer at Bahia where I shipped on
board the American Barque "<unclear/> bound
<catchwords>for</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.022"/>

for San <sic>Franchisco</sic> at which port I
shipped on board the American Ship "Flying
<unclear/>" to Shanghai then from said port
on board said vessel bound for New
York; Touched at the Island of St 
Helena, where on account of a previous
disagreement with the Captain, I got my
discharge; How I shipped on board the
American Barque "Governor Carver" of
Westport, Rhode Island, United States of
America, where of Charles Mason was
Master, and bound on a whaling cruise
for which purpose I shipped as Boatswain
and Boatsteerer. Three days after leaving
St Helena, I saw several whales round the
ship, and inquired of the Second Mate "Why
dont we <unclear>lower</unclear> after these whales?" He replied
we arnt after these kind of Whales"
<catchwords>I</catchwords>

<gap reason="possible missing page" extent="1 page?"/>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.023"/>

About 9 days out from St Helena, stood
off and on, off Little Fish bay for three
days; Second day of said three days, went
on shore with two boats, about two miles
north of Fort in said bay; Obtained about
40 barrels water, towed them off. Fourth
day after sighting Little Fish bay and
thirteenth from St Helena, entered and dropped
anchor in said bay, about two ship's lengths
from said Fort. when the Capitan went
on shore. Two Custom House Officers
came on board but seeing no cargo on
board, left at about 9 Oclock. Lay till
about 11 Oclock; when the boats returned,
having the Captain ashore. Weighed
anchor under command of First Mate and
dropped it again in about half an hour
after sailing that time in a northerly
<catchwords>direction</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.024"/>

direction, which brought us off the North
point of the bay. Lowered four boats and
proceeded on shore, a little to the northward
of said north point; I was on board the
first boat which struck the shore <sic>commandded</sic>
by the second Mate, where we met
the Captain and other five Portuguese,
having in their possession, Seventy-five
Negro Slaves, which we shipped on board
said boats, and from thence to said American
Barque "Governor Carver". Captain
still on shore. said slaves' arms were
secured behind them by means of grass
ropes. On reaching the vessel the Tripots
were removed and Bulkheads knocked
away, and slaves were then unshackled
to said bars, on doing which, grass ropes
were removed. The four boats again
<catchwords>returned</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.025"/>

returned to the shore; I being as before
in second Mates' boat; Reached the
shore where we again met the Captain and
said companions; I saw a number of black
men, but as to their being slaves, I cannot
swear. Jumped out of the boat, my reason
for which was demanded by the Mate.
My reply was to answer a call of Nature
and taking advantage of this excuse, I
ran away and hid in the hills, till
daybreak, when I ascended one of said
hills and saw said American Barque "Governor
Carver" getting under way; I saw her
stand apparently to the northward under
a good breeze, and about 9 oclock, she
was nearly out of sight to the northward.
Same day British Mail Steamer "Lincolnshire"
arrived from Lisbon. About 12 oclock started
<catchwords>for</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.026"/>

for the town of Mossamedes; Little Fish
bay, and there met on the beach Captain
James of the said Steamer "Lincolnshire" from
whom I asked a passage to Loanda
where I could secure the protection of an
American Consul there being none in
Mossamedes; He requested me to assist
his men to ship some bullocks and
then to go on board myself, which I
did on same day. Do no remember
whether it was same evening or next that
the Steamer sailed for Loanda. During
the <sic>disembarcation</sic> of said seventy five
slaves, one of the Boatsteerers remarked
that if procurable two hundred and fifty
slaves would be shipped. Arrived at
Loanda September 24th. immediately after
which I landed and presented myself 
<catchwords>to</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.027"/>

to the United States Commercial Agents
who on hearing my statement, gave
me protection, and during the interval
from said date, till the 5th inst; was 
from day to day <unclear/> examined
by him regarding <sic>preceeding</sic> statement
and on one occasion was sent to the
British Commissioner of the Slave
Trade in this City for examination;
I did not claim from him British
protection, but in answer to a question
of where I was born, I said I was
by birth a native of Liverpool, England
but that for several years I had been
sailing under the American Flag, as
an American sailor, and have had
protection papers, last of which was
procured at New London, State of Connecticut
<catchwords>United</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.028"/>

United States of America, five years ago.
The British Commissioner who is also British
Consul, then said, You are then an Englishman
and as such, I shall ship you on board
of the English Brig "Elizabeth" then in
this port and sailing on the 4th inst. and
into which vessel I was accordingly shipped,
but previous to which, he gave me a
despatch, which on arrival in England, I
was to deliver to the Foreign Office in
London and they would look after me.
Owing to now compliance with some of the
<unclear/> regulations, I was taken from on
board said Brig "Elizabeth" by the
Portuguese authorities.</p>

<p>I still declare myself to
be an American Citizen and as such
ask American protection.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.029"/>

<p>I do hereby solemnly declare
and state, that all the foregoing statements
are true, which I have declared in
presence of three witnesses, Namely,
Augustus E. B. Gover, Merchant, Native 
of Salem, Mass, United States of America.
Isaac Barnett, Native of the Isle of
Wight, and Master of the British Barque
"Eastward Ho" and Kirkman Finlay
of Glasgow Scotland.</p>

<p>So help me God.</p>

<p>Done in triplicate at St Paul de
Loanda on this the tenth day of 
October, One thousand, eight hundred
and sixty five.</p>

<p>Edward Baxter His X Mark</p>

<p>Witnesses<lb/>
Augt. E. B. Gover<lb/>
Isaac Barnett<lb/>
Kirkman Finlay</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.030"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda Oct 10th 1865</p>

<p>Sworn before me this tenth day of 
October, in the year of Our Lord, One thousand, 
eight hundred, and Sixty-five, and I further 
certify that the above named Edward 
Baxter does not know how to read or 
write, and that I have carefully read 
this document over to him and he has 
certified to the same by his mark in
this my presence.</p>

<p>Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.031"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda Oct 10th 1865</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the 
receipt of your despatch of the 9th inst, requesting of 
me information regarding a report made by Edward 
Baxter, a run-away seaman of the American 
Whaling Barque, "Governor Carver" at Mossamedes 
to the effect said Barque did take in slaves, while 
at anchor at Mossamedes, during the past 
month &amp; for which reason said seaman 
Edward Baxter gave as an excuse for deserting 
said vessel.</p>

<p>I have the honor to forward you 
<catchwords>enclosed</catchwords>

<fw type="address"><unclear/><lb/>
<unclear>Anton de Mello Varajãs</unclear><lb/>
Colonial Secretary for the
Province of Angola</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.032"/>

enclosed, for the information of the Honorable 
Conselho de Governo, a copy of two depositions,
signed by him; One taken before 
the British Consul &amp; the other before me 
by which it will be seen that the honor of 
Portugal as well as the United States is brought 
into question.</p>

<p>I most respectfully request of the 
Provincial Government to use all endeavors 
to search out the truth of this important 
case, that not only the honor of Portugal but
also that of the United States may be indicated;
I therefore propose that said 
seaman be sent to Mossamedes, as I think, 
on the spot, the Provincial Government, will 
have a better opportunity to judge the true merits 
of the case &amp; better qualify me to bring to 
the notice of the United States Government <unclear>a</unclear>

<gap reason="possible missing page" extent="1 page?"/>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.033"/>

his representation. I felt apprehension of his
veracity &amp; therefore adopted a <unclear>mood</unclear> of indifference
towards him &amp; employed him with some light work
about my house.</p>

<p>From day to day I would question
&amp; cross question him closely about the circumstances
connected with the Barque "Governor Carver" with a
<unclear/> to compare one statement with another. It was
also with this intention I sent him to you as
"Commissioner of the <unclear>mixed</unclear> Commission" that you
also might extract from him information to compare
afterwards with that he furnished me.</p>

<p>I must confess: I was
somewhat surprised when I learned at a late
hour that you had shipped him as a British
subject on board of the British Brig "Elizabeth",
&amp; I am glad to note in your despatch of yesterday
that your action was unintentional, although I
<catchwords>gave</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.034"/>

gave you no cause whatever for you to suppose I
had done with him. My mind was relieved of
a great responsibility when it came to my knowledge
that for some slight error of Police regulation
Baxter was taken out of the Brig Elizabeth by
the Portuguese Authorities before she went to sea.
You also much be well aware that such a grave
subject as the charge made against the American
Barque "Governor Carver"; my Government
will look to me for explanations.</p>

<p>Last evening in the presence
of important witnesses, I took the deposition of said
Edward Baxter on the charge prepared by him
against the character of the Barque "Governor Carver"
I enclose you a copy which will prove to you the
grounds which justify me in handing said Baxter
over to the Provincial Government for them, at my
request to thoroughly investigate this important
<catchwords>case</catchwords>

<gap reason="possible missing page" extent="1 page?"/>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.035"/>

that the honor alike of Portugal &amp; the United
States now involved, may be properly vindicated
&amp; better qualify me to bring the case to the
notice of my Government.</p>

<p>I have the honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your Most Obedt Servant.<lb/>
(Signed) Augustus Archer Silva.<lb/>
Commercial Agent.</p>

<note type="label">Enclosure<lb/>
with Despatch No. 15.</note>

<note type="label">My Despatch to British
Consul in reply to
his Despatch of the 
9th of October</note>

<note type="label">No. 1</note>

<note type="label">October 10th 1865.</note>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.036"/>

<note>Translation</note>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p><sic>I</sic> accordance with your last despatch
concerning the seaman Edward Baxter and in
obedience to the orders of the Hon Council of
Government, acting as Governor General, I
am directed to inform you that you can order
the said seaman to be sent on board the
Corvette "Infante D. João" today, to be
placed at the disposal of the Chief of the Naval
Station, for the purpose mentioned in your
said despatch.</p>

<p>God preserve you!</p>

<p>Secretary General's office at Loanda October 12th 1865</p>

<p>(Signed) Antonio de Mello Varajãs<lb/>
Government Secretary General.</p>

<fw type="address">To The<lb/>
United States Commercial Agent</fw>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.037"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda October 12th 1865</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Agreeable to the wish of the Hon "Conselho
de Governo," I have the honor to send on board
of your ship, Seaman Edward Baxter who
deserted from the American Whaling Barque
"Governor Carver" at Mossamedes.</p>

<p>You are well aware of the object
of his presence on board of your ship, and I
hope his testimony at Mossamedes may lend to
clear up the mystery which now hangs over
the character of said American Barque, and
the authorities of that place.</p>

<p>I have the Honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your most obdt Servt<lb/>
(Signed) Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent</p>

<fw type="address">Captain Joaqm de <unclear>Viegas de O.</unclear>
Commanding<lb/>
H. M. <unclear>T.</unclear> Ship<lb/>
"Infante D. João."</fw>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.038"/>

<p>British Consulate Loanda<lb/>
14th October 1865.</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
of your despatch of the 10th inst. enclosing a certified
copy of the deposition made before you by Edward
Baxter, a seaman who deserted from the American
Barque "Governor Carver" on the pretext that she
had shipped a cargo of slaves.</p>

<p>As I understand you to
claim Baxter, as a deserter from an American
ship, I can have neither the right, nor have I the
slightest desire to contest the claim.</p>

<p>I have the honor to enclose a certified
copy of the statement made in my presence by Baxter
of the alleged shipment of slaves, and I take the
<catchwords>opportunity</catchwords>

<fw type="address">A A Silva Esqre.<lb/>
United States Commercial Agent<lb/>
&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.039"/>

opportunity of observing that it is entirely false that
any conversation of the nature mentioned took place
between us, declared by him in his depositions.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir,<lb/>
Your most obedient<lb/>
humble Servant.<lb/>
(Signed) W. Vredenburg.<lb/>
Consul.</p>

<note type="label">
<p>Enclosure<lb/>
with Despatch No 15.</p>

<p>Despatch from the
British Consul with
certified copy of Baxter's
Deposition.</p>

<p>No 10<lb/>
October 14th 1865.</p>
</note>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.040"/>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>Having returned from Mossamedes where I 
<unclear/> the United States Citizen Edward Baxter for the 
purpose of ascertaining the truth of a statement made by 
him of a shipment of slaves having been effected on the 
Bay of Mossamedes. I have to inform you that the 
Governor of that district, co-operating with me, entered 
into a minute inquiry in presence of several persons and 
of Edward Baxter himself without sharing any 
efforts that might tend to the discovery of the truth.</p>

<p>From the results of these investigation which 
are now submitted to the Hon Council of Government 
to become <sic>evidident</sic> that the statement is a false one.</p>

<p>Said Edward Baxter whereby contradicts 
his statements in various instances and proves from his 
own evidence the falsity of several points set forth in
his statement. The fact that becomes evident is 
<catchwords>that</catchwords>

<fw type="address">United States Commercial Agent.<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.041"/>

that whether from not agreeing with the Captain
of the Barque "Governor Carver" or because he may 
have been punished for his misconduct and deserted 
the vessel, remaining some days in the neighborhood 
of the town, eating and sleeping in different houses, 
whose owners he afterwards pointed out as being 
in conspiracy with the Captain of the vessel at the 
time of shipping the slaves and to whom he had 
said that it was easier to cut his throat, than to
return on board the ship he had deserted, for the 
reason that he was on very bad terms with the Captain,
and it was only after the vessel had sailed that he 
went to the town where he slept one night.</p>

<p>Whether in revenge to the Captain or from 
any other bad feeling, the said Edward Baxter 
has made a fake statement involving not only 
the authorities, but also several individuals some of 
which have been detained and are now awaiting 
<catchwords>their</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.042"/>

their trial, that has to be instituted for having 
been pointed out by him as having assisted the 
Captain in shipping the slaves as he had 
related.</p>

<p>God preserve you!</p>

<p>Sloop Infante D. João, at anchor in the
Port of Loanda 30th October 1865.</p>

<p>(Signed) Joaquim Viagas de O.<lb/>
Commander</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.043"/>

<p>Translation</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>The Council of Government acting as Governor 
General of this Province has much pleasure in informing
you, that from the inquiries instituted at Mossamedes 
by the Governor of that district, it has been most 
authentically proved that the accusation of the 
seaman Edward Baxter of the American Barque 
"Governor Carver" alluded to in your despatch of 
the 10th October, is a false one.</p>

<p>The accusation is of the gravest 
character, affirming that a shipment of slaves 
had been effected close to that town. Said 
seaman is therefore a prisoner, according to 
our criminal code of laws and will consequently 
be tried and punished for which purpose he 
is already in Jail.</p>

<p><catchwords>The</catchwords>

<fw type="address">To The<lb/>
Commercial Agent of the United States<lb/>
of America.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.044"/>

The Council of Government has to thank you 
for your services in producing said seaman, thus 
facilitating the discovery of the truth, alike important 
to the Portuguese Nation and the United States of 
America; But you will yet render greater 
service, if you should arrange in such a way 
as to cause said Barque to come to this Port, at 
an early date, by addressing, through the Governor 
of that place, an order to all American Whalers 
calling there, in order that notice may be 
conveyed to her, so as to identify the seaman</p>

<p>God preserve you!</p>

<p>Palace of the Government, at Loanda. Novr 1st 1865.</p>

<p>(Signed) Luis José Mendes Affonso<lb/>
President of Council of Government.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.045"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency.<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda Nov 5 1865.</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your despatch
of yesterday's date, wherein I am informed that 
the depositions of the American Seaman, Edward Baxter,
taken at Mossamedes, proved by authenticated evidence that 
the accusation made by him against the people of that place 
and the character of the American Barque "Governor 
Carver" was false;</p>

<p>Reserving my comments on this subject, for a 
subsequent opportunity. I have only to remind Your 
Excellency, that I claim the right, to respectfully 
request of you, the kindness to furnish me at your 
earliest convenience with copies of all the depositions 
<catchwords>taken</catchwords>

<fw type="address">His Excellency<lb/>
The President of the<lb/>
Conselho de Governo.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.046"/>

taken at Mossamedes by the Authorities of that place, 
that I may be enabled not only to express to you my views
on this subject, but also to possess myself with information 
that I may represent, clearly the case to my Government.</p>

<p>Your Excellency will have the goodness 
to understand that this Agency does not approve of the 
manner in which Edward Baxter has slandered 
the honor of Portugal on Portuguese Territory, but it 
reserves for itself the right, to thoroughly investigate the 
case, on the part of the United States Government, in 
which light I have the honor to request the depositions 
herein named.</p>

<p>I have the honor<lb/>
To be,<lb/>
Your most Obedt Servant<lb/>
(Signed) Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.047"/>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt 
of your despatch of the 3d inst, in which you request 
copies of the depositions taken at Mossamedes, relative 
to the supposed shipment of slaves in the proximity 
of that town, as stated in this city by the seaman 
Edward Baxter, a naturalized American.</p>

<p>In answer I have to inform 
you that those deeds are four in number and very 
voluminous. That at the time you asked for them
the originals had already been sent to the respective
Judge, for him, within 8 days, to pronounce verdict 
upon the charge brought against that seaman for 
false statement. This has now been done and 
intimated to the culprit in accordance with the 
Commercial Treaty between the United States of 
America and Portugal. That in the mean time 
<catchwords>said</catchwords>

<fw type="address">United States Commercial Agent.<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.048"/>

said seaman has withdrawn his former statements, as
false, and in public audience, as is shown from
the enclosed deposition, which I have the honor 
to hand you.</p>

<p>I believe this document will dispense 
with those requested in your said despatch, which
clearly proves the falsity of the accusation. This is 
more than proved by his spontaneous and voluntary 
confession.</p>

<p>Nevertheless if you still consider them 
indispensable, they will be sent to you, as soon 
as copies can be taken by the Court.</p>

<p>God preserve you!</p>

<p>Palace of the Government at Loanda<lb/>
November 9th 1865</p>

<p>(Signed) Luis José Mendes Affonso<lb/>
President of the Council of Government</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.049"/>

<p>Translation</p>

<p>Certified Copy</p>

<p>Feliciano Gonçales de Espirito Santo <unclear>Cinsha</unclear> clerk to
the judge of the Criminal Court in this district &amp;c.
I certify being the clerk in court during the proceedings 
in investigating the truth of an accusation made by 
the American Seaman Edward Baxter before the 
judicial authorities of this place, of a shipment of 
slaves in the Bay of Mossamedes, in which record 
of page 45, an inquiry is seen as follows. Terms 
of Inquiry. In the year of our Lord 1865, on the 
4th day of November, in the City of Loanda and 
in the Criminal Court of the district, present Dr. 
Carlos Pacheco de Bettencourt, Judge of the
Criminal Court with exercise in both sections 
of this tribunal together with me Feliciano Gonçales 
de Espirito <unclear>Cinsha</unclear> his clerk, and the Prisoner 
Edward Baxter for the purpose of being re-examined.
This was performed in the following manner.
<catchwords>In</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.050"/>

In the presence of the witnesses Luis Pedro Ferreira
and José Antonio de Santos, Public Officers of 
the Court who gave oath before the Judge to 
verify the <gap/>, in writing the questions and 
answers are through the interpreter Francisco 
da Silva Marquis <unclear>Porto</unclear>, a Merchant of this place 
whose oath was taken by the Judge to faithfully 
translate and transmit to the prisoner, the questions 
made by the Judge and to me the answers given by 
him, which he promised to fulfill. Thus  
through the said interpreter, the Judge inquired 
of the prisoner, his name, place of birth, age, 
name of father, condition in life, profession,
last situation, if he had ever before been in 
prison, and if he enjoys the liberty of his occupation;
to which, he replied that his name 
was Edward Baxter, Native of Liverpool, age 
25 years, a son of John and Mary Baxter, 
<catchwords>married,</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.051"/>

married, a seaman, and that he enjoys the 
liberty of his profession, that his last residence 
was at Mossamedes from where he came to this
city, having remained there only a short time, and
that he had never been in prison before. Being
further questioned by the judge as to his nationality 
he answered that he was an American Citizen, 
having been naturalized as such about nine years 
ago; He, the said prisoner then addressing the 
interpreter said that the accusation made by him 
both to the American and British Consuls and 
to the Government of this Province, of a shipment 
of slaves made in the Bay of Mossamedes on board 
the American Barque "Governor Carver" was 
false and that he declared it to be such to the 
Judge; whereupon being asked by the Judge 
for what purpose he had made such a statement. 
He replied, that having deserted the said Barque, 
<catchwords>and</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.052"/>

and fearing future punishment, he had invented 
that means, not only to avoid it but also in the 
hopes of obtaining a passage gratis to England 
and it was with those deeds that, on his arrival 
here, he applied to his Consul Mr Silva.</p>

<p>All the above statements having to be 
made known, the Judge caused this record to 
be drawn out and after being read and explained
to the prisoner, by the interpreter was signed by 
both, together with the witnesses and myself, the 
clerk signing for the prisoner, he not knowing how 
to read or write. and I, Feliciano Gonçales de 
Espirito Santo <unclear>Cinsha</unclear>, Bettencourt, Francisco 
da Silva Marquis <unclear>Porto</unclear>, Luis Pedro Ferreira,
José Antonio de Santos.</p> 

<p>No more was contained in said
interrogation, of which I have caused a true 
and faithful certified copy to be taken from 
<catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.053"/>

the original documents, in my possession, which 
has been compared and signed by me and filed 
according to law. Loanda November 8th 1865. I, 
Feliciano Gonçales de Esperito Santo e Cinsha, Clerk
who have written and signed it, and confirmed 
by us, José Solomão de Lewis Perveira Batalha, 
and Feliciano Gonçales de Esperito Santo e <unclear>Cinsha</unclear></p>

<p>A true Copy</p>

<p>(Signed) Antonio de Mello Varajãs<lb/>
Government Secretary</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.054"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency.<lb/>
St Paul de Loanda Novr 20 1865.</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>I have the honor to request of you the kindness 
to deliver the enclosed letter to Captain Charles Mason 
of the American Barque "Governor Carver", when
his vessel enters your port and who, I understand, 
is cruizing off your Coast.</p>

<p>The recent unfortunate circumstance
connected with the false accusation made by Edward 
Baxter against the <unclear/> inhabitants of your 
quiet village and the reputation of Barque 
"Governor Carver", was received here with doubt by 
everyone and his subsequent confession was no
more than was generally anticipated.</p>

<p><catchwords>It</catchwords>

<fw type="address">To The<lb/>
Illustrious Senhor<lb/>
Fernando da Costa Leal<lb/>
Governor General of Mossamedes</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.055"/>

It must have been extremely unpleasant to the 
inhabitants of Mossamedes and particularly to 
yourself to have your character defamed by 
the base accusation of having the slave trade revived
at your very door more especially at a 
time when it had become a fixed fact that for
many years no instance of this nefarious nature 
has been recorded but on the contrary, your 
district has flourished by increased Commercial 
and agricultural prosperity, to the great admiration 
of all interested in the welfare of Angola.</p>

<p>I have already exchanged congratulations 
with the Honle Conselho de Governo for the 
happy termination of this disagreeable case; I 
also expressed to them my thanks for this cordial 
cooperation and promptness of action, which had 
the final results to force from Edward Baxter 
his voluntary confession; I am not unmindful
<catchwords>that</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.056"/>

that a portion of this credit belongs to you and you will 
please accept the acknowledgement of my warmest 
sentiments.</p>

<p>I have written my government a minute 
description of the whole case and I am confident they 
will appreciate the able manner in which the 
authorities of this province defended the innocence of 
the American Barque "Governor Carver".</p>

<p>I have the Honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your most obedt Servant.<lb/>
(Sg) Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent</p>

</div1>


<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.057"/>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/> 
St Paul de Loanda Novr 20th 1865.</p>

<p>Sir;</p>

<p>On the 24th of September, Edward Baxter, styling 
himself an American Seaman, presented himself to this 
Commercial Agency for protection, and on oath, before 
witnesses, declared that, he ran away from your vessel 
at Little Fish Bay, for the reason that you had 
shipped, at that place, a cargo of slaves. </p>

<p>This report, very naturally created 
much excitement and anxiety with the Local Portuguese 
Authorities and myself, who proceeded, at once to investigate 
the truth. Baxter was examined by the 
Authorities of this place and by the British Consul 
also, and at my request was sent to Little Fish Bay 
on board of the Portuguese Corvette "Infante D. João,"
<catchwords>which</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Captain Charles Mason<lb/>
of the<lb/>
American Barque "Governor Carver" </fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.058"/>

which vessel left here October 12th and returned on the 
30th of the same month, on which day, I received a 
communication from the Commander, informing me 
that Baxter failed to prove, on the alleged <unclear/>, the 
accusation he had made against your vessel and the 
inhabitants of that industrious village. Baxter was 
then, by order of the Portuguese Government, imprisoned.
A few days after he was brought before the Judicial 
Tribunal of this City and indicted with the charge
of having made false accusation and ordered, again, 
to prison, to await his trial. Baxter, before the
court, became alarmed and to a Portuguese gentleman 
he confessed that everything he had said was false 
and a pure invention of his own. He was brought 
again before the Judge and made a formal confession, 
of which I have the honor to enclose a copy. Baxter 
is still in Prison, waiting his trial. The acting 
Governor General told me, a few days ago, that 
<catchwords>the</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0069.059"/>

the penalty of his crime, by the criminal laws of 
Portugal was very light and that he would only be 
reprimanded and set at Liberty. As soon as 
this takes place, I shall order Baxter back to 
Prison and there confine him four months, on the 
charge of having deserted your vessel and I hope, 
in the meantime, you will come to Loanda to 
claim him. Your presence here will also do 
much good. I have been requested by the Governor 
General of this Province to invite you to 
visit this Port.</p>

<p>I have the honor<lb/>
To be<lb/>
Your most obedt Servt.<lb/>
(Sg) Augustus Archer Silva<lb/>
Commercial Agent.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
