<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, T. Thomas Fortune, "Will the Afro-American Return to Africa?" (1892)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0001</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Will the Afro-American Return to Africa?</title>
<author n="Fortune, T. Thomas">T. Thomas Fortune</author>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
<date when="1892-04">April 1892</date>
<biblScope unit="page">387-391</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Clay, Henry, 1777-1852</term>
<term>Holman, William Steele, 1822-1897</term>
<term>Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865</term>
<term>Napoléon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821</term>
<term>Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Alps</term>
<term>Chicago (Il.)</term>
<term>Europe</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-02-22" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p387" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0001.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Will the Afro-American Return to Africa?</p>

<p>By T. Thomas Fortune.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>There are some questions absurd to ask and ridiculous to
answer; but as most questions propounded are of this kind,
sensible men treat them with generous toleration, upon the
theory that error cannot long prosper if reason will take the
trouble to combat it. People of superficial intelligence would
have no occupation if they could not ask questions, which busy
and thoughtful people must answer, or witness the triumph of
error and humbug and the multitude's worship of them.</p>

<p>Will the Afro-American return to Africa? This question has
been asked regularly for more than half a century by people of
one sort and another; but, since the war of the rebellion, in the
thoughts of some people, especially those engaged in foreign
mission work, it has been stereotyped, like the "Jobject!" of
Congressman William Steele Holman, for emergent use.</p>

<p>The story is told of three London tailors, who once got off in
a corner by themselves and solemnly resolved that they were the
people of Great Britain. It was a glorious moment in their lives.
That action, silly from every view point, made them famous; and
most that we do is an appeal to posterity. Since they lived,
resolved and died (even tailors die!), a great many people have
laughed at their silliness, but imitated their example.</p>

<p>A handful of people, who imagine that they control the matter
entirely, insist that the Afro-American must, will, shall return to
Africa. They will not listen to any argument. They will not
be moved by any appeal to reason, to facts as stubborn as fate, to
barriers as insurmountable as the Alps over which Napoleon
climbed into the camp of the astonished Austrians. What is the
use, these good people contend, of reaching a decision, if you are
not going to die by it? Even so must have reasoned the three
tailors of Tooley Street. If the Afro-American was not such a
stubborn creature, entirely devoted to worship of the flesh-pots
of the United States, bent upon questioning the disposition to
be made of him by philanthropists and other kindly disposed
people, he would act upon the decision that he must go and
begin the pilgrimage immediately, regardless of his best interests.
The people who insist that we shall go back to Africa are really
good people. They mean well, most intermeddlers do, but they
are both imprudent and impudent. They have never been to
Africa; they do not know anything about the country or its
people. They look at the situation from one point of view, and
we look at it from another. They will not understand that




<pb xml:id="p388" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0001.002.jpg"/>



dreams are dreams, and that facts are facts. They would not be
philanthropists if they did. As they spend most of their time
thinking for others, often at a comfortable salary, they will not
understand why others should bother to think for themselves.
And in all sorts of quarters just now, the greatest surprise is
manifested because the Afro-American is demonstrating that he
has any mind whatever and can use it for thinking purposes. It
nearly takes their breath (and occupation, too) away.</p>

<p>Ever since the American Colonization Society was organized,
more than a half century ago, for the purpose of accommodating
those Afro-Americans who wanted to return to Africa, the question
of Afro-American colonization has occupied more or less of
the public attention. It was a dream of Henry Clay, who was
opposed to slavery, and of Abraham Lincoln, who did not believe
that the Afro-American could live here as a freeman, that colonization 
would solve the problem. Perhaps it would have done so,
if the Afro-American, before and since the war, had not set his
face against it, as the devil is said to set his against holy water.
He would not have it; he will not have it; and all the philanthropists 
and other good people who want to have it, having
decided that he must have it, are simply horrified, cast down, at
their wits' end, because of it They have spent millions of money
and years of honest toil, in attempting to put their decision into
something they could "point to with pride," and of which they
could exultantly exclaim, "I told you so!" but Liberia is all that
they have brought forth. I do not wish to be understood as in
any way underrating Liberia as a government There is not
enough of it, perhaps. I simply emphasize the fact here, that if
the dreams of those who are responsible for its existence had
been such as they anticipated and predicted, the country would
to-day contain a million or more Afro-Americans, instead of the
handful that it does contain. Instead of being an infant in population, 
it would be a giant. The Afro-American has simply
refused to go to Liberia as a race; and when he has gone as an
individual, he has, in many instances, returned by the next
steamer, as my good friend Bishop Turner is said to have done,
although he has been anxious for twenty years for an opportunity
to die there.</p>

<p>The Afro-American has reasoned, that if fifteen millions of
Europeans have, since 1820, deemed it wise and advantageous to
come to the United States, it would be wise and advantageous
for him to remain here. What was good enough for the oppressed 
and starving peasants of Europe and the peons of China,
was good enough for him, despite the arguments of those who had
decided, that he must go. This is one view of the matter, and,
perhaps, an important one, to a thorough understanding of the
colonization failure. Men do not usually run away from opportunities 
which the rest of mankind are rushing forward to enjoy.
The Afro-American is just like other people in this respect. Is
he unlike other people in any respect?</p>




<pb xml:id="p389" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0001.003.jpg"/>



<p>Now, what are some of the reasons why Afro-Americans have
refused to go to Africa in the past, and have no intention of going
in the future? Affecting to believe that there are no reasons
against going, the philanthropists and other good people who
insist that we must go, will hardly be able to contain themselves
when they discover that they have been slumbering in the day-
light.</p>

<p>(1) Afro-Americans are not Africans. The slave trade
between the United States and Africa ceased in 1808. Since that
time a few stragglers have come here, but, in the main, the accessions 
have been too inconsiderable to enter into the calculation
at all. In consequence of this, Afro-Americans know, practically,
nothing about Africa, and take only a sentimental interest in it
and its people. They have forgotten the language of the country
and abandoned the religion of its people. They have thrown off
all heathenish practices.</p>

<p>(2) Africa is a country without an organized government, an
accepted religion, and a uniform language. In a different article
from this, I have said that habitat, language and religion prescribe
a man's nationality and fix his citizenship. If Africa had a regular
government, a great many of us might seek its protection.
Civilized men don't abandon organized government for chaos.
The population of Africa is supposed to be 100,000,000; the in-
habitants speak as many languages as there are tribes. Now, if
every one of the 8,000,000 Afro-Americans should go to Africa,
would they swallow up the 100,000,000 natives, or would they
be swallowed up? Jonah could not swallow the whale, and,
therefore, the whale swallowed Jonah.</p>

<p>(3) What assurance have Afro-Americans that they would not
starve to death in a country without organized industries, or be
slaughtered by hostile natives, or die from the ravages of climatic
diseases? Some who have spied out the land relate that each
one of these hoodoos has a tooth as sharp as a serpent's, and
about as deadly. People go to a new country to better their
condition; not to starve or be slaughtered by accommodating
natives or an inhospitable climate. Many of these disadvantages
will be overcome in time; but they will be overcome by
Europeans, with home governments and fabulous wealth behind them.
European rule in Africa is no more advantageous than the rule
of descendants of Europeans in the United States; and wherever
the European goes in Africa, he subjects or exterminates the
natives. In the organized European governments in Africa, they
are barred out.</p>

<p>(4) Afro-Americans feel that the United States is their country,
and that they have as much right to enjoy its advantages as have
others of their fellow-citizens. They have labored to build up
its grandeur; they have fought and died to defend its honor and
to perpetuate its integrity; they own a vast volume of real and
personal wealth here, which they have acquired by infinite industry




<pb xml:id="p390" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0001.004.jpg"/>



and economy; they have a heritage in the government
and in the soil, consecrated by the bones of their dead, which
have no price and can be purchased with no money; and they
find that, in the condition of freedom, their position is growing
better and more secure every year, due, mainly, to the development 
of a more self-reliant and self-supporting manhood and
womanhood. While the surplus population of all the civilized
governments are given a cordial and pressing invitation to come
here and enjoy the wealth of our soil and the liberality of our
institutions, Afro-Americans cannot understand why they should
have a cordial and pressing invitation given to them to betake
themselves out of the country. Instead of accepting the invitation 
as a compliment, they regard it as an insult. If they do not
always proclaim it from the housetops, it is because they consider
silence to be the most sarcastic form of contempt. That they
should be asked, seriously, to leave a country they had enriched
with their toil and defended with their lives, and that grave Senators 
in the Congress should propose that public money should
be placed at their disposal to expedite their self-expatriation,
seems to them insult so glaring as to relieve them of the necessity
of organized protest. Such baseness carries upon its face a
sufficient condemnation and rebuke. It is like asking a coequal
heir to abandon his portion of the estate, in order that there may
be absolute harmony in the division of the benefaction.</p>

<p>I think these reasons are sufficient to show why Afro-Americans 
do not, should not, and will not return to Africa.</p>

<p>The sentiment that the Afro-American should return to Africa
is by no means general. Far from it. The great mass of our
fellow-citizens would oppose any proposition intended to coerce
us into leaving the country, if any such was contemplated or
proposed. They rightly believe we are old enough to decide the
question of residence for ourselves; but a few people, bent upon
doing the same thing, can make a great noise. A small spark,
dropped in a cow-shed, started a fire that destroyed the greater
part of Chicago. And as the three tailors of Tooley Street were
convinced that they were the people of England, so a few people
in the United States have always presumed to speak for all the
people upon questions affecting Afro-Americans. So persistent
and ululative have they been that many have accepted the false
prophets to be the Simon-pure articles; but the whole race-
question in the United States has reached a stage where the
Afro-American resents the assumption that he has no tongue, no
voice, and no brains in his head. The good people who persist,
annually, in getting off in a corner by themselves and resolving
for Afro-Americans may delude and impose upon themselves,
but the rest of mankind laugh at them.</p>

<p>Over and above the reasons already given to show that Afro-
Americans will not return to Africa, as a whole, stands the further
reason that it would be a physical impossibility to do anything



<pb xml:id="p391" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0001.005.jpg"/>


of the sort. Enough ships could not be put into commission,
without demoralizing the commerce of the world, to transport,
annually, the natural increase of the Afro-American population.
A statistician has been at the pains of demonstrating this fact.</p>

<p>When the question of expatriating Afro-Americans was being
discussed in the Congress, a remarkable feature was made prominent. 
Most of the leading newspapers in the Southern States
opposed the proposition and characterized it as being unwise, the
consummation of which would disorganize and demoralize the
entire industrial system of the South. A great many people, who
cannot sleep because of the presence of the Afro-American
among them, will not take the trouble to ascertain that the Afro-
American is the backbone of the labor force of the South, and
that if he should fold his hands and sit down for a week the
wheels of Southern industry would cease to turn for that length
of time, and that millions of wealth would, in consequence, stand
idle throughout the Republic. But what do such people care
about facts? Humbug is their stock-in-trade.</p>

<p>Will the Afro-American return to Africa?</p>

<p>He will not.</p>

<p>I will not here enter into a discussion of the missionary
question. In the years to come, when we shall not need every
decent missionary that we manufacture for home consumption,
we will contribute our proper share of noble men and noble
women, and of our abundance, to the evangelization of Africa.</p>

<p>New York.</p>

</div2>


</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
