<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0767">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from George Strickland to James D. Porter, November 11, 1887</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0767</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from George Strickland to James D. Porter, November 11, 1887</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Gorée-Dakar, 1883-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Service General Services Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T573, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1887-11-11">November 11, 1887</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Cleret</term>
<term>Geoffrey</term>
<term>Kent</term>
<term>Ramadi</term>
<term>Restoul</term>
<term>Taylor, Charles H. J.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places"> 
<term>Dakar (Senegal)</term>
<term>Gorée (Senegal)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Strickland, George</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Vice-Consul</roleName>
<placeName>Gorée-Dakar (Senegal)</placeName>
<date when="1887-11-11"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36031491">Porter, James D. (James Davis), 1828-1912</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1887-12-20"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-06" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="20170619_142512"/>

<note>Department of State Received Dec 20 1887</note>

<note>No. 73.</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Goree-Dakar, November 11, 1887.</p>

<p>Mr George Strickland<lb/>
To the Department of State</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Enclosing the Testimony given by
Mr. Strickland to the Examining Magistrate
in the Inquest held on what is known as
the "Fez Affair", with remarks.</p>

<p>See No. 70 of October 9, &amp; No. 71 of October 14.</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents:</p>

<p>Reproach addressed to Mr. Strickland
by Delegate of Interior Department
of the Colonial Government for not covering
with an envelope a letter from Captain
Kent to the "Governor of Dakar" should
have been made to the British Vice-Consul
whom alone it concerned.</p>

<p>Agent of the Messageries Maritimes
S.S. Company guilty of discrimination
in refusing passage to a U.S. Minister.</p>

<pb n="20170619_142823"/>

<note>No. 73.</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
Goree-Dakar, November 11, 1887.</p>

<p>Honorable James D. Porter,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor to enclose the testimony
which I have this day given to the
examining magistrate in the inquest which
is being held following orders from Paris
on the now somewhat famous "Fez affair".</p>

<p>With reference to the last paragraph
of my deposition I would remark
that Mr. Cleret, the Delegate of the Interior
Department of the Colonial Government
to the second arrondissement, has but recently
arrived, which perhaps explains his confounding
in his letter "The United States
Consul on board the 'Fez' off Dakar" as he
wrote on the envelope, the English Vice-Consul
who was actually concerned in
Captain Kent's letter, and myself who had 
simply handed it to Mr. Restoul.</p>

<p>I bet to add that it seems to me
that the refusal to receive Mr Taylor on
<catchwords>board</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142835"/>

board the mail-steamer is a clear case of
discrimination on the part of Mr. Restoul,
the agent of the Messageries Maritimes line
of steamships, (also a new-comer) because 
those steamers come from Brazil where
yellow fever and cholera are endemic,
whereas the "Fez" was put in quarantine
simply because it is customary here
at this season to inflict five days on
all arrivals from the south. It follows
that the passengers already on board
the mail were more likely to be 
contaminated than the gentleman who was
refused. Two days had already elapsed,
and supposing Mr. Taylor to have finished
the five days on shore he could
not have been refused, which is absurd
when it is remembered that the voyage
to Europe is considerably longer. The fact
is that it is a procedure quite regular to
thus transfer passengers from the south, and
one often effected in the case of those arriving
by the "British &amp; African" boats. Whether Mr.
Restoul enjoys such limitless discretionary
powers, I do not know.</p>

<p>I am, Sir, your obedient servant,<lb/>
George Strickland,<lb/>
Vice-Consul</p>

<p>1 Enclosure. Testimony of
Vice-Consul Strickland 
in the "Fez affair"</p>

<pb n="20170619_142845"/>

<p>Consulate of the United States<lb/>
at Goree-Dakar, Senegal<lb/>
November 11, 1887.</p>

<p>George Strickland,<lb/>
Vice-Consul.</p>

<p>Testimony given by Mr. Strickland
to the Examining Magistrate in the Inquest
held at Goree following orders from Paris on
what is known as the "Fez affair", before
treated of in Despatches No. 70 of October 9, and
71 of October 14, 1887 from this Consulate to the
Department of State.</p>

<p>Enclosure No. 1, in
Despatch No. 73.</p>

<pb n="20170619_142855"/>

<p>Testimony given by Vice-Consul
George Strickland to the Examining Magistrate
in the Inquest held following orders from
Paris on what is known as the "Fez Affair"
on November 11, 1887 at Gorée, Senegal.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="fr">

<p>Je, George Strickland, agé de 23 ans 1/2, 
Vice-Consul des Etats-Unis d'Amerique au Sénégal,
y demeurant, in parent, ni allié, ni au
service des inculpés, dépose,</p>

<p>Le 8 Octobre vers 8 heures 1/2 le matin,
je reçus de Monsieur Charles H. J. Taylor,
Ministre Resident et Consul-General des Etatis-Unis
á Liberia, une lettre datée de la veille, dans
laquelle il me faisait savoir que passager àbord
du "Fez" et pressé d'arriver en Amerique, il
désirait, on prendre le premier paquebot allant
au nord, ou que le Fez pût continuer de suite
sa route: il ajoutait que le capitaine de ci
vapeur ayant des difficultés avec les autorités
de Dakar ne pouvait reprendre la mer
et était en quarantaine. Il me priait de
lui procurer l'autorisation de descendre à
terre a fin de profiter de la première occasion.
Dans ce but j'allais faire visite à
Monsieur Geoffroy, medecin principal de la
marine, qui me dit que Monsieur Taylor,
<catchwords>s'il</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142902"/>

s'il était en quarantaine à Dakar ne
pouvait descendre à terre, sans aller d'abord
au lazaret, mais qu'il pouvait être transbordé
sur un paquebot si le capitaine
du paquebot y consentait.</p>

<p>Je m'embarquai ensuite pour me
rendre le long du "Fez", mais à peine avais-je
quitté le warf, que je rencontrai le canot
de ce navire, et l'officier qui le montait me
donna trois lettres en me disant que l'une
était pour moi et les deux autres pour le
Gouverneur de Dakar et le Vice Consul d'Angleterre.
Il me demanda si les papiers
du bond se trouvaient à Gorée prétendant
que ce renseignment avait été donné par
le port de Dakar où ils avaient été vainement
reclamés; et que chaque fois que
l'embarcation s'était rendue à terre, elle
avait toujours été renvoyée. Monsieur 
Ramade le consignataire du "Fez" qui
se trouvait sur le warf, en entendant
cela, manifesta une grande surprise que
le "Fez" eut été mis en quarantaine à
Dakar alors qu'il avait été admis en
libre pratique à Gorée.</p>

<p>Je me rendis la suite le long du
bord et la Monsieur Taylor, le capitaine, 
<catchwords>Monsieur Kent</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142906"/>

Monsieur Kent, son second et plusieurs passagers
m'apprirent qu'ils étaient arrives à Gorée 
le 7 à 8 heures du matin, qu'après avoir
été admis en libre pratique, ils s'étaient 
rendus sur l'avis du consignataire au pou-ton
charbonier pour prendre 20 tonnes de
charbon et que pendant qu'ils étaient ainsi
occupés, des noirs s'étaient presentés et après
avoir demandé la patente de santé avaient
disparu en emportant cette pièce, qu'aucune
notification de la quarantaine ne
leur fut faite, et qu'ils pensaient qu'il n'y
avait pas de règlements distincts pour Dakar
et pour Goree; qu'après avoir terminé leur 
charbon, des gens du bord s'étaient rendus
à l'échelle au warf pour réclamer la patente,
et du linge laissé à terre lors d'un
précédent voyage, et qu'on les avait
chassés comme des criminels en les menaçant
même d'emprisonnement s'ils debarquaient
et que c'etait pourtant la première fois
qu'une autorité francaise leur parlait
de quarantaine; que la patente de santé
ne leur avait pas été delivrée malgré
la demande qui en avait été faite; et
qu'à raison de cette circonstance le vapeur
n'avait pu continuer sa route.
<catchwords>Je crus</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142913"/>

Je crus d'abord qu'il n'y avait qu'un mal
entendu, et je promis au capitaine et à ces
messieurs de voir le vice-consul anglais et
d'arranger l'affair.</p>

<p>Je me rendis à Dakar et en passant
à la Direction du Port, je demandai
où se trouvaient les papiers du "Fez" et il
me fut répondu qu'ils étaient encore chez
le medecin arraisonneur. Je me dirigeai
alors du coté de l’hôtel des Messageries
Maritimes où loge Monsieur Restoul, Vice-Consul
anglais qui est en même temps
agent de cette compagnie, mais avant
d'y arriver, je rencontrai un ancien
domestique que je chargeai de remettre
à Monsieur Restoul la lettre qui m'avait
été confiée le matin et de lui annoncer
ma visite. Quelques instants après ce
domestique me rejoignait, tout essoufflé,
et m'apprenait que Monsieur Restoul
aussitot après avoir pris connaissance de
sa lettre l'avait saisi au collet en le
menaçant de le faire arrêter. A cause
de cet incident, j'allais immédiatement 
chez ce monsieur, et il m'expliqua tout
d'abord qu'il avait rudoyé mon domestique,
pensant que c'etait un homme du
<catchwords>"Fez"</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142921"/>

"Fez" qui avait violé la quarantaine comme
cela s'était produit déja. Il me dit aussi que
le capitaine de ce navire, et les gens au bord 
qui étaient venus au debarcadère, avaient tenu
des propos outrageants pour les autorités françaises,
et qu'ils devaient de l'argent en ville: qu'il se
proposait d'adresser une plainte au Foreign
Office, et que le cas serait en outre soumis au
procureur de la République. Je lui réponds
que le capitaine se plaignait, au contraire,
des difficultés que lui avait suscitées l’autorité 
et que pour parvenir à une entente équitable
il voulait conférer avec lui. Il me dit qu'il
irait à bord. Je m'en allai, mais en causant
avec certaines personnes de Dakar, je
remarquai que l'on était généralement
indisposé contre le capitaine et les gens
du "Fez".</p>

<p>Vers deux heures et demie, je me
rendis le long du bord et je ne cachai pas
mon impression à Monsieur Taylor et au
capitaine, et je leur dis que l'affaire paraissait
prendre une tournure sérieuse, que
l'on parlait en ville d'un débarquement de
passagers opéré la veille, et que mon intervention
ne servirait à rien puisque le
vice-consul anglais blamait lui même leur
<catchwords>conduite</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142927"/>

conduite. Ils me répondirent qu'ils n'avaient
jamais été declarés en quarantaine, et que
seul deux français étaient descendus dans la
soirée après la ménace qui leur avait été 
faite d'etre emprisonnées en cas de debarquement.
Pen après Monsieur Restoul arriva
et il ent une discussion assez vive avec le
capitaine. Celui-ci lui demanda meme
s'il pouvait dire en sa présence qu'il ne
le protegerait pas. Pendant tout le colloque,
Monsieur Restoul s'obstinait a réclamer
600 francs pour des avaries faites parait
il, par le "Fez" lors de son dernier passage
à Dakar a des chalands de la compagnie
des Messageries Maritimes. Le capitame
répliqua qu'il ne paierait jamais
cette somme parce qu'il n'avait commis
aucune faute, et qu'il n'était pas responsable
di cet accident: qu'au contraire, s'il
avait souffert des avaries, il aurait poursuivi
la compagnie qui ne peut obstruer
une rade avec les chaines d'amarrage de
ses chalands: qu'en tout cas, ou ne pouvait
le retenir a Dakar pour cette raison,
et qu'étant chargé d'un courrier postal
belge, il ferait payer chaque heure de
retard, et poursuivrait l'affaire en haut
<catchwords>lieu</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142934"/>

lieu pour avoir justice. De mon côté, croyant
que le "Fez" serait encore sur rade au moment
du passage du paquebot des Messageries (ce
qui eut lieu du reste) je demandai à Monsieur
Restoul si Monsieur Taylor pouvait
prendre passage à bord. Il refusa d'une
façon categorique en disant que le Ministre
venait d'un pays contaminé et ne pouvait
s'embarquer sur un des paquebots de la
compagnie. A la fin Monsieur Rostoul invita
le capitaine à écrire qu'il refusait
de payer la somme qui lui était reclamée
et lui promit à cette condition ses papiers.
Le capitaine se retira un instant dans sa
chambre et revint avec un papier qu'il
remit à Monsieur Restoul et que celui-ci lui
retourna pour être signé. En partant Mr.
Restoul exigea que le canot au bord le suivit
à terre pour rapporter la patente. Le
capitaine fil armer son embarcation en remarquant
que c'était la quatrième fois
qu'il l'envoyait à terre.</p>

<p>Je retournai ensuite à Dakar pour
des affaires personelles, et lorsque je m'embarquai 
pour Goree, je vis le canot du "Fez"
qui attendait prés de l'eschelle. Les marins
me dirent qu'ils avaient les papiers et me
<catchwords>prièrent</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142940"/>

prièrent de demander au Port si l'on accepterait
des livres Sterling pour payer la blanchisseuse
de leur linge. Je fis la commission 
au fils du lieutenant du port qui me
répondit qu'il n'y aurait aucune difficulté.
Il m'appris au meme temps que son père
avait été insulte la veille par les gens du bord.
Je m'embarquai ensuite et je m'arretai en
route pour prevenir ces Messieurs que les papiers 
avaient été remis et qu'ils pouvaient
appareiller. Arrivé à Gorée, ou me demanda
si j'étais monté à bord du "Fez" et sur mon affirmation
ou me laissa debarquer. Le surlendemain 
j'ecrivis à Monsieur Restoul pour <unclear>lieu</unclear>
demander les raisons pour les quelles il avait refusé
au Ministre des Etats-Unis à Liberia
de prendre passage sur le paquebot des Messageries
pour le cas écheant fournir des explications
à mon gouvernment sachant du
reste qu'il y avait des précédents et que
Monsieur Taylor en parlerait; mais ma lettre
est restée sans réponse.</p>

<p>Je termine ma déposition en protestant 
respectueusement contre la leçon de politesse
que Monsieur le Délégué de l'Intérieur
a voulu me donner: Il me reproche de
n'avoir pas mis sous envelope une lettre
<catchwords>du capitaine</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142948"/>

capitaine Kent, que j ai bien voulu lui faire
parvenir par l'intermédiaire de Monsieur
le Vice-Consul d'Angleterre. Il aurait dû
écrire à celui-ci qui seul avait à se charger
des affaires du capitaine du "Fez", sujet anglais.
J'affirm enfin que le billet lorsque il a
eté remis à Monsieur Restoul n'était pas
"un chiffon de papier, froissé et malpropre"</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<p>The foregoing might be briefly 
translated thus:</p>

<p>I, George Strickland, aged 23 1/2
years, Vice-Consul of the United States of America
for Senegal, there residing, and being 
in no way connected with the persons herein
involved depose,</p>

<p>On the morning of October 8, 1887, at 
about 8 1/2 o'clock, I received from Mr. Taylor,
Minister Resident and Consul-General of the
United States to Liberia, a letter bearing date
of preceding day in which he informed me
that he was a passenger on board the English
steamer "Fez" and anxious to arrive in
America but on account of difficulties which
<catchwords>the ship</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_142953"/>

the ship had with the authorities at Dakar,
she could not continue her voyage and was
in quarantine. He desired that she might
be allowed to proceed immediately or that
he might land in order to wait the first
northern bound mail, and engaged me
to procure for him such authorization. I
therefore sought an interview with the principal 
medical authority, Doctor Geoffrey,
who said that if Mr. Taylor was in quarantine
at Dakar, he could not land without
going to the lazaret, but that he could
be transferred directly to another ship with
the consent of the captain.</p>

<p>I thereupon embarked to go to the
steamer but had hardly left the wharf
when I met a boat from the "Fez". The
officer in her gave me three letters, one for
me from Mr. Taylor, and the other two
for the "Governor of Dakar" and the British
Vice-Consul. He asked me to find out
if the papers of the "Fez" were in Goree
saying that such information had been given
them by the Port at Dakar where they had
asked for them in vain; their boat having 
been ordered away each time that it went
to the mole. Mr. Ramade, the consignee
<catchwords>of the</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143000"/>

of the steamer at Goree who was on the wharf,
manifested surprise and made the remark that
it was curious for the "Fez" to be quarantined
at Dakar when she had had free pratique at
Goree.</p>

<p>I then went alongside the English Steamer
and there I saw Mr. Taylor, Captain Kent,
his officers, and several passengers, who told me
that they had arrived at Goree the 7 at 8 AM
where they were admitted without quarantine,
and after having conferred with their consignee,
they had steamed over to the coal-hulk to take
twenty tons. While they were thus occupied some 
negroes arrived alongside and asked for the bill
of health which was given up to them, and they
disappeared with it on shore. No notification
of quarantine was given them, and they thought
that there could not be a distinct regulation 
for Goree and for Dakar. After having finished
coaling, they went to the landing to get
their papers and to find some washing which
they had left on a previous voyage, but they 
were received like criminals and were threatened
with imprisonment if they should land,
notwithstanding that it was the first time
that an authority had mentioned quarantine.
Although they asked for their bill of health,
<catchwords>it was</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143007"/>

it was withheld, and for that reason the steamer
could not go to sea. I thought that it was
probably a misunderstanding and promised them
that I would see the English Vice-Consul and
arrange the matter</p>

<p>When I reached Dakar, I inquired at the
"Direction of the Port" in passing where the papers
of the "Fez" were to be found and was answered 
that they were still with the visiting doctor.
I then directed my steps towards the house
where lives Mr. Restoul, General-Agent of the
Messageries Maritimes line of Mail Steamers at
Dakar, and also British Vice-Consul, but before
I had reached there, I met a former servant
to whom I gave the letter entrusted to me for 
the English consul and charged him to deliver
it and at the same time to announce
my visit. I had gone but a little way when
my man came running after me, panting
and excited, and said that Mr. Restoul had
seized him by the collar, handled him roughly
and had threatened to have him arrested. I
went immediately to see what was the matter,
and the gentleman explained that he had 
taken my servant for some one from the "Fez"
who was violating the quarantine, as some 
of them had already done. He further said
<catchwords>that the</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143014"/>

that the captain and others from the steamer had
been outrageously disrespectful to French authorities
and that they owed money in Dakar. He
intended to complain to the Foreign Office and said
that the case would be submitted to the State 
Prosecutor here. I replied that I came from the
steamer and the captain and gentleman on board
complained on the contrary of the difficulties
which the authorities themselves had raised and
in order to have an equitable hearing they
wished to confer with him. After he had promised
to go off in the afternoon, I left him 
but in talking with other persons of note,
I observed that the people of Dakar were
generally against the "Fez".</p>

<p>At about half past two, I went again
alongside and told them that the trouble
was more serious than I had supposed, that
I was told that some of them had been on
shore the previous night and that people
were generally stirred up. I added that
I could do no more because their own consul
was mal-disposed towards them. They
acknowledged that two passengers had been
on shore but they were themselves Frenchmen
and they declared that they had not been
formally advised of quarantine and the
<catchwords>threat</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143022"/>

threat of imprisonment before spoken of was
the only intimation. Here Mr. Restoul arrived,
and a lively discussion took place between
him and the captain in which the
latter asked the former if he meant to tell
him to his face that he would not protect
him. During the colloquy their Vice-Consul
persisted in demanding the sum of 600 francs
for damage done to a coal-lighter of his
company by the "Fez" on her former voyage.
The captain replied that he would never 
pay it because the fault was not his and
he was not responsible for the accident; that
on the contrary, had his steamer suffered injuries,
he should have claimed damages from
the company which has no right to obstruct
the harbor with the hidden chains
of its lighters; and that in any case, he could
not be stopped on his voyage for such a 
reason, and as he carried the Belgian mail,
he should make it his business to push the
matter the fartherest possible and make somebody
pay every hour of his delay. For
my part, thinking that from the look of 
things the "Fez" would be still in the harbor
when the regular mail of the Messageries
Maritimes which was expected should
<catchwords>(and did)</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143029"/>

(and did) arrive, I asked Mr. Restoul if the
United States Minister could take passage on
board, and he refused absolutely saying that he
came from an infected country and he could
not allow him on a ship of his company. In
the end Mr. Restoul demanded that the captain
write his refusal to pay and promised
him his papers on that condition. Captain
Kent withdrew in the cabin and in a moment
reappeared with the paper which after being
read by Mr. Restoul was returned to be signed.
Upon leaving the latter required that the
captain send in his boat to bring back the
papers and the latter remarked that that
would make the fourth time that he had 
already sent it for the same purpose.</p>

<p>I then returned to Dakar on personal
business, and when I came down to the
landing to reëmbark I saw the boat of
the "Fez" and those in her told me that they
had received their papers. They desired me
to ask at the Port office if there would be any
difficulty about passing the money on Shore
to the washerwoman for whom they were
waiting, and I therefore saw the Harbor-master's
son who said that there would
be none in the least. He told me at the same
<catchwords>time</catchwords>

<pb n="20170619_143037"/>

time, that his father had been insulted the
day before by the people from on board the
"Fez". I then started for Goree and in passing
the steamer I told Mr. Taylor and 
Captain Kent that their papers were in their
boat and that they might begin to get their
anchor. Arrived at Goree, I was asked if
I had been on board the "Fez" but on my
affirmation was allowed to land.</p>

<p>On the 10th, I wrote to Mr. Restoul
asking him his reasons for having 
<del>toul</del> refused the United States Minister to
Liberia passage on his mail-steamer, in
order that I might give explanations to
my government. I was aware that there
were precedents and that Mr. Taylor
would bring up the subject upon his arrival.
I have never received a reply 
of any kind.</p>

<p>I finish my testimony by respectfully
protesting against the lesson which the Hon.
Delegate of the Interior has seen fit to give me. 
He reproaches me for not having covered with
an envelope a letter by Captain Kent of which
from complaisance I served as simple carrier to
the British Vice-Consul. It was to the latter that
he should have written for Captain Kent is a British
Subject.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
