<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.government.0009">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Treaty of Commerce between Ethiopia and the United States (1903)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.government.0009</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Treaty of Commerce between Ethiopia and the United States, December 27, 1903</title>
<title level="m">Treaties and Other International Agreements of the United States of America, 1776-1949</title>
<author>Bevans, Charles I.</author>
<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>U.S. Government Printing Office, 1971</publisher>
<date when="1903-12-27">December 27, 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">658-659</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Government Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62344773">Menelik II, Negus of Ethiopia, 1844-1913</term>
<term>Skinner, Robert P.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Addis Ababa (Ethiopia)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-01" who="kln">encoding</change>
<change when="2021-12" who="kln">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p658"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">Ethiopia</head>

<head type="sub">Commerce</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Treaty signed at Addis Ababa December 27, 1903<lb/>
Senate advice and consent to ratification March 12, 1904<lb/>
Ratified by the President of the United States March 17, 1904<lb/>
Effective from March 17, 1904<lb/>
Ratification notified to the King of Ethiopia August 2, 1904<lb/>
Proclaimed by the President of the United States September 30, 1904<lb/>
Expired March 17, 1914</p>

<p>33 Stat. 2254; Treaty Series 439</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Treaty of Commerce</head>

<p>[Translation]</p>

<p>His Majesty Menelik II, King of Kings of Ethiopia, and the United States of America, having agreed to regulate the commercial relations between the two countries and develop them, and render them more and more advantageous to the two contracting Powers:</p>

<p>His Majesty Menelik II, King of Kings of Ethiopia, in the name of the Empire, and Robert P. Skinner, in the name of the United States of America, have agreed and stipulated that which follows:</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article I</head>

<p>The citizens of the two Powers, like the citizens of other countries, shall be able freely to travel and to transact business throughout the extent of the territories of the two contracting Powers, while respecting the usages and submitting themselves to the tribunals of the countries in which they may be located.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article II</head>

<p>In order to facilitate commercial relations, the two Governments shall assure, throughout the extent of their respective territories, the security of those engaged in business therein, and of their property.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p659"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article III</head>

<p>The two contracting Governments shall reciprocally grant to all citizens of the United States of America and to the citizens of Ethiopia, all the advantages which they shall accord to other Powers in respect to customs duties, imposts and jurisdiction.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article IV</head>

<p>Throughout the extent of the Ethiopian Empire, the citizens of the United States of America shall have the use of the telegraphs, posts and all other means of transportation upon the same terms as the citizens of other Powers.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article V</head>

<p>In order to perpetuate and strengthen the friendly relations which exist between Ethiopia and the United States of America, the two Governments agree to receive reciprocally, representatives acceptable to the two Governments. These representatives shall not however, be maintained at their posts,
unless they are agreeable to the receiving Power, in such cases, they shall be replaced.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article VI</head>

<p>The duration of the present treaty shall be ten years. It is understood that at the expiration of these ten years the two Governments shall be able to modify all or any part of this treaty. The Government which shall request at that time the modification, shall make its proposal to the other Government one year before the expiration of the treaty.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Article VII</head>

<p>The present treaty shall take effect if ratified by the Government of the United States, and if this ratification shall be notified to His Majesty Menelik II, King of Kings of Ethiopia, within the period of one year.</p> 

<p>His Majesty Menelik II, King of Kings of Ethiopia, in the name of his Empire; Robert P. Skinner in virtue of his full powers, in the name of the United States of America, have signed the present treaty, written in double text, Amharic and French, and in identical terms.</p>

<p>Done at Addis-Ababa, this seventeenth day of December, one thousand eight hundred and ninety-six in the year of grace (corresponding to December twenty-seventh, 1903).</p>

<p>Robert P. Skinner<lb/>
[Seal of Menelik II]</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>