<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0247">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Joseph C. Hartzell to John Hay, October 31, 1898</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0247</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Joseph C. Hartzell to John Hay, October 31, 1898</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1898-10-31">October 31, 1898</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term> 
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bailly-Forfillere, Jorge</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/19678646">Hanotaux, Gabriel, 1853-1944</term>
<term>Pauly, Adriano</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3656148122897295200005">Roustan, Théodore 1833-1906</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/21264538">Smith, Isaac Townsend, 1813-1906</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cavalla River</term>
<term>Ivory Coast</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>San Pedro River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Kroo</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>


<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14310823">Hartzell, Joseph C. (Joseph Crane), 1842-1929</persName>
<roleName>Special Envoy to U.S. from Liberia</roleName>
<placeName>New York (New York)</placeName>
<date when="1898-10-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76456718">Hay, John, 1838-1905</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2020-02-17" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw"> encoded</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#unm"> transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170616_151019"/>

<ab type="letterhead">Joseph C. Hartzell,<lb/>
Bishop of Africa,<lb/>
Methodist Episcopal Church.<lb/>
American Address:<lb/>
150 Fifth Avenue.</ab>

<ab type="letterhead">"Princes shall come out of Egypt; Ethiopia shall soon stretch out her hands unto God." &#8212; Psalm 68.31.</ab>

<p>New York, October 31, 1898.</p>

<p>The Hon. John Hay,<lb/>
Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.,</p>

<p>My Dear Sir:-</p>

<p>I have the honor to submit to you an additional document 
to my communication delivered to you in person in your office Wednesday,
October 19, bearing upon the present condition of the Republic of 
Liberia. This document is a copy of an article that has recently 
appeared in an English paper, and presents so pertinently additional 
matter in reference to the crisis in which the Republic of Liberia 
now finds itself that I deem it important that you should have it.</p>

<p>The Hon. Isaac Townsend Smith, Consul in this City for the 
Siam Government, is called to Washington on official business, to meet 
the Minister of that country, and I take the liberty of asking him to 
hand it to you in person.</p>

<p>Mr. Smith has given large attention to the history and present 
condition of Liberia, and will also be prepared to give additional 
information if so desired.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, dear sir,<lb/>
Yours sincerely,<lb/>
JC Hartzell<lb/>
Special Envoy to U.S. from the<lb/>
Liberian Republic</p>

<pb n="20170616_151029"/>

<p>LIBERIA</p>

<p>From our Liverpool Correspondent.</p>

<p>The sad murder of two French travelers in the territories of the 
Liberian Republic has provided the French Government with a powerful and 
singularly opportune weapon in the furtherance of its policy of gradual 
encroachment upon that Negro State. The German Emperor has recently 
shown to the world to what excellent use, in the shape of territorial 
aggrandizement, the assassination of a few missionaries may be put; and 
although Messrs. Bailly-Forfillere and Pauly were not missionaries, their 
deaths may be turned to an equally good account, for, both with the 
Chinese Empire and the Republic of Liberia, the possibilities of a
successful resistance to preposterous demands for compensation are not 
perceptible.</p>

<p>I do not know whether the French Government has demanded compensation 
from the Republic. But the designs of France on Liberia have become 
so palpable during the last few years that it would be displaying 
a crass stupidity not to take very serious notice of this incident in
light of the consequences to which it may give arise.</p>

<p>As most people know, Liberia is an independent Negro Republic 
which owes its inception to the philanthropic instincts to the people of
the United States, following in the wake of our own somewhat similar 
efforts in Sierra Leone. A colony of freed American negroes was gradually 
formed at Monrovia and various other points on the Grain Coast, and 
in 1847 the colonists were endowed with the constitution of the United 
States. Ever since, the Liberian Republic has eked out a somewhat 
miserable existence, falling every year deeper into debt, and 
conclusively providing in a thousand ways that the American negro lacks the
elementary principles of self-government, being deficient in the very
essentialties of constructive administration. Certain foreign powers

<pb n="20170616_151024"/>

have endeavored to take advantage of the utter incapacity of the 
Liberians, and their motives in doing so are not far to seek. Not only 
are the territories owned by the Liberian Republic quite exceptionally 
rich in West African products, but it so happens that the Liberian
coast is the home of the very best labor which West Africa can produce. 
The fame of the Krooboy is proverbial; without his magnificent muscles 
and his cheerful willingness to work, our colonies would suffer most 
severely; it would be almost impossible for merchants to carry on several
important branches of their business, and British steamers would be 
deprived, to their disadvantage, of native firemen and stokers.</p>

<p>French and German Intrigues.</p>

<p>It must be perfectly obvious to all those who are in any way 
interested in this question that for years past two great Powers, France 
and Germany, have been silently, and without undue ostentation, working 
to get Liberia under their control. Whether there be collusion between 
them in this particular case is uncertain, but as Franco-German interests 
work harmoniously together in other parts of Africa, the hypothesis is 
by no means an unlikely one. However, that may be, France as is 
customary with her, is seeking to attain her ends through political 
action; Germany principally by commercial transactions on a large scale.
The former hopes to establish, if, indeed, she has not already 
established a sort of right of pre-emption over the whole of the Liberian
territory, filching here and there a slice when the opportunity presents 
itself. Germany is endeavoring to get the finances of this unfortunate 
State into her own hands, and, what perhaps is more dangerous still, 
trying to obtain a monopoly over Kroo labour throughout the territories
of the Republic.</p>

<pb n="20170616_151035"/>

<p>French intrigues in Liberia are not of yesterday. In 1879 a 
very definite rumour arose that France had offered protections to Liberia,
which would probably have been accepted by the latter had not the 
American Government, ever mindful of its inexperienced offspring stepped 
in and intimated to the French Government that such a course would be 
viewed with disfavour in the States. In 1884 the rumours were renewed,
and we find United States informing M. Roustan (French Minister at Washington)
that "Liberia, although not a colony of the United States, 
began its independent career as an offshoot of that country, which bore 
to it a quasi-parental relationship, which authorized the United States
to interpose its good offices in any contest between Liberia and a 
foreign State, and that a refusal to give the United States an opportunity 
to be heard for this purpose would make an unfavorable impression 
on the minds of the Government and the people of the United States."
Again, in 1887, on the reported French aggression in Liberian territory,
the United States were compelled to draw attention of the French 
Government to the fact that their relations with the Republic of Liberia 
had not changed, and that they still felt justified in employing their 
good offices on her behalf.</p>

<p>The Treaty of '92.</p>

<p>For five years the French desisted from their efforts. But on
December 8, 1892, they succeeded in inducing the foolish legislators of 
Liberia to accept a treaty by which France, while making some so called
concessions in the interior, which the French knew would be no more use 
to Liberia than to the Emperor Menelik, grabbed a large slice of Liberian
territory between the San Pedro and <sic>Cavally</sic> Rivers, substituting the 
latter river for the former as the boundary between the French possessions

<pb n="20170616_151120"/>

on the Ivory Coast and Liberia. By this means a valuable portion
of Liberia territory became French. And, to accentuate the irony of 
the situation France is now repudiating her "Concessions" in the interior 
to Liberia, on the plea that added geographical knowledge has materially 
altered the conclusions upon which the arrangement was based.</p>

<p>But the treaty did more than that. There can be no doubt as to 
the motives of the policy which dictated Article V. of the Franco-Liberian 
Agreement, nor that M. Hanotaux, in getting it accepted, showed his 
usual diplomatic skill. The translation of Article V. (the text is in 
French) reads as follows:-</p>

<q>In recognizing to the Republic of Liberia the limits which 
have now been fixed (after stripping Liberia of part of her 
dominions France graciously allows her to retain the rest) the Government 
of the French Republic declares that it only intends binding itself
towards the Republic of Liberia, free and independent, and makes all 
its reserves in case this independence were to be impaired or in
the event that the Republic of Liberia should alienate any part 
of the territories which are recognized to her by the present 
Convention.</q>

<p>The designs of France are at once disclosed in the above Article. 
If Liberia wishes at any time to dispose of a portion of her territory 
to another power, France tears up the Convention, and reserves herself 
the right to take any action which may seem fit to her. In other words,
it is a distinct threat to Liberia never to cede any of her territory 
to anybody but France, under penalty of diplomatic remonstrance, followed 
by physical action, which would obviously entail more land-grabbing.</p>

<pb n="20170616_151128"/>

<p>GERMAN CONCESSION-HUNTERS.</p>

<p>We must now turn to German proceedings in the Republic. Her
merchants and her traders have been worming themselves for years past 
into the very vitals of Liberia. Rubber concessions, coffee concessions,
territorial concessions of all kinds obtained by the judicial expenditure 
of "palm oil"; loans contracted; a gradual but steady grip closing 
round the finances of the country; and now the boldest stroke of all,
the purchase by a German firm of the monopoly of recruiting and shipping 
Krooboys all along the Liberian coast. Small wonder that this latest
barefaced attempt to capture the free labour market of West Africa has 
evoked a spirited protest from the Liverpool Chamber of Commerce.</p>

<p>Now it is necessary that the Governments of Great Britain and of 
the United States should look this matter squarely in the face. I have 
shown, I think conclusively, that the future of Liberia is being gravely 
compromised by French and German action. "Her very independence is at 
stake, and the freedom of her subjects imperilled. Are the statesmen 
of the United States, who in 1879, in 1884, and again in 1887, forbade 
outside interference with Liberian affairs &#8212; are they prepared in 1898 
to acquiesce in Liberia becoming an extension of the French Ivory Coast?
As for Great Britain her duty is clear. She should refuse peremptorily 
and at once to countenance any sort or kind of arrangement which places
restriction on the free recruiting of Krooboys on the Liberia Coast.
That done, London and Washington must arrive at an understanding which 
shall save Liberia both from the incompetence of her own legislators, 
and from becoming a prey to the cupidity of the Continental Powers.</p> 
   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
