<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0076">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Crisis, "Africa and the World Democracy" (1919)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0076</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Africa and the World Democracy</title>
<title level="j">The Crisis</title>
<biblScope unit="volume"/>
<biblScope unit="issue"/>
<date when="1919-02">February 1919</date>
<biblScope unit="page"/>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51708094">Angell, Norman, 1874-1967</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/34476326">Du Bois, W.E.B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/63869009">Hayward, William, 1877-1944</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9866919">Johnson, James Weldon, 1871-1938</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44314950">Kallen, Horace Meyer, 1882-1974</term>
<term>King Lukenga</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term>Marshall, Napoleon Bonaparte</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/8220846">Ovington, Mary White, 1865-1951</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44346731">Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/30419881">Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/259813355">Schieffelin, William Jay, 1866-1955</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62614395">Sheppard, William H. (William Henry), 1865-1927</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9111467">Shillady, John R., 1875-1943</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/37162522">Spingarn, Joel Elias, 1875-1939</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/89457467">Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>France</term>
<term>Lake Sheppard</term>
<term>Louisville (Kentucky)</term>
<term>New York (N.Y.)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Germany</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Bakuka</term>
<term>Congolese</term>
<term>Hereros</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-08" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0076.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Africa and the World Democracy</p>

<p>A Report</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Africa must ultimately be returned to the Africans. They are the best custodians of their lives and ideals. This was the thought developed at the meeting for the Pan-African Movement, held January 6, 1919, at Carnegie Hall, New York, under the auspices of the N. A. A. C. P. Mr John R. Shillady, Secretary of the Association, presided.</p>

<p>The man who was first presented to the audience was too shattered to speak, but his mere presence was a source of inspiration, and in itself constituted a strong plea for the renewed consideration of Negro rights. This was Captain Napoleon Bonaparte Marshall, who was commissioned as Lieutenant two years ago, and who on his arrival in France was made Captain and Judge Advocate by Colonel Hayward. Captain Marshall has been wounded several times and now is wearing a steel harness.</p>

<p>Interest in African affairs was immensely stimulated by the remarks of Dr. William Henry Sheppard, of Louisville, Ky. Dr. Sheppard has been a missionary to Africa and led the first known expedition into the forbidden land of King Lukenga. He also found a new tribe called Bakuka and discovered a lake in the interior of the Congo region which in 1910 was named Lake Sheppard by the Belgian Government.</p>

<p>This pioneer into Central Africa did much to bring the cause of native Africans close to the hearts of his audience. In a speech frequently intermingled with words and expressions in African dialect he told of the lives of those far-off peoples who are not naturally unkind, and who fight the invader only to protect themselves. If the visitor can satisfy the inhabitants of an African village as to his good intentions, he is made welcome. The tribes among which Dr. Sheppard had lived had reached a high state of civilization. They manufactured cloth, thread, and fashioned needles of iron; they made hats of cowrie shells and had razors which were deftly wielded by the women who are the African barbers.</p>

<p>And then Dr. Sheppard told a horrible thing. One day a hostile African king was reported to be close at hand with his forces. At the risk of his own life the missionary travelled to the camp of this invader. He was received and ushered into the chamber of the king. And there he saw eighty-one right hands which had been cut off and were in process of being cured! Above them waved the flag of Belgium and the king on being questioned produced papers from Belgian Leopold, of evil fame, asking for ivory, rubber or <hi rend="italics">hands of men!</hi> Dr. Sheppard insists that the horrors of the Congo were the immediate result of Leopold's personal interest and not connected with the interests of the Belgian Government. The distinction is fine.</p>

<p>After some musical numbers had been strikingly rendered by the Linwood Home Quartet and also by the Band of the "New Fifteenth," the discussion shifted then from the relation of actual experiences to the presentation of the extremely welcome theories of Professor Horace Meyer Kallen, of Harvard University, who is now working with Norman Angell on the League of Free Nations, and who is soon to attend the Peace Conference.</p>

<p>Professor Kallen struck at the economic cause which lies back of the long and unclean story of atrocities in Africa. It is the greed, he declared, of a few men who persist in using both their black and white fellows to enrich themselves. Traders cross from Europe not to sell the native what would bring him happiness, but what would bring the white man wealth. The articles mostly offered for sale are rum and old-fashioned guns.</p>

<p>When the natives gradually realizing that they are being made the victims of greed and exploitation offer resistance, the intervention of the home government is called in, the resistance is put down with a ruthless hand and a <hi rend="italics">new colony is founded!</hi> The lot of the natives of such a colony is a horrible one before they reach the sate of subjection which will best serve the ends of the European country. Thus the Germans in Middle Africa treated the splendid tribe of the Hereros just as the Belgians treated the Congolese,&#8212;virtually wiped them out of existence.</p>

<p>The remarkable thing is that, according to Professor Kallen, Europe has really gained nothing by her exploitation of Middle Africa. White people do not want to go there to live. They prefer America or Australia. Without the existence of trading companies and the ambitions of European bankers, Africa would be left to work out her salvation as best she might. The cheapness of native labor constitutes a serious menace, for it works to the disadvantage of European labor. It is to the interest of the rank and file of mankind everywhere that middle Africa be regarded as a trust for the plain peoples of the world.</p>

<p>This would call for a League of Free nations whose purpose should be not to exploit but to encourage self-development. Experts are needed from all nations who understand conditions in Africa. Colored peoples, as the ones most concerned, must be included in such an organization.</p>

<p>At the close of Professor Kallen's remarks, Mary White Ovington, Chairman of the Board of Directors of the N. A. A. C. P., was presented. During the absence of Major Spingarn, who is abroad, Miss Ovington has been Acting-Chairman, but by a recent election she has become Chairman in full. Miss Ovington read the following significant cable which has been sent from France to the business session of the annual meeting

<pb xml:id="p2" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0076.002"/>

of the N. A. A. C. P., by Dr. W. E. B. Du Bois:</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">"Greeting annual meeting. Race and friends uniting here to secure recognition throughout world on terms of full equality. Soldiers returning determined to join in struggle for justice to all in America. In the world crisis let us strive together without compromise or hesitation."</hi></p>

<p>James Weldon Johnson, Field Secretary of the N. A. A. C. P., followed the reading of Dr. DuBois' message with a statement of three reasons why the N. A. A. C. P. is interested in the discussion of the African question.</p>

<p>1. Because no other nation is likely to bring it up.</p>

<p>2. Because this is really an international question. Africa was at the bottom of the war. If this question is not settled, war will continue.</p>

<p>3. Because the N. A. A. C. P. is interested in questions concerning the Negro everywhere.</p>

<p>Mr. Johnson then left the subject of Africa and launched upon a magnificent plea for the establishment of the rights of Negroes in America. The American Negro problem is not going to be settled at Versailles. This is a domestic trouble and our fight must be at close quarters. The economic phase is important and must be dealt with. But there are two other conditions which we must meet. These are:</p>

<p>1. Bitter race hatred.</p>

<p>2. National apathy and indifference.</p>

<p>It is hard to tell which works the greater havoc, but on the whole the second is, in the last analysis, the more disastrous. This last the N. A. A. C. P. means to attack during this year.</p>

<p>"By intelligent, persistent, aggressive agitation," the speaker concluded, "we are going  to startle, to sting, <hi rend="italics">to whip</hi> this nation into action! The war is over and no miracle has happened. We are going to fight not for the right to fight in France, but to fight more effectively here!"</p>

<p>A brief statement followed then by Charles Edward Russell, one of the founders of the N. A. A. C. P., and a member of the Diplomatic Mission recently sent to Russia by the United States. Mr. Russell declared himself heartily in favor of the internationalization of the former Germany colonies.</p>

<p>William Jay Schieffelin, who has recently been made Colonel of the "New Fifteenth," also expressed his interest in the movement of the N. A. A. C. P., and his hopes for its success.</p>

<p>In accordance with suggestions offered by Professor Kallan and others, a cablegram was worded to President Wilson and a resolution drawn up for the Senate of the United States, urging their consideration of the African question.</p>

<p>The death of Theodore Roosevelt also evoked an expression of sympathy from the audience.</p>

<p>The cablegram and resolutions follow:</p>

<p>Woodrow Wilson,<lb/>
President of the United States,<lb/>
Paris France.</p>

<p>Mass meeting, January 6, Carnegie Hall, New York, under auspices of National Association for Advancement of Colored People, greets the President of the United States and pledges him loyal support in his efforts toward establishment of a universal League of Free Nations which shall have among its central duties the protection and development of the peoples of Middle Africa.</p>

<p>John R. Shillady, Secretary.</p>

<p>Resolutions Adopted at the Mass Meeting of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Carnegie Hall, Jan. 6, 1919</p>

<p>Resolved, That this mass meeting of citizens of the City of New York, held at Carnegie Hall, Monday evening, January 6, 1919, under the auspices of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, to consider "Africa and the World Democracy," urges upon the Senate of the United States the necessity for the creation at once of an international League of Free Nations which shall be charged, among other things, with the care and protection of the peoples of Middle Africa.</p>

<p>Resolved, That the citizens of the City of New York, in a mass meeting held at Carnegie Hall, Monday evening, January 6, 1919, express their deep sense of loss at Colonel Roosevelt's death and their keen sense of appreciation of the passion for fairness and right dealing which characterized his thoughts and actions in all his relations with his colored fellow-citizens.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
