<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0061">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, "Free Rum on the Congo" (1888)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="caa">Chelsea A. Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0061</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Free Rum on the Congo</title>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
<date when="1888-04">April 1888</date>
<biblScope unit="page">67-69</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>International Conferences</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/49285683">Hornaday, William T. (William Temple), 1854-1937</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Basin</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Netherlands</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-10-31" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2019-04-29" who="#caa">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p67"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>Free Rum on the Congo.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Mr. W. T. Hornaday's book on this subject is published by the 
Women's Temperance Publication Association. It is a terrible tale
of sin and misery, equal in moral and physical horror to the awful
story of free opium in China. In the New York <hi rend="italics">Tribune</hi> there is 
an extended notice of Mr. Hornaday's book which says that "When
a number of States meet together in international council it may
easily happen that the ethical standard finally dominating the proceedings 
is as much below the average of popular morality.
This was very clearly the case at that Berlin Conference of 1884-'85
which adopted the principle of free trade for the Congo, and in so
doing at one stroke deprived the Congo Free State of a revenue for 
subsistence and threw Africa open to a crusade of debauchery. No
more humiliating spectacle is often afforded the world that was exhibited 
on this occasion; when the United States and Great Britain
vainly protested against the monstrous wrong projected against helpless 
heathendom by all powerful Christendom, and when the German 
and Dutch makers and sellers of the vilest alcoholic poisons,
literally dictated their own terms to the Great Powers, and secured
solemn assent to the infamous principle that the right to sell rum
on the Congo without restriction was of more importance than the 
right of the African people to protection against physical and mental ruin.</p>

<p>"The evil work was consumated, however, and ever since a river
of rum, broad and deep almost as the Congo itself, has been pouring
into Africa. This is the first civilizing step taken by the Christian
Powers since the abolition of slavery. As the evidence brought
together by Mr. Hornaday in his telling little book clearly shows, the 
question of free rum on the Congo is rapidly assuming a gravity not
even second slavery. It may be that through the slavery
of the past a considerable part of the negro family will ultimately be
raised to real civilization, enlightenment and prosperity. But no
future good can by any possibility spring from the present evil of free

<pb n="p68"/>

rum on the Congo. The African races have a natural passion for
intoxicants, and their climate is deadly to drinkers. These two facts 
are the keys to the whole situation. Rum has been welcomed by
these grown-up children with fearful avidity. So eagerly is it sought,
so precious is it held, that in many parts of Africa it has become the
currency of the country. For purposes of barter it has superceded
cloth and beads and everything else. Traders who have taken caravans 
into the interior loaded with the usual articles of truck have 
been obliged to return to the coast because the natives refused 
everything but rum.</p>

<p>"Mr. Hornaday gives statistics which show that in one year&#8212;1885&#8212;
over 10,000,000 gallons of alcohol liquors were exported by the
United States, the Netherlands, Germany, France, and Great Britain,
to the Congo country. It is true that Germany and the Netherlands
shipped by far the greater portion of the filthy stuff, their share
amounting to 8,000,000 out of 10,000,000 gallons. It is to keep the
way open for this abominable German and Dutch traffic that the
other nations are discrediting themselves by participation in the
shameful policy of free rum. Not that the United States and
England are themselves guiltless. In the year named above New
England rum to the amount of 737,650 gallons found its way to the
Congo, and Great Britain sent 311,384 gallons. Neither the one nor
the other quantity is considerable enough to afford even the most
conscienceless kind is obviously the controlling influence in the case
of Germany and Holland, but America and England are plainly sacrificing
their characters and soiling their records only that some greedy
and brutal foreign traders may be enriched through the ruin of the 
Negroes.</p>

<p>"There are in the Congo Basin just about as many people as in
the United States at the last census. How many there will be ten
years hence, however, is quite another consideration. In what we
call civilization at home, population increases in a known ratio. In
what we call civilization abroad, population shrinks with appalling 
rapidity. The Christian's rum has blasted savage races all over the
globe. They wither under its destructive contact. At the rate it is
now being poured into the Congo country only the usual results can 
be anticipated.</p>

<p>"The remedial measure proposed by Mr. Hornaday is a new
conference of all the Powers to restrict and control the rum traffic.
In considering the probabilities of success in such an undertaking, it

<pb n="p69"/>

must be remembered that the United States, Great Britain, Italy and
Belgium, are already committed against free rum on the Congo. Germany 
and the Netherlands are the obstacles to Christian legislation.
With them the apparent controlling motive is naked greed of gain.
The question is whether these recalcitrant Powers can be persuaded
or shamed into abandoning the position they have taken; whether
they can be induced to confront the wrath of their rum makers and
sellers, in short.</p>

<p>"Free rum on the Congo could only be defended under a system
of devil-worship. No consistent Christian can possibly excuse or
abstain from denouncing it. But if Christendom by mere inaction
suffers the evil to survive and spread, what is the religion worth?
The question is compact and clear. The churches must take it up.
It is emphatically their business. But it is also the business of every
man and woman who respects and believes in modern civilization, and
who has any feeling for humanity beyond what a savage possesses.
As the case stands free rum must flourish on the Congo for twenty
years unless the General Act of the Berlin Conference is superseded
by fresh legislation. If, however, nothing is done to check the
abominable traffic, it is evident that in much less than twenty years
the inhabitants of the Congo Basin will have been fatally corrupted.
Prompt, vigorous, and general action,is demanded, and to the end
the facts may be made known we hope that a wide circulation
will be given Mr. Hornaday' striking account of the situation."</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
