<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>E. Benjamin Andrews - "Uncle Sam in Africa," The History of the Last Quarter-Century in the United States 1870-1895 (1896)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0018</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">The History of the Last Quarter-Century in the United States 1870-1895</title>
<author n="Andrews, Elisha Benjamin, 1844-1917" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/58084314">E. Benjamin Andrews</author>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
<date when="1896">1896</date>
<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">1-9</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
<term>International Conferences</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18379845">Bennett, James Gordon, 1841-1918</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46772111">Bismarck, Otto, Fürst von, 1815-1898</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100173535">Burke, Edmund, [1729?]-1797</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29571391">Hastings, Warren, 1732-1818</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/115616647">Kasson, John A. 1822-1910</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/60425677">Sanford, Henry Shelton, 1823-1891</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry Morton, 1841-1904</term>
<term>Tisdell, N. P.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Lake Tanganyika</term>
<term>Livingstone Falls</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Austria</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Netherlands</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>Switzerland</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Arab</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-09" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">The History of the Last Quarter-Century in the United States 1870-1895</head>

<head type="sub">By<lb/>
E. Benjamin Andrews<lb/>
President of Brown University</head>

<p>Volume II</p>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head type="sub">Chapter I</head>

<head type="sub">Monroe's Doctrine and Arthur's Practice</head>

<head type="sub">Uncle Sam in Africa.</head>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

<p>In 1884 occurred an event presaging a change in the time-honored foreign policy of the United States. Our diplomatic representatives took leading part in the Berlin Conference of that year, a conference which dealt with important questions touching the Dark Continent.</p> 

<p>In September, 1876, Leopold II., King of the Belgians, had convened at his palace a conference of African travelers, to discuss the best means of opening equatorial Africa. Half a

<pb n="p2"/>

year later a Congress was convoked at the same place, where appeared delegates from Austria, Belgium, France, Germany, the Netherlands, Spain Switzerland and the United States, A committee of three, headed by the King, and including General Henry S. Sanford, of Florida, representing the English-speaking races, recommended the formation of an International African Association, to found "hospitable and scientific" stations in Africa under the association's own flag. A chain of such stations was formed from Zanzibar to Lake Tanganyika.</p> 

<p>The royal enterprise was advertised to the world mainly by the labors of Henry M. Stanley. Born in 1841, near Denbigh, Wales, where he was known as John Rowlands, from three years of age to thirteen the lad lived and was schooled inside St. Asaph Poor-house. He later ascribed all his success to the education here received. When sixteen he shipped for New Orleans, where he found a foster-father in a trader named Stanley, whose name he assumed and henceforth bore. At the outbreak of the civil war his energy took a military turn, and the man who was later reverenced by the Congo blacks as "Father and Mother of the Country," enlisted on the pro-slavery side. He was taken prisoner, escaped at night by swimming a river amid a storm of bullets, and made for Wales, but not to stay. Returning, he enlisted once more, this time in the Federal navy, acting presently as ensign on the flagship Ticonderoga. Peace restored, the path of a newspaper correspondent in wild and distant lands attracted the bold fellow; and we find him by turns in Spain, Turkey and Syria.</p> 

<p>Stanley's fame was not sealed, however, till James Gordon Bennett, of the New York <hi rend="italics">Herald</hi>, despatched him to the

<pb n="p3"/>

Dark Continent to "find Livingstone." More explicit directions would have been impossible at the time, as well as needless and insufferable for Stanley. The new explorer found the old one, who refused to return to civilization before completing his explorations. Livingstone died in Africa, his work still incomplete, but it was taken up and astonishingly supplemented by his strong successor. The Queen sent Stanley a gold snuff-box set with diamonds. France decorated him with the cross of the Legion of Honor. Bismarck entertained him. Leopold II. treated him as if he had been a prince of the blood. The poor-house boy became the most famous man on earth.</p> 

<p>After Stanley had discovered the Upper Congo in 1877, "The <hi rend="italics">Comité d'Etudes</hi> of the Upper Congo," a branch, or 

<pb n="p4"/>

perhaps a partner, of the International African Association, devoted its labors to that region. In 1884 General Sanford wrote: "This work has developed into extraordinary proportions and has had for practical result the opening up to civilizing influence and to the world's traffic this vast, populous, and fertile region, securing certain destruction to the slave trade wherever its flag floats." The flag—blue, with a golden star in the centre—was as yet unrecognized. The United States, so prominent in the inception of the enterprise, was the first to recognize it. In his annual message for 1883, President Arthur called attention to the work of the association, "of which a citizen of the United States was the chief executive officer." "Large tracts of territory," he said, "have been ceded to the association by native chiefs, roads have been opened, steamboats placed on the river, and the <hi rend="italics">nuclei</hi> of States established at twenty-two stations under the flag, which offers freedom to commerce and prohibits the slave trade. . . The United States cannot be indifferent to this work nor to the interest of their citizens involved in it. It may become advisable for us to co-operate with other commercial powers in promoting the rights of trade and residence in the Congo valley, free from the interference or political control of any one nation."</p> 

<p>The succeeding April the Secretary of State found himself authorized to proclaim "that in accordance with the traditional policy of the United States, which enjoins their careful attention to the commercial interests of American citizens, avoiding at the same time all interference in the controversies engaged in between other powers or the conclusion of alliances with foreign nations, the Government of the United States declared its sympathy with and approbation of the humane and noble object of the International Association of the Congo, acting in the interest of the Free State established in that region, and commanded all officers of the United States, either on land or sea, to recognize the flag of the International Association as that of a friendly government."</p>

<pb n="p5"/>

<p>This step was much criticised abroad. The scramble for "a piece of Africa" had begun, and the association, which, unrecognized, might be a cat's paw, once recognized became a rival. France and Portugal, each of whom had her claim (one very ancient, the other just laid, but both much cackled about) to lands occupied by the association, were especially nettled. A French paper petulantly dubbed Uncle Sam the new State's "godfather." Had the claims mentioned been fully conceded the new State would have been left without sea-coast. The adjustment gave to the new-flag nation a coast frontage of from thirty to forty miles north from the Congo estuary, as well as a vast empire of back country. The guarded recognition by the United States at this juncture was, as Stanley said, "the birth unto new life of the association, seriously menaced as its existence was by opposing interests and ambitions." More vital ends than these touching the African continent waited to be attained, appealing to " the commercial interests of American citizens," and to their "sympathy" and "approbation." Besides, Americans had founded Liberia, American missionaries were not few in Africa, a wealthy American journalist had furnished the means for rescuing Dr. Livingstone and a famous American explorer performed the task. All these facts aroused public interest here and led to our participation in the Berlin Conference.</p>

<p>This step was as fiercely criticised at home as our recognition of the blue flag had been abroad. The timid shrieked appeal to the Monroe Doctrine. Our commercial interests in Africa, it was said, were small, even <hi rend="italics">in posse</hi>. Considered as <hi rend="italics">dis</hi>interested, the action was denounced as meddling. We should regret it, critics said, when the Nicaragua controversy reached an acute phase. The

<pb n="p6"/>

correspondent of the London <hi rend="italics">News</hi> considered the conspicuous part taken by our delegates in the conference an intimation that this country was henceforth to be more active in foreign affairs.</p>

<p>The Conference assembled in November, 1884. It was formally opened by Prince Bismarck, who stated its main objects to be: 1. To secure free navigation and trade on the River Congo. 2. To secure free navigation of the River Niger. 3. To determine the formalities to be in future observed for the valid annexation of territory on the African continent. The neutralization of the Congo and Niger, an American proposition put forward by our delegate, Mr. Kasson, was attained in part, but not perfectly, owing to the opposition of France. The treaty powers promised, in case of war by or against a possessor of Congo land, to lend their good

<pb n="p7"/>

offices to induce both belligerents to keep hands off from the free trade belt, which included much French and Portuguese as well as other territory. In the event of disagreement touching the free trade belt, the powers undertook to resort to mediation before appealing to arms, and reserved the option of proceeding by arbitration. The motion to restrict the sale of liquor in the Congo basin, though introduced by Italy, was also of American origin. It was bitterly assailed by Germany and Holland, but was partly realized afterward when measures were adopted to prevent the introduction of liquor into tracts 

<pb n="p8"/>

yet uninfected, or where the Mohammedan religion forbade its use. The United States, with England, joined the enlightened King of the Belgians in securing provisions for the preservation and amelioration of native races, the suppression of slavery and the slave-trade, and the encouragement of all religious, scientific and charitable enterprises, with perfect religious liberty for white and black. Arrangements were made to include the neutralized strip in the Postal Union.</p> 

<p>Mr. N. P. Tisdell, appointed by the United States Government to report upon its advantages for American trade, was unfavorably impressed with the country and the character of the natives. Yet subsequent events justified Stanley's assertion that the course of the United States toward the new sovereignty was "well worthy of the great republic." The aborigines no longer dreaded the merciless Arab slave-raider, for his power was broken. Cannibals who in 1877 assailed

<pb n="p9"/>

Stanley with flights of poisoned arrows soon enlisted in the little standing army of the Free State. The sale of liquor, arms and gunpowder was restricted. Commerce more than doubled the proportions it had when the Conference rose. A railroad around Livingstone Falls was begun and part of it speedily in operation. It is to be said that rumors, for the time impossible either to verify or to refute, reached the press, of outrages upon natives at the hands of Belgian officials, grosser than those which Burke imputed to Warren Hastings.</p> 

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>