<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0963">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John H. Smyth to Frederick W. Seward, December 7, 1878</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0963</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John H. Smyth to Frederick W. Seward</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in Monrovia, 1852-1906</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="microfilm">M169, Roll 3</biblScope>
<date when="1878-12-07">December 7, 1878</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Despatches</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Gola</term>
<term>Vey</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Smyth, John H.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Consul General</roleName>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1878-12-07"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/77754769">Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1878-01-13"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-10" who="#kln">Transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="Roll3-2061.jpg"/>

<p>C. No 4.</p>

<p><del>Legation</del> Consulate General of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, Dec. 7, 1878</p>

<p>Mr. J. H. Smyth to the Secretary of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Report of the trade and industry of Liberia for the fiscal year ending September 30, 1878.</p>

<p>Synopsis:</p>

<p>The delay of the report, the agriculture of Liberia, reflections upon manufacturies, forests, mines, fisheries; report of imports and exports, and reasons for their meagerness, a reference to the decadence of Liberians, the last emigration, cause of absence of reference to the revenue.</p>

<pb n="Roll3-2062.jpg"/>

<p>C. No 4.</p>

<p>Legation of the United States,<lb/>
Monrovia, Liberia, Dec. 7, 1878.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>I have the honor, after an unavoidable delay, to transmit as full a report of the trade and industry of Liberia for the last fiscal year, as it has been possible to obtain.</p>

<p>As the Liberian fiscal year terminates September 30, 1878, and it is not till the 15th or 20th of November that the reports are at the seat of Government, my tardiness, I hope, is <catchwords>satisfactorily</catchwords>

<fw type="address">Hon. F. W. Seward,<lb/>
Ass't Sec'y of State<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</fw>

<pb n="Roll3-2063.jpg"/>

satisfactorily explained and understood.</p>

<p>Agriculture:</p>

<p>Since coffee has become a valuable commodity, the agricultural class has seemingly neglected all else and devoted itself to its culture. So great has been the demand for coffee scions, and so large have been the profits realized by purchasers that, it is rumored that, the legislature proposes the passage of a law making the duty upon their exportation, and the seed also, so exorbitant <catchwords>as</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2064.jpg"/>

as to amount to a virtual prohibition of sale. With this prospect the people are dissatisfied.</p>

<p>Manufacturies:</p>

<p>Nothing has been done in this line of industry, nor in the utilization of the products of the forests, except as to the palm.</p>

<p>Mines:</p>

<p>The absence of geologists, the indifference of government as to this industry has made all below the surface as a sealed book. From specimens <catchwords>shown</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2065.jpg"/>

shown of hard and soft coals that have been discovered, it is clear, if attention were given to mining, coal would be a source of commercial profit, seeing that Sierra Leone is the only coaling station on the west coast; and the coal gotten there is brought from England and Scotland at very great cost.</p>

<p>Silver, gold, lead of the finest quality, iron and copper have been found to exist here, more as the result of chance than design. These facts before us, it is reasonable to <catchwords>assume</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2066.jpg"/>

assume that, with necessary means and requisite ability, mining could be made a source of wealth to the Republic.</p>

<p>Fisheries:</p>

<p>While the waters of the Republic swarm with the finny tribe, our country and England furnish this coveted article of food in salt.</p>

<p>Imports, Exports, vessels and tonnage:</p>

<p>The imports and exports for the fiscal year ending September 30, 1878, are inclosed as received <catchwords>from</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2067.jpg"/>

from the Comptroller of the Republic. He seems to have no means of informing me whence the imports come, with exception of the single article, tobacco. As to the arrival and departure of foreign and domestic vessels and their tonnage, I learned from the collector that during the last and present administrations, no reliable statistics of this nature were kept. The meagerness of the statistics furnished must be accounted for and is, by the officers of Government <catchwords>whose</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2068.jpg"/>

whose duty it is to furnish them.</p>

<p>Population:</p>

<p>As no census has ever been taken, it is difficult, nay impossible, to be accurate as to the number of souls in Liberia. Of American Liberians there is supposed to be from 10 to 12,000, of native or aboriginal people quite 1,000,000. The American Liberians are steadily dying out, and from the appearance of the descendants of the pioneers it is beyond doubt that they possess little of the vital forces <catchwords>of</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2069.jpg"/>

of their progenitors. The average Liberian woman is fragile in form, emaciated in facial appearance and sickly and wanting in procreative power: while the men are small in body, short in statue, with little physical strength. Both sexes die young.</p>

<p>The union of these people, as a consequence is productive of sickly issue.</p>

<p>One cause of this sad condition of health, this degeneracy may be found in the isolation of the Liberian from the healthy native <catchwords>element</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2070.jpg"/>

element; the need of an infusion of native blood by intermarriage.</p>

<p>Emigration:</p>

<p>The emigration during the past year is quite familiar to the country as far as the transit of the emigrants is concerned and the sufferings they endured. Very few have died of fever though most of them have been its victims.</p>

<p>While these people were very cordially received, when their real condition became known the interest formerly felt underwent a <catchwords>visible</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2071.jpg"/>

visible change, which was not surprising.</p>

<p>These people ignorant of the requirements of a new country, came without money, came possessed of no intellectual training, came with an ignorant christianity, which however well suited to the plantation in the days of their thraldom, can be of no possible use in the christianization of a people like the Veys or the Golas; the former of which tribe have a written language, and many of whom are ambitious to become Arabic <catchwords>scholars</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2072.jpg"/>

scholars; and the latter tribe a people of strong intellect. In short they could influence no tribe of which I have any knowledge or information, for obvious reasons.</p>

<p>These people are not unlike the majority of emigrants that have preceded them, being mere laborers. Liberia has an abundance of mere laborers in Liberians and natives, the latter can endure the rigors of climate, require for their labor less compensation than the emigrant. The average wages paid the <catchwords>native</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2073.jpg"/>

native laborer is form 3. to $4. per month with rations, rice and fish; with the advantages indicated in his favor; while the American Liberian receives double this amount and like rations.</p>

<p>While the Republic needs accessions as laborers in its ample field, it requires a higher order of labor, a higher order of intelligence than is ordinarily discovered in emigrants; mechanics, agriculturists, men of scientific acquirements, and liberal education, and a priesthood <sic>thouroughly</sic> cultivated, <catchwords>are</catchwords>

<pb n="Roll3-2074.jpg"/>

are its immediate needs.</p>

<p>Though the native is a <sic>heathan</sic>, there are not a few who are semi-civilized, and from the latter class the uneducated preacher cannot elicit attention, and by them the ignorant emigrant is regarded with contempt, and justly so, on account of his arrogance.</p>

<p>The emigrant comes to Africa with a fancied superiority to his native brother, which he the native does not fail to discern, and which has been so general that, it has resulted most <catchwords>unfavorably</catchwords> 

<pb n="Roll3-2075.jpg"/>

unfavorably to the Republic in the past, and if not wisely noted, and a new policy adopted may be more so in the future.</p>

<p>When the message of the President shall appear, I shall be able to furnish information as to the revenues of the Republic.</p>

<p>With distinguished consideration and respect, I have, Sir, the honor to subscribe myself,<lb/>
Your obd't serv't<lb/>
Jno. H. Smyth</p>

<p>Inclosure</p>

<p>1. The Comptroller's report of Exports &amp; Imports.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>