<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.government.0010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Brussels Geographical Conference - Resolutions of the Conference Concerning the System of Organization (1876)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.government.0010</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Resolutions of the Conference Concerning the System of Organization</title>
<title level="m">Africa and the Brussels Geographical Conference</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10222960">Banning, Émile, 1836-1898</author>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Sampson Low, Marston, Searle &amp; Rivington, 1877</publisher>
<date when="1903-12-27">December 27, 1903</date>
<biblScope unit="page">156-157</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>International Conferences and Treaties</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Government Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Brussels (Belgium)</term>
<term>Central Africa</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-01" who="kln">transcription, encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head>Brussels Geographical Conference</head>

<p>(12, 13, and 14 September, 1876).</p>

<pb n="p156"/>

<div2 type="section">

<head>Resolutions of the Conference Concerning the System of Organization.</head>

<p>1. There shall be established an international commission of
exploration and civilisation of Central Africa, and national
committees which shall keep themselves in communication
with the commission with the view of centralising, as far
as possible, the efforts made by their fellow-countrymen,
and to facilitate, by their co-operation, the execution of the
resolutions of the commission.</p>

<pb n="p157"/>

<p>2. The national committees constitute themselves in such
manner as may seem to them preferable.</p>

<p>3. The commission shall be composed of the presidents of the
principal geographical society which are represented at
the Conference of Brussels, or who may subsequently give
in their adherence to its programme, and of two members
chosen by each national committee.</p>

<p>4. The president shall have the power to admit into the
association countries which were not represented at the
Conference.</p>

<p>5. The president shall have the power of filling up the
international commission by adding to it effective members and
honorary members.</p>

<p>6. The central committee, after having drawn up its regulations,
shall make it its duty to direct by means of an executive
committee the enterprises and operations aiming at the
fulfilment of the object of the association and to administer
the funds supplied by government, by the national
committees and by individuals.</p>

<p>7. The executive committee shall be appointed under the
president, and shall consist of three or four members
nominated beforehand by the present Conference and 
subsequently by the international committee.</p>

<p>8. The members of the committee shall hold themselves in
readiness to answer to the summons of the president.</p>

<p>9. The president appoints a secretary-general, who by the very
fact of his nomination will become a member of the international
commission and of the executive committee; the 
president also appoints a treasurer.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>