<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0048">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from John T. Bradberry to William H. Seward, July 31, 1863</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0048</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Dispatch from John T. Bradberry to William H. Seward</title>
<date when="1863-07-31">July 31, 1863</date>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">1</biblScope>
<date from="1854-01-12" to="1893-03-29">January 12, 1854 - March 29, 1893</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Birney</term>
<term>Brookhouse, R.</term>
<term>Cunningham, Robert</term>
<term>de Andrade, José Baptista</term>
<term>Flores, Francisco Antonio</term>
<term>Willis, John G.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Angola</term>
<term>Boston (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>Havre de Grace (Maryland)</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
<term>New York</term>
<term>Salem (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>St. Helena</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Bradberry, John T.</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent for Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1863-07-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42616145">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1863-11-05"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-04-29" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and addition encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0048.001"/>

<note>Recd 5 Nov.</note>
<note>(No. 4)</note>

<p>July 31/63<lb/>
Commercial Agency of the United States<lb/>
at St Paul De Loanda</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I have the honour of advising you
of my arrival at my Post of Duty on the 15th
day of July 1863. After a passage (by sea) of
Sixty Days, and ten days occupied in transit
between my Place of Residence (Havre De Grace Md.)
and detention in Boston Harbor by contrary
minds, the latter occupying nine days, <sic>makeing</sic>
in all Seventy Days transit;</p>

<p>I have drawn upon the Hon Secretary of
the Treasury for the amount due me for transit
viz $217.56. being obliged to allow 15 pr cent
upon the face of the Draft, netting me $186.93
the net amount due me after deducting $2.28
for internal revenue tax, and $3.00 for Passport
forgotten while in Washington;</p>

<p>I was unable to wait upon his <sic>Exelency</sic>
"Sr. José Baptista D' Andrade" Governor
General of the Province of Angola, until the 30th
of July, in consequence of formalities necessary
to be observed;</p>

<p>Having complied with the customary
Etiquette of the Country, on the said 30th of July,
I called upon his excellency, accompanied by
John G. Willis, Esq. and Snr. Francisco Antonio Flores
as interpreter and presented my commission
for his inspection, he was entirely satisfied
that it was Genuine.</p>

<p>But it having been customary for Agts
here to be furnished with an Exequatur, in accordance
with the 10th article of the Treaty of 1840. He
could not recognize me in the official "Boletin

<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page"/>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0048.002"/>

furniture viz Chairs, settee, &amp;c. and a book
case or "Escritoir" obtained by me by Receipting
for it to Mr Willis (a copy enclosed) for
the purpose of keeping the Archives and Books
belonging to this agency safe;</p>

<p>The said property was in possession
of Mr Birney, formerly U. States Naval Store
keeper here, left with Mr Cunningham by
Mr Birney as property of the United States, and
by him left with Mr Willis, each of the
last named Gentlemen giving their receipts
to their <sic>predisessors</sic> for the property;</p>

<p>When I presented the Order of your
Honour upon Mr Cunningham for articles in
his possession, to Mr Willis, I called his
attention to the latter clause of said Order
namely "and all other property in your possession
belonging to the United States" Mr. Willis
informed me that the said property was not
intended to be included by said order, because
it is property under the exclusive control of
the Navy Department;</p>

<p>Not being prepared in the <sic>absense</sic> of
instructions in the premises to controvert this
position, I leave it; simply calling the
attention of the Department to the facts, to the
end that in case it was the intention to place
said property in my possession, that neither
my Bondsmen or myself be held responsible
for it, inasmuch as the said property is
not now, or ever has been in my possession;</p>

<p>I beg leave to call your attention
to a custom (or Practice) that has obtained here,
regarding the place of Deposit of Ships Papers,

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0048.003"/>

namely by Sec 479 <sic>manuel</sic> of 1863 it is made
the Duty of every Master of an American Vessel
to deposit the papers (ships Papers) with the Consular
Officer, and in default heavy Penalties;
but here the ships papers are retained by the
Custom House authorities, consequently no
Consular Certificates (as per instructions) can
be given;</p>

<p>Mr Willis assures me that he has attempted
to induce an abandonment of said practice.
but without effect, and from present information
upon the subject, I am induced to believe that
the services of one having higher powers than
myself, (probably our Minister to Portugal) is
necessary to accomplish the desired reformation
and enable ship masters and Commercial agents
to comply with the United States Law;</p>

<p>By schedule no 1 (herewith enclosed) it
will be perceived that this Post has no Books
of Record as required by sections 391-392 of
<sic>manuel</sic> of 1863. Consequently the Records are 
upon unbound detached <sic>peices</sic> of paper, very 
liable to loss by accident;</p>

<p>Other articles also are much needed as
per enclosed schedule No 3. Please send them
as soon as practicable, the agency being
absolutely destitute of them;</p>

<p>Mr Willis informs me that he has
received notice that a box containing a 
flag and other articles has been sent to this
Post via New York, but it has not been
received here, and it is probably now lying
in that City or entirely lost</p>

<p>There is no certain way by which articles

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0048.004"/>

intended for this Post can be sent, except via
Salem Mass, Care of R Brookhouse &amp; co, and 
viz England, Care of U.S. Consul of St Helena
and via Lisbon, care of U.S. Consul at
Lisbon, no vessels sail from the U.S.
Direct to this Port, except from Salem Mass
and occasionally one from Boston;</p>

<p>I have the Honour of informing your that
it has been and is now the Custom at this Port
for Oaths to be administered by the Commercial
Agents to Citizens of the United States;</p>

<p>By Circular No 8 of Feb 21st 1863, directed
to me; and by Art <unclear>1st</unclear> of said Circular, I understand
that I am instructed to render an account
for office Rent to the amount attained by General
instructions, namely, 10 per cent on the amount of
salary which I am thankful for; inasmuch as
the salary allowed is barely adequate to a
support;</p>

<p>Not being engaged in trade of any kind
the room occupied by me is used exclusively
for the business of the agency;</p>

<p>It gives me much pleasure to acknowledge
the kindness of John G. Willis Esq in
affording me every <sic>desireable</sic> facility for
transacting the business of the agency;</p>

<p>With much Respect<lb/>
I have the Honour to be<lb/>
Yours Most Obed<lb/>
John T. Bradberry<lb/>
Com Agt</p>

<fw type="address">Hon<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
of the United States Washington</fw>

</div1>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<p>Loanda July 30th 1863</p>

<p>Received this day from John G Willis
Esqr one Escritoir or book case as a 
Depository for archives, books and
papers belonging to the United States
Commercial Agency at St Paul De Loanda,
and to be returned when called for</p>

<p>John T. Bradberry,<lb/>
Com Agt</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
