<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.drama.0002">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Abyssinia (1906)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.drama.0002</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Abyssinia</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/16669091">Rogers, Alex, 1876-1930</author>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70655904">Shipp, Jesse, 1859-1934</author>
<date>1906</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Imagined Africa</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Drama</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62344773">Menelik II, Negus of Ethiopia, 1844-1913</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abyssinia</term>
<term>Addis Ababa (Ethiopia)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.analysis.0014">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-10" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">Abyssinia</head>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Characters</head>

<list>
<item>Jasamine Jenkins, Always with the money.</item>
<item>Rastus Johnson, U.S.A., The money.</item>
<item>Elder Fowler, Pastor of the largest Colored Baptist Church in Wilson County, Kansas.</item> 
<item>Miss Primly, A dear friend of Ras's family.</item>
<item>Aunt Cally Parker, Ras's Aunt Leading Sister in Fowler's flock.</item>
<item>Wong Foo, Chinese cook.</item>
<item>Serena, Miss Primly's niece.</item>
<item>Lucinda, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Nettie, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Dalphne, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Frank, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Authur, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Sophronia, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Mandy, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Matilda, Friend of Ras's family and member of Fowler's Choir.</item>
<item>Oscar, Helper around Caravan.</item>
<item>Sonny, Helper around Caravan.</item>
<item>King Menelik II, King of Kings of Abyssinia</item>
<item>The Affa Negus Tegulet, King Menelik's Chief Justice.</item>
<item>Shambal Bolasso, Tegulet's nephew, a captain in Menelik's army.</item>
<item>Zamish, Tegulet's trusted servant.</item>
<item>Serena, Shambal Bolasso's escort.</item>
<item>Oureeka, Shambal Bolasso's escort.</item>
<item>Hasid, A drunken soldier.</item>
<item>The Bijirondi, Baggage man.</item>
<item>The Bishop.</item>
<item>The High Priest.</item>
<item>Fai-Tu, Queen of Abyssinia.</item>
<item>Varinoe, Market Girl.</item>
<item>Ulissa, Market Girl.</item>
<item>Allamo, Market Girl. and</item>
<item>Miram, A market girl.</item>
<item>Americans with Caravan, Abyssinian soldiers, citizens, wood carriers, water carriers, market girls, beggars and a few more.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Synopsis</head>

<p>SCENE I. Mountain Pass near Capitol, Addis Ababa. An Abyssinian guard-house.<lb/>
Time: Monday evening.</p>

<p>SCENE II. Plains near Borema Springs.<lb/>
Time: Tuesday, 4 P.M.</p>

<p>SCENE III. Borema Springs, the last camping place before reaching Addis Ababa.<lb/>
Time: Tuesday, Sunset.</p>

<p>SCENE IV. Market Place outside the walls of Addis Ababa.<lb/>
Time: Wednesday.</p>

<p>SCENE V. King Menelik II. Audience Chamber.<lb/>
Time: Thursday, 5 A.M. (All affairs of state are attended to at this hour)</p>

<p>SCENE VI. King Menelik II. Throne room.<lb/>
Time: Thursday evening (Being the Queen's birthday and the feast of the King of Kings of Abyssinia </p>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Note</head>

<p>Meaning of Abyssinian words used throughout the play.</p>

<list>
<item>Janhoi - King or Emperor.</item>
<item>Affa Negus - Chief Justice.</item>
<item>Shambal - Captain Leader of 1000 men.</item>
<item>Ras - Prince.</item>
<item>De Jas - General.</item>
<item>Bijirondi - Baggage man.</item>
<item>Aga-fari - Receives people and distributes King's orders.</item> 
<item>Tej - The National drink (Intoxicant)</item>
<item>Salaam Allah - "The peace of God be with you"</item>
<item>De-shi - Alright, We all agree &amp; etc.</item>
</list>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Prologue</head>

<stage>Time: Monday Evening.</stage>

<stage>(Mountain pass near the Capitol, Addis Ababa, an Abyssinia guard house. Soldiers singing an ode to Janhoi (King or Emperor) at raise of curtain)</stage>

<stage>(First half sang with curtain down)</stage>

<p>"JANHOI"</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Soldiers of the King are we,</l>
<l>We bow to his supremacy,</l>
<l>We know naught of disloyalty,</l>
<l>Hence can not spare an enemy.</l>
<l>We do not know the world called fear,</l>
<l>We're gay and glad when danger's near,</l>
<l>From the borders of our sister"Land of Zion"</l>
<l>We're the war kings of the mighty "Land of the Lion"</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Cheers, boisterous revelry, then curtain music through [...] leading to curtain)</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Janhoi, Janhoi, Janhoi,</l>
<l>For thee we take our stand</l>
<l>Oh! mighty one, thy will be done on this our native land.</l> 
<l>We beg Janhoi for peace and joy,</l>
<l>For all that justice brings</l>
<l>Forever we will loyal be,</l>
<l>To thee Oh! King of Kings.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(At finish of song, enter from Guard-house, Shambul Bolasso.)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Salaam Allah</p>
<stage>(Salutes soldiers)</stage>
<p>it does me good to see you in such fine spirits, my friends.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>HASID</speaker>
<p>I beg your pardon, Shambul Bolassa, we are not in fine spirits</p> 
<stage>(Hiccoughs)</stage>
<p>the fine spirits are in us</p></sp>

<stage>(Soldiers laughs)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Very good boys, but I'm afraid this is the last spiritual [...] meeting you'll have for some time. We've got to get back [...] harnese again. There were an uprising three weeks ago in [...] division of Arusa, and I've been informed by my Uncle, [...] Negus, that we are liable to be ordered south at any time within the next few days.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERMA</speaker>
<p>Nothing would suit me better at the present time, I'm ready to start at once.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>And I And I And I.</p></sp>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 1</head>

<sp><speaker>HASID</speaker>
<stage>(With hiccough)</stage>
<p>Me too.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(Laughing)</stage>
<p>Hasid, I'm afraid if we started to-night, you wouldn't get very far, at the same time that won't prevent Semra from passing the Tej just once more to everybody</p>
<stage>(Pause)</stage>
<p>except Hasid.</p>
<stage>(Soldiers laugh and push Hasid good naturedly. After cups are filled)</stage> 
<p>Is everybody supplied?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Es-she, Es-she.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Then here's success to the "Jolly Jungle Boys"</p></sp>

<p>"Jolly Jungle Boys"</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Oh! we're the Jolly Jungle Boys and happy little chaps,</l> 
<l>O-------oh!</l>
<l>We're known in ev'ry country that is marked upon the maps</l> 
<l>Oh;-----Oh------oh!</l>
<l>We love to tease the tiger and kidd the kangaroo,</l>
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>For we're the happy, snappy chappies, savage through and through,</l> 
<l>Oh!---oh------oh!</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>"Kiddy-come-kick-the-cocoanut-and-kick it-to-Kan-ka-kee"</l>
<l>That's the college cheer we learned at Congo-by-the-sea,</l>
<l>We led our class in cussedness and took the cake for noise,</l>
<l>For we're the handy dandy (MM-mm-mm-mm) Jungle Boys.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>We kill the cruel Kaffirs and we hate the Hottentots,</l> 
<l>Oh---oh</l>
<l>And when the leopard sees us, he is sure to change his spots,</l> 
<l>oh---oh</l>
<l>The big gorilla loves us and we monkey with the monk</l> 
<l>Oh---oh</l>
<l>The elephant will let us put our collars in his trunk</l> 
<l>Oh---oh---oh.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Oh when the sun is setting and the sky is filled with stars,</l>
<l>Oh!--oh</l>
<l>We smoke the serpents from their holes with pipes and black cigars,</l> 
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>The lazy lizard loves to listen to our jokes and noise</l>
<l>oh!---oh</l>
<l>The big giraffe is sure to laugh to see our jungle joys</l>
<l>oh!---oh</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>When we grow up to man's estate and fight the Zulu clan,</l> 
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>We'll murder every mothers son that's darker than a tan,</l> 
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>We'll kill their sacred cattle and we'll carry off their gals</l> 
<l>oh!---oh</l>
<l>Then if there isn't blood enough we'll fight among our pals.</l> 
<l>oh!---oh.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Our Chief is king of savages and cuts a lot of ice,</l>
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>But fears the jolly Jungle Boys and treats us mighty nice</l>
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>He always asks advice of us to carry on his wars</l>
<l>Oh!---oh</l>
<l>And we'd have whipped the English if we'd fought among the Boers.</l> 
<l>Oh!---oh.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(At finish of song, enter from L.4.E., from fly gallery, coming down mountain, Affa Negus Tegulet with servant bearing lantern. Bolassa discovers Tegulet, calls soldiers)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Fall in</p>
<stage>(Bus. for soldiers, all form line)</stage>
<p>Your Excellency does me a great honor to call at such an unusual hour, may I inquire if your health is good?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Is it very likely that I would be stumbling around over these hills at night if I required the attention of a sick nurse?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>No your Excellency, but I thought, ah - I thought you eh--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Heard an annual noise I did a lot of boisterous singing, something modern in the way of European tactics, you're teaching your men, I judge?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Hardly that Uncle, but your Excellency has over looked the fact that this is your 60th birthday and we, your humble servants</p>
<stage>(Bow)</stage>
<p>were celebrating the happy event Long live his Excellency the Affa Negus Tegulet.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Long live the Affa Negus Tegulet.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>HASID</speaker>
<p>Long live Aff' Negs Teg--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Send those young men to their quarters.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Squads, order arms at a trail, squads forward march squads right twos right column left!</p> 
<stage>(Exit soldiers in guard-house)</stage>
<p>Your orders have been obeyed your Excellency. Allow me once more to congratulate you. By the death of the Emperor, you look good for three score years more, that is if your present physical condition is to be taken into account.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Your flattery doesn't alter the fact that old age removes the fire and vigor from both mind and body therefore, one does not care to be reminded with each succeeding year, that the journey of three score and ten allotted to man's career of usefulness, has been almost completed.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>But your Excellency I trust will be an exception to the rule and if, the signs are right, you have many years of usefulness left, but what of the upraising in the Arusa Division?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>The chronic complaint of too much taxes levied by the Government flavored with an argument against the law controlling the sale of live stock to foreigners, seems to have furnished an excuse foe one Yarabu, a Galla Chief, to incite his people to open rebellion, which has since been suppressed and Yarabu himself made prisoner at Harrar, but unfortunately he has escaped.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Well the chief trade of those people down there, is in horses donkeys, camels and food animals of which foreigners are the best buyers, are they not?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Well!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Begging your pardon in advance, but isn't the law that brought about this outbreak, a little unjust?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>It is not for you to judge whether the laws of Janhoi be just or unjust.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Admitted my dear Uncle, but we whose proudest boast is that our institution have remained unchanged since the days of her Imperial Highness, the Queen of Sheba, are many centuries behind the civilization of the present age and stringent laws aimed at foreigners, has had much to do with our present condition.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>You went to Europe to learn the art of war, you return to teach the science of Government. The future welfare of Abyssinia demands that we place a check on the aggressive Policy of all Nations. Stringent Laws for the Government of our own people, should in no wise offend foreigners.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>I bow to your superior judgement in matter of state, but what of this fellow, Yarabu?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>If captured he must be returned to Harrar, unless Janhoi orders otherwise</p>
<stage>(Turning to servant who is asleep)</stage>
<p>Zamish here!</p>
<stage>(Goes over and kicks Zamish who is frightened by kick)</stage>
<p>Give me the proclamation from Harrar.</p>
<stage>(Zamish gives scroll of paper to Tegulet who passes the same to Bolassa)</stage>
<p>You will find here a description of Yarabu, read it at your leisure. In the mean time, I have decided to have you meet and conduct into the Capitol, a Caravan of strangers from America. You will very likely find them at Borema Springs, take a small escort, say about four and start at noon. I shall accompany you.</p></sp>

<stage>(A shot is fired by guard. Bus.)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>What's the trouble, Oureeka?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>OUREEKA</speaker>
<p>A lion Shambul, a lion.</p> 
<stage>(Excitedly)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Semra hand me your gun quick.</p>
<stage>(Bus. for lion soldiers, three or four leave guard house, cross stage and creep up path toward lion, guns in hand. Bolassa at cue fires, lion falls over cliff, soldiers run to spot where lion falls, looks down make picture, backs to audience.)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>The King of the forest has ventured on Hostile Territory and has been completely vanquished it is thus that Abyssinia should deal with aggression, whether of man or beast.</p></sp>

<stage>(CURTAIN.)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 2</head>

<stage>Time: Tuesday, 4 P.M.<lb/>
Place: Plains near Borema Springs</stage>

<stage>In the prospective Spinx, etc. a scanty bit of vegetarian. Near an oasis Caravan in motion, noise incidental to travel: "Whoa!" "get up!" "get out of the road!" etc. At rise of curtain, caravan halts.</stage>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Whoa! Whoa! stop, I tell you! Your ears must be full of sand if you can't hear me when I tell you to stop.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<p>What in the world's the matter now, Aunt Cally?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>I've been tellin' that fool mule for the last five minutes that something about this saddle is busted and I wanted to get down and fix it, and he paid just as much attention to me as the backsliders that sets in the front row of Mount Zion Baptist Church pays to Hezekiah Tompkins when he's preaching against wearing of fine raiments and puttin' on airs, when the presidin' elder of the church ain't had a collection the entire summer, big enough to pay for a watermelon.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Madam, if you will allow me, I will assist you to Terra-firma----</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>You'll 'sist me to what?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>To the ground, to solid earth to Terra-firma.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Terrible Firmness is a might poor name for all this sand and rocks we've been ploughin' through for the last two weeks but don't stand there lookin' like the last rose of summer, jes 'sist me down and let me straighten out my avoirdupois.</p></sp>

<stage>(Preacher assists Mammy to alight and fixes saddle)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(at the top of her voice)</stage>
<p>If anyone has no objections, and I hope they haven't, will someone kindly, I say kindly tell me why we are fritting away our time and ruining our complexions in this sislying atmosphere, when my Syce informs me we go into camp two hours hence.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Just you tell Mr. Sizer--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>I said my Syce I mean the boy that takes care of my mule.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Well then tell your Souse, or whatever he is, that the waist band on my mule is busted and we're waitin' for repairs</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Well I shan't wait here any longer, I am going to catch up with those that have gone ahead, in the meantime, you can do the same that is, if that poor little worn out beast can carry you fast enough. Get up!</p>
<stage>(Looks back, calls loudly: "Serena!")</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<stage>(Submissively)</stage>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<stage>(Miss Primly exits, with Aunt Cally staring after her, hands on hips)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Coughs to attract Mammy's attention)</stage>
<p>Madam, shall we proceed?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Indignantly coming down stage and going back to look after vanishing eccentric lady)</stage>
<p>Did you hear--</p>
<stage>(Goes back up stage and returns, swallows before speaking with emphasis)</stage>
<p>that mutton face Hussy. Did you hear her?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>I regret to say that I did hear the remark made by the lady whose face so muck reminds you of a sheep, and--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Shut up!</p>
<stage>(With angry emphasis)</stage> 
<stage>(Exit Aunt Cally and Elder Fowler. Enter several girls riding donkeys, laughing and chattering)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>DALPHNE</speaker>
<p>I say girls, I don't think we ought to stay so far behind the rest.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>NETTIE</speaker>
<p>Well the only way to make this donkey hurry, is to put a sack of oats on a stick and hold it in front of his nose.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>I haven't got any oats, but I've got a cheese sandwich in my pocket whose got a stick?</p></sp>

<stage>(Girls all talking at once and laughing exit)</stage> 

<stage>(Music Entrance of Ras and Jas, Ras riding mule led by servant followed by Jas. Both have rifles)</stage>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Signals to Ras with auto fog horn. Ras stops and looks back)</stage>
<p>That's your cue to dismount and perform the duties of rear guard of this Cavalcade.</p></sp>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 3</head>

<stage>Time: Tuesday Sunset.<lb/>
Borema Springs.</stage> 

<stage>Camp tents spread in grove of palms. Moonlight effect. Servants kneeling. Rest of Caravan grouped up stage. Chorus singing "Ode to the Sun" at rise of curtain.</stage>

<stage>"ODE TO THE SUN"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Then the sun in regal splendour glides the hill tops to the West,</l> 
<l>And the Oriental day of work is done,</l>
<l>We chosen of Mohammed bow to Allah Ever Blest,</l>
<l>Whose glory is reflected by the sun.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHANT</l>
<l>Oh, setting sun desert thy chosen never.</l>
<l>Oh, Wondrous One Thy glory lives forever.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Hail to the Sun with praises never ending.</l> 
<l>Hail to the Sun while planets are ascending.</l> 
<l>Beam Thou on us Oh, Sun of joy and sorrow,</l> 
<l>We say farewell to greet Thee on the morrow.</l>
</lg>

<p>2.</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>When the minarets of Mecca silhouette against the sky</l> 
<l>And the deserts mark the shadow of the palm,</l>
<l>We chosen of Mohammad bow to the great Solar Eye</l> 
<l>While realms of Islam slumber in the calm.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHANT</l>
<l>Oh, Sun of Men the night has sounded warning.</l> 
<l>But come again when dawn awakes the morning.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(At finish of chorus, enter from L.2.E. Miss Primly. Chorus retires up stage.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(To Serena who is kneeling)</stage>
<p>Get up from there! Is there any way in this world I'll ever be able to keep you looking respectable? Down on your knees singing with these heathens.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<stage>(Still kneeling, looks up with serious expression)</stage>
<p>I wasn't singing, I lost the buckle of my belt and I was looking---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(interrupting, snatches Serena to her feet)</stage>
<p>Tie your belt with a rope. You don't need a buckle on your belt to be in style out here in this wilderness</p> 
<stage>(Serena starts to protest)</stage>
<p>Shut up! How dare you talk back to me! Didn't I tell you about talking back to me?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<stage>(Submissively)</stage>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Don't I do everything in the world to make you happy?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Haven't I sat all day cutting down my hats, feathers, dresses and shoes for you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>And do you think if you wasn't my niece I'd do anything at all for you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<stage>(As if about to cry)</stage>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Can't you say anything but "Yes Mam"</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<stage>(Wiping her eyes)</stage>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(Disgusted, catches hold of Serena by arm and shakes her)</stage>
<p>Get out of my sight before I lose my temper.</p>
<stage>(Turns as if to start away)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker>
<p>Yes Mam.</p>
<stage>(Miss Primly looks amazed. Turns again and is confronted by Elder Fowler)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Miss Primly, if you don't mind, would you sew a button--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting indignantly)</stage>
<p>No Sir!</p>
<stage>(Starts to exit in direction taken by Serena. Bumps into Aunt Cally who drops cup and saucer she is carrying)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Excuse me</p>
<stage>(With head high staring straight ahead exits)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Gasping for breath)</stage>
<p>If I didn't want to lose my religion I'd say something----</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>A soft answer turneth away wrath.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>And a soft head gives advice where it ain't wanted.</p></sp>

<stage>(Elder Fowler raises hands deprecatorially, then places them together as if in silent prayer and exits)</stage>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>I don't know as I ought to said that to Elder Fowler, but he's the most aggravanist man this side of Kingdom Come.</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter Chinaman L.2.E. singing softly, carrying tea-pot, passes in front of Aunt Cally who stares at Chinaman)</stage>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>A penny for your thoughts, Aunt Cally.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>I was just thinking what in the name of goodness was keeping them boys, Rastus and Jasamine and whether they was lost or not</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>Don't bother about them, they'll be along presently.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>You know honey, I'm mighty superstitious.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>Superstitious?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Yes, I always did b'lieve in signs. When I was home and a cat crossed my path something always happened. Well, that Chinaman is just like a cat. He's always slippin' and slidin' and you never kin hear him and every time he's passed in front of me yet, something happened.</p>
<stage>(Indicating with hand pointing toward Wong Foo)</stage>
<p>And he's just passed.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>There's nothing wrong with Wong Foo, he's real clever. I've been teaching him how to sing native American
songs.</p>
<stage>(Calls Wong Foo)</stage>
<p>Come here, Wong.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<stage>(With tea-pot in hand)</stage>
<p>Washa malla?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>Aunt Cally wants you to---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>There ain't nothin' I want him to do but stay as far as possible from me, if he don't----</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Wait a minute Aunt Cally.</p>
<stage>(Calling to Mandy)</stage>
<p>Bring Aunt Cally something to sit on.</p>
<stage>(Mandy brings a dress suit case. Aunt Cally is seated on end of dress suit case by Lucinda)</stage> 
<p>You be the audience and listen to the concert.</p>
<stage>(Addressing Aunt Cally)</stage>
<p>Mrs Audience, allow me to introduce the singing marvel of the 20th Century, Mr Wong Foo.</p> 
<stage>(Addressing Wong Foo)</stage>
<p>Didn't I tell you, you must always bow to your audience?</p>
<stage>(Wong Foo bows to Aunt Cally, who nearly falls from seat)</stage>
<p>Now sing after me</p></sp>

<stage>(Sing chorus of any popular song, line at a time, each line repeated in turn by Wong Foo. When Wong Foo is through, Aunt Cally applauds violently. Seat is turned over and Aunt Cally is caught in arms of Elder Fowler who enters back of Aunt Cally just as Wong Foo finishes. Chinaman busy at tripod with tea-pot while water is heating, smokes Chinese pipe.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>(Resting in Elder Fowler's arms, looks up, closes her eyes, opens them again and sighs)
Oh! it's you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Helps Aunt Cally to her seat, who as soon as she gains her equilibrium, rises)</stage>
<p>I come along just in time.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>I don't know what I'd do without you, Elder Fowler, you certainly was a ministering angel at that minute.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>I am always glad to be of service to you, Mrs Parker</p>
<stage>(Bows profoundly, removes dress suit case. Aunt Cally bows as Elder turns toward her. Elder bows again)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>You know Elder, last night after I said my prayers and laid down, I was thinking---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting, looking in Aunt Cally's eyes)</stage> 
<p>Yes!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Whose head is turned slightly away when Elder Fowler interrupts, turns quickly toward the Elder and looks at him suspiciously)</stage>
<p>I said last night after I said my prayers and laid down, I was thinking----</p> 
<stage>(Eyes Elder intently)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Yes Mrs. Parker, you said you was thinking---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Decidedly--)</stage>
<p>Yes, that's what I said, I was thinking-</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Demurely)</stage>
<p>Thinking of what, Mrs Parker?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Thinking I was the biggest fool that ever left Kansas and if it wasn't that Ras promised me I'd see Jerusalem 'fore I got back so I'd have plenty to talk about next winter, I wouldn't come, in the first place and 'twixt you and me and the gate post, I wish I was right back where I come from-either there or down in Dixie where I was born.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>You are from the South, then?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Sarcastically)</stage>
<p>Yes from the South where all the rest of you come from 'riginally</p>
<stage>(With hands on hips)</stage>
<p>I'm from Ware County, Georgia, just a few miles from Way Cross, the biggest town in the County and I wish I was there to-night.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>You are suffering from Nostalgia.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>I ain't suffering from nothin', much less the disease you're talkin' about, Elder Fowler.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>I mean you're home sick.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Well why didn't you say that at first? Yes I'm home-sick. I'm just naturally chuck full of memories of the South.</p></sp>

<stage>"WHERE MY FORE-FATHERS DIED"</stage> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>My thoughts are over yonder in old Dixie cross the sea,</l>
<l>I can see all of my old friends watching there to welcome me.</l>
<l>I can see their faces glowing as they each one clasp my hand,</l> 
<l>With that firmness that's so hard to find outside of Dixie land</l>
<l>I am home sick, oh so home sick and the folks at home all know, </l>
<l>That fond mem'rys of the South land beckons me so I must go.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>I can see the old log cabin where the honey-suckles twine</l>
<l>I hear the mocking-birds sweet note I smell the jasmine,</l> 
<l>The picture thrills me thro' and thro' and often times I sigh,</l> 
<l>For Dixie land that good old land where my fore-fathers died.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>I have traveled most all over, been in almost ev'ry clime,</l>
<l>And most ev'ry place it seems like it stays winter all the time,</l>
<l>Then the flowers they don't bloom the same, the sunshine's not as bright</l> 
<l>The moon it seems dissatisfied, the stars they don't shine right</l>
<l>I am tired out with strangers where you look for smiles in vain,</l>
<l>I am longing for old Dixie, yes I want the South again.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(After song is finished, exit Aunt Cally. Enter Oscar calling loudly to attract attention of Elder Fowler who is apparently some distance away. Oscar stutters)</stage>

<sp><speaker>OSCAR</speaker>
<p>Elder Fowler!</p>
<stage>(Prolong)</stage>
<p>Elder Fowler!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Enters hurriedly)</stage>
<p>What's the trouble, Oscar?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>OSCAR</speaker>
<stage>(Stuttering)</stage>
<p>The-the-thebag-ba-ba-bag-bag-baggage man wa-wa-wants yo-yo-you.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Oh! the Bijirondi wants me.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>OSCAR</speaker>
<p>Ye-ye-yes the Bi-bi-bi-bi- </p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker> 
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Never mind saying it twice, I understand.</p></sp>

<stage>(Both hands in front of Oscar's face as if to stop him from speaking, then hurriedly exit in search of Bijirondi L.2.E. Miss Primly calls off stage)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Wong Foo! Wong Foo!</p>
<stage>(Enters seeing Wong Foo exclaims)</stage>
<p>Oh! there you are and as usual taking things easy</p>
<stage>(Crosses over to Wong Foo who is sitting, nodding with pipe in mouth)</stage>
<p>Bless my soul, I believe he's asleep</p>
<stage>(Shakes Wong, who drops pipe, jumps to his feet startled)</stage>
<p>Wake un here, didn't I send you for this tea an hour ago?</p> 
<stage>(Bus. for Wong - Miss Primly dragging him along)</stage>
<p>I'll show you how to keep me waiting, be careful don't spill that tea on me</p></sp>

<stage>(Lets go of Wong who exits running, followed by Miss Primly still talking. Enters Sam, Jim, George, John and Frank in time to see exit of Miss Primly and Wong. All laughing, enter R.3.E.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>SAM</speaker>
<p>What's the matter with Miss Primly?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JOHN, JIM, FRANK &amp; GEORGE</speaker> 
<stage>(Altogether)</stage>
<p>She's alright.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>FRANK</speaker>
<p>I say fellows, I don't feel altogether right about Ras and Jas they should have put in an appearance long ago.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
<p>This isn't the first time we've went into camp without them, they'll pull up alright.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JOHN</speaker>
<p>Yes, they'll never get lost as long as Aunt Cally's voice is left to stir the breeze, that is if they are anywhere within the ten mile limit.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JIM</speaker>
<stage>(Laughing)</stage>
<p>You'd better not let her hear that last remark,</p> 
<stage>(Stops suddenly)</stage>
<p>by jove I've an idea.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JOHN</speaker>
<p>Anything to break the monotony, what is it?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JIM</speaker>
<p>We'll serenade the camp, but we'll stand over here by Aunt Cally' Cally's tent and if she comes out and puts up her usual kick about the noise we're making, we'll jolly her by telling her we were trying to remind her of the happy days of her youth when she used to listen to ye olden songs in "Twilight at Home Sweet Home"</p></sp>

<stage>"TWILIGHT AT HOME SWEET HOME"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Now is the hour when from the wood, the nightingale's sweet song is heard</l> 
<l>Now is the hour when the lover fond and good is breathing love in ev'ry</l> 
<l>There is no other time either day or night,</l>
<stage>(whispered word)</stage>
<l>When anything seems just the same as at twilight.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Dreaming in twilight at home sweet home,</l>
<l>Dreaming of wondrous things that are to come,</l> 
<l>To-night we live on Venus and the next on Saturn roam</l> 
<l>We then visit Mars and a thousand more stars</l>
<l>In twilight at home sweet home.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Sweet scented winds and waters clear, they whisper sweet songs in your car</l> 
<l>Now is the hour after sunset in the west when Nature lulls her family to</l> 
<l>List' to the crickets song see the glow worm's light</l>
<stage>(rest)</stage>
<l>There's no thoughts like the ones that come just at twilight.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(Tents are made transparent in this scene, showing occupants in different attitudes, such as writing letters, reading books by spirit lamps &amp; etc. At finish of song, enter Elder Fowler and several servants)</stage>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker> 
<stage>(To singers)</stage>
<p>Boys I'm sorry, but you'll have to help me notify every body, that the camp will have to be moved up in the hills yonder</p>
<stage>(Pointing off L.3.E.)</stage> 
<p>The Bijirondi here</p> 
<stage>(Indicating Attara)</stage>
<p>claims that a severe storm is rapidly approaching and it would be much safer in the hills, as a number of caves up there will afford ample protection from the weather. No one has retired for the evening as yet I judge, and as it's only about twenty minutes distance, we'll walk and--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting, pokes head out of tent, white rag around head)</stage>
<p>You mean you and the rest of them will walk, but if I've got to move this evening, you'll furnish me with the necessary means of locomotion</p>
<stage>(Shuts flap of tent violently)</stage></sp> 

<stage>(Several girls enter during confusion incidental to taking down tents.)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>DALPHNE</speaker>
<p>What's the matter, Elder Fowler?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>NETTIE</speaker>
<p>Will I have to walk, Uncle Rube?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>LUCINDA</speaker>
<p>Why can't we ride, I don't see any reason---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Every body is going to walk---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Enters from tent, interrupting)</stage>
<p>Make exceptions, Rube Fowler, make exceptions, where is my souce?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<stage>(Calls to servant)</stage>
<p>Here boy, show Mrs Parker to her mule.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>HASID</speaker>
<stage>(Pointing off stage)</stage>
<p>Over here.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Elder Fowler, would you 'blige me by 'sisting me to the where-bouts of that mule?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>Just a minute Mrs Parker,</p>
<stage>(Calls to Wong Foo who enters L.3.)</stage>
<p>Stay here and wait until Ras and Jas comes along. Keep one mule for their traps. We're going to camp in the caves</p>
<stage>(Pointing off L.3.E.)</stage>
<p>up in those hills beyond. Keep a sharp lookout for them understand---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>And if they don' show up inside of one hour, you notify me 'cause I'm coming back to look for them at the end of that time.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker> 
<p>This way Mrs Parker.</p></sp>

<stage>(Exit all except Wong and mule. Bus. for Wong with mule. Wind begins to blow slightly. After noise of Caravan dies away, enter Tegulet Bolasso, four soldiers in front. Wong frightened on seeing soldiers, attempts to escape, but is caught by two soldiers, one soldier holds Wong's mule)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(Examines Wong then turns to Tegulet with nod of head toward Wong)</stage>
<p>Chinaman?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Ask him what he is doing here.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Are you traveling alone, of not where are the rest of your friends</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<p>Me wait for Melican man Ras, Melican man Jas.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Oh!</p>
<stage>(Turning to Tegulet)</stage>
<p>He's a part of the Caravan from America</p>
<stage>(To Wong)</stage>
<p>Where is the rest of your party?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<p>Pleacher man say up hill, caves letter place.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>What part of America does this strange tribe inhabit?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>They are not natives of America, but many thousands have migrated there. I understand him to say they have camped in the hills yonder</p>
<stage>(Points in direction taken by Caravan)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<stage>(Looking up)</stage>
<p>We must hurry on to the camp before the storm breaks</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERMA</speaker>
<p>What shall we do with this fellow?</p>
<stage>(Meaning Wong)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Release him and follow the trail to the hills beyond.</p>
<stage>(Wong uneasily watches exit of Tegulet, Bolassa and soldiers, Togulet and Bolassa talking as they exit)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Has that strange type of Humanity, invaded the European Countries</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(Laughing)</stage>
<p>You'll find a few anywhere and everywhere</p></sp>

<stage>(Conversation interrupted by music for entrance of Ras and Jas. Ras calls)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Loudly)</stage>
<p>Wong!</p></sp>

<stage>(Wong is startled. Ras by pointing attracts Jas's attention to Wong. Jas enters eating crackers, chicken, in hand, gun under arm)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(To Wong)</stage>
<p>Where is the camp?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<p>Camp moved up on hill Saba</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Oh! they left you to show us the way?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<p>Yes, me show Saba.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(To Jas)</stage>
<p>How many of these crackers have you eaten?</p>
<stage>(Jas holds up three fingers and continues eating crackers)</stage>
<p>Remember if you eat ten of those crackers in ten minutes, you are to get Ten Dollars for each cracker, on condition you don't drink any kind of fluid.</p>
<stage>(Jas nods and holds up four fingers and continues eating crackers. The wind at this point gets stronger, clouds begin rolling, storm of locusts pass. Bus. for Ras and Jas. Ras looking up then to Jas)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(To Jas)</stage>
<p>I guess we'd better move along Jas before this storm catches us.</p> 
<stage>(Jas holds up five fingers, continues eating, but looks up uneasily)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(To Wong)</stage>
<p>Why did they leave one mule instead of two?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>WONG FOO</speaker>
<p>You no ride mule, mule carry plaps.</p></sp>

<stage>(Thunder and lightning storm grows)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I understand, they left the mule to carry our traps.</p>
<stage>(Gives his gun to Wong, then to Jas)</stage>
<p>Let me have your gun.</p></sp>

<stage>(Jas releases gun. Ras starts to take chicken. Jas turns away and holds up first five, then one finger, indicating that he has eaten six crackers. Storm becomes vicious. Storm music here. Jas fills mouth rapidly and motions for Ras to depart. Loud peal of thunder followed by lightning. Jas now thoroughly frightened, allows crackers to drop from mouth. Lightning strikes tree, splitting same. Ras and Jas both try to mount mule. Wong exits hurriedly. Mule stubborn. Storm at height of fury. Jas pushing Ras pulling mule. EXIT)</stage> 

<stage>(CURTAIN)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 4</head>

<stage>TIME: Wednesday.</stage>

<stage>(Market place just outside the City walls at Addis Ababa. Enter chorus with wares which they place in booths after finish of chorus.)</stage>

<p>CHORUS</p>

<stage>"THIS IS OUR HOLIDAY"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>The hour is nearing Es-she-Es-she,</l>
<l>'Tis time for cheering Es-she-Es-she</l>
<l>And at this hour we will devour pleasure most greedily.</l> 
<l>Bright shines the glorious sun on this our holiday</l>
<l>May he with fortune smile when we our wares display</l>
<l>All hail the hour when we will devour pleasure most greedily</l> 
<l>All hail the hour, pleasure devour on this our holiday.</l>
</lg>

<stage>"SILKS AND LINEN LACES"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Fine silks and linen laces, ribbons and pretty faces,</l> 
<l>We come to offer you our wares</l>
<l>We come each holiday, feeling the self same way</l> 
<l>We're bright and have no cares</l>
<l>Bright joyous happy faces</l>
<l>Fine silks and linen laces</l>
<l>Come now, won't you buy our wares</l>
<l>You buy some silk and you buy some laces,</l> 
<l>You buy a kiss from some pretty faces,</l> 
<l>Come now and buy our wares</l>
</lg>

<stage>"SWEETS"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Sweets, sweets, sweets sweets,</l>
<l>Come have a try at our dainty sweet meats</l>
<l>They are delicious and lumps of delight,</l>
<l>Just try them and you'll find that they're quite alright,</l> 
<l>For they're sweets, sweets, sweets, sweets,</l>
<l>Come have a try at our dainty sweet meats</l>
<l>If you'll try them to-day, you'll have little to pay</l>
<l>For our sweets, for our sweets, sweets, sweets.</l>
</lg>

<stage>"DONKEY"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Come take a ride on a donkey,</l>
<l>You'll surely think it's nice</l>
<l>You simply hold on like a monkey</l>
<l>And we're sure that you won't mind the price</l> 
<l>Just take a ride on a donkey</l>
<l>The many sights to see</l>
<l>Take advice for it's nice</l>
<l>Try it twice pay the price,</l>
<l>For a ride, for a ride on a donkey.</l>
</lg>

<stage>"TEJ"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Tej, Tej sparkling exhilirating soothing and ennervating,</l> 
<l>Tej, Tej everyone drinks Tej</l>
<l>If you should a gallon take you won't have a bad headache</l> 
<l>That's Tej ---Cheers ------That's Tej.</l>
</lg>

<stage>"FLOWERS"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Lily fair of golden hue, sparkling still with silvry dew,</l> 
<l>She smiles and throws a kiss to you,</l>
<l>Beware she smiles for other too.</l>
<l>The flowers that bloom as dawn awakes,</l>
<l>Then fade and die as night o'er takes,</l>
<l>Are but as hearts that live and break</l>
<l>And sob and die for loves own sake.</l>
<l>Achillea grand and strong now must sing to you her song,</l> 
<l>She sings of heroes, what they've done,</l>
<l>Sings of victories lost and won</l> 
<l>Sings if new worlds just begun</l> 
<l>Sings all the whole day long.</l>
</lg>

<stage>"FINALE TO ENTIRE OPENING CHORUS"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>We have flowers to please the eye,</l> 
<l>Silks and ribbons to beautify</l> 
<l>Things to drink and things to eat</l> 
<l>Souvenirs that are a treat,</l>
<l>Woven goods of ev'ry shade</l>
<l>From sea-green to marmalade,</l>
<l>Bluchers with tassels for little boys</l>
<l>Tigers and other jungle toys,</l>
<l>Ear-rings, anklets bracelets and bangles,</l> 
<l>Pendants, neck ware head gear and spangles</l> 
<l>Anything that heart could wish</l>
<l>From elephant straight down to fish</l>
<l>We're gay and glad joyous and merry,</l>
<l>We're happy and bright youthful and cheery.</l>
<l>Bluchers with tassels for little boys,</l> 
<l>Tigers and other jungle toys,</l>
<l>We're gay and glad joyous and merry</l> 
<l>Woven goods of every shade,</l>
<l>From sea-green to marmalade,</l> 
<l>We're gay and glad and merry</l> 
<l>We're happy and bright and cheery</l> 
<l>Lily fair of golden hue.</l>
<l>Come take a ride on a donkey.</l> 
<l>Sing a long of the flowers.</l> 
<l>Happy merry joyous hours.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(SING)</stage>

<p>(At finish of chorus, enter Bolassa. Girls gather around Bolassa. Girls soliciting patronage for wares, all talking at once)</p>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Wait a minute girls, allow me first to congratulate you, Your fresh young voices are excelled only by your exceeding good looks</p>
<stage>(Bows)</stage>
<p>I hardly expected such a welcome, allow me to thank you again and again, your singing---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VARINOE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>But we were not singing for you, Shambal Bolasso you know when Miram is around you are not so free with your compliments.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>I don't have the opportunity, Miram does all the talking</p>
<stage>(Girls laugh. Girl nearest Varinoe pushes her good naturedly. Varinoe shakes her head defiantly, all retire to booth. Enter Tegulet calls to Bolasso.)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Bolasso!</p>
<stage>(Bolasso turns quickly, goes to meet Tegulet)</stage>
<p>report to Jan Hoi the arrival of the American Caravan, in the mean time I shall make inquiry concerning the man Yaraboo.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(To soldier)</stage>
<p>Serma!</p></sp>

<stage>(Serma turns and salutes)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Leave your escort, you'll no doubt find them where they are at present, when you return</p></sp>

<stage>(Exit Tegulet and Bolasso. Girls make grimaces, then laughing come to center of stage. Four soldiers group up stage)</stage>

<sp><speaker>ULISSA</speaker>
<stage>(Mischievously)</stage>
<p>Hasn't the Affa Negus Tegulet a lovely disposition?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ALLAMO</speaker>
<p>He seems to forget he was once young.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ULISSA</speaker>
<p>Yes but that was long, long ago, how could you expect him to remember it.</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter Miram, singing lively melody, French preferred. Finish same in center stage, then archly looks at her companions and laughs merrily)</stage>

<sp><speaker>ALLAMO</speaker>
<p>Miram is very happy to-day.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Why shouldn't I be happy</p>
<stage>(Quickly)</stage>
<p>I've been to the American Camp and sold out.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS GIRLS</speaker>
<p>Sold out!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<stage>(Talking rapidly)</stage>
<p>Yes and I gave them some lovely bargains too, every body wanted a souvenir and they got them, listen</p>
<stage>(all gather around)</stage>
<p>A string of beads worth four Piastres in the market here, I sold for twelve</p>
<stage>(Girls Exclaim)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>GIRLS</speaker>
<p>What!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Yes and a pair of bracelets worth three salts, I sold for a very fat woman who couldn't wear them, for Two Dollars and added a couple of Piastres, just to make her believe she had a bargain, wasn't I generous?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ULISSA</speaker>
<stage>(With mock concern)</stage>
<p>You'll be arrested for high-way robbery.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Not much, I've set the price for the market to-day and you must follow suit. At least add 75 to your price, they're so generous they won't mind, and another thing girls, they have a Ras with them and another gentleman with the title of Jas</p>
<stage>(Confidentially)</stage>
<p>and I've heard some awful queer things about them.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VARINOE</speaker>
<stage>(Sarcastically)</stage>
<p>Do they eat little girls?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Not when they are as old and tough as you are.</p> 
<stage>(Girls laugh. Varinoe with angry toss of head exits)</stage>
<p>As I was about to say, one of the guides who understands them thoroughly, told me the following things about the American women. Those that nature has seen fit to make fat, go days at a time without food and allow themselves to be fastened in cages over tanks of hot water, in order to melt the fat, so that they can become thin, and the thin ones stay in bed and eat oats, the same kind of oats horses eat, also some strange kind of nuts made of grapes. Along with this, they are ordered by their medicine man to laugh so that they may grow fat, fancy this? After they reach the age of twenty-five years, they don't have any more birth-days for three years, and then they are only twenty-six years old, and when by this process, twenty-eight years have been reached, no more birth-days are celebrated, isn't funny?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<stage>(With bated breath)</stage>
<p>And the men?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Well to give you an idea; men with an income of Ten thousand a year are always in debt and in consequence, lead miserable lives, while others raise a family of ten children on Ten Dollars a week and are happy. I must go now and get a fresh supply of goods.</p>
<stage>(Starts to exit, discovers Ras approaching from R.3.E)</stage> 
<p>A busy day is in front of you girls,</p>
<stage>(Points to R.3.E)</stage>
<p>here comes the Ras</p></sp>

<stage>(Cue for song)</stage>

<stage>(Enter Ras. Bus. for Ras spending and giving money)</stage> 

<stage>"RASTUS JOHNSON U.S.A."</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>I won some coin some time ago in the Louisiana Lottery,</l>
<l>I bought five hundred suits of clothes and went the world to see</l>
<l>The first place that I landed on was London o'er the way,</l>
<l>Where I changed my clothes so much they called me lightning Rastus J.</l> 
<l>But the thing that worried the people was my Nationality</l>
<l>So I wrote these lines to sing to them when they would question me.</l> 
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>I'm just plain Rastus Johnson from U.S.A.</l>
<l>I'm traveling 'round to see the sights and throw some coin away,</l>
<l>I don't know my ancestry, I'se just born down in Tennessee,</l>
<l>Thank you, just Rastus Johnson from U.S.A.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>From London I just thought I'd take a run to dear old Paris gay,</l> 
<l>To buy more wine and see more sights and throw more coin away</l> 
<l>But to tell you all the truth folks, Paris ain't no hit with me,</l> 
<l>'Cause all you get on every hand's "Wee-wee, Monseur, wee-wee"</l> 
<l>A man once said to me says he you'se Coon African</l>
<l>I fairly screamed, screamed I no sir I'll have you understand.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>I'm just plain Rastus Johnson from U.S.A</l>
<l>Now I think sir that you are simply poking fun at me,</l>
<l>To add insult to injury, the man just grinned and said "Wee-wee"</l> 
<l>Assault and Batt'ry Rastus Johnson U.S.A.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(After song, exit. Enter Jas, preceded by two servants carrying extra large dress suit case about seven feet long (Practical) with clock spring in lock with alarm to be set, going when key is inserted in lock. Jas, after examination of his clothes, takes whist broom from pocket, carefully brushes himself, motions for servant to place case in position to be opened, inserts key after alarm has finished, opens case, removes cuffs and collars, puts same inside of case, takes out clean linen, causes case to be set on end so as to form screen, goes behind screen, hangs prop coat, suspenders and other wearing apparel on top of case, servants close case. Jas notices in direction of gates, servants exit with case, followed through gates by Jas who assumes a walk indicating importance, introductory music of the song "Don't" is played here. Enter Miss Primly who finds Serena at booth apparently purchasing goods during soft vamp from orchestra, Miss Primly carrying satchel full of pamphlets.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker> 
<stage>(Loudly)</stage>
<p>Serena!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERENA</speaker> 
<stage>(Turning)</stage>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(Grimaces)</stage>
<p>How do you ever expect me-</p>
<stage>(Stops short)</stage>
<p>Never mind</p>
<stage>(Calls boy)</stage>
<p>You'll do</p>
<stage>(Opens satchel, takes out pamphlets, piles same in arm of boy during operation, talks as follows)</stage> 
<p>I never saw anything like it in my life, of course if I talked until I dropped dead &amp; etc.</p>
<stage>(When enough pamphlets have been given boy)</stage>
<p>These pamphlets will teach these poor benighted people the value of the little word "Don't", distribute them, please.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>THE BOY</speaker>
<p>Yes Mam.</p></sp>

<stage>(Miss Primly grimaces then commences the song "Don't")</stage>

<stage>"DON'T"</stage> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>There's large microbes in everything so all the Doctors say,</l>
<l>They warn you of the fact in all the papers ev'ry day,</l>
<l>Now I am glad that I at least have some mind of my own,</l>
<l>Or else they'd have me leaving almost everything alone.</l>
</lg> 

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Don't eat, that is the main thing they advise you not to do</l>
<l>Don't drink, not even water is the next thing they hand to you</l> 
<l>Don't kiss beware and if you're asked be sure to say "I won't"</l> 
<l>They say there's eighty-thousand microbes on each kiss so don't</l> 
<l>Advice is cheap I've always heard and I believe it's true,</l>
<l>Advice that folks can't use themselves they always give to you</l> 
<l>Now here's some that's no good to me which you are welcome to</l> 
<l>Some very good household advice on things you should not do.</l> 
<l>Don't keep your milk too near the ice in August it will spoil,</l> 
<l>Don't worry about moths just get a tub of fresh coal oil</l>
<l>And pour it on the dry goods where the moths all congregate</l> 
<l>And to this add a lighted match then go somewhere and wait.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Now when it comes to Christmas time you need lots of advice</l>
<l>And possibly some other things and many need the price,</l>
<l>Don't worry with your dinner the things you're going to eat,</l>
<l>Eat you dinner at some friends house, they will think it quite a treat</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Don't worry the poor children with the Christmas tales of yore,</l> 
<l>Don't tell them what you never had they've heard all that before,</l> 
<l>What is the good in grumbling on our merry Christmas day,</l> 
<l>Tho' it kills you, smile with everything you have to give away.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Now here's a few exclusive don'ts concerning peoples health,</l> 
<l>They're just as good for poor folks as they are for folks of wealth</l> 
<l>Don't lose your temper quickly it will make digestion bad,</l>
<l>If accidents should happen take it easy, don't get mad</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Don't make a lot of fuss if someone steps upon your corns</l>
<l>Don't think mean things and wish the stepper never had been borne</l> 
<l>If someones umbrella end should stick into your eye,</l>
<l>Don't scream and carry on, just go and get another eye.</l> 
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Here's some superstitions don'ts they need a little pluck,</l>
<l>You've simply got to follow them, they'll bring all kinds of luck</l> 
<l>If your rabbit foot don't work well don't be a bit output,</l>
<l>All in the world you've got to do is get a big pig foot.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Don't show your lucky pig foot, keep it hid that's what I mean,</l> 
<l>Don't look at it in day time what you need's a moon light scene</l> 
<l>Then find a spot and bury it and tho' this way sound strange</l>
<l>If you sit on that spot three months your luck is bound to change</l>
</lg>

<stage>(At finish of song, Miss Primly exits through gate. Enter Elder Fowler and Aunt Cally, stops long enough to deliver the following)</stage>

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Well this takes the biscuit. At home they lock up houses, they lock up stables and they lock up chicken-coops, but this is the first time I ever saw people lock up a whole town.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ELDER FOWLER</speaker>
<p>The gates are open, so I judge there'll be no objections to our entering the City</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>AUNT CALLY</speaker>
<p>Follow me, we'll enter alright.</p></sp>

<stage>(Elder Fowler and Aunt Cally start to exit. Aunt Cally bumps into Miram who is entering from gates. Aunt Cally looks scornfully at Miram. Exit through gate Miram, staring after Aunt Cally. Enter Jas, who almost runs over Miram, stopping on tip-toe to avoid contact with hat in hand)</stage>

<sp><speaker>ULISSA</speaker>
<p>Is that the other titled gentleman?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>That is it.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ULISSA</speaker>
<p>He seems very anxious to win your love.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Or else, as in the story of the monkey and the lion "Die Trying"</p></sp>

<stage>"DIE TRYING"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Once on a time a monkey man loved a little monkey maid,</l>
<l>And ev'ry night in her father's tree they'd spoon so people said</l>
<l>Things went on well 'till a Lion bad caught the monkey man one day</l> 
<l>And took him to a dark, dark cave and hid him safe away,</l>
<l>Then the Lion swore to the monkey maid that his love would never die</l> 
<l>And she poor foolish maid just blushed and then said with a sigh.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>I must say that I can't see, how on earth you could come to me</l> 
<l>And mean it when you say you're love's undying.</l>
<l>Still if you say that you'll be true, what is a poor little monk to do</l> 
<l>But to win your love or else to die a trying.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>The lion wed the monkey maid then he took her far away,</l>
<l>And made her work all the time and then would beat her ev'ry day</l> 
<l>She waited long 'till at last one night Mister Lion came home drunk,</l> 
<l>She left him and heart broken she went back to find her monk,</l>
<l>The legend says she found him, swore her love would never die,</l>
<l>If he would take her back, then he said with a happy sigh.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(After song "Die Tryin'," exit Miram and girls working in song. Enter from L.2.E. Ras, from L.3.E. Bolasso. Jas appears in gate seeing Bolasso, immediately exits. Bolasso does not see Jas, crosses stage from left to right and exits. Ras goes up to gate calls:)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Jasamine!</p>
<stage>(Jas peeps to make sure Bolasso is not present, then slowly enters. Ras catches Jas by arm, pulls him down stage, laughingly inquires)</stage>
<p>What's the matter?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>You'd better let these people know who I am, especially that fat soldier, I don't think he likes me.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Carelessly)</stage>
<p>Oh! he's alright, to show you how he stands, he secured an invitation for our party to attend one of their annual celebrations at the Palace to-morrow night. He calls it "The Feast of the King of Kings of Abyssinia." You know this Country is full of Kings, but Menelik is the main guy. I promised the officer, we would contribute to the Emperor's Entertainment.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Say Ras, I don't like this stuff they drink around here, see if you can got the King to order a little Anheuser and Bush for the entertainment, will you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Looks around suspiciously)</stage>
<p>I want to put you wise. In this Country they hear our people calling me Ras, consequently I'm taken for a Prince of some sort, so in order to keep them from being disappointed I've confessed---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>That you're just plain Rastus Johnson from Kansas.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Nothing of the sort, I told them I was travelling incognito. My Kingdom was---</p></sp> 
<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Wilson County, Kansas.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Oh! no that's too commonplace.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Did you find out whether a Jas cuts any figure?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>A De Jas over here, is a general in the army. I told them you left off the De part of your title, because in our Country, great fighters were very modest and always travelled incognito, so all you've got to do is poke out your chest and every body will be afraid of you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Aside)</stage>
<p>Everybody except that fat soldier.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Act like a man of importance, spend your money as if you found it in the street if you want to be popular and above everything, hold your nerve-</p></sp>

<stage>(Bolasso enters. Ras is noticed by Jas)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Hurriedly)</stage>
<p>I'll be back in a minute.</p></sp>

<stage>(Exit L. Bolasso exits center, Ras gazes after Jas, who exits quickly. Ras turns as if to cross stage when Miram enters from R. Miram makes courtesy, Ras bows, same is repeated several times)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Do you think you could learn to-</p> 
<stage>(Quickly)</stage>
<p>of course you couldn't it's too sudden</p> 
<stage>(Slower)</stage>
<p>but I thought you-uh, you-uh and then again I might have known You see, this morning when you as down to our Camp, I didn't, I didn't, well for that matter neither did you, of course it's really too much to expect a person-</p>
<stage>(Makes several efforts to continue, fans violently with hat)</stage> 
<p>Isn't it warm?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>I thought the weather decidedly pleasant to-day, sir.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Of course it is, how kind of you to say so. You see where I come from.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>I'm sure the place you came from must be beautiful</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Yes Kansas</p>
<stage>(Confusedly)</stage>
<p>I mean Kansas City. No, no I mean, well, you never saw anything like it in your life.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>Kansas?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Disgusted)</stage> 
<p>No no.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker> 
<stage>(Inquiringly)</stage> 
<p>Kansas City?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Aside)</stage>
<p>It's a shame to spring this on her.</p>
<stage>(With important air)</stage>
<p>you see where I came from, I'm the King Bee of the village.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<stage>(Vaguely)</stage>
<p>Then you're a Village King. Tell me about your beautiful home, I'm so anxious to know all about it.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Aside)</stage>
<p>It's a shame to take the money, I wonder if she can stand it</p>
<stage>(Then looking intently at Miram)</stage>
<p>Close your eyes and let the fairy wings of fancy carry you through an undulating region, intersected by valleys, where all the beauties of Nature are collected to delight the eye of man. Silver rivulets that glitter for a moment and with rapid flight, disappear as if swallowed up by the verdant banks that mark their course, leaving in their wake, the fragrance of wild flowers, whose perfumes kisses the breast of bright plumaged birds as they wing their way at dawn, o'er fields of golden grain. Where the rays of the setting sun peeping through the dense foliage of an ivy covered retreat, tint in glowing colors, the expectant faces of its occupants Maidens singing an Ode to Their King on the Isle of Content.</p></sp>

<stage>(Change style of delivery here)</stage>

<stage>(During speech, lights are slowly lowered until completely out at finish. Chorus in dark until change, then lights up gradually, discovers Jas in Oriental make up a six women, three on a side chained to bracelets on his arms. The market scene is transformed to grotto or foliage surrounding with chorus grouped as follows: All women reclining, servants (men) fanning them and serving them in different ways to remain the same throughout.)</stage>

<stage>"IT'S HARD TO FIND A KING LIKE ME" </stage>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>Isle of content redolent settlement,</l>
<l>We represent competent and loyal subjects</l>
<l>Magnificent eminent Queen of the Orient,</l>
<l>Our voices raising, we are ever praising beauteous Island of Content.</l></lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>I feel as tho' I'm fit to rule in almost any land,</l>
<l>And tho' I've never been to school most things I understand</l>
<l>I know all 'bout the war and things and believe that war is right</l> 
<l>But I'll stay here while the chorus sings and hear folks 'bout fight</l></lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>To hear his Highness talk like this is good proof of his worth</l> 
<l>We're proud to know we've got the wisest ruler on this earth</l></lg></sp>

<p>Refrain</p>

<lg type="verse"><l>Yes it's hard to find a King like me the other Monarchs have my sympathy,</l> 
<l>There's the Czar of Russia the ruler of Prussia and Mister Roose-v-e-l-t.</l> 
<l>There's the noted King of Italy the Emperor of Germany</l>
<l>Of course they're all getting their portion but it's more than a notion,</l>
<l>When you try to find a King like me.</l></lg>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker> 
<stage>(sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>Now I rule everything in sight as far as I can see,</l>
<l>Why even the very air that's breathed is also ruled by me,</l>
<l>Of Brigham Young you all have heard old Utah's famous son,</l>
<l>He looks like three small dimes to me, I've got sis-teen to his one.</l></lg></sp>

<p>Refrain</p>

<lg type="verse"><l>Now you talk about the Sultan of Turkey, he looks like a cold storage fowl to me,</l>
<l>I'll go further in saying that the King of Spain is a large thick frost with me.</l>
<l>There's the High Mogue of China Lan' and the wise gazabe that rules Japan,</l>
<l>Put your 'cyclopedia and your his'trys in a bunch, take a long day off and bring your lunch,</l> 
<l>When you try to find a King like me.</l></lg>

<stage>(At finish of song lights out all exit. Market scene resumes its original appearance. The singing of introductory choruses to commence when lights go out at end of song and slowly die away as lights go up. Miram is standing near booth R.2.E rubbing her eyes in bewildered fashion. Jas enters L.2.E starts to cross stage, sees Miram, turns abruptly, goes to booth occupied by Varinoe.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(To Varinoe)</stage>
<p>Lady I'm from America. I'm a Jas over there</p>
<stage>(Varinoe makes courtesy Jas bows repeatedly)</stage>
<p>I want to buy a souvenir from you 'cause I think you're the prettiest girl in the market</p>
<p>(Varinoe makes courtesy, hands Jas large ornament)</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>VARINOE</speaker>
<p>Would you like this -</p></sp>

<stage>(Interrupted by violent commotion off stage. Enter from L.3.E. four soldiers with Ras struggling to free himself followed by crowd of citizens)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>Friends pray roll me what am I to do,</l>
<l>When you will not allow me to explain to you,</l>
<l>Evidently there has been some mistake,</l> 
<l>I'll make all plain if you'll but let me speak</l></lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Can it be true? Can it be true?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<stage>(Male)</stage>
<p>Yes we have taken the fearless Yaraboo.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>Then let us our voices raise to Janhoi in loudest praise,</l> 
<l>And may all they that wrong would do</l>
<l>Be dealt with same as Yaraboo.</l></lg></sp>

<stage>(During above "Then Let us our voices &amp; etc.," the four guards are taking Ras out through gates, the mob following to gates reaching same just as they are closed with Ras and guards on outside, leaving chorus inside. They are attracted by Jas singing, he having come on while they were taking Ras out, having had Bus. &amp; etc.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>He is not Harry boo-oo-oo</l> 
<l>Tell me what did he do-oo-oo</l></lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<stage>(male)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>He's a bad bad man from Aroosa Land,</l> 
<l>And all wise Natives understand,</l>
<l>That all such Chiefs of war and strife,</l> 
<l>Are better off outside this life</l>
<l>He's a rebel bold, he's a traitor too,</l> 
<l>But Janhoi knows just what to do</l> 
<l>This riot and revolt must go</l> 
<l>Allegiance is all we know.</l></lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>That all such Chiefs of war and strife</l> 
<l>Are better off outside this life.</l></lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>For goodness sake don't get excited</l> 
<l>There's no old wrong that can't be righted.</l></lg></sp>

<stage>(Music simmers down, possibly to vamp for following song, during said music, Jas gather the bunch around him saying, "He's alright, you're all wrong, he ain't no Colla-boo, he's jes my frien', Rastus Johnson, the man wid all the money in the world) </stage>

<stage>"THE MAN WITH ALL THE MONEY IN THE WORLD"</stage>
 
<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>No doubt none of you'se ever had no real nice rich friends,</l>
<l>Who had to carry twelve experts to count the coin he spends,</l>
<l>Say if you ain't never had one, find one 'cause it sho' is great</l>
<l>To get all that you ask for and never have to wait.</l>
<l>Don't you know there ain't no tellin' how much trash my friend has got</l> 
<l>And when I stop to figgerm then I figger like as not.</l></lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>Dat he's the man with all the money, all that ever has been made</l>
<l>A dollar's same's a penny with holes thro' the Indians head</l>
<l>You kin scream it that's what I mean, scream my frien's a thoroughbred</l> 
<l>Cause he's got all the money in the world.</l></lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(sings)</stage>
<lg type="verse"><l>If you'se got plenty money you kindo jes as you please,</l>
<l>Buy twelve or fourteen houses jes to lounge in at your ease,</l>
<l>My frien' gives me more money ev'ry day than I kin count,</l>
<l>Jes hands it out in bunches, don't care nothin' 'bout amount,</l>
<l>When I was young my folks said I thought money growed on trees</l> 
<l>I 'spects it do and if so, then my frien' owns all the trees.</l></lg></sp> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<stage>(Same as before)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>VARINOE</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>If you have so much money</l> 
<l>If you will please pay me.</l></lg></sp>

<stage>(Music softens up for Jas's speech and business of searching himself &amp; etc.)</stage>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Pay you! Will I pay you! well I should say I would</p>
<stage>(Searches finds nothing)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>VARINOE</speaker>
<p>It seems that you have no mon-ee, you try to make a fool of me</p></sp>

<stage>(Breaks trick over Jas's head, he screams "help!" Mob starts with music)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<stage>(Male)</stage>
<p>Away with the thief and have him understand, That for such a crime, he must lose his right hand.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<stage>(Man from mob)</stage>
<p>Suppose we do it now, come men I'll show you how.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SOLO</speaker>
<p>Stop! men, take him away, we have a King and he has the say.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>Away! Away! he has ruined our festive day,</l> 
<l>Away! imposter thief!</l>
<l>We have a King and he has the say,</l>
<l>To the King we'll take him straight away</l> 
<l>Away Away</l></lg></sp> 

<stage>(Turmoil Riot Confusion &amp; etc.)</stage>

<stage>(CURTAIN)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 5</head>

<stage>Time: Thursday A.M.</stage>

<stage>(Audience chamber in Menelik's Palace. Divan L. Table and Chairs in front of divan Papers seals &amp; etc. on table. At rise of curtain, Tegulet is pursuing Bolassa's report of capture of Yarabu).</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Is my report to Janhoi, of the capture of Yarabu, satisfactory to your Excellency?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>With one exception your report is accurate.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>What have I failed to mention?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>The part your men took in the affair.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Hannibal the Oarthaginian general, slew between Forty and Fifty Thousand men at Cannae. Frederick the Great of Leuthen defeated Eighty Thousand Austrians. Napoleon whipped the combined armies of Austria and Russia at Austerlitz. Wellington won the battle of Waterloo and with your permission, my Dear Uncle, as my report will show, Shambul Bolassa captured Yarabu.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>And if I was not your Uncle?</p>
<stage>(Enter Zamish from door R.)</stage>
<p>Well Zamish -</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>ZAMISH</speaker>
<stage>(Salutes)</stage>
<p>The market girl Miram desires to speak with Shambul Bolassa.</p>
<stage>(Looking suspiciously at Bolassa)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Admit her.</p>
<stage>(Tegulet goes to table and arranges articles on table)</stage></sp> 

<stage>(Enters hurriedly Miram, who salutes Bolassa and Tegulet followed by Miss Primly)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>I beg your pardon, Shambul Bolassa for disturbing, but -</p> 
<stage>(hesitating)</stage>
<p>I-</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Speak out, what can I do for your?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<stage>(Salutes Bolassa)</stage>
<p>In the market yesterday, Ras Johnson and Jas Jenkins, two members of the American Caravan, were taken by your soldiers -</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Yes and I think it was an outrage.</p></sp>

<stage>(Tegulet looks severely at Miss Primly. Bolassa surprised. Miss Primly subsides)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>And after much persuasion by the women folks--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Yes I was one of them, I--</p></sp>

<stage>(Tegulet and Bolassa show impatience by staring at Miss Primly who stops talking)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>I ventured to come here to ask you, if you wouldn't be lenient as possible and use your influence with his Excellency, the Affa Negus Tegulet</p>
<stage>(Salute quickly)</stage>
<p>to have them returned to their friends.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>I'm afraid you're mistaken as to the identity of one of them.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>No she isn't either, she knows exactly what she's talking about in the first place--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting angrily)</stage>
<p>Hold your tongue.</p></sp>

<stage>(Miss Primly makes motion as if to catch hold of tongue)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>I'm quite sure both of them came with the American Caravan and besides, Ras Johnson told me to remind you, that you yourself had secured an invitation for him and his party to the Palace to-night and unless you released him, he would not be able to attend.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>See to this at once and report to me here, the result of your investigation.</p></sp>

<stage>(Exit Tegulet center. Bolassa watches exit)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Depend on me to sift the matter thoroughly-</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Well I'm glad he's gone.</p></sp>

<stage>(Bolassa turns to Miram)</stage>

<sp><speaker>MIRAM</speaker>
<p>You'll do what you can for them, won't you Shambul Bolasara?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Anything to be obliging run along, I'll follow you.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>MISS PRIMLY</speaker>
<p>Would you mind if we walked?</p></sp>

<stage>(Exit Miram and Miss Primly with head in air)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(Meditatively)</stage>
<p>Just my luck, and I sat up all night to make out that report.</p>
<stage>(Strikes the door angrily which has been closed by Zamish. Exits)</stage></sp>

<stage>(Anthem played off stage, enter Priests followed by Tegulet, all go to table and with exception of Tegulet, sit gong sounds off stage)</stage>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>The signal for the Lion of Judah has been sounded. Let the servants of his gracious Majesty in accordance</p></sp>

<stage>(All bend heads over table)</stage>

<stage>(Enter two soldiers followed by Menelik soldiers with guns in hand station themselves on opposite sides of throne. (On divan) When Menelik sits, all rise from table, arrange themselves along side of wall to left "C" Tegulet nearest divan two soldiers follow and station themselves on opposite sides of door. Menelik rises with hand extended as if conferring a blessing)</stage>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>Salaam, Allah.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>SOLDIERS</speaker>
<p>Salaam Allah.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>You may speak Tegulet, but be brief. I would not mar the pleasure of the day with too much business</p> 
<stage>(Menelik sits after speech)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Brevity in this case, your Majesty, is an absolute necessity. The report looking to the re-organization of our financial system is unfinished. The present medium of exchange has been in vogue many centuries and is very difficult of re-adjustment Therefore, we your humble servants, beg your indulgence for an extension of time.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>Granted Anything else?</p></sp>

<stage>(Tegulet picks up large bundle of manuscripts)</stage>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>A petition, your Majesty-</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting impatiently)</stage>
<p>No petitions.</p>
<stage>(Tegulet lays aside manuscript quickly and picks up paper with seal attached)</stage></sp> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>At the last meeting of the council, the merchant Ali Obi was proven guilty of stealing from his customers by giving short measure.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>Yes, I remember he came before me for sentence to-day, any thing else?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>One more item, your Majesty, two members of the American Caravan were arrested in the market place yesterday, in the case of one, there is possibly a mistake, if so I have sent Bolassa to clear up the matter, the other is charged with stealing a vase. Ali Obi and Jasmine Jenkins, the prisoners await your Majesty's pleasure.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker> 
<p>Bring them before me</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter prisoners chained together, followed by soldier. Prisoners are placed between doors, soldier stations himself at door on R. Enter Semra hurriedly, gives gun to guard at door, walks to center facing Menelik, kneels and salutes Menelik, then rises)</stage>

<sp><speaker>SERMA</speaker>
<p>With your permission, your Majesty -</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>Speak, Semra.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>SERMA</speaker>
<p>Shambul Bolassa reports he has just taken Yarabu.</p></sp>

<stage>(Menelik rises with subdued excitement. Semra salutes, walks backward to door takes gun. Exits)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>Members of the council: I shall make an example of this rebellious chief. Time after time, concession after concession has been made to these unruly people of the Arusa Division. Leniency in similar cases in the past, has been mistaken as fear on my part. I shall dispel the allusion and at the same time, satisfy an overweening ambition that doubts the wisdom of a descendant of the Queen of Sheba to legislate with justice for all the people of Ethiopia. I shall send Yarabu with an escort of a thousand soldiers, back to the Arusa Division, but I shall send him back piece at a time and when all the parts shall have arrived in the public market place of his native village, I wish my own hand, shall feed his body to the Hyenas, as a warning to any and all who shall attempt to defy the mandates of Menelik, the second King of Kings of Ethiopia.</p></sp>

<stage>(Enter Ras. Followed by Bolassa, Ras goes to center. Bolassa stops long enough to salute Menelik, then advances to Ras's side. Ras in same costume worn when arrested. Menelik angrily inquires who is this person that does not know how to appear before a king?)</stage> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You see Mr. Menelik, on account of the peculiar circumstances surrounding my case, I had not choice in the matter of dress and I --</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Silence! Bolassa, who is this person?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>Ras Johnson your majesty, leader of the American Caravan.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I was arrested yesterday in the market place--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>A mistake your Majesty, made by four of my men who believed, on account of his strange dress, tallying somewhat with the description sent from Harrar, that he was Yarabu</p></sp>
<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>You owe an apology to this young man, but for the present, business of more importance requires your immediate attention. Go back to the prison and return to my presence with Yarabu</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<p>I regret to inform your Majesty, that Yarabu while resisting capture, was severely wounded and died a few minutes after, I sent Semra with report of his arrest.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<stage>(Meditatively)</stage>
<p>Fate was kind to Yarabu, I intended-but no matter</p>
<stage>(Impatiently)</stage>
<p>The prisoner Ali Obi</p>
<stage>(Ali Obi is led before Menelik by soldiers at R door)</stage>
<stage>(To Ali Obi)</stage>
<p>Your offense calls for no comment on my part. This is the second time that you have been convicted of dishonest dealing with your customers The first time you were fine, but in your case fines are not affective. In the market-place at noon to-morrow, your right hand will be severed at the wrist All thieves must pay the same penalty.</p>
<stage>(With nod of head to soldiers)</stage>
<p>Take him away!</p>
<stage>(Turns to Tegulet as if in conversation, while soldier removes prisoner)</stage>
<p>Now Tegulet, the foreigners.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>TEGULET</speaker>
<p>Accused by the market girls of taking a vase Eighty Piastres, and not paying for the same.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I haven't gotten any money with me, but if you gentlemen will give me twenty minutes, I'll bring you a cart load of Piatstres. I know somebody has made a mistake, so if you will call all bets off, I'll make good for my friend Jas.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<p>That young man will not be allowed to remain in this chamber if he speaks again without my permission</p> 
<stage>(To Jas)</stage>
<p>Of course you can explain why you failed to pay for the vase?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I didn't have the chance, I had just put my hands on the-</p>
<stage>(hesitating)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker>
<stage>(supplying the word)</stage>
<p>Vase.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Yes, when the soldiers come along with Ras and I jist forgot I had the, the the thing in my hand. I never intended to steal it. Why since I've been old enough to understand right from wrong, My ole Mammy always taught me to keep my hands off other peoples property but I suppose when I was a little fellow I didn't always take Mammy's advice. Now and then I used to go into Farmer Dale's watermelon patch and examine the melons to see if they were ripe, and sometimes when I've caught him dozing on his front porch, I've sneaked back into the orchard and took a few peaches or apples but I reckon that didn't make me any worse than the rest of the boys, for there wasn't one in the neighborhood would have a missed a chance like that, and since I've growed up, I've lived so I could look any man or for that matter, woman in the face, and say, I never took the price of even an apple from anybody and now I'll leave off where I begun. I didn't know I had the thing in my hand. I never intended to steal it and I know you wouldn't have my hands cut off.</p>
<stage>(Pleadingly look at hands)</stage>
<p>These hands I've got to work with to make a living, because a woman has made a mistake and accused me of being a thief.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>KING MENELIK, II</speaker> 
<stage>(Rises)</stage>
<p>I shall send for the market girl. If after hearing her story, I decide to release you on payment of the cost of the vase, four strokes on the gong in yonder lobby will be sounded. If on the contrary, you hear but three, your fate will be the same as that of the thief Ali Obi.</p></sp>

<stage>(When door is opened O. anthem is played off stage Menelik followed by Tegulet, Priests and soldiers exit, leaving Bolassa, Ras, Jas and guards)</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOLASSO</speaker>
<stage>(To Ras)</stage>
<p>Come we will wait for the decision here.</p></sp>

<stage>(Pointing off stage through door at right, exit Bolassa)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Grasping Jas's hand sympathetically)</stage>
<p>If the decision is against you I'll use every dollar I have to make them change their mind</p></sp>

<stage>(Ras holds Jas' hand for a moment, then exits hurriedly without looking back. Jas unconsciously starts to follow Ras. Soldiers close door between them. Jas looks pleadingly at soldiers, soldiers stare straight ahead. Jas scratches head dubiously, looks resignedly at soldiers, then audience.)</stage>

<stage>"HERE IT COMES AGAIN"</stage>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>I b'lieve I'm 'bout to find myself where I started from,</l>
<l>They say that money does all things well I've been handlin' some</l>
<l>And yet I knew bad luck would come, it's plain as A.B.C.</l> 
<l>'Cause something's buzzing in my ear and whispering to me.</l></lg></sp>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>Here it comes again plague take it, here it comes again</l>
<l>But when that feeling comes a-stealing, it's not use to complain</l> 
<l>I thought that Jonah spell had passed, but I was figuring too fast</l> 
<l>My dream it was too good to last</l></lg></sp>

<stage>(spoken)</stage>

<p>Dog bite it, here it comes again.</p> 

<lg type="verse"><l>I had brain fever one time and had fierce pains in my head,</l> 
<l>And now I know exactly what Doc. Smith meant when he said</l> 
<l>"If any time insanity should stare you in the face,</l>
<l>You'll find an awful funny strange sensation taking place."</l></lg> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Here it comes again</p></sp> 

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Good gracious, Here it comes again,</l>
<l>But when that feeling comes a-stealing, it's no use to complain,</l> 
<l>The Doctor says it's a fact, that I'm some kind of maniac,</l>
<l>My upper story it is cracked,</l></lg>

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<p>I feel it, here it comes again.</p> 

<lg type="verse"><l>Last Tuesday night I gave up drink because I had to quit,</l>
<l>The purple snakes and crocodiles most had me in a fit,</l>
<l>I didn't mind the yellow rats, for they was kind of tame,</l>
<l>The thing that threw the scare in me was just too bad to name.</l></lg>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Here it comes again</p></sp> 

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Heavings! here it comes again,</l>
<l>I know it wants me 'cause it haunts me and drives me most insane,</l> 
<l>It's got a pair of bloodshot eyes, a tail and horns of awful size</l>
<l>It must be Satan in disguise,</l></lg>

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<p>Oh Mercy! here it comes again.</p> 

<lg type="verse"><l>Ben Brown and I once met two girls who called him 'cross the street</l> 
<l>One had a face that looked just like a yard of sausage meat,</l>
<l>I said to him "She sure has the limit face on her"</l>
<l>Just then he kicked me hard and said "why that's my sister sir"</l></lg>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>There it wuz again</p></sp>

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Dod bust it, there it was again,</l>
<l>He kicked me cruel, like a mile and caused me lots of pain,</l> 
<l>Said I "You are mistaken Ben, I meant the other homely hen"</l> 
<l>"Why that's my wife" said he and then,</l></lg>

<stage>(Imitates being kicked)</stage> 

<p>Oh! Ouch!</p> 

<lg type="verse"><l>When I was quite a little lad, I got this tip from Ma,</l>
<l>That heaven helps the ones that helps themselves, it's scripted law</l> 
<l>That day I helped myself to pie and pudding from the shelf,</l>
<l>And now when in a bank, I'm saying to myself.</l></lg>

<p>Here it comes again</p> 

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Dod rot it; here it comes again,</l>
<l>But if I do it I will rue it and end up in a pen,</l>
<l>Them green-backs looks so nice and new, I really should abstract a few</l> 
<l>I thought that "helping graft was through,</l></lg>

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<p>But hang it, here it comes again.</p> 

<lg type="verse"><l>I'm very fond of chickens, but they never took to me,</l>
<l>It seemed somehow that they'd get soared and fly right up a tree,</l> 
<l>At night I'd go to Squire Smiths and coax them out with bread,</l> 
<l>But they was all so scared of me, that now I 'spose they said.</l></lg> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>Here it comes again</p></sp>

<stage>(Cackles)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Here it comes again,</l>
<l>That chicken feeling comes a-stealing, it's up with some poor hen,</l> 
<l>It ain't no use for you to beg, and if he gets you by the leg,</l>
<l>You'll never lay another egg,</l></lg>

<stage>(Crows)</stage>

<p>Here it comes again.</p>

<lg type="verse"><l>One night we went to Chinatown and while down there it seems,</l> 
<l>A "Chink" presented me a pipe that gave me funny dreams,</l>
<l>I dreamt a lovely fairy came and sat upon my knee,</l>
<l>She said that I was handsome and she loved on one but me</l></lg>

<stage>(Lights pipe)</stage>

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<lg type="verse"><l>Here she comes again Oh! joy and rapture here shes comes again,</l> 
<l>I'm bound to marry that sweet fairly, Oh! lady tell me when,</l>
<l>She answered with a pretty pout, that she is mine without a doubt,</l> 
<l>But shucks! My pipe is going out, Dod burn it, there she comes again</l></lg></sp>

<lg type="verse"><l>One night I had a poker fit and had it might bad.</l>
<l>So I went to a game and took all of the coin I had</l>
<l>I got four Kings which looked quite sweet and then I bet my all</l> 
<l>A man shoved in his money, showed four aces said "I call"</l></lg> 

<sp><speaker>CHORUS</speaker>
<p>There it wuz again</p></sp> 

<stage>(Spoken)</stage>

<lg type="verse"><l>Gol blame it! there it wuz again,</l>
<l>I had a feeling of crooked dealing but how could I complain,</l> 
<l>He wuz a crook, I do believe, but how could I renig or grievem</l> 
<l>He had a razor up his sleeve (Oh! mercy) there it wuz again.</l></lg>

<stage>(After song gong sounds at regular intervals three times, then after a pause, slightly longer than the rest is sounded a fourth time Jas starts joyfully for door)</stage>

<stage>(Curtain)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Scene 6</head>

<stage>Time: Thursday Evening.</stage>

<stage>(Throne Room, Menelik Palace. No dialogue. At march from orchestra, enter Priests followed by Tegulet and Bolassa then Menelik and Queen Taitu on throne. Tegulet and Bolassa back of Menelik four soldiers at foot of throne. Ballet commencing with dance (Minuet) of Priests followed by Turkish women. Hawaiian and Native Abyssinian women in order named. Then Ras and Jas with Aunt Cally, Miss Primly, Elder Fowler and rent of American party.</stage>

<stage>"GOOD BYE ETHIOPIA"</stage>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Good news folks, good news and true,</l>
<l>We know you want to hear it, so we'll tell it to you.</l>
<l>We just got a cablegram from home</l>
<l>And all it said was they one word "Come"</l>
<l>So all get ready and commence to pack</l>
<l>The time has come when we must go back.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<l>CHORUS</l>
<l>Good-bye good-bye Ethiopia we may come back some day,</l> 
<l>You have been good to us, your land would do for us</l>
<l>But we can no longer stay</l>
<l>Good luck, good luck to our new found friends,</l>
<l>To keep your friendship we will try,</l>
<l>We all wish you success, may you ever progress,</l>
<l>Ethiopia, good-bye.</l>
</lg>

<stage>(At finish of song, emblems trophies &amp; etc. in hands of all (Except American party) thrust forward electric effects to be arranged to suit taste.)</stage>

<stage>(Curtain)</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="section">

<head type="sub">Epilogue</head>

<stage>Time: Tuesday 4 P.M.<lb/> 
Place: Plains near Borema Springs.</stage> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I thought as much. Here I am devoting every minute of my valuable time, improving your physical condition and Pedistrianism is the best means to that end, and this is the way you appreciate it and I suppose you'll round off your ingratitude by asking me to dismount so that you can ride?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Words fail to explain how much I appreciate your devotion to my physical condition. You've proved that to my entire satisfaction when ever there was a chance for both of us to ride, you've always let me walk and another thing, there never was a selfish bone in my body.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Then why do you wish me to dismount?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Sympathy for the mule.</p></sp>

<stage>(Ras dismounts)</stage>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You're right, you're right</p>
<stage>(Ras goes over and shakes Jas's hand)</stage>
<p>You've a great big heart in that rusty body of yours. I never thought there was such a thing as sympathy in your make up. I was just going to dismount and let you ride.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Well if that's the case, I ---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>No, no not another word, you're about to say you're sorry you spoke to me in that manner after all my kindness</p>
<stage>(Shakes hand violently)</stage>
<p>but you're right, you're right, you're always right</p>
<stage>(Calls to servant)</stage>
<p>Hadji!</p>
<stage>(Stops shaking Jas's hand, takes roll of money from pocket)</stage>
<p>Here's Five Dollars, take that poor little beast safe into camp, we'll walk. I never gave the matter a thought. Poor little beast.</p>
<stage>(Exit servant. Ras watching exit, expressing mock sympathy by wagging head murmuring)</stage> 
<p>sympathy for the--</p>
<stage>(Goes to Jas and shakes his hand once more saying)</stage>
<p>you're right, you're right.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Didn't you forget something?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Forget what?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>To kiss the mule good-bye.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Takes roll of money from pocket)</stage>
<p>Here's a couple of thousand, buy yourself an automobile, forget the mule and be happy, take the world as it comes and like me, look at things with the eye of a Philosopher.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>And you's a Philosopy?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Philosopher.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>What's the duty of a Philosophiloso-</p>
<stage>(finally add pede)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Philosopher.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Well what's his duty?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>To look on the bright side of other people's troubles when you haven't any of your own.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Shaking Ras's hand violently)</stage>
<p>You're right, you're right.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Now we understand each other, I'll let you into a little secret.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Before you tell me that secret, give me one of the crackers you've got in your pocket?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You must learn to withstand temptation. Over feeding is not conducive to good physical condition, allow me to quote Shakesphere on the subject "Fat paunches have lean pates and dainty bits make rich the ribs, but bankrupt quite the wits" and I want you to have your wits about you at all times.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>The day that Shakesphere said that, I bet he hadn't walked 14 miles with nothing but a ham sandwich under his belt.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Takes out roll of money)</stage>
<p>Here's Ten Dollars, we'll reach the Capitol to-morrow, when you get in town buy yourself a good chicken dinner. Forget your troubles of the day before and be happy.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Shakesphere, Ten Dollars and an argument to keep from giving me a single cracker. Ras Johnson that's the personification of meanness.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I have to be cruel to be kind, when I brought you away from home you was the acme of physical perfection, do you suppose I'm going to allow you to gorge yourself until you become absolutely useless to yourself or any one else a disgruntled, dyspeptic, unfit for the association of respectable people?</p>
<stage>(pause)</stage>
<p>No Sir!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(To audience)</stage>
<p>Did you ever see a man stick so tight to a cracker?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>As I was about to say, I have a little secret I want to impart. You remember I caught Fifteen Thousand Dollars in the Louisiana Lottery and paid off a Nine Hundred Dollar mortgage on that 125 acres we have down in Wilson County, Kansas.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Umph! Umph!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You know I promised Aunt Cally, Uncle Rube Fowler, Miss Primly and the other girls, I'd take them abroad.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>And me-</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Of course you, you're here ain't you? Well at first I only figured on going as far as Paris.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Dance and Sing)</stage>
<p>As I stroll along the Boise-de-Boulogne.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Slapping Jas on back)</stage>
<p>We had a good time in Paris, Eh! Jas?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Returning slap with interest)</stage>
<p>Go on Donne-Lui Ce qui est La, Madam? Oh pshaw!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>That will do how, that will do. As I was saying, I didn't intend to go any further than Paris, but something happened in Paris.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Yes you got arrested for fighting a French man.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>No, no, I mean something important happened</p>
<stage>(looks around suspiciously beckons for Jas to come closer. Bus. for Jas)</stage>
<p>You know Wilson County is the center of the oil industry of Kansas, well the biggest oil well in the County was discovered within the borders of that 125 acres. Our agent sold the 25 acres surrounding the oil well, for a big bunch of money and I received the coin the day before we left Paris, hence the fresh supply of Mazuma.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>After you give me one of them crackers, there's another secret that's been troubling me more than anything else</p>
<stage>(Looks around suspiciously then whispers)</stage>
<p>Why did you leave the Boise-de-Boulogne for the sandy De-Dez?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Sighes)</stage>
<p>Paris is a wonderful place-attractive, luxurious, magnificent who could forget the Palais Royal, Louvre, Luxembourg--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>And the Bois-de-Boulogne.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Shrugs shoulders, gesticulates like Frenchman)</stage>
<p>To pick up my narrative--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>If it don't make any difference to you, would you mind picking up a cracker at the same time?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Ignores question)</stage>
<p>This fresh supply of money gave me an opportunity to gratify my one life long hobby "Astronomy."</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Ras Johnson, you've talked about more funny diseases since you've had money, then any man I've ever seen. Neuritis, Neuroma, Neurosis. Nephritis of the Pedal extremities, Chiropody and now you've got the Hobbyastronomous.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Astronomy isn't a disease, its a science. Astronomy treats of the heavenly bodies. Considered as to their nature, heavenly bodies may be divided into two great classes. Class one: incandescent bodies which shine by their own light. Class two: opaque bodies which are visible only by reflecting the light of some incandescent body in their neighborhood. Now the three fundamental facts which determine the phenomena of Astronomy are: The Globular form of the earth, its diurnal rotation on its axis and its annual revolution around the sun. To represent the position of the stars, astronomers imagine circles on the Celestial sphere, corresponding to the circles of longitude and latitude on the earth. To explain to you longitude and latitude, the Meridian of Greenwich, Celestial meridians and the like, would be a waste of time, but I might be able to interest you----</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>If you'd just show me the photograph of a cracker---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Now if I should take you at your word and afterward didn't give you the cracker, it's more than likely you would have a serious case of muscular contraction of the oesophagus, in that case, what would you do?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Say my prayers.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>If you'll agree not to interrupt me for five minutes, I may furnish you with a few of these crackers.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I'll sign the Armistice.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>As I was saying, I might be able to interest you by stating that I lingered a bit in the rear of the Caravan to-day to try an experiment.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>I thought---</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>But you are not to think at all and by interrupting me, you have broken your agreement on the cracker question.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I appeal from the decision.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>I'll give you the crackers if you'll just keep still.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Unconditional surrender.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>To resume: I'm going to try an experiment and I know of no better place than here on the Continent where the first authoritative school of astronomy had its birth, I refer to the Alexandrian school. If what I learned of a disciple of this school of astronomy at Cairo, be true, I shall be able to bring about any weather condition I desire which of course will be a great benefit to Kansas. Change day-light to darkness, darkness to moon- light, moon-light to star light and visa versa</p>
<stage>(Jas starts to speak)</stage>
<p>Don't interrupt please, my first attempt will be to produce total darkness-</p>
<stage>(Looks at gun carefully)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Making mock address to audience)</stage>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, with the kind permission of the audience, Rastus Johnson will smother the sun.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Walking down stage two or three steps and fondling gun)</stage>
<p>I will now bring about a total eclipse. For your benefit, I will explain what an eclipse is. An eclipse is an obstruction of the light of a heavenly body by another, effected either directly by its intervention between the body and the observer, or indirectly by its interception of the source of light which illuminates the body-</p>
<stage>(To Jas)</stage>
<p>You understand, don't you?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(By expression shows he doesn't understand)</stage> 
<p>Oh! yes!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Very well. Of course this being a total eclipse, will be unlike the eclipse of 1928 and 1967.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(With emphasis)</stage>
<p>When?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Calmly)</stage>
<p>1928 and 1967. In these two, the moon's shadow will just graze the pole of the earth.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>In 1928 and 1967</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>In 1928 and 1967.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Excuse me Professor, but ain't this 1905?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>This is A.D. 1905.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Looks intently at Ras, then to audience)</stage>
<p>Decision reserved until the mental responsibility of the defendant has been established.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>That you are skeptical, does not surprise me at all, but as in all cases where science is concerned, people of your mental calibre, must have an ocular demonstration, and that I shall try to give you by first counteracting the calorific rays of the sun, thereby causing an unusual humidity--</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker> 
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Further explanation unaccompanied by ocular demonstration will not be tolerated. According to Hoyle, the best proof of the pudding is the eating, so let's taste.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Raising gun and pointing upward and off stage in L.2.E.)</stage> 
<p>Stand behind me and observe.-</p>
<stage>(Fires gun, the report of which must be very light. Louder reports to follow off stage about ten seconds later, then the gradual lowering of the lights. When about two thirds down, insert colored medium until total darkness. Ras and Jas stand with back to audience Ras produces small pocket lamp which he lights)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I'm awful glad you sprung that light, I ain't skeered, but Ha! ha!</p>
<stage>(Without humor)</stage>
<p>I-I you know I jes' naturally when the sun-when the sun say ain't there some way you can use the best part of the sun for your experiment and let me have the rest of it?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Excitedly pointing upward)</stage>
<p>See!</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Frightened)</stage>
<p>Who! What! Where?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>The stars one by one are peeping from the firmament.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I wish they wouldn't be so bashful and come right out, no excuse for peeping when there ain't nobody to--</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<stage>(Interrupting)</stage>
<p>Ah!</p>
<stage>(Long drawn)</stage>
<p>There's Luna also.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Inquiringly)</stage>
<p>Who's loony?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>The moon</p>
<stage>(Enthused)</stage>
<p>Isn't it beautiful?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Pantomimes to audience that Ras is crazy and conveys the idea that he (Jas) is humoring him by showing great interest, looks intently at the moon and rapturously exclaims)</stage>
<p>Lovely. Lovely.</p>
<stage>(Pause then)</stage>
<p>Say Ras, you ain't forgot them crackers, have you?</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Wait a minute</p>
<stage>(Fires gun, light report as before, followed about five seconds later by loud report off stage. One of the stars takes on the appearance of a comet. The same to be repeated two or three times. Drop must be made transparent and lights worked from behind)</stage>
<p>Try your gun, but be careful not to fire in the direction of the moon.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>You said try your gun and I presume you mean for me to alter the appearance of one of the stars and I have selected that Luminary</p>
<stage>(Pointing to star nearest the moon)</stage>
<p>next to Luna so stand back and take note of the experiment.</p>
<stage>(Shoots, light report from gun followed immediately by several loud reports off stage. Moon increases in size. Picture in moon. Bus. &amp; etc.)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You've made a mess of everything, now I'll be compelled to reverse the present condition.</p>
<stage>(Shoots. All lights go out)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<stage>(Excited)</stage>
<p>Say Ras, light that light again.</p>
<stage>(Ras produces pocket lamp. Just then, chicken crows off stage)</stage>
<p>Ras are you going to give me some of them crackers?</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Here, take all of them</p>
<stage>(Gives crackers to Jas. Again, the chicken crows, louder and louder this time)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Rastus Johnson, do you hear that voice calling out in the wilderness?</p>
<stage>(Takes light, picks up stone, leaves stage R.2. E. Ras watching, lights come up slowly until full up. Bus. catching chicken. Jas returns with chicken)</stage></sp>

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>You've got keen ears, Jasamine Jenkins.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>I'd a knowed that voice in the middle of the Red Sea, Rastus Johnson.</p></sp> 

<sp><speaker>RASTUS</speaker>
<p>Come we'll depart, Jasmine Jenkins.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker>JASAMINE</speaker>
<p>Lead on, we'll follow</p>
<stage>(Holding up chicken, follows. Exit to music)</stage></sp>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>