<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0198">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Garretson W. Gibson to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen, February 19, 1883</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="caa">Chelsea A. Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0198</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Garretson W. Gibson to Frederick T. Frelinghuysen</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date when="1883-02-19">February 19, 1883</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Encounters with Africans</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32012452">Clay, Henry, 1777-1852</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/74647197">Everett, Edward, 1794-1865</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54969088">Harper, Robert Goodloe, 1765-1825</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10224864">King, Rufus, 1755-1827</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/59096754">Madison, James, 1751-1836</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100204775">Marshall, John, 1755-1835</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/20476583">Monroe, James, 1758-1831</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18600856">Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895</term>
<term>Smyth, John H.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32431122">Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4944460">Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Alabama</term>
<term>Arkansas</term>
<term>Arthington (Liberia)</term>
<term>Brewerville (Liberia)</term>
<term>Junk River</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Louisiana</term>
<term>Mississippi</term>
<term>North Carolina</term>
<term>Sherbro River</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Sierra Leone River</term>
<term>Sinoe River</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
<term>St. John's River</term>
<term>Saint Paul River</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Gullinas</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Gibson, Garretson W.</persName>
<roleName/>
<placeName>Monrovia (Liberia)</placeName>
<date when="1883-02-19"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/58082142">Frelinghuysen, Frederick T. (Frederick Theodore), 1817-1885</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1883-03-27"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#kln">reviewed</change>
<change when="2019-06-21" who="#caa>">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.001"/>

<note>Department of State Received Mar 27 1883</note>

<p>Department of State.<lb/>
Monrovia February 19th 1883.</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I had the honor to forward you a despatch last year, asking
the consideration of the Government of the United States of
America to several matters in connection with the welfare and
interests of this Republic.</p>

<p>Having up to the present received no
acknowledgement of that communication and in view of the fact
that our complications in connection with the North West Boundary
Question have increased rather than diminished, I beg to enclose
a copy herewith fearing that the original may have miscarried.</p>

<p>I have the honor also to forward you a copy of a Resolution
of the Senate of this Republic adopted at its late session touching the
question of the North West Boundary which it had under consideration</p>

<p>The fact that the government of the United States unsolicited
by that of Her Majesty the Queen Great Britain and Ireland and
this State to act as umpire on this question, and in case of any disagreement

<fw type="address">Hon. F. C. Frelinghuysen<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
For the United States of America &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.002"/>

on the part of the Commissioners representing the two governments
the decision of the United States would be final. I beg to call your
attention to this understanding, and to request that your Government
will be kind enough to give some expression on the subject, so as to set
the matter at rest.</p>

<p>I need scarcely mention that this perplexing question
has been and still is the source of deep concern to this Republic, and
a termination of the dispute by the kind intervention of your Government
would be hailed with great delight and profound gratitude by the
citizens generally.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
Your most obedient Servant,<lb/>
G. W. Gibson</p>

<p>Enclosures.<lb/>
1. Dispatch dated Feby 2. 1882<lb/>
2. Senate Resolution on Draft convention</p>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.003"/>

<p>Department of State<lb/>
Monrovia February 2, 1882</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I am directed by the President after careful and anxious
deliberation in the Cabinet, to request you to lay before your 
Government the following:</p>

<p>The Republic of Liberia whose origin and history are well
known to the Government of the United States has now reached
a period in her history when she sorely needs and is fully able to
bear a large influx of civilized descendants of Africa from the
United States. An important addition to her civilized population
is imperatively demanded if she is to go on extending her influence
and pushing her free institutions against the encroachment of
foreigners.</p>

<p>The Natives in the interior of the Republic are anxious for
the planting of civilized settlements on the beautiful hills and in
the futile valleys which diversify their interesting country. We are 
pushing on as fact as we can get the immigrants from the United
States, and our new settlements of civilized industry
as they advance.</p>

<p>Arthington and Brewerville founded about ten years ago in
dense forests by freed men from North Carolina, Mississippi, Alabama

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.004"/>

Louisiana and Arkansas are now beautiful coffee groves with their
computable frame buildings Christian Churches, School houses and
Workshops, and as the Representatives of the Christian religion and
of American life are attracting the Aborigines drawing them both
within and around the settlements. But in view of the vast work
to be done, it is comparatively little that can be prosecuted or 
accomplished by the few emigrants sent out at irregular intervals by a
private association depending for its means upon voluntary 
contributions.</p>

<p>For the last ten or fifteen years the operations of the American
Colonization Society have been confined to one section of the
Republic for the most of means to send immigrants as formerly
to different points along the Coast. The consequence is that the
civilized population in the three leeward counties is rapidly 
diminishing and leaving the Aborigines to the money of the intrigues
of designing foreigners who are anxious to see the prestige of Liberia
not only lowered but destroyed among the natives on the Coast,
hoping that eventually the Six hundred miles of much coveted
coast with its accessible and desirable interior may fall into
the hands of some European power. In relation to the commercial
possibilities of Liberia, and the dangers to which she is exposed from
external agencies, I beg to refer you to the despatch of the Hon.
John H. Smyth, the late Minister Resident here, published in the
Foreign Relations of the United States for 1880. pp 691-707.
<catchwords>The</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.005"/>

The native wars which occur periodically among the Aborigines
and which are the result in part of old feuds leaving their origin
in the days of the horrible slave trade, can never be permanently
suppressed on the Coast and in the adjacent interior without the
presence in these territories of civilized settlements. Even in the
immediate presence a neighborhood of so powerful a Government
as that of Sierra Leone it is impossible to prevent the recurrence of
desolating wars in the purely native districts to the detriment of
trade and against the progress of the people.</p>

<p>The Sherbro and Sierra Leone rivers within British jurisdiction
and having no settlements of civilized people are frequently the scene
of ruinous tribal wars, while the St Paul's, the Junk, the St. John's,
and the Sinoe Rivers within Liberian jurisdiction and settled by
Colonists are entirely free from such disturbances. It is in the
North western and South eastern frontiers of the Republic and 
in localities within our boundaries distant from the civilized 
settlements where periodical wars now occur, and where trade
is interrupted.</p>

<p>The long pending question relating to the Northwestern 
boundary of the Republic is a source of continual annoyance and
irritation; and the arrangement of it appears to be beyond the
scope of ordinary diplomacy. The country must be settled by
civilized immigrants</p>

<p>During the negotiations of 1850 with aboriginal authorities

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.006"/>

for the cession of the Gullinas and adjacent territory which
Liberia now claims as it Northwestern limits the Commissions of the
Liberian Government agreed that schools should be established
and settlements made in that part of the country, but the need
of immigrants in other portions of the Republic, and the supply
from United States being very limited prevented the Government
from carrying out that part of its promise to the Gullinas people
and the scarcity of men for the educational necessities of the
Country, prevented the sending of teachers to them. This caused
dissatisfaction among them and was used by avaricious foreigners 
to stimulate their hostility to the Republic. But the Government 
is satisfied set that the establishment of settlement in the
country would set at rest forever all disputes about boundary,
and bring the Aborigines peacefully under the unquestioned
jurisdiction of Liberia.</p>

<p>In view of an increased manifestation of a determination 
of some of the European powers to take advantage of the
commercial possibilities of this Country: it is now a time of 
considerable anxiety with this government. The efforts of British
traders in our immediate neighborhood in the North, French
enterprises in the Northeast, the restless condition of the Aborigines
in some sections of our Republic, all conspire to cause us no little
alarm. Every thing is harassingly uncertain, and if we do not
get an accession of intelligent and enterprising immigrants over

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.007"/>

conditions may become very serious indeed.</p>

<p>It is in view of these facts that the President directs me
to ask the assistance of your Government to send us a few of
the thousands of civilized Christian negroes in your Country, who
are anxious to cast in their lot with Liberia, but who lack
the means of transportation and of a start on their arrival
in the land of their fathers.</p>

<p>Large numbers of people in the Southern section of 
your Country of good industrious habits, who would be hardly
missed from the Six millions of colored people, have been for
years making application to the government of the United States
for aid to emigrate to the land of their fathers.</p>

<p>These people who would not be missed among you would 
create a nation on this side of the water.</p>

<p>Liberia is the offspring of American benevolence and
this little Republic in Western Africa has exerted an influence
upon the adjacent tribes almost without a parallel in 
the history of Colonies. A few thousand immigrants
from the United States have drawn under their influence
from the stagnant and barren heathenism of ages over a
million of people, and without force or money have assimilated 
them by industrial, social and religious influence
and made them a part of a christian Republic based upon
the traditions of the United States.</p>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.008"/>

<p>The Republic of Liberia in these features of freedom and equal rights
of universal education, without distinction of classes, which so favorably 
impress the aboriginal mind, is an illustration of the kind
and practice of American institutions. Half of the public domain
of Liberia is held in trust for the settlement of the black people
of the United States. Every black man in America has a claim 
to a homestead in Liberia and the Government is bound by
law to grant ten acres of land to every adult, and twenty-five
acres to every family who come to this country from the
United States.</p>

<p>Our relations then to the American Government are
peculiar, and our claim to sympathy and assistance from
the United States is almost that of an American Colony.</p>

<p>In view of these facts therefore, and of the fact that
the American Colonization Society is unable to cope with the
present exigences of the work, and in view also of the part which
the American Government from the beginning of the Colony has
always taken in forwarding its interests, the President feels
that he may venture to solicit aid from your Government
to increase our civilized population, strengthen the foundations,
and enlarge the boundaries of the State, and consequently spread
peace and quietness throughout districts ever harried by restless
marauders thus opening and keeping open a highway for the
vast trade of Soudan which could be easily drawn in this

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.009"/>

direction instead of giving in such large quantities across the desert
to the Mediterranean; and the demand for American manufacture
in the interior is practically unlimited.</p>

<p>The President also desires me to say that it would be of 
incalculable advantage if one of the United States could
be detailed from the Mediterranean squadron once a year
between the months of December and March to cruise on 
the Liberian Coast. This would greatly assist us in maintaining 
the prestige of the Republic among the Aborigines at distant
points from the settlements along the Coast, and in infusing
new energy into the movement of our revenue officers. For
want of a Coast police the revenue from the Customs is very
inadequately collected.</p>

<p>The President ventures to call attention to the fact that
among the members of these who fostered Liberia in her early
days, and who did not think it contrary to the laws of the
United States that your Government should assist this
infant nation were leading American statesmen such as 
President Madison and Monroe in honor of whom the Capital
is named, Chief Justice Marshall, Bushrod Washington, General
Harper, Henry Clay, Daniel Webster, Rufus King, Edward Everett
and others. The President hope therefore that it will be considered
within the competence and ability of the United States
Government to come to the help of Liberia in the present
<catchwords>emergency</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.010"/>

emergency by small appropriation to aid deserving persons to come
and occupy the localities threatened from abroad, and thus save
us from the anxieties which perplex, and the dangers which menace
us.</p>

<p>I am further interested to say that for these advantages which
we ask of the United States, the Government of Liberia will be 
prepared under a special treaty to concede certain privileges to American
citizens doing business in Liberia, not granted to other foreigners,
privilege which if American capitalists would avail themselves of
them, would give them the virtual control of u large portion of the
trade of Coastal Africa, and American products and shipping would 
enjoy advantages which European traders have many years
sought in vain at the hands of the Government of Liberia.
The whole <unclear extent="one word"/> country lies before the American traders and
Agriculturists through Liberia the country to the penetration
and commercial possession of which French inspirations and
energies are now directed.</p>

<p>Should your Government take into favorable consideration
the requests and propositions made in this communication
and should desire it, the President will appoint one or two
special Commissioners to visit Washington to treat with the
Government of the United States in relation to these 
important matters.</p>

<p>Availing myself of this opportunity to assure you of

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.011"/>

my very high consideration and esteem.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be Sir<lb/>
Your Most Obedient Servant.<lb/>
G. W. Gibson</p>

<fw type="address">To the Honorable<lb/>
Secretary of State<lb/>
of the Untied States of America<lb/>
Washington
D.C.</fw>

</div1>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.012"/>

<p>Join Resolution
of thanks to the government of the
United States of America,
and an expression of gratitude to
Commodore. R. W. Shufeldt, U.S.N.</p>

<p>Whereas the government of the United
States of America, at the request of the
governments of Great Britain and
Liberia readily consented to act as 
Umpire in the settlement of the Liberian
North West Boundary Question and
appointed Commodore R. W. Shufeldt,
U.S.N. of the Flagship "Ticonderoga" 
to act on their part in the adjustment 
of the Liberian North West Boundary 
called in question by the English
Government and in view of the remarkable 
patience with which the Commodore
and his officers waited upon the movements 
of the Commissioners to their adjournment.
Therefore Resolved by the Senate and
House of Representatives of the Republic
of Liberia in Legislature assembled:</p>

<p>1. That the Legislature of Liberia by this resolution 
tender the thanks of the People of
Liberia to the Presidents of the United States
<catchwords>and</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0198.013"/>

and to the American Nation for
the cheerful manner in which they
accepted the joint solicitation of
the governments of England and
Liberia to use their good offices and Umpire,
as well as for their choice of so
able a naval officer as Commodore
Shufeldt to perform this important
Mission.</p>

<p>Resolved, That the government
of Liberia express their entire 
satisfaction with the efforts of the Commodore
to have the final and satisfactory
adjustment of this <unclear>vexed</unclear> question;
and they would record their gratitude 
to Commodore R. W. Shufeldt,
U.S.N., and his gallant officers.</p>

<p>Approved Jany. 1st: 1880.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
