<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0005">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John H. Smyth, "The African in Africa and the African in America" (1895)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0005</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The African in Africa and the African in America</title>
<title level="m">Apropos of Africa: Sentiments of Negro American Leaders on Africa from the 1800s to the 1950s</title>
<author>Smyth, John H.</author>
<editor>Kilson, Martin</editor>
<editor>Cromwell, Adeleide</editor>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>Frank Cass &amp; Co. LTD., 1969</publisher>
<date when="1895">1895</date>
<biblScope unit="page">49-58</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Imagined Africa</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Pan-Africanism</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9813857">Barth, Heinrich, 1821-1865</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61118399">Bowen, J. W. E. (John Wesley Edward), 1855-1933</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52473598">Colenso, John William, 1814-1883</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39456173">Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/97107753">Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603</term>
<term>Freeman, Martin Henry</term> 
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/69070194">Gordon, Charles George, 1833-1885</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71547594">Heeren, A.H.L. (Arnold Hermann Ludwig), 1760-1842</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/172419710">Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100225976">Herodotus</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14841695">Horton, James Africanus Beale</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51777477">Nachtigal, Gustav, 1834-1885</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/106963836">Park, Mungo, 1771-1806</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27187771">Schweinfurth, Georg August, 1836-1925</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/63570490">Smyth, John H., 1830-1888</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry M. (Henry Morton), 1841-1904</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/88054980">Venn, Henry, 1796-1873</term><!-- unsure -->
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36925883">Wilberforce, William, 1759-1833</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abeokuta (Nigeria)</term>
<term>Asia</term>
<term>Cameroon</term> 
<term>Central Africa</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Constantinople (Ottoman Empire)</term>
<term>Europe</term>
<term>Gold Coast</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Israel</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>North Africa</term>
<term>North Carolina</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Rome</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Turkey</term>
<term>West Africa</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Spain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Abyssinian</term>
<term>Arku</term>
<term>Bassa</term>
<term>Carthaginian</term>
<term>Congo</term>
<term>Ebo</term>
<term>Egyptian</term>
<term>Fula</term>
<term>Gola</term>
<term>Grebo</term>
<term>Jolof</term>
<term>Kroo</term> 
<term>Mandingo</term>
<term>Moorish</term>
<term>Nubian</term>
<term>Pessey</term> 
<term>Sosoo</term>
<term>Vey</term>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Islam</term>
<term>Catholic</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-14" who="#kln">edited encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">scanned, OCRed, and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p49"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">The African in Africa and the African in America*</head>

<head type="sub">The Hon. J. H. Smyth, LL.D.</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="text">

<p>The fact will be readily admitted by those most familiar with the
sentiment of a large and not unimportant portion of our American
citizenship, who, by the fortunes and misfortunes of war, viewed from
the standpoint of one or the other combatants of the sanguinary
struggle of 1861-62-63-64, were made equal before the law with all
other citizens, that as a class they are averse to the discussion of
Africa when their relationship with that ancient and mysterious land
and its races is made the subject of discourse or reflection. The remoteness 
of Africa from America may be a reason for such feeling;
the current opinion in the minds of the Caucasians, whence the
American Negroes' opinions are derived, that the African is by
nature an inferior man, may be a reason. The illiteracy, poverty, and
degradation of the Negro, pure and simple, as known in Christian
lands, may be a reason in connection with the partially true and
partially false impression that the Negroes, or Africans, are pagan
and heathen as a whole, and as a sequence hopelessly degraded beings. 
These may be some of the reasons that make the subject of
Africa discordant and unmusical to our ears. It is amid such embarrassments 
that the lecturer, the orator, the missionary must present
Africa to the Negro in Christian America.</p>

<p>In view of recent newspaper articles about migration of Negroes
to Liberia, so much has been recently said by men of African descent
of prominence, and by men of like prominence of uncertain descent,
and by men of other races than the Negro, of Liberia and Africa
generally, that I deem it a duty as an American citizen and a Negro,
in vindication of the men and women of like descent with myself,
citizens of the United States, to state some facts explanatory of and
in rebuttal of much that has been said, ignorantly, unwisely and  

<fw type="note">* Professor J. W. E. Bowen, Ph.D., D.D., Editor, <hi rend="italics">Africa and the American Negro</hi>. Addresses &amp; Proceedings of the Congress on Africa held under the auspices of the Stewart Missionary Foundation for Africa of Gammon Theological Seminary in connection with the Cotton States and International Exposition, Dec. 13-15, 1895. Atlanta: Gammon Theological Seminary, 1896. pp. 73-83.</fw>

<pb n="p50"/>

unsympathetically, to the detriment of the effort being made at self-government 
in Liberia, West Africa. The people who constitute the
inhabitants and citizenship of Liberia (the largest portion of the
latter class are American Negroes from the Southern part of the
United States) are possessed of and imbued with the sentiment and
the civilization peculiar to this section of our country. That these immigrant 
Negroes who migrated to West Africa, or began migration
as far back as 1820, and who continue to go thither, have a better
field there, with less embarrassing environment, to prove their capacity 
for self-government, for leadership in State-craft than their
brethren in the northern, western and southern portions of the
United States, will scarcely be seriously denied or questioned.
This conceded, it seems to me that wisdom, self-respect, race loyalty,
and American patriotism would show themselves richer to withhold
judgment as to the success of the experiment being made in Africa for
self-government until such time as this immigrant people and their
descendants have lived in Liberia, Sierra Leone, the Gold Coast, the
Camaroons and other parts of West Africa long enough to assimilate
the sentiment of liberty and rule, the general heritage and possession
of the native African, than it has shown itself in echoing the expression 
of opinion of white men, whatever their learning or literary
capacity, who estimate the progress of the Negro by the standard of
their own race with its superior opportunities, advantages and facilities.</p>

<p>Until we have demonstrated ability for organization, for government, 
and have shown effective cohesiveness and leadership here in
the United States, it may be a little immodest to hastily and unadvisedly 
make up the record adverse to our immediate kith and kin,
who less than sixty years ago made the first step on lines of independent 
form of government of themselves, and have successfully maintained 
themselves against the greed of Spain, the aggrandizement
of France, and the envy and cupidity of the merchant class of England 
without active assistance or defense of our formidable North
African squadron; without an army and without more than one
gunboat, the property of the Republic.</p>

<p>Liberia is the only democratic republican form of government
on the continent of Africa of which we have any knowledge. The
civilization of the people constituting the majority of the citizenship
of Liberia is American. It embraces that phase of our American system 
which has made the autonomy of the south distinct from that of
all other parts of our common country. This is the resultant of the
outgrowth of the laws and customs of the severalty as well as the

<pb n="p51"/>

jointness of that system of government which exists in the South.
In so far as the civilization of the United States on analysis is differentiated 
as northern, southern, eastern, and western, and in the south
as Virginian, Carolinian, Georgian, it may be said, that the people
composing the nation have transferred such American phases of
government to this part of Africa.</p>

<p>The pioneers of this colony, the descendants of them, and the
immigrants that have gone from here at varying periods of time
within sixty years, like those of us who have remained, have been the
unhappy victims of the influences of an alien, racial oppression; are
fragments of races and tribes, and lack much in capacity for maintaining 
a stable form of government without the aid which comes
from the moral support of the United States. But notwithstanding
the embarrassments and difficulties of this youthful nation, the
elements of success are being gradually, surely and deeply laid in
industrial and agricultural concerns. The masses of the people are
directing their effort to agriculture, the development of the soil, and
are leaving the matter of coast-commerce or barter to the few.</p>

<p>No epitome or summary of Liberia would be worthy of the name
which failed to take note of the renaissance of education under the
scholarly Blyden and Freeman, both of whom have been presidents
of Liberia College. When the former scholar came to the presidency
of the college, then was commenced the work of the adaptation of
the training of the youth for the definitive and distinct purpose of
advancing the nation on the line of race. This institution has sent
forth strong Negro men, who are unperverted in their instincts,
strong in their race loyalty, and unhampered by a civilization upon
which the individuality of the race is not stamped. Such a civilization,
unmodified, is unsuited to the African in Africa, or out of Africa
and although it may develop him religiously, in manly, self-reliant
feeling, it will make him a weakling and will be destructive of true
manhood, self-respect and race integrity.</p>

<p>It is lamentable that two hundred and fifty years have removed us
to a far greater distance from Africa than the geographical measurement 
which separates America from Africa, and to-day that continent
is perhaps of less interest to the educated and refined Negro of
America than to his thrifty, industrious and adventurous white
fellow-citizen....</p>

<p>The wrong done us here in America, the wrong done us in Turkey
in Asia, and Turkey in Europe, and Constantinople, is being recognized 
at the center of Anglo-Saxon civilization, as is honestly indicated 
by utterances such as these: "It is too late to ask, 'Are we

<pb n="p52"/>

our brother's keeper?"' Three centuries ago the plea might have
seemed specious, but since then Europe has made itself guilty towards 
Africa of the blackest series of crimes that stain the foul record
of civilized history. The actual appalling state of things in Africa
is the result of the policy of Europe towards the African races.
European contact has brought in its train not merely the sacrifice,
amid unspeakable horrors, of the lives and liberties of twenty million 
Negroes for the American market alone, but political disintegration, 
social anarchy, moral and physical debasement, the decay of
the simple arts and industries which had been developed during centuries 
of undisturbed and uneventful existence. Christian Europe, it is
true, no longer openly tolerates the slave trade, but Christian Europe
furnishes the arms by means of which the slave trade is carried on.
The European explorer paves the way for the Arab man-hunter; in
his track follow not the blessings of civilization, but conflagration,
rapine, and murder, and European trade, while extinguishing native
handicrafts, places within the African's grasp the power of self-destruction 
by spirits and of mutual destruction by firearms.</p>

<p>I am aware that it will be insisted by some who have failed to give
this matter the consideration which it merits, that we are a part of
the greatest composite nationality, and therefore, any influence that
would make the Negro less American and more African than he is,
would be injurious to the best interest of our American nation. I
would gladly impress upon persons entertaining such thoughts, that
race allegiance is compatible with patriotism, with love of the land
that gave us birth. This has been abundantly shown to be true with
reference to the Jews. Whatever doubts may be entertained upon
this point on account of their wide religious divergence from other
religionists, must undergo a change in the presence of the admonition 
given in a missive sent to Israel by the Prophet Jeremiah, and
which has been faithfully conformed to by Israel and the descendants
of Israel: "Serve the King of Babylon, and live. Build ye houses and
dwell in them; and plant gardens and eat the fruits of them. And
seek the welfare of the city whither I have caused you to be carried
away captives, and pray unto the Lord for it; for in the peace thereof
shall ye have peace."</p>

<p>Though we are a part of this great national whole, we are a distinct 
and separate part, an alien part racially, and destined to be
so by the immutable law of race pride, which is possessed by our
white fellow-citizens, if not by us. The sentiment, the something
stronger than sentiment which makes an English American proud
of his connection with Britain, a French American proud of his connection 

<pb n="p53"/>

with La Belle France, and a German American fondly attached 
to the memories of the fatherland, and all European races of
their Aryan descent, has something that partakes of the moral sublime. 
Truly "language and religion do not make a race."</p>

<p>The characteristics, peculiarities, idiosyncrasies and habits have
been determined by what has been displayed and noted of Negroes
under influences foreign to them and beyond their control. This has
been the cause of inaccurate knowledge of the races of Africa on the
part of the whites, and inaccurate knowledge on the part of the
Negroes themselves....</p>

<p>The Civilized Negro here has but recently emerged from slavery
and been recognized a freeman; and though guaranteed in the possession 
of political rights, is still hampered by his inability to understand 
himself, by the conviction that on account of the political unity
of the races here, his end must be reached by pursuit of the same line
followed by the controlling races.</p>

<p>The condition of the race past and present here makes the American 
Negro African, without the peculiarities of his race; and African
only as to the hue of his skin and his blood. The black man here is
Americanized, and as a sequence, sectionalized.</p>

<p>Now the difference between Africa in America, and Africa in
Africa being recognized, let us look to Africa in Africa. The races of
Africa have not been a subject of Caucasian study.</p>

<p>The Egyptian, Carthaginian, and Moorish people are imperfectly
known, and the interior, eastern, western races, are still more imperfectly 
understood, and for very prudential reasons,—the uncompromising 
conditions of climate toward European peoples, and the
almost insuperable difficulties of ingress to the country. . . .</p>

<p>The testimony of Africans, distinguished for their knowledge of
their countrymen, for their learning and character, should be looked
to, and consulted as authorities in these matters. The Arku and Ebo
races are not to be known through the flippant and inconsiderate
statements of some ignorant European who finds to his surprise and
annoyance that he cannot successfully take advantage of them in a
business transaction, and as a consequence declares the former people
a deceptive, ignorant class, and the latter an insolent, lazy set. You
are to read the history of these races in the light of what the learned
Dr. Africanus Horton has written in his "Africa and the Africans,"
and what his lordship Bishop Crowther experienced in his successful
labor of love among his own and other races.</p>

<p>A comprehensive knowledge of the Christian, Mohammedan, and
heathen Africans of Central and West Africa must be read in the

<pb n="p54"/>

light of the full and exhaustive information to be found in the writings 
of Edward W. Blyden, D.D., LL.D., late president of Liberia's
college. Christianity in the third and fourth centuries among the
Africans must be studied, in the Africans' fathers, and in Lloyd's
North African Church and in Abyssinian traditions.</p>

<p>The missionary work in West Africa in the fifteenth century may
be read in the voluminous Spanish and Portuguese and Italian state
papers and travels. A few most valuable ones as to the Congo races
are to be found in an English translation made during the reigns of
Henry VIII. and Elizabeth. Bishops Crowther and Colenso may be
read on African character with profit. There are two classics, African,
which should be read: A. H. L. Heeren, African Researches, and a
portion of Herodotus.</p>

<p>For quite fair treatment of African character, French and German
explorations are interesting and in English, Mungo Park, Livingstone,
and Gordon Pasha.</p>

<p>Having directed attention to the means and some of the sources to
be relied on for facts concerning native African character, I now
point to some illustrations of error and wrong in dealing with the 
African in Africa.</p>

<p>It is not to our century alone that we are to look for active but
mistaken effort to christianize Africa. There has existed no African
mission, which, in the same period of time, attained to such proportions
as the Portuguese mission in the Congo region during the
fifteenth century. A cathedral and churches adorned, beautified, and
glorified that portion of West Africa, and a Congo gentleman, after
pursuing the necessary course of study in Spain prescribed for the
priesthood, was made a bishop, and returned to his country to carry
on the work of christianizing his people through the religion of
Catholic Rome. All this work passed away. The ships which brought
priests as outward passengers took the human product of the race
back as homeward cargo. The theory and practice of the European
being in opposition, the one to the other, the work perished. The
the fetich of the cross in the hands of the Portuguese, did not deter them
from knavery and theft and murder, and the Congoes concluded that
their fetiches were less harmful than the alien Portuguese.</p>

<p>Africans cannot be influenced by aliens, who, however Christian,
seek to subvert their manhood. With the African at home, service to
God and service to his fetich will not be yielded if manhood be the
sacrifice.</p>

<p>He may be forced to accept a dogma or a religion, but will not
receive either under such circumstances. Alien races can aid the pro- 

<pb n="p55"/>

gress of Christianity and civilization among Africans, but cannot
control it with hope of ultimate success in Africa. . . .</p>

<p>In the British colony of Sierra Leone opportunity is afforded to
study native character, as at no other place with which I am acquainted. 
The representatives of not less than a hundred tribes may
be seen here and of not a few races. Here one may see the stately and
grave Mandingo, the diplomatic Sosoo, the frail but handsome Foulah, 
and the paragon of men, the magnificent Jollof, "his complexion
free from any taint of Abyssinian blue or Nubian bronze, intensely,
lustrously, magnificently black."</p>

<p>Of the foregoing races there has been no acceptance of anything
of foreign civilization. These races represent a very high and unique
type of Mohammedanism and Arabic training. They have adopted
the religion of the Prophet and made it to conform to themselves.
They have written their own commentaries on the sacred book. They
are not controlled by the Arab, the Persian, or the Turk as to their
conception of the Koran. Their women share in common with the
men in the instructions of the masters. But there are two distinct
races here, and some of each of them in Liberia, the Ebo and Arku
races, among whom is displayed the highest type of English civilization, 
with their free, unhampered peculiarities and idiosyncrasies.
These two races control and direct commercial interest in Sierra
Leone, on the Gold Coast and at Lagos, and have brought peace
to war and order from confusion in the independent Negro nations
of Abbeokuta.</p>

<p>Among these races, in religion are the Crowthers; in medical and
surgical science, the Davises and Hortons; in jurisprudence, the
Lewises and McCarthys; in pure scholarship, the Blydens, Coles,
and Quakers; in the mercantile profession, the Boyles, Williams,
Grants, and Sawyers. The time was when these two races were opposed 
to each other, but happily much of the tribal hatred has been
destroyed by contact and education. These people are distinct in their
bent of character. The Arku race is marked by a suavity of manner,
a disposition to please, which borders on obsequiousness, and are
industrious. They live upon a very little that they may save very much.
They are never found to be improvident. The women make most
affectionate wives, and have no peers in the world in their disposition
to prove themselves helpmeets. It is said that the refusal by a husband 
to allow an Arku wife to help him, not infrequently causes
marital difficulties. She prefers to trade than to remain indoors
attending to her domestic affairs and babies. In complexion this
race represents the average dark complexion of the American Negro.</p>

<pb n="p56"/>

<p>The Ebo is a proud, daring race. They are always industrious,
are fond of display, and in their hospitality are ostentatious. It
may be asserted that there exists no evidence to show these people
ever to have been pagan, in their home on the Niger or elsewhere.
As a race they have never received either Christianity or Mohammedanism 
but claim to believe sincerely in God. Those in the British
colony have assimilated Christianity and some have attained to the
highest culture and refinement. The first Negro graduate of Oxford
was an Ebo. The most distinguished physician—-Negro physician--
living up to 1884 was Dr. Horton, an Ebo. The knowledge of reading,
and writing and ciphering, in short, rudimentary training in this
colony, has been very thorough. To Wilberforce and Venn be lasting
honor and praise for their effective work in the British colonies of
West Africa. . . .</p>

<p>The principal races here are Mandingos, Kru and Graybo and
Bassa people, cognate races; Veys, Golas and Pesseys. My contact
Has been with these races in the civilized settlements, and in their
own towns and villages. It would be a task to describe them with the
accuracy their tribal and racial differences merit....</p>

<p>The Golas as a race are courageous and intrepid, and kindly in
their relation with the Americo-Liberian, preferring peace with
them to war. The Pesseys, once a martial race, have by internal dissension 
and wars with other races, to an alarming extent lost their
independence and many of that once noble race have been made captives
to other peoples and slaves. As slaves they are highly valued,
being indefatigable laborers, and therefore admired bondsmen by
their masters. Their language has the softness and liquid sweetness of
Italian, being in striking contrast to the harshness of the Kru and
Greybo tongue. . . .</p>

<p>I should perhaps leave an impression which would be misleading
as to Liberia and Africa unless I be more explicit. If you have observed, 
in any utterance of mine, anything about Africa which seems
to possess in itself, or as to the races of that continent, a roseate hue,
be pleased to remember that I have faintly, and with unartistic hand,
shown you a part of this garden of the Lord and limned its inhabitants
with the pencil and brush of an amateur; and I appeal to Mungo
Park, the sainted Livingstone, Barth, Schweinfurth, Nachtigal, and I
may risk Stanley in the rear of this galaxy of friends of Africa, for
more accurate data for larger and fuller experiences. But I may
astound you when I say that Africa fears not the invasion of her
shores by Europe and the rightful acquisition of her territory, and
that no Negro who knows Africa regards the European's advent

<pb n="p57"/>

there as a menace to the progress and advancement of her races,
except when they bring with them rum and fire-arms. I am pronouncedly, 
and have been since I first stepped upon the soil of my
fatherland in 1878, an African colonizationist, but I am so in a
strictly qualified sense, as is shown in the official statement made to
my and your government—made from the United States Consulate 
General, Monrovia, under the date of February 21, 1883.</p>

<p>It may not be inopportune or out of place to say, in the interest
of the prospective immigrant and in the interest of Liberia, that it
is perhaps unwise for persons to emigrate here simply for the purpose 
of being free and enjoying complete civil liberty and social
equality. The State is young, and, though poor in developed resources, 
is vigorous in purpose and effort, and needy only of additional 
influences of civilization which are possessed by those who, at
their homes, have displayed the ability of independent labor and
proprietorship. That is to say, that the man needed as an immigrant
here is one who, in his home, displays industry and fixedness of
purpose sufficient to cause him to stick at work of some kind until he
has earned and saved enough to purchase a comfortable home, is
competent to control it and does control it, or a man who has entered 
upon a business and has self-denial enough to continue in it to
the end of respectably supporting himself and family, or who
has made himself a boss of some supporting trade—a man who is not
directly dependent upon being a common servant, and who is not an
ignorant laborer incapable of turning up something by his innate
good sense and the God-given push within him. . . .</p>

<p>As a clear understanding of the conditions of labor here is important 
to that class of foreign Negroes who contemplate settlement
here. The possession of a few hundred dollars, skill in labor, and
executive ability, constitute a capital that cannot but secure a most
<sic>confortable</sic> living here with a probability of wealth.</p>

<p>Unless the Negro out of Africa goes to Africa seeking a home because 
he has none; goes of his own volition, with as correct a knowledge 
of Africa as may be obtained from the writings of trustworthy
African travelers and explorers and missionaries, reinforced by race
loyalty, and with greater confidence in himself and his race than in
any alien self and alien race; goes from a sense of duty imposed by
his Christian enlightenment, and not unprovided with ability and
previous experience to organize and control labor, with as ample
means as he would go with from the Atlantic coast of the United
States to the Pacific slope for the purpose of engaging in business,
he is wholly and entirely unsuited for Africa, and would impede by

<pb n="p58"/>

his presence not only the progress of Liberia (if he went thither), but
any part of Africa by his unprofitable presence, and ought to be
denied the right to expatriate himself.</p>

<p>If by anything that I have said you have been impressed with the
fact that you are descendants of African races and as a consequence
that you are a separate and distinct people from Caucasian races,
and that the highest excellence to which an individual can attain
must be to work according to the best of his genius, and the other
to work in harmony with God's design in his creation, on his race
line; if I have impressed you at all with the wisdom or propriety
of confiding in the highest Negro authorities and the best alien writings, 
for reliable data respecting our race in the fatherland, and thereby 
awakened in you an interest and sincere desire for the well being
of Africa and her races, for our people, and for accurate information
concerning that most ancient, and most mysterious of lands; then I
led conscious of having made a contribution of information not
wholly valueless to my countrymen that may tend to modify and
dissipate general ignorance of us and of our antecedents and their
country; and I have done something toward awakening your dormant
self-respect, and given you some conception of the dignity which
attaches to Negro manhood, and created in you a preference for
your race before all other races; and this sentiment, if produced,
will place you en rapport with the Negroes in Africa, who have no
conception of any land greater, more beautiful than their own; any
men braver and manlier than themselves, any women better, <sic>lovlier,</sic>
and handsomer than African women. Then you will retire from this
place with a feeling of stimulus rather than of satiety, of unrest rather
than of repose; then shall I retire from my effort to interest you in
Africa in Africa, and Africa in America with satisfied pride in having
performed something of duty as a Negro—clear in his conviction
of the high destiny in reserve for Africa and its races, and of your
duty to be loyal to the race, since true allegiance will make us
sharers in that glory which the sacred writing declares shall come,
when Ethiopia shall stretch forth her hand unto God.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>