<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0522">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from Robert S. Newton to George L. Rives, November 15, 1888</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0522</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from Robert S. Newton to George L. Rives</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date from="1888-11-15">November 15, 1888</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Folque</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Ambaca (Angola)</term>
<term>Cazengo (Angola)</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
        
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Newton, Robert Scott</persName>
<roleName>Acting U.S. Consul at Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<date when="1888-11-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29909070">Rives, George Lockhart, 1849-1917</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
<date when="1888-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-01-15" who="kln">Reviewed transcription and encoded</change>
<change when="2019" who="caa">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0522.001"/>

<note>Department of State Received Dec 31 1888</note>

<note>No. 1</note>

<p>United States Consulate<lb/>
St. Paul de Loanda<lb/>
15 November 1888</p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I have the honor to report for the information of the
Department, that on the 31st October, the first
section, consisting of 45 kilometers, of the Royal
Trans African Railway from Loanda to Ambaca, was 
opened to the public. The inauguration ceremony
was gone through in the presence of the whole of the
commercial community and great numbers of the
native population the religious portion blessing the
engine &amp;c, being undertaken by the Vicar General, in
the absence of the Bishop. After the religious part of
the ceremony was concluded, the directing Engineer
and representative of the company, Major Folque of
the Engineers, spoke on the previous attempts made
to establish a Railway system in the same direction,
of the many difficulties they had had to encounter
(and which they had succeeded in surmounting)
in their endeavours to carry the project to a 
practical commencement; eulogising the enterprise
<catchwords>and</catchwords>

<fw type="address">To The Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington D.C.</fw>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0522.002"/>

and energy of the Portuguese nation in the
development of her colonies, especially in Africa,
and claiming for this undertaking the making of 
a new era in the prosperity of this large province
of Angola, and in the civilisation of the African
race generally.</p>

<p>The line passes through districts alternating
between large tracts of prairie, wooded hills, and
fertile valleys watered by rivers and streams.
The country about the margins of these rivers is
already cultivated both by natives and Europeans,
and produces fruit in abundance, vegetables,
sweet potatoes, and large quantities of sugar cane.
With the facilities now offered by the Railway for
the carriage of machinery and materials for 
building purposes there is every prospect in the
near future of the large tracts of uncultivated
land being made to yield their quota of agricultural
produce.</p>

<p>There are proofs at hand of the utilizing of
this enterprise to the commercial community
generally, and to the agriculturist in the interior.</p>

<p>Large quantities of coffee are stored in the
district of Cazengo, owing to the want of carriers.
Thus the produce is tied up to the serious loss of
<catchwords>both</catchwords>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0522.003"/>

both agriculturists and merchants here. The
coffee market in Europe is much better now than
it has been for several months, but the merchants
here are simply debarred from taking advantage 
of it, as they cannot get the coffee off the plantation
and in the meantime they not only lose a good
market, but interest is running on the Capital
so locked up. If the Railway were completed
to this district, all such risks would be
completely done away with.</p>

<p>If now that they have commenced, they will
go ahead and carry the line to completion as quickly
as possible, the prosperity of the province would be
assured. They have however, a rather difficult
country to go through before they reach Ambaca,
and there is not much prospect of the line being
completed within three years.</p>

<p>A train runs from Loanda daily over
the open sections, and the natives are already
beginning to make use of it</p>

<p>I am Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Robt S Newton<lb/>
In charge of US Consulate</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>