<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0340">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from D. L. Marsins to Commander of French War Vessel, March 13, 1883</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Brown, Sophie A." xml:id="sab">Sophie A. Brown</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0340</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Letter from D. L. Marsins to Commander of French War Vessel, March 13, 1883</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States Consuls in St Paul Loanda</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">Roll 4</biblScope>
<date when="1883-03-20">March 20, 1883</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Encounters with Natives</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Brazao, Antonio F.</term>
<term>Dore, Walter</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Loanda (Angola)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>France</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-08" who="kln">reviewed and edited.</change>
<change when="2019" who="#sab">transcribed, encoded.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0340.001"/>

<p>Loango March the 13th 1883.</p>
 
<p>To the Commander of the French War Vessel<lb/> 
To anchor in Loango <unclear extent="one word"/></p>

<p>Sir.</p>

<p>Having heard from several white men, that you had, or were going to take Possession of this Country, in the name of the French Government, and having heard also that the Natives in that case would out of revenge, attack, plunder, and destroy the several trading houses in this place, and afterwords take to the bush, I, undersigned a citizen of the United States of North America doing business in this place, and in other points near here, having American and British property in charge, find myself obliged to address you the following considerations</p>

<p>That it is almost certain that as soon as the Natives find out that you are taking possession of their country, they will out of revenge, attack the factories, and plunder and destroy everything, thus entailing ruin on innocent traders, who have nothing whatever to do with these questions.</p>

<p>That the presence of your vessel, will not deter them from so doing, as they will very likely make a night attack, and by making it general preclude the possibility of the white men helping each other.</p>

<p>That as soon as they have plundered and destroyed the Factories, killing very likely also some of the white men, they will take to the Bush, as the loss of their villages is as nothing to them, making it impossible to find and punish them.</p>

<p>Considering these Circumstances, the Undersigned think it incumbent to him, as a citizen of the United States

<pb facs="Scan20001"/>

of America, as proprietor and Agent, having American and British
property in charge, to formally protest against you and the
French Government individually and collectively, for any loss or
damage that may accrue to him through any <sic>through any</sic> 
Acts caused by yours or by the French Government orders,
including additional expenses and loss of time or any other damage
direct or indirect.</p>

<p>Hoping that you will take due notice
of this my formal protest, (a copy of <sic>wich</sic> will be forwarded
to the American Consuls at Gaboon and Loanda),
and that you will kindly send me an acknowledgement
of his receipt, I remain with the greatest consideration</p>

<p>Most Respctly,<lb/> 
Your Obedt Servant<lb/>
D. L. Marsins.</p>

<p>Witness.<lb/>
Antonio F. Brazao<lb/>
Walter Dore</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>

