<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0569">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Dispatch from Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton, December 31, 1891</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea A" xml:id="caa">Chelsea Animwaa Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0569</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Héli Chatelain to William F. Wharton</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">5</biblScope>
<date from="1891-12-31">December 31, 1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64810727">Arnot, Fred. S. (Frederick Stanley), 1858-1914</term>
<term>Bannister, Edward</term>
<term>Baracho, Dantas</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5231569">Braconnier, Charles-Marie de</term>
<term>Faulkner</term>
<term>Hyde, J. Chester</term>
<term>Mushiri</term>
<term>Sharpe</term>
<term>Taunt, Emory H.</term>
<term>Vandevelde</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/284497166">Wahis, Théophile, 1844-1921</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Benguela (Angola)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Gaboon</term>
<term>Garnganze</term>
<term>Katanga (Congo)</term>
<term>Loanda (Angola)</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Novo Redondo (Angola)</term>
<term>Oporto (Portugal)</term>
<term>San Salvador (Congo)</term>
<term>São Tomé</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term>English</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Baptist</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68793274">Chatelain, Héli</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent at Loanda</roleName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda, Angola</placeName>
<date when="1891-12-31"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70343272">Wharton, William Fisher, 1847-1919</persName>
<roleName>Assistant U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>
<date when="1892-02-23"/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2020-01-28" who="kln">Reviewed transcription and encoded</change>
<change when="2019" who="caa">Transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.001"/>

<note>No. 17</note>
<note>Department of State Received Feb 23 1892</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/> 
St. Paul de Loanda, Dec. 31, 1891</p>

<p>Mr. Heli Chatelain<lb/>
To the Department of State.</p>

<p>Subject:</p>

<p>Miscellaneous News.</p>

<p>Abstract of Contents.</p>

<p>I - The first rains have been abundant. Hence: sickness,
perspective plenty, lack of free labor, and greater demand
for unfree labor, and increased traffic in same.</p>

<p>II - The Congo-State recruiting agent, tho' offering high prices,
has not yet obtained any men. The idea of Angola's independence 
gaining ground both in Portugal and here.
The three principal political convicts continue to escape. The
commissioner for boundaries with Congo State still here. The
government immigrants a curse rather than a blessing.</p>

<p>III - A new line of steamers has been started by a Jewish firm.</p>

<p>IV - A young man from Congo District, belonging to Baptist
Mission there, is released, owing to my unofficial <del>steps</del> intercession</p>

<p>V - A missionary on the Congo wants to know whether he has not
the right to fly the stars and stripes, as he pleases.</p>

<p>VI The King of Garenganze rejects the British Protectorate</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.002"/>

<note>No. 17</note>

<p>Consulate of the United States,<lb/>
St. Paul de Loanda, Dec. 31, 1891</p>

<p>Honorable William F. Wharton<lb/>
Assistant Secretary of State,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>Sir:</p>

<p>Desiring to inform the Department of various
occurrences, each of which is not important enough
for a special Report, but may be of some use, especially 
to the editor of the Consular Reports, I
collect them all in one Despatch of Miscellaneous
News.</p>

<p>I. Rains, Sickness, Plenty, Lack of free labor and 
demand for unfree labor. After two years of drought,
the first rains (Sept. to Jan.) have been very copious
and this fact is attended by the three following consequences: (1) With the unusual dampness of the season,  
fevers and other tropical diseases have increased to an 
alarming extent. Nobody escapes the effects of the miasma;
one by one, all are laid on the sick-bed, some
to rise no more, the great majority, to ail on for
some time and then resume their normal state
and usual occupations. I have been suffering

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.003"/>

these two months from a kind of rheumatism and
hand have had two review attacks of fever.</p>

<p>(2) With the drought, the dearth is coming to an 
end, and 1892 promises to be a your of plenty.
How great the dearth was, may be inferred from
the fact that large quantities of Brazilian manioc-meal ("farinha de pás") were imported into this land
of manioc and sold for about half the price of the
best native article, while foreign (American) corn,
rice and beans successfully competed with those
of the country. One good result of the dearth is that
the natives have learnt to eat bread, and having 
once acquired the habit, are not likely to give it
up with the return of cheap native produce. This enlarged
consumption of bread means an important increase 
in the importation of American flour.</p>

<p>(3) As soon as the showers soften the soil, the natives 
leave the exacting service of the whites and take
the cultivation of their own fields. This causes
a lack of carriers for the rubber and wax of the
far interior as well as for the coffee of the Cazengo
plantations and a general insufficiency of free
hired laborers for the railroad and all other
work depending on them. This shortening necessarily 
entails an increased demand for unfree,

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.004"/>

or contract, labor. Within a short time, the prices of 
"servicaes" at Novo Redondo (Novo Redondo) and Benguella,
which are now the principal markets, have risen from 
40 to 70 milreis (one milreis = $1.09) per head, and the
prices may rise to double that amount before long.
The dealers say that the Congo State recruiting agent
offers them 750 milreis per man, and make this a 
plea for screwing up the prices of course the greater
the profits realized in the business the greater also the
activity developed in procuring the merchandise, that
is in "redeeming" slaves from the interior, which is 
simply a revised edition, of the old slave-traffic.</p>

<p>II Political News. The Congo State officer, Mons.
Braconnier, who has taken the place of the unfortunate
Vandevelde, as recruiting agent of 500 Angola
men for the Congo State army is still here at a hotel
waiting for the Portuguese residents to relax their 
opposition to this exportation of unfree labor. The
resistance of the colonists to the home government
in this matter has met with the approval of the whole
colonial and liberal press in Portugal. Some papers even 
go so far as to advise Angola to demand self government 
and prepare its independence. The prospect of 
bankruptcy in Portugal inclines the Portuguese residents 
in favor of the native ideal of independence.</p>

<p>Rather separation than shame is the motto of many.
Meanwhile, here as in Portugal, men of action are

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.005"/>

not to be found.</p>

<p>Aided by friends and officials, the three principal
rebels of the late insurrection at Oporto, have managed
to escape from their exile. One went to Gaboon; the 
whereabouts of the two others is known only to the friends
who saw them off.</p>

<p>Senhor Dantas Baracho, the Portuguese Commissioner
for defining the Eastern boundary of Angola with the
Congo State has been here since August doing nothing but earn
his salary, the total of which is said to amount to
twelve Pounds (60 dollars) per day. Nor is there any
sign or probability of his going to his destination
before next May or June. As his salary is charged 
to the Provincial Treasury, the dissatisfaction of the
colonists may be imagined.</p>

<p>Every Portuguese packet continues to bring from
50-60 emigrants sent to the West-Coast by the
Portuguese Government in order to deplete the
prisons and get rid of dangerous and starving
tramps. While rational colonization would be 
a blessing to the Province and the home-country,
this kind of assisted emigration is a curse and
a source of endless troubles.</p>

<p>III New Line of Steamers. Nothing proves better
the immense resources and growing prosperity
of the Province then the rapid and steady development 
of steam navigation. While our

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.006"/>

Philadelphia Board of Trade and enterprising men
of Baltimore and New York have talked for years
about a steam ship line to connect America with
Africa, and have not yet reached the point of sending
a trial steamer, the humble Jewish firm of Benchimol 
&amp; Sobrinho (Lisbon &amp; Loanda) has within
five months bought, repaired and run between Angola,
S. Thomé, Lisbon and Liverpool, four old English
steamers, a far trips of which will suffice to pay 
their cost. Without lowering the freight-charged
by the other company without Government aid, the enterprize 
has proved a grand success.</p>

<p>There is some talk of a third Portuguese Company
running steamers between the same ports.</p>

<p>IV - Vita case. About a year ago, a pupil of
the Baptist Mission at San Salvador (in the Congo
District of this Province) called Vita, accidentally
shot one his comrades. He was examined by the
Portuguese Resident (who knows neither English nor
the Kongo language) and sent, a prisoner, to 
Loanda, there to be judged by the competent authority.
As, after months of waiting, the missionaries 
heard nothing about the lad, two of them 
came at different times to Loanda to find out
his whereabouts and to have him bought to trial
Mr. Ed. Bannister (then acting British Consul)
did what he could for them, but in vain</p>

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.007"/>

<p>Hearing of my arrival, the missionaries thought my
popularity might be more successful, and wrote to 
ask my intervention on the lad's behalf. I answered,
that, as the lad was a Portuguese subject I could
do nothing officially, but would use my private <unclear>influence</unclear>
in favor of their protégé. Not only was I immediately 
told where the prisoner was, and allowed to see him,
but the "Delegado" who was to judge the case, and
to whom I explained the particulars, released the
poor fellow with the statement that the papers 
concerning the case had disappeared. The young
man had been kept eight months in jail without
trial and (forgotten as his case was) might have
rotted away there, had not his missionary protection 
persevered to the end.</p>

<p>V Stars and Stripes in Congo State. On Dec. 8
Rev: J. Chester Hyde, of the American Baptist <unclear>Mission</unclear>
wrote to me as the nearest consul, since the <del>absence</del> death
of Lieut. Taunt, desiring some information on the
right of flying the Stars and Stripes in the Congo 
State. "In Nov. (1891)" says <unclear>he</unclear> "Governor General
Wahis; returning from the interior, visited me, and
I flew the stars and stripes in his honor. The
next day the commissary of our district informed 
me that only consuls were allowed
to display their national colors beyond the
limits of Matadá and I was requested to comply

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.008"/>

with the laws. Perhaps you may have some instructions 
concerning the stars and stripes. I answered
that (1) the Congo State is outside my consular sphere,
(2) but I would communicate the matter to you, and (3) 
in my private opinion the display of flags is a matter
of courtesy, not of right, but that if, in <unclear>identia</unclear>
circumstances, other nationalities were allowed to
display their colors, an American might expect the 
same privilege.</p>

<p>Complaints against over regulation and taxation,
and irksome red-tape in the Congo State are general
among traders and missionaries of all nationalities.</p>

<p>VI I have just seen, on his way home, Mr. Faulkner,
a Canadian missionary, who spent a few years in Katanga,
or Garenganze, as it is known through Fred.
A. Arnot's book. He told me how Mushiri, the 
King of Garnganze, was alarmed when he saw Mr.
Sharpe, the agent of the "British South Africa Company"
approach his capital from the East, "by the back door"
as he styled it, and how he absolutely rejected the 
proposed British Protectorate and bade Mr. Sharpe
leave his country at once, as soon as he heard that the
British wanted his copper mines. As is well known,
the Congo State has already conceded all those mines
and the whole of Mushiri's Kingdom to the Belgian
Katanga Company, though no Belgian had ever set
there a foot or got permission from Mushiri to exploit

<pb facs="teaa.en.letter.0569.009"/>

his land and mines. Quite recently the Belgian
expedition of said Company and the Congo State
have been at Mushiri's capital and may have 
been more fortunate than Mr. Sharpe.</p>

<p>I am, Sir,<lb/>
Your obedient servant<lb/>
Heli Chatelain<lb/>
U.S. Coml Agent</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>