<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0056">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>African Repository, "The United States and Liberia. Letter from Commodore Shufeldt" (1881)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Akyeampong, Chelsea" xml:id="caa">Chelsea A. Akyeampong</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0056</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The United States and Liberia; Letter from Commodore Shufeldt</title>
<author n="Shufeldt, Commodore">Commodore Shufeldt</author>
<title level="j">African Repository</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
<date when="1881-10">October 1881</date>
<biblScope unit="page">126-130</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Slave trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/161996663">Coppinger, William, 1828-1892</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18600856">Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Baltimore (Maryland)</term>
<term>Canary Islands</term>
<term>Cape Verde</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Madeira</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>New York (N.Y.)</term>
<term>Sierra Leone</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Mohammedanism</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-10-30" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2019-04-22" who="#caa">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p126" n="teaa.en.periodical.0056.001"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>The United States and Liberia.</p>

<p>Letter from Commodore Shufeldt.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>The following interesting letter from Commodore Shufeldt is calculated
to awaken national interest to the importance of protecting
Liberia in all her rights and liberties, and of strengthening her by intelligent 
and well-appointed emigrants with the powerful aids of civilization.</p>

<p>Washington, D.C. April 6, 1881.</p>

<p>William Coppinger, Esq., Secretary American Colonization Society.</p>

<p>Dear Sir:&#8212;I regret that other engagements prevent my participation
in your public meeting to be held in New York in behalf of the
interests of the Republic of Liberia.</p>

<p>In view of the many failures which have been recorded in every
age of the world, that colony may be regarded as a success; yet to
to those familiar with the present condition of Liberia it is evident that
a crisis in her existence has been reached in which she requires the active 
and persistent efforts of her friends. With all due consideration,
not only for the patient efforts of the Society of which you have so long 
been the esteemed secretary, but for the exertions of Christians and
philanthropists throughout England and America, I think there has 
been too much "waiting upon Province" for advancing the interest
and strengthening the position of the colonists in Africa. Added to
the disadvantages of a decreasing revenue, a growing debt and an entire 
absence of foreign capital, (investment of which is discouraged
by Liberian laws,) there seems to be languor in place of decided action
among the men who believe in the capabilities of the African race for
self-government, and an utter indifference on the part of the United
States towards a colony planted by ourselves in behalf of a race subject 
for many years to our oppressive laws, and barred by our statutes
from taking its place among the nations.</p>

<p>It has been stated and generally believed that the climate of Liberia 
is fatal to its prosperity. This in a measure perhaps is true, but 
true only in the same degree as in all tropical countries in either
hemisphere. Malarial fevers prevail, but not of a fatal type, and certainly 
not more aggravated than on our Southern sea-board or throughout 
Central America. Even if the climate <hi rend="italics">is</hi> injurious, it is an evil
which disappears from day to day and year to year in proportion as 
the country is cleared and population increased. If many of the colonists 
suffer from climatic ills, it is due partly to the hardships incident
to emigration, but in my opinion more particularly to the fact that
many if not most of the emigrants are of a mixed blood, and consequently 

<pb xml:id="p127" n="teaa.en.periodical.0056.002"/>

inherit the delicacy of constitution common to mulattoes in
this country.</p>

<p>Of all the checks to the progress of Liberia, climate, in my opinion,
is the least. Its great bars to advancement are: first, the rivalry of
the colony of the British crown at Sierra Leone; second, the great
flood of Mohammedanism coming from the north and east of the Republic, 
with apparently irresistible force; third, the want of steam communication 
and the consequent steady flow of emigration from this
country; and lastly, the indifference of the United States Government
and the people to the Republic, not only in a Christian and philiantropic 
point of view, but perhaps more tangibly in its commercial aspect
as the objective point for American trade on the west coast.</p>

<p>It may readily be understood that Sierra Leone, under the protection 
of the powerful Government of Great Britain, possessed of ample
means and always sustained by military force, urged on by the persistent 
efforts of British traders to monopolize more and more the valuable 
trade of interior Africa, is constantly encroaching on Liberian 
territory, both upon its sea-shore and upon its rather indefinable internal 
limits. This aggression, although not countenanced, nor perhaps
understood by the people of Great Britain, is nevertheless going on, until 
at last Liberia, losing not only her territory, but, consequently, her 
revenue, will dwindle into a mere trading post or missionary station.
It is a well-known fact that British steamers stop regularly for the purpose 
of landing and receiving cargoes on at least two points within
the Liberian limits, as understood in this country, without regarding
the custom laws of the Republic. The goods thus landed and received
are taken to and from the interior of Liberia, thus not only defrauding
her revenue, but encouraging the natives to disobey and hold in con-
tempt all her laws. The Liberian Government made its first grave
mistake in appealing to the British crown for protection from this injustice. 
Its appeal should have been to the United States, which, under 
treaty, is required to protect the colony from the natives within its
borders. I do not wish to underrate the many kindnesses of the British 
Government, and particularly of the British people, extended in earlier 
times toward this struggling colony. In the great effort made by
England for the abolition of the slave trade on the west coast of Africa, 
Liberia was her <hi rend="italics">moral</hi> ally at least, but times and conditions are 
changed, and although the foreign slave trade has been abolished, yet 
it is a well-established fact that domestic slavery exists, not only 
among the tribes within Liberian territory, but throughout Africa, and
to-day contributes by its labor to the commerce of that continent, from 
which England derives such immense profits. The English philanthropists

<pb xml:id="p128" n="teaa.en.periodical.0056.003"/>

take no note of this fact, while the colonial governments and
the British merchant take advantage of its results.</p>

<p>However lamentable, it is nevertheless true that Mohammedanism
is carrying all before it in a religious point of view. It has already
reached to within 150 miles of Sierra Leone and Monrovia, the capital
of Liberia, establishing every where its fundamental dogmas of polygamy 
and slavery. To those who believe in a higher and purer religion
this forebodes a struggle prolonged in to the centuries; for it is safe to
predict that within the next half century the native tribes of Liberia
itself will be converted to that faith unless the Christian friends of the 
African race in this country and in Europe rouse themselves and determine 
to resist its encroachments.</p>

<p>The want of steam communication with this country, by which
alone a constant flow of immigration, as vital to an infant colony as
life-blood to the human system, (we prove it by the constantly increasing 
wealth and prosperity of our own country,) accounts for the poverty 
and slow growth of Liberia. A steam communication not only fosters
this immigration, but creates a trade to supply the ever increasing
wants of the colonists, who in turn barter the products of their new country 
for our manufactures. It is the merest folly to suppose that in the 
near future the native African will become a voluntary and persistent
tiller of the soil for the sake of the gain arising from commerce. He
cultivates the earth to the extent of his necessities, and while the colonists 
can utilize him in a desultory way, Liberia must look to her imported 
citizens for a steady development of her agricultural wealth I
fear very much that the Liberian himself does not quite appreciate this
fact. A steam line from New York or Baltimore via Madeira, the Canary 
Islands, the Cape de Verde, Sierra Leone and Monrovia, would not
only prove remunerative at this time, but would rivet that country to this
in such a way as not only to inure to our commercial good, but insure the
progress and prosperity of Liberia. One thing is certain, unless American 
capitalists can be found to build American ships for this purpose,
but a few years, or perhaps months, will elapse before the English merchant 
will embrace the opportunity, and we shall have the mortification 
of seeing the English flag doing the work between America and
her colony, thus depriving us of the benefits of opening a trade
with Africa, the last and richest field left to the progressive merchant
and Christianity must go hand in hand in the proselyting of Africa.
The people of the United States, therefore, whether actuated by the
desire of gain or the desire of good, are interested in the establishment 
of steam communication between these two countries. Immediate

<pb xml:id="p129" n="teaa.en.periodical.0056.004"/>

and energetic attention to this fact will obviate that last and
greatest bar to Liberian progress&#8212;the indifference of the people and
Government of the United States to Liberian interests.</p>

<p>The press&#8212;the great motor of public opinion in this country&#8212;rarely 
writes an encouraging word,or urges its readers to an intelligent consideration
of the great problem now working itself out in Liberia. The
ill-timed and ill-digested effort of the Negroes themselves in this country, 
which ended in the first and only voyage of the bark Azor, was ridiculed 
throughout the land, and quoted as evidence of the incapacity of
the race to do anything for itself. No consideration whatever seems to 
have been given to the condition of poverty and ignorance which
checked and hindered these poor people in their first effort to reach a
land free from the moral oppression of a superior race. Letters about
Liberia speak frequently with quiet self-conceit of the amusing characteristics 
of society there, overlooking the fact that those people,
emerging from a state of ignorance and quasi-slavery, are struggling by
the lights they have towards a higher plane, during which struggle
they must necessarily endeavor to imitate the manners and customs
of their superiors in the land which they have left. That these imitations 
are sometimes grotesque there can be no doubt, but from the 
thinking man such efforts merit sympathy rather than derision. At
all events, if in the destiny of mankind it is written that the struggle 
of the inferior to the plane of the superior is to go on throughout the
centuries to come, then this, the first effort of the African race to establish 
a free government upon its own soil, merits and should receive
the sympathy and encouragement of every man, woman and child in America.</p>

<p>But the apparent indifference of the American Government
to the permanency and prosperity of Liberia has, if possible, less excuse. 
Our statesmen, in the study of our interests and in the guidance
of our policy, should long ago have seen that in encouraging Liberia
they would not only afford an outlet to a discontented class of our 
citizens, and an offset to the predominance of European power upon
the continent of Africa, and gain a stand-point for effort as a Christian 
nation, but would create and foster a market for manufactures
which are not only each year demanding foreign marts, but already
eagerly sough after by the 200,000,000 of people who dwell upon that
portion of the earth's surface. I do not expect, nor indeed is it necessary, 
that the Government of the United States should take any aggressive 
position towards other countries on the African question.
A friendly note to a friendly Power, simply indicating that we take an
active interest in Liberia, and would not be willing to see her territory

<pb xml:id="p130" n="teaa.en.periodical.0056.005"/>

curtailed or her trade restricted, and the occasional visit of an
American man-of-war to indicate to the tribes within Liberian boundaries 
that the laws of Liberia must be respected, would suffice, at
least at present, to insure the existence of the Republic.</p>

<p>Much more on this interesting subject occurs to me, but I have said
perhaps all that you will care to read, and some things in which perhaps
you do not quite concur; but at all events you will permit me to subscribe 
myself a friend to Liberia.</p>

<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
R. W. Shufeldt.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>

