<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0002">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Daniel De Leon, The Conference at Berlin on the West-African Question (1886). Analysis</title>
<author n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0002</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>

<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="document" target="teaa.en.periodical.0011">Document</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-21" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-08-05" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<div2 type="bibliography">
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Conference at Berlin on the West-African Question</title>
<author n="De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914">Daniel De Leon</author>
<title level="j">Political Science Quarterly</title>
<date when="1886-03">March 1886</date>
<biblScope unit="pages">103-139</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="part">portions of the pamphlet relating to the Berlin Conference</biblScope>
</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Article Analysis</head>

<p>Curaçao-born, Jewish intellectual Daniel De Leon joined the Socialist Party in 1890 while in the United States. He began working with the American Federation of Labor, but in 1895, left the group to form the Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance.<ref type="footnote" target="n00.01">1</ref> A noted Socialist scholar, De Leon offers an anti-imperialist, Socialist interpretation of the Berlin Conference, in which he provides historical background to what he called the "West-African Question." De Leon considers the Berlin Conference "an event unique in the history of political science," because it brought together all the "important powers" of Europe&#8212;except Greece and Switzerland&#8212;and the United States. More importantly, he argues that the conference was purely motivated by economics, despite its pretensions at being a diplomatic gathering, serving the interests of German Chancellor Bismarck and Germany to not only secure trade rights in West Africa, but also to find land for German settlers.<ref type="footnote" target="n00.02">2</ref></p>

<p>De Leon's article offers a detailed history of the African Question that takes into account the role of Spain and Portugal in establishing sustained contact with West Africa in the fifteenth century. As De Leon points out, Portugal proclaimed "inchoate rights of ownership" over the Congo (Zaire) River and most of the West African coast based on the right of discovery which was upheld by the papacy. Portuguese trade dominance in the region went relatively unchallenged for nearly 400 years, however, in the nineteenth century, as Europeans increased their exploration of Africa after the abolition of the slave trade, Portugal's near trade monopoly in the region was challenged. The Berlin Conference, in effect, divested Portugal of its control over the navigation of the Congo River.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="excerpts">

<head type="main">Excerpt Analysis</head>

<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0011.e001">

<p>Cabinda was an Atlantic coast port city located at the mouth of the Congo River. Beginning in the fifteenth century, the Portuguese—followed by the Dutch and the English—established trading posts in the city. European merchants traded for palm oil and enslaved Africans, and Cabinda became integral to the Atlantic trade. In the nineteenth century, Cabinda rejected the slave trade and began engaging in "legitimate" trade led by resident merchants, most notably Chico Franque, a Brazilian trader. In 1883, the governor of Angola sent Guilherme de Brito Capelo to occupy Cabinda and Massabi. Both cities lay on the north coast of the Congo River, and King Leopold II claimed the Portuguese possessions as part of his Congo Free State. During the Berlin Conference, the Portuguese argued strongly for their rights to Cabinda which the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref> recognized in 1885. Cabinda became a Portuguese enclave surrounded by the French Congo and the Congo Free State, however, as the above excerpt attests, the French were not satisfied with this disposition. While the 1885 Treaty of Simulambuco established the Portuguese Congo—of which Cabinda was a part—it was the Franco-Portuguese Convention of May 12, 1886 that drew the boundaries between the French possessions in the region and Portuguese Cabinda.<ref type="footnote" target="n01.01">3</ref></p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0011.e002">

<p>The Portuguese&#8212;led by the governor of Angola, José Coelho do Amaral&#8212;seized Ambriz in 1855. A port town under African rule, Ambriz had access to the Loge River, which flows directly into the Atlantic Ocean. After the Portuguese occupation of the town, Ambriz and Luanda served as the main ports for Portuguese trade and constituted part of the buffer zone that separated the Portuguese kingdom of Angola from the indigenous kingdom of Kongo. After the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref> declared the Loge River the southern boundary of the Congo Basin, Ambriz benefited from the Angolan rubber and coffee trade as well as its proximity to the Congo Free State.<ref type="footnote" target="n02.01">4</ref> As this excerpt highlights, France and Portugal clashed over the boundaries of their colonies, territories, and protectorates in West Africa. Like the British and the Dutch, the French argued for extending their trade to Ambriz on the Loge River, which De Leon mistakenly refers to as the Ambriz River.</p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0011.e003">

<p>Cape Padron is located on the left bank at the mouth of the Congo River. Named by the Portuguese explorer Diogo Cam (or Diogo Cão) in 1484, the cape gave the Portuguese direct access to the Congo (Zaire) River. On May 4, 1493, Pope Alexander VI issued the Papal Bull "Inter Caetera," which gave Spain rights to claim and exploit the Americas based on the country's first "discovery" of a land unpopulated by Christians. This document laid the groundwork for the "<ref type="external" target="http://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-by-era/imperial-rivalries/resources/doctrine-discovery-1493">doctrine of discovery</ref>," which Portugal used to solidify its claim to exclusive trading rights with Africa, as it was the first European nation to navigate the African coast from the Azores to Zanzibar from the late fourteenth century to the turn of the sixteenth century.<ref type="footnote" target="n03.01">5</ref> Portugal attempted to maintain their claim of sovereignty over the area north of Cape Padron and the Congo River, however the <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref> required free navigation of the Congo, which opened up the cape to other European "powers."</p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0011.e004">

<p>Located on the Congo River, Noki (also spelled Nokki) was a European trading post that fell under Belgian control in 1884. The <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">General Act of the Berlin Conference</ref> recognized Portuguese control over "legitimate" trade in that region as far inland as Noki. It was the "principal port" in the Portuguese side of the Congo River and had been an important stop on the caravan trade from the coast to the kingdom of Kongo.<ref type="footnote" target="n04.01">6</ref></p>

</div3>


<div3 xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0011.e005">

<p>In 1472, Portuguese explorer Fernão do Pó became the first European to spot the island of Bioko (or Bioco) and the coast of present-day Cameroon. The Portuguese claimed Bioco as a colony and renamed it Fernando Po after the explorer. The island served as a base for Portuguese participation in the Atlantic trade, including the slave trade. In the eighteenth century, Portugal ceded the island to Spain to settle a dispute over territory in South America. Through the Treaty of El Pardo in 1778, the Spanish gained control of not only Fernando Po, but also the island of Annobó and trading rights in the Gulf of Guinea. From 1827-1834, the British used the island as a base to combat the slave trade along the Guinea Coast. During that period, missionaries and formerly enslaved Jamaicans settled on the island, and shortly thereafter, Africans, Europeans, and Creoles began cultivating cocoa. By the 1880s, the island experienced a "cocoa boom."<ref type="footnote" target="n05.01">7</ref> DeLeon suggests that when the Berlin Conference convened, Fernando Po had become an important entrepôt for maritime traders seeking access to the interior of Africa. Chancellor Bismarck clearly wanted to "profit" from the location of the island to foster trade with Africans on the Atlantic Coast and the interior via the Congo River and its tributaries that emptied into the ocean.</p>

</div3>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<note xml:id="n00.01">1. August C. Bolino, "American Socialism's Flood and Ebb: The Rise and Decline of the Socialist Party in America, 1901-1912," American Journal of Economics and Sociology 22, no. 2 (April 1963): 289; See L. Glen Seretan, <hi rend="italics">Daniel De Leon: The Odyssey of an American Marxist</hi> (London: Harvard University Press, 1979).</note>
<note xml:id="n00.02">2. De Leon, "The Conference at Berlin on the West-African Question," 103; George Shepperson, "The Centennial of the West African Conference of Berlin, 1884-1885," <hi rend="italics">Phylon</hi> 46, no. 1 (1st Qtr., 1985): 41.</note>

<note xml:id="n01.01">3. J.D. Hargreaves, "The Berlin Conference, West African Boundaries, and the Eventual Partition" in Stig Förster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 316; Toyin Falola, ed., <hi rend="italics">Africa: African History Before 1885, Volume 1</hi> (Durham: Carolina Academic Press, 2000), 351; Charles E. Nowell, "Portugal and the Partition of Africa," <hi rend="italics">The Journal of Modern History</hi> 19, no. 1 (March 1947): 11-12.</note>

<note xml:id="n02.01">4. Irene S. Van Dongen, "Coffee Trade, Coffee Regions, and Coffee Ports in Angola," <hi rend="italics">Economic Geography</hi> 37, no. 4 (October 1961): 331; Toyin Falola, ed., <hi rend="italics">Africa: African History Before 1885, Volume 1</hi> (Durham: Carolina Academic Press, 2000), 348-350; Charles E. Nowell, "Portugal and the Partition of Africa," <hi rend="italics">The Journal of Modern History</hi> 19, no. 1 (March 1947): 4; Ieuan Griffiths, "The Scramble for Africa: Inherited Political Boundaries," <hi rend="italics">The Geographical Journal</hi> 152, no. 2 (July 1986): 204-205.</note>

<note xml:id="n03.01">5. E. G. Ravenstein, "The Voyages of Diogo Cão and Bartholomeu Dias, 1482-88," <hi rend="italics">The Geographical Journal</hi> 16, No. 6 (Dec., 1900), 625-655.</note>

<note xml:id="n04.01">6. Thomas Lewis, "The Old Kingdom of Kongo," <hi rend="italics">The Geographical Journal</hi> 31, no. 6 (June 1908): 589, 598.</note>

<note xml:id="n05.01">7. Stig Förster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 131, 224; W. G. Clarence-Smith, "African and European Cocoa Producers on Fernando Pó, 1880s to 1910s," <hi rend="italics">Journal of African History</hi> 35 (1994): 179-199.</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>
</TEI>