<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0010">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, "The Race Question in Africa" (1909)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0010</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Race Question in Africa</title>
<author/>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
<date when="1909-04">April 1909</date>
<biblScope unit="page">421-422</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords>   
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/86844032">Carpenter, Frank G. (Frank George), 1855-1924</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="places">
<term>British East Africa</term>
<term>England</term>
<term>German East Africa</term>
<term>Johannesburg (South Africa)</term>
<term>Kimberley (South Africa)</term>
<term>Nyassaland</term>
<term>Uganda</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-03-05" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p421" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0010.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Race Question in Africa.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">
               
<p>No less a writer than Frank G. Carpenter is authority for the statement 
that the race question in the English African Colonies is becoming 
a matter of serious concern.</p>

<p>The Kaffirs are increasing in intelligence and are beginning to feel
the injustices heaped upon them in the poor provisions made for their
education; in the miserable wages paid them in some sections—about
3 cents a day; in the enormous hut and other taxes laid upon them
for which no benefits are returned; in being excluded from walking
on the sidewalks. Says Mr. Carpenter, "At present the black man here
has no opportunity to get a college education. He is not allowed to
go into the universities of South Africa, and as a rule the people
would rather keep him uneducated.</p>

<p>They look upon the natives as their God-created hewers of wood
and drawers of water, and they want them to continue so. They
would rather that they should not own real estate nor go into
business. The mechanics and foreman, among the whites would rather
not have the blacks learn trades, and they desire to keep the labor
of the two races distinct.</p>

<p>In Kimberly and Johannesburg the natives are paid about $1 a
day, but in Uganda, in British East Africa and German East Africa
the pay is only 3 cents a day and the whites claim it is wrong to pay
more, as the native will not work for better wages. One of these
employers of labor in Nyassaland claimed that it is spoiling the
native since the law no longer allows the white man to whip the
native laborer! Think of that and then cease to wonder why the
race problem in Africa is beginning to loom large.</p>

<p>But that's not all. Out of the pittance paid the natives, they are
required to pay six shillings or $1.50 a year as a road tax, or else give
one month work in lieu. One month out of a year to be given for the
public benefit. There is a hut tax, a' dog tax and a wife tax in South
Africa, none of the benefits of which go to the native.</p>

<p>When Mr. Carpenter asked the American foreman of an African
                                                           
<pb xml:id="p422" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0010.002.jpg"/>

mine whether he could punish his men when they did not please him
the foreman replied with much naivete:</p>

<p>"There is no trouble about that. If you want to mash the face of
a black down here all you have to do is to see that you get him
alone in one part of the workings. You can then treat him as you
will, and if he makes any complaint you can say he assaulted you.
The word of a black man is never taken here as against that of the
white man, and so we can run things about as we please."</p>

<p>What is the world coming to when men can so treat other men
in the land of their birth and then appear surprised at the evidence
of discontent that begins to arise. If England does not know of these
highhanded abuses, it is high time that it should be informed by
some of its statesmen in Parliament; if it does and does not act
then it must not be surprised when the storm comes; for the spirit
of the age is fighting for every man in bonds, whether he be white,
black or brown; and no nation can win against the cause of civilization.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
