<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0080">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Pauline E. Hopkins, "The Dark Races of the Twentieth Century, Part IV&#8212;Africa" (1905)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0080</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Dark Races of the Twentieth Century, Part IV&#8212;Africa</title>
<author n="Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930">Pauline E. Hopkins</author>
<title level="j">Voice of the Negro</title>
<biblScope unit="volume"/>
<biblScope unit="issue"/>
<date when="1905-06">June 1905</date>
<biblScope unit="page"/>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71570755">Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich, 1752-1840</term>
<term>Freidig</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/185887979">Gannibal, Abram Petrovich, 1697?-1781</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44333482">Hopkins, Pauline Elizabeth, 1859-1930</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/10719257">Le Maire, Jacques-Joseph</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46974880">Lislet Geoffroy, Jean-Baptiste, 1755-1836</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/62344773">Menelik II, Negus of Ethiopia, 1844-1913</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abyssinia</term>
<term>Algeria</term>
<term>Arabia</term>
<term>Canary Islands</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Dahomey</term>
<term>Egypt</term>
<term>Fezzan Tunis</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Gambia</term>
<term>Morocco</term>
<term>Mount Atlas</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Red Sea</term>
<term>Sahara Desert</term>
<term>Senegal</term>
<term>Sennaar</term>
<term>South Africa</term>
<term>Vienna (Austria)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Abyssinians</term>
<term>Armenian</term>
<term>Ashantis</term>
<term>Bantu</term>
<term>Berbers</term>
<term>Caucasian</term>
<term>Egyptians</term>
<term>Ethiopians</term>
<term>Fellahs</term>
<term>Gallas</term>
<term>Hebrews</term>
<term>Hottentots</term>
<term>Kaffirs</term>
<term>Nilotic</term>
<term>Nubians</term>
<term>Sechuano</term>
<term>Zingian</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-18" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Dark Races of the Twentieth Century</p>

<p>Part IV&#8212;Africa:</p>

<p>Abysinians, Egyptians, Nilotic Class, Berbers, Kaffirs, Hottentots, Africa of Northern Tropics (including Negroes of Central, Eastern and Western Africa), Negroes of the United States.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>When we consider the fact that there are 1,300,000,000 people in the world and that only about 375,000,000 are white (or one-quarter of the globe's population), we are not surprised that the dominant race dreads a "dark peril," and sees in every movement made by the leading representatives of dark peoples, a menace to his future prosperous existence.</p>

<p>Most of the 1,000,000,000 of dark-skinned brethren are found in Africa, the vast south-western peninsula of the Old World: No other division of land on the globe has such a compact and rounded outline. Access to the interior is rendered difficult because of the general absence of gulfs and large inlets. With the rapid advance which exploration has made in Africa in recent years, there has followed a great rivalry among European nations for colonies and protectorates; but while great wealth and boundless avenues for commerce have been opened up, civilization has been a mixed blessing to the natives, and today the eyes of Christendom are fastened upon the Congo Free State and its attendant acts of atrocity in the enforcement of slavery within its borders. The regeneration of Africa is upon us, but blood and tears flow in its train.</p>

<p>The characteristics of the people comprising African stock may be described as having heads rather long than broad, hair black and rarely straight, and the skin almost invariably black or very dark.</p>

<p>Abyssinians</p>

<p>The Abyssinians, or Ethiopians, comprise the people of the elevated plateau of Abyssinia. Under this general designation are comprehended many tribes&#8212;speaking different languages, but whose origin has long been a puzzle to historians. In stature they are rather below than above six feet, and are fairer than Negroes, with an oval face, a thin, finely-cut nose, good mouth, regular teeth, and frizzled hair. Abyssinia is interesting both in geographical and ethnological features. So striking is the resemblance between the modern Abyssinian and the Hebrews of old that we are compelled to look upon them as branches of one nation in spite of strong evidence to the contrary. As this theory is forbidden us, how are historians to account for the existence of this almost Israelitish people, and the preservation of a people so nearly approaching to the Hebrewin, inter-tropical Africa? Very recently Abyssinia has become a place of great interest to Americans. A treaty has just been signed between the United States' government and "Menelik II, by the Grace of God King of Kings of Ethiopia." It is a curious fact that the United States authorities maintain friendly relations with all independent black governments, although dealing severely with its own Negro population. To what end is this?</p>

<p>The United States Consul-General gives an interesting description of the military manœuvres of Menelik's troops. He says in an extended article: "The escorting troops then wheeled, and moved on in advance. Their numbers increased so rapidly

<pb n="p2"/>

as we approached the city that we were finally preceded by 3,000 men.</p>

<p>"Surrounding their chief, the warriors marched in most extraordinary confusion, sometimes performing evolutions, sometimes walking their horses, and sometimes galloping. It was a beautiful spectacle. No two costumes were alike. Saddles and bridles were decorated with gold and silver fringe. Bucklers of burnished gold and silver fringe. Bucklers of burnished gold were carried by soldiers, and from their shoulders flew mantles of leopard and lion skins, of silk, satin and velvet. Only the bright rifle-barrels marked the difference between these Ethiopians and the army of their forbears who followed the Queen of Sheba when she went down into Judea. We were spellbound by the moving mass of color, across which floated the <sic>wierd</sic> music of a band of shawm players&#8212;playing as they had played when Jericho fell.</p>

<p>At the farther end of the audience-hall sat the Emperor upon his divan or throne. . . On each side of the throne stood two young princes holding guns, and back of it and extending on both sides until they merged into the crowds waiting in the aisles, stood the ministers, judges, and officers of the Court. A subdued light softened the colors and blended them harmoniously."</p>

<p>The Egyptians, Berbers, and Nilotic People</p>

<p>Egypt, as we all know, was once the scene of a noble civilization. Egypt was in close proximity to Arabia, but the two people have met very different destinies. The Arabian worshipped one god; the Egyptians paid homage to foul deities. Their physical characteristics were also different; the Arabian had a restless visage, lean and active figure. The Egyptians had voluptuous forms, long, almond-shaped eyes, thick lips, large, smiling mouths; complexions dark and coppery&#8212;the whole aspect that of the genuine African character, of which the Negro is called an exaggerated type.</p>

<p>The Berbers comprise the native population of the Sahara desert of the country north of it, and the original population of the Canary Islands. This section of African stock is near the Egyptian frontier in Fezzan Tunis, Algeria, and Morocco. Their language is allied to the Hebrew and Arabic, and hence is called <hi rend="italics">sub</hi>-Semitic. The tribes bearing this name are very numerous. One very interesting fact in reference to the Berbers is that the extinct aboriginal inhabitants of the Canary Islands owed to them their origin. These were the "fortunate isles" of the early Roman poets, the "Hesperides," or "isles of the blest," of many a song-writer.</p>

<p>The Gallas are spread over eastern inter-tropical Africa and are a formidable and warlike people. In complexion they are brown, their hair worn in tresses over the shoulders. They are of the type which fill up the transition from the Armenian type and the Western and Central African Negro. The Gallas come under the Nilotic class who inhabit the Valley of the Nile.</p>

<p>The Nubians are a most interesting class also. They are of a reddish-brown complexion, but of a shade not as deep as the East African Negro. The hair is frizzled and thick. Under the name "Nubian" are comprehended two sections of people alike in physical character, but speaking distinct languages. These are the Eastern Nubians and the Nubians of the Nile. The Eastern Nubians are a handsome people living near the Red Sea. The Nubians of the Nile extend from Egypt to the borders of the Sennaar.</p>

<p>Kaffirs</p>

<p>Under this name are comprehended all the South African races. Many tribes and even nationalities, all allied, however, by common customs and similar dialects, come under their name. The word "Kaffir" is

<pb n="p3"/>

considered by them a term of contempt; but as each division of the nation to which it applies as a separate name, their language supplies no substitute, unless the general terms Sechuano, Bantu or Zingian&#8212;all of which terms have been applied to the Kaffir race by different ethnologists&#8212;be received in its place. The Kaffirs are one of the widest spread of the African families. The Kaffirs are blackish-red in complexion and the hair crisp. The men are a handsome set, very tall with an intellectual cast of countenance. They show much aptitude for civilization, but their origin is a mystery to scientists. The Kaffirs are great warriors.</p>

<p>Hottentots are supposed to be the original inhabitants of South Africa, and were conquered by the Kaffirs. Between the two tribes there exists undying hatred. Bushmen and other allied tribes are found in South Africa. A number of African kingdoms have become famous among civilized peoples: The Kingdoms of Dahomey, Ashanti, etc.</p>

<p>Everyone is familiar with the story of the conquest of Dahomey by General Dodds. The Amazon warriors of this kingdom are women of prowess who have astounded and amazed the world. General Dodds was himself of Negro descent; he was accorded high honors for his victory upon his return to France.</p>

<p>The Ashantis have been the Spaniards of Southwest Africa, and they have persecuted other tribes assiduously. They are a famous tribe and of a warlike disposition.</p>

<p>Africa is such a wide ethnological region that were we to attempt to describe it even in the most abstract manner, we would need as many volumes at our command as we have had pages in this short sketch. When Africa is mentioned, people instantly associate the tribes as one vast mass of hideous ignorance. Such is far from the case. Some of the tribes are as fine specimens of manhood as one could wish to meet. In proof of the versatility of its people we have but to refer to the great advance of the Negroes of the United States&#8212;a heterogeneous mass composed of contributions from nearly all the tribes of the fatherland. In America a great problem has been worked out&#8212;the problem of the brotherhood of man, represented by the highest intellectual culture among Negroes, that can be shown by any other race in our cosmopolitan population. "God's image he, too, although made out of ebony." Says Blumenback: "I am acquainted with no single bodily characteristic which is at once peculiar to the Negro, and cannot be found to exist in many other and distant nations."</p>

<p>Le Maire says in his travels through Senegal and Gambia, that there are Negresses as beautiful as European ladies.</p>

<p>The Negro Freidig was well-known in Vienna as a masterly concertist on viol and violin. The Russian colonel of artillery, Hannibal, and the Negro Lislet of France, who on account of his superior meteorological observations and trigonometrical measurements was appointed correspondent for the <hi rend="italics">Paris Academy of Sciences</hi>.</p>

<p>In an able article of the <hi rend="italics">Southern Quarterly Review,</hi> 1855, we note these facts:</p>

<p>"In the whole range of the African continent we discover the same endless variations and gradational blending between the widest extremes, exhibited by all the other people of the earth. In color they vary through every shade from the European that sometimes appear in Egypt, and still exists in the neighborhood of Mount Atlas, to the polished ebony of the thoroughly dyed Negro. In physiognomy, they range between the elegant Grecian outline, and the exaggerated monstrosity of prognathous development. In texture of hair they exhibit every grade from the soft Asiatic and even auburn locks of some Egyptians, to the Auranian Berbers, through the long, plaited ringlets of the Morooran Kaffirs, and short, crisp curls of the Nubian, the thick

<pb n="p4"/>

and frizzled, wolf-like covering of the diffused Gallas and the still more woolly-headed growth of the Fellahs, and the thoroughly developed Negro tufts of the Guinea tribes. In every <sic>inportant</sic> part that marks varieties in man, the inhabitants of Africa vary with such indefinite blendings of one grade into another, between the Caucasian standard and the lowest Negro specimen, that it is impossible to draw a line of division at any point of the skull, and affirms that here one type ends and another begins."</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
