<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0090">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Missionary Review, "Africa" (1883)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0090</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Africa</title>
<title level="j">The Missionary Review</title>
<pubPlace>Princeton (N.J.)</pubPlace>
<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">62-64</biblScope>
<date when="1883-01">January 1883</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54942091">Blyden, Edward Wilmot, 1832-1912</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51080627">Browne, Hugh M. (Hugh Mason)</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/161996663">Coppinger, William, 1828-1892</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/818337">Garnet, Henry Highland, 1815-1882</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17098270">Stewart, T. McCants (Thomas McCants), 1854?-1923</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Abyssinia</term>
<term>Algeria</term>
<term>Benguela (Angola)</term>
<term>Bihé (Angola)</term>
<term>Cape Colony</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Egypt</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
<term>Gambia River</term>
<term>Ogowe River</term>
<term>Massamedes (Angola)</term>
<term>Mediterranean Sea</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Natal</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Senegal River</term>
<term>St. Paul's River</term>
<term>Timbuctoo (French Sudan)</term>
<term>Zambezi River</term>
<term>Zanzibar</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empire">
<term>France</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>African Methodist Episcopal</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-25" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0090.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>XI. Africa.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Opening to Civilization.&#8212;Mr. Wm. Coppinger, Secretary of the American Colonization Society, in his third annual statement, well says:</p>

<p>"There has never been a more intense and concentrated effort to open a continent than is now directed towards Africa. From Algeria, from Egypt, from Zanzibar, from the mouth of the Zambesi, from Natal, from Cape Colony, from Benguela, via Bihe, from the Congo and the Ogove, the Niger, the St. Paul's, the Gambia and the Senegal, the influences of exploration, commerce, missionary and colonization endeavor are penetrating the vast interior with so much energy and success that, with whatever difficulties and obstacles, the result cannot be doubtful. A few years will give access to the immense and varied treasures of a magnificent quarter of the globe and bring its mighty domain under the sway of Christian civilization."</p>

<p>Mr. Coppinger recognizes the energetic efforts of the French in connecting the upper waters of the Niger with Senegal by railway; their project, still urged, for building a railway across the desert from Algeria to Timbuctoo, and flooding parts of the desert; and speaks of the rapid growth of French interests and influence in the African States bordering on the Mediterranean; and of their bill before the Chamber of Deputies for creating an African army of 58 battalions, 301 companies of infantry, 75 squadrons of cavalry, and 13 batteries of artillery, with 90 guns, besides the engineer and transport services.</p>

<p>The Portuguese, too, are developing fresh activity, establishing prominent stations in all their African possessions, each with a military commander, having a staff composed of a surgeon, chaplain, and a dozen or more carpenters, masons, farmers and other master workmen&#8212;the first of these stations to be at Bihé, the point chosen for the Mission of the A. B. C. F. M. The government of Portugal has contracted for a packet service between Lisbon and Massamedes, the steamer to call at the intervening ports along the West coast of Africa. The Italian government, too, is alive to African interests, aiming to secure amicable relations with King John, of Abyssinia.</p>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<pb xml:id="p2" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0090.002"/>

<p>Liberia College.&#8212;We are glad to see Dr. Blyden seems intent on promoting the efficiency of this college, at Monrovia. He is reported to have secured two able men, Rev. T. McCants Stewart, Pastor of the Bethel African M. E. Church in Sullivan street, New York, and Rev. H. M. Browne, to fill professorships. Mr. Browne, latterly supplying the late Dr. Garnet's Shiloh Presbyterian Church in Twenty-sixth street, New York, has also the appointment of U. S. Consul at Monrovia. We wish these brethren health and long years of service, with great success in training young Liberians for usefulness.</p>

<p>Dr. Blyden, President of the College, reports increasing prosperity among the emigrants who have gone from this country, and speaks of the prospects of Liberia with much hopefulness. We notice that the bark Monrovia recently sailed from New York carrying some 50 emigrants. Of the increasing commercial interests of Liberia, we notice that the bark Monrovia, sailing thence the 14th of April last, brought 150,000 pounds of coffee, with a good supply of other products, and another American vessel was loading at the same time, to sail in a few days.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
