<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0087">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Washington Bee, "False Representations About Africa" (1885)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0087</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">False Representations About Africa</title>
<title level="j">The Washington Bee</title>
<pubPlace>Washington (D.C.)</pubPlace>
<date when="1885-11-28">November 28, 1885</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Journal</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Bivden</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51080627">Browne, Hugh M. (Hugh Mason)</term>
<term>Johnson</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17098270">Stewart, T. McCants (Thomas McCants), 1854?-1923</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Liberia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Vey</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-11-21" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb xml:id="p1" facs="teaa.en.periodical.0087.001"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>False Representations About Africa.</p>

<p>Prof. Stewart Denounced.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>Washington, D.C. Nov. 21st. '85.</p>

<p>Editor of the Bee:</p>

<p>Your paper of this date contains the following: "Prof. Stewart comes out in a letter stating that neither he nor Prof. Browne will return to Africa." Please do me the justice and my friends the favor to insert the following statement in the next issue of the Bee.</p>

<p>Of this letter I know nothing. I returned to this country, as I stated in the New York Sun shortly after my arrival, to urge upon the American Boards interested in Liberian Colleges the absolute necessity of their heeding the conviction of His Excellency, President Johnson, the noblest Liberian of them all; viz, "I am still decidedly of opinion, that the more work the friends in America can do independently of the Board here (Liberia) the better it will be. Only those who have witnessed it, can form an idea of the petty, low, mean, political tricks played in educational work here."</p>

<p>For this purpose alone I returned: and worked to accomplish it till it was discovered that the treasurer of the New York Board had made some very unfortunate investments of the funds, which now make it impossible for these friends to prosecute any but a very limited educational work. Hence I am no longer connected <sic>wiith</sic> Liberian College, which fact I regret because of the possibilities of this institution if it only can be put in the proper hands. That  I did my best to secure its proper management, the best people in Liberia, the Board in America and several of the ablest scholars and educators of this country have testified in terms of which those much worthier than I would be proud.</p>

<p>The very day on which I received the flattering resolution reluctantly <sic>desolving</sic> my relation with Liberian College and thus commending me to others; we most cordially commend him as a Christian gentleman and a scholar to those who are engaged in African Christianization, believing as we do that his heart is set upon that great work. I began my application to the Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church for an industrial educational work among the Vey people. My plans for this work have been adopted and I am now under my second appointment to Africa, where I intend spending my active life. I went of my own accord to Africa. No one persuaded me. Now that I have been, my contract with the free-born native African, in his beautiful country, has made it impossible for me to labor willingly any where else.</p>

<p>It is in him and in Africa that I beheld the solution of the much discussed "Negro problem." The free-born native African alone possesses the potentialities requisite to demonstrate the fact that the Negro is "a man and a brother." I glory in the opportunity given me to spend and be spent in the cause of Christian education in Africa; and I believe most implicitly that this will become, in a few years, the most cherished and anxiously sought field of labor of the enlightened colored men and women of the United States. Already thousands of us devoutly join in Dr. Livingston's dying prayer: "That God's richest blessing may fall upon every one who attempts to repress the slave trade, uproot idolatry, establish, pure homes, commerce and education and found permanent Christian institution in Africa."</p>

<p>Regarding Prof. Stewart, I have refused repeatedly since Oct. 23rd, 1883 to have any thing to do with him. To my sorrow I have learned that he is neither honest nor truthful. To be charitably frank, I really believe him not as sane as he might be.</p>

<p>When he ran away from Liberia at the beginning of Dr. Bivden's attack on the "new professors," which Stewart himself caused, I wrote the following to the American Board. "I have just learned that Prof. Stewart intends returning in a few days. I certainly can't understand such a step, unless it be made from a want of interest in the great work to which we have given you gentleman our pledge; and to which we owe our earnest and faithful service. His return at this particular time is sadly inopportune&#8212;it is a cowardly retreat&#8212;a wanton violation of the confidence placed in him by your gentlemen. There is absolutely no ground for such an action on his part."</p>

<p>The secretary in New York wrote me that his return at first shook the confidence of some of the best friends of the cause, but that he had convinced them that the return was providential since Stewart was better adopted to raising funds in America than engaging in the work on the ground. Hence Prof. Stewart began begging at a salary of $1200 per year and traveling expenses. He is now no longer connected with the work because he failed to raise enough money to pay his traveling expenses, and further because members of the Board have also been convinced of his insincerity.</p>

<p>The following extract from the last of three letters which he has written me, since his return, asking for my friendship (not one of which I condescended to answer) is a good sample of his insincerity and unblushing untruthfulness. He writes me thus: "Be of good cheer, be patient, success to you will come. How it will be with me I can't tell. In public addresses I am saying what the situation at Monrovia does not justify and it is getting embarrassing."&#8212;The underscoring is his also&#8212;I had written to the American Boards protesting against such of these misrepresentations as I had seen in print.</p>

<p>Thanking you for your kindness,<lb/>
I am, Yours truly,<lb/>
Hugh M. Brown.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
