<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0006">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>George Washington Williams - A Report Upon the Congo-State and Country to the President of the Republic of the United States of America (1890)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0006</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">A Report Upon the Congo-State and Country to the President of the Republic of the United States of America</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100373407">Williams, George Washington, 1849-1891</author>
<title level="j">LSE Selected Pamphlets</title>
<date when="1890">1890</date>
<publisher>British Library of Political and Economic Science</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Banana (Congo)</term>
<term>Bangala (Congo)</term>
<term>Boma (Congo)</term>
<term>Bosoko (Congo)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Itimberi River</term>
<term>Kasai River</term>
<term>Leopoldville (Congo)</term>
<term>Lukunga (Congo)</term>
<term>Lumani (Congo)</term>
<term>Manyanga (Congo)</term>
<term>Matadi (Congo)</term>
<term>Stanley Falls</term>
<term>Welle River</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Belgium</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-04-01" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-11-13" who="#kln">added subtype</change>
<change when="2014-08-08" who="#kln">Initial transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">A Report Upon the Congo-State and Country to the President of the Republic of the United
States of America</head>

<head type="sub">Geo. W. Williams</head>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

<p>L'Etat Indépendant du Congo was created and became
the successor of l'Association Internationale du Congo. The
King of the Belgians was now requested, or rather became
the natural chief of the new State, as he had been of the
Association; but there was a constitutional obstacle in the way
of his Majesty assuming the legal headship of this African State.
Article LXII (62) of the Belgian Constitution provides, -- "The
King cannot be at the same time chief of another State, without
the consent of the two Chambers. Neither of the two Chambres
can discuss this subject unless two-thirds at last of the members
composing it be present, and the resolutions can only be passed
providing it is supported by two-thirds of the votes." I translate 
and insert here the record of the proceeding by which
Leopold II became the Sovereign of the Congo State. "The Belgian
Legislative Chamber, by a resolution, adopted in the Chamber of
Representatives the 28th of April 1885, and in the Senate April
30th 1885, authorized His Majesty Leopold II, King of the
Belgians, to become the Chief of another State, in conformity
with article 62 of the Belgian Constitution." The resolution is as
follows: "His Majesty Leopold II, King of the Belgians, is authorized 
to become the Chief of the State founded in Africa by
l'Association Internationale du Congo. The union between Belgium
and the new State shall remain exclusively personal."</p>

<p>On the 1st of August 1885, His Majesty notified the Powers
that the possessions of l'Association Internationale du Congo
would in the future constitute l'Etat Indépendant du Congo;
that he had assumed, in accord with the Association, the title
of "Souverain de l'Etat Independant du Congo;" that the relation
between Belgium and this State was exclusively personal,
and that it was to remain perpetually neutral.</p>

<p>On the 30th of October 1885, His Majesty, as Sovereign of
the Congo State, issued a Decree creating three Departments
for his new State Government, and naming three chiefs, lst
Department of Foreign Affairs, including Justice, with three
Bureaux: a. Foreign Affairs, b. Postal and Maritime, c. Judicial
affairs; 2nd Department of Finance; a. General taxes, b. Land
Department, c. Pay and Auditor's Department; 3rd Department
of Interior: a. Administration, b. Roads and communications,
c. Army and Navy.</p>

<p>The three heads of departments constituted a council,
under the Presidency of the Sovereign, who is the absolute
Ruler. His councelors may recommend but can never share
his authority. He makes all the laws under the title of "Decrees,"
and from his decisions there is no appeal. His Government
is denominated as local, the European portion of the Congo-State.</p>

<p>In the Congo there is a Governor-General, in charge
of the State, who issues such laws as he feels are necessary
under the title of "ordonnances," but except they are reissued
as a "Decree" by the Sovereign within six months, they are
null and void. There are an Inspector-General, Secretary-General, 
Procurer-General, Finance-General, Judges and Commissaires
of Districts. There are postmasters, transport-officers
and clerks of various kinds.</p>

<p>A small portion of the country, claimed by the Independant
State of Congo, is divided into Military Districts; the rest is
dominated by natives whose lawful possession it is. There are
eleven Military Districts, viz: 1. Banana, 2. Boma, 3. Matadi,
4. Manyanga, 5. Lukunga, 6. Leopoldville, 7. The Kassai River,
8. Bangala, 9. Basoko, 10. Lumani, 11. Stanley Falls. There
are two "Military and Commercial Expeditions" on the Itimberi
and Welle Rivers, and a third has just started.</p>

<p>Each one of these military districts is commanded by an
officer of the Belgian Army, supported by other officers and
non-commissioned officers. The "Commissaire of District" is
of one of three classes, and needs not always be an army
officer, for he deals with civil affairs only. All disputes and
native palavers are settled by the military commander, and
sometimes by the commissaire of the district, and their decision
is final. When an offence has been committed against the
State, the native may be fined, emprisoned or enslaved. In the
Upper-Congo the State officials generally demand slaves for
settling natives palavers. They promise to liberate these people
after seven years service. As far as I have been able to investigate, 
this system of Government is unjust, capricious and
absolutely cruel. There is scarcely one percent of the State
officials, military and civil, who know the native language;
and frequently the interpreter, an uneducated negro from
Zanzibar or the East-Coast, knows little French, and puts questions 
indistinctly, or translates the testimony of the natives
indifferently. I have seen this in the Supreme Court at
Boma also. I called the attention of the Clerk of the Court
to the poor French of the Interpreter, and he told me that,
if that were all, it would not be so bad; but that the fellow
was a notorious liar into the bargain! And yet upon this
stammering patois hangs the bondage or liberty, the peace
and property of many a native.</p>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>

</TEI>
