<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0069">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Colored American Magazine, Benjamin M. Nyce, "The Influence of Talladega College" (1906)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0069</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Influence of Talladega College</title>
<author>Nyce, Benjamin M.</author>
<title level="j">The Colored American Magazine</title>
<date when="1906-04">April 1906</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Feering, Maria</term>
<term>Nyce, Benjamin M.</term>
<term>Sheppard, Lucy J. Gantt</term>
<term>Thomas, Lillian</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-11-05" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p4"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">The Influence of Talladega College</head>

<head type="sub">By President Benjamin M. Nyce</head>

</div2>

<div2 type="article">

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

<p>Do the students do what they can to support themselves and is there an increase toward self-support which induces toward self respect? Are they in turn becoming the helpers of their people? Let the story of Talladega College in Africa, Lucy Gann Sheppard, Maria Feering and Lillian Thomas working in the hear of the Congo Free State be your answer. Let thousands in every

<pb n="p5"/>

walk of life in the South, with Talladega's Christian training, be your answer. Let hundreds of loyal alumni who have given thousands of dollars to the institution and who have to-day forty of their own children at Talladega be your answer.</p>

<p>These facts concerning the Negro cannot be gainsaid. When he is helped he improves very rapidly. If flat on his back he is always looking up and is grateful for assistance. Left to himself and his old time surroundings he is not improving, he is retrograding. Work for the southern Negro must be pushed. We cannot stop if we would. National destiny is concerned in this matter. Now as surely as in '61 and '65 our peril is largely in the South and thither we must send our forces. We must increase and better supply the army that is here warring against ignorance and sin. A little aid will go a great way in the South. What in a northern college would be considered a trifle, in a southern school would be considered a princely sum. Board is cheap, dress is plain, salaries are meager. A small sum would endow a scholarship and not a large sum would provide perpetually for a teacher. What is expended on one gymnasium in the richer states would equip an industrial department in the South. No colleges need help more than these and nowhere will aid go farther than among the schools which are doing as exigent and as fruitful a work as the sun shines upon. Yet no colleges are so liable to be neglected, and for obvious reasons. The abolitionists

<pb n="p6"/>

are mainly an extinct race. War memories are fast fading. Few now read Uncle Tom or think of his cabin. A new generation has arisen which knows not the black Joseph or whether he be still in prison or not. Continually the stream of benevolence is irrigating places already well watered, while currents small and few flow toward he more needy South. For the present the help needed must come largely from the North. There is no other base of supplies. The South, white or black, is not yet able to meet the need, although in many  cases they are doing what they can. There is no better way to help save the country and at the same time lift up the dark continent, than to generously equip these southern colleges. This beyond question is the most wise and efficient means of solving the great educational and missionary problem in which both North and South must share the responsibility.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
