<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Albert Bushnell Hart - "Negro Colony of Liberia, 1817-1861," The Foundations of American Foreign Policy (1901)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0019</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">The Foundations of American Foreign Policy</title>
<author n="Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61535364">Albert Bushnell Hart</author>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>The Macmillan Company</publisher>
<date when="1901">1901</date>
<biblScope unit="page">1-9</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Emigration</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/58082142">Frelinghuysen, Frederick T. (Frederick Theodore), 1817-1885</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61535364">Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/74134457">Kendall, Amos, 1789-1869</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76349832">Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/20476583">Monroe, James, 1758-1831</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/90717491">Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43344010">Stockton, Robert Field, 1795-1866</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Montserado (Liberia)</term>
<term>Central America</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-10" who="kln">encoding and transcription.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p150"/>

<div2 type="title">

<head type="main">The Foundations of American Foreign Policy</head>

<p>By<lb/>
Albert Busnell Hart<lb/>
Professor of History in Harvard University</p>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p150"/>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head type="sub">49. Negro Colony of Liberia, 1817-1861.</head>

<p>[ . . . ]</p>

<p>While Brother Jonathan was adding to his

<pb n="p151"/>

territory, and gaining experience in colonization, a movement had begun for ridding him of a part of his children, by colonizing the free blacks in Africa. The first trouble was to find a part of the earth where persons would be received who, as Jefferson neatly phrased it, were "not malefactors, but guilty of what the safety of society under actual circumstances obliges us to treat as a crime"&#8212;that is, men who were determined to be free. In 1820 the first realization of the idea was carried out by President Monroe, in connection with the American Colonization Society, when eighty-six negroes were sent to the African coast. From that time for many years the United States took, in the scattered settlements first known as Liberia and Monrovia, an interest summed up by Amos Kendall as follows: "To colonize captured Africans, to build homes for them, . . . to purchase ships for their convenience, to build forts for their protection, to supply them with arms and munitions of war, to enlist troops to guard them, and to employ the army and navy in their defence." If this be an exaggerated statement, it is certainly true that the permanent site of the colony&#8212;at Cape Montserado&#8212;was secured by Lieutenant Stockton of the United States ship <hi rend="italics">Alligator</hi>, and that the United States paid for supplies to keep the colonists alive.</p>

<pb n="p152"/> 

<p>In 1837 the people of these African settlements constituted themselves the commonwealth of Liberia, and in 1847 the little state declared itself sovereign and independent. Like many other small nations, Liberia soon found herself involved in a quarrel with Great Britain. Had the settlement been one of white men, there can be little doubt that the United States would have acknowledged the duty of protecting it. As it was, the administration of President Polk refused even to acknowledge Liberia as an independent nation. England, however, came to terms with the little land, agreed to respect the "sovereignty" of Liberia, and gave her a cutter with four guns&#8212;all exactly like a picture in <hi rend="italics">Punch</hi>; but not till 1862 did the United States recognize Liberia as a sister nation. In 1884 Secretary Frelinghuysen said that "Liberia, although not a colony of the United States, began its independent career as an offshoot of the country, which bears to it a <hi rend="italics">quasi</hi>-parental relationship."</p>

<p>The colony of Liberia is almost the only example of an eddy of American civilization turning eastward; and it was too feeble a movement to affect either slavery or territorial rights in America or Africa. President Lincoln made an attempt to revive the scheme by placing a new colony in Central America, and was much disappointed at the refusal of 

<pb n="p153"/> 

the Central American colonies to receive free negroes. Perhaps the Liberians may some day be stirred up by the good fortune of the Hawaiians to offer themselves to be a recognized colony of Brother Jonathan's. At present our relation to Liberia is practically that of a protectorate.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>