<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0245">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from J. C. Hartzell</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh" xml:id="unm">Unyoh Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0245</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from J. C. Hartzell</title>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Notes from Liberian Legation In U.S. to Department of State, 1862-1898 T807</title>
<publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">T-807, Roll 1</biblScope>
<date/>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>

<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>    
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Caulfield, J. W.</term>
<term>Sherman, John</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Cape Palmas (Liberia)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Monrovia (Liberia)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Methodist</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Hartzell, J. C.</persName>
<roleName>Bishop of Africa and Special Envoy on behalf of Liberian Government</roleName>
<placeName/>
<date/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName/>
<roleName/>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-02" who="#kln">reviewed, encoded</change>
<change when="2019-10" who="#lkw">encoded</change>
<change when="2019-09" who="#unm">transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb n="20170616_150944"/>

<gap extent="apparently seven pages"/>

<p>independence of that Republic.</p>

<p>(sgd) John Sherman.</p>

<p>Washington,<lb/>
March 13, 1897.</p>

<p>(2) I am to assure your Government that Her Majesty's Government 
take equally with the United States Government a special
interest in the independence of Liberia, and would share the concern 
of that Government should any prospect of the absorption of 
Liberia by a foreign power develop in the future.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,<lb/>
J. W. Caulfield.<lb/>
Administrator.</p>

<p>Other documents and letters could be added indicating the 
serious crisis which has come to the Republic of Liberia and the 
anxiety with which its administration looks to the United States
and Great Britain for sympathy and practical assistance. Naturally 
Liberia turns first of all to America, from which country 
came its founders and which their children have been taught to 
regard with almost filial affection. Next to America stands Great
Britain in the thought and confidence of Liberia, and if America 
can not give practical aid in this time of need the Republic will 
hope that her Majesty's Government will hear its plea for friendly 
assistance.</p>

<p>While in London en route from Africa to America, I presented 
my letter from Liberia to the foreign office and her Majesty's 
Government, and was <del>guaranteed</del> granted a cordial and extended interview.
The result of this interview was to the effect that England was 
friendly to Liberia but felt that it would be proper for her to 
wait for the United States to take the initiative in any movement 
which had to do directly with that Government.</p> 

<pb n="20170616_150949"/>

<p>I was given to understand that there was but little doubt 
that Great Britain would co-operate, if requested to do so, in any
<sic>iniative</sic> movement which the United States might inaugurate in
guaranteeing the independence of Liberia, and <del>any</del> tender friendly aid in
strengthening its Government and developing its territory.</p>

<p>To say that the hope of the friends of the negro as a 
nation-builder have been realized during the last fifty years in Liberia 
would not be true; on the other hand, to accept the uncharitable
and unkind criticisms of the struggling Republic which are heard 
along the coast from among <del>traiters</del> traders and travelers, and even reiterated 
in Europe and America would be <del>adding</del> doing great injustice to 
the people of Liberia. Liberia is one of the several centres of 
Missionary operations under my official care as the Bishop of 
Africa representing the Methodist Episcopal Church, and in my official 
duties I have made two visits to the Republic and visited 
all its principal centres and sought carefully to study the 
conditions and outlook of its Government and people. When we consider
the difficulties which the Republic has had to meet in a new, and 
<del>to many</del> hostile clime; their lack of wealth and experience in Government, 
surrounded and permeated by multitudes of barbarous heathen 
and subjected constantly to the uncharitable criticisms of 
white <del>traiters</del> traders and travelers; the marvel is that so much in the
way of <del>official</del> efficient Government and advance in social conditions, has 
been accomplished. True their national domain, rich in mineral 
and agricultural possibilities has as yet been but little explored;
but it is also true that, until within a very few years, but 
little advance has been made by other nations on either coast 
of the continent in extending practical and efficient Government 
among the natives of the Interior. It must also be remembered 
that the advance made the past few years outside of Liberia has
been the result of enormous expenditures in money, backed by 

<pb n="20170616_150955"/>

powerful Governments, able to command the <del>bext</del> best administrative 
talent.</p>

<p>The moral obligation of the United State to Liberia is unquestioned. 
For more than two generations a large number of prominent 
philanthropists and statesmen in America, have done what they 
could by moral and financial aid, to help Liberia. Several of the 
great church organizations of this country have expended large
sums of money and sent out scores of missionary ministers and 
teachers for the Liberian people. We have over nine millions of 
negroes in America among whom there is a profound sentiment that 
in some way they are to aid in the redemption of Africa. This 
sentiment has been inculcated into their minds for generations by <del>the</del> American
statesmen and clergymen. Liberia is to-day practically, the only 
open door for the intelligent and aggressive negro men and women 
in America to enter upon <del>an</del> educational and missionary work among
their race in Africa. If Liberia can be assured a stable Government, if
her custom receipts and expenditures can be efficiently administered, 
if she can have aid in the development of her educational system,
if her domain can be explored and lines of communication
be opened up between different portions of her territory, if her 
mineral and <sic>aggricultural</sic> possibilities can be developed; in
short, if United States or England alone or in co-operation with
each other, will now hear the cry of Liberia for protection, 
encouragement and such practical assistance as can be easily and
properly given, there will be no question not only as to the <del>preminance and</del>
<sic>permant</sic> success of Liberia as a Government, but also the <del>a</del> way will
be opened for many of our Afro-Americans to have honorable 
share in the redemption of the land of their fathers.</p>

<p><del>A specific</del> The request of the Liberian Government is, that a 
treaty be <del>made</del> negotiated that will guarantee the independence of 
that Republic and the integrity of its territory. Such a treaty if once promulgated would end all 

<pb n="20170616_151000"/>

anxiety on the part of the struggling Republic as to other nations
who are now anxious to secure its territory; it would greatly improve 
the Republic's financial <del>and</del> standing and possibilities; and 
would strengthen every element of its Government, <del>and</del> as well as every
social, educational and religious endeavor among its people. </p>

<p>Among the practical results likely to be assured from such a 
treaty might be named the following:-</p>

<p>(1) The Naval vessels of the United States would visit 
the Liberian ports and there would be such interchange of National 
and Social amenities as would have a large moral effect upon the 
surrounding heathen tribes.</p>

<p>(2) If thought desirable on the part of the United States 
a coaling station with suitable adjacent <del>mines</del> lands could be
established at Cape Palmas or Monrovia.</p>

<p>(3) Scientific exploring expeditions with the co-operation 
and possible direction of Americans or Englishmen could be 
carried out.</p>

<p>(4) American capital would be encouraged to enter Liberia 
and would no doubt find profitable investment.</p>

<p>(5) A very great impetus would be given to educational 
and church work throughout the Republic now being carried on by 
benevolent and church organizations in America.</p>

<p>Africa, outside of the Republic of Liberia, which Republic is about as 
large as the state of Nebraska, is rapidly passing under the rule 
of European white Governments. Liberia the offspring of American
philanthrophy and co-operation is the only civilized Government in
Africa, controlled and manned by negroes, and upon that Government 
the friends of the negro throughout the world have looked with 
great anxiety. America is morally bound to co-operate in every 
way possible to insure the success of the experiment. Recently in

<pb n="20170616_151005"/>

the most marvelous manner America has assumed broader and larger 
relations to the world and its people outside of her own domain, 
and this appeal from Liberia comes at a time when the responsibilities 
and duties of America to the needy of other lands, have been 
most powerfully impressed upon the National heart and conscience.</p>

<p>I will sail for Africa within a few weeks and my first point 
of Episcopal visitation will be Liberia. Any service which it is in my
power to render in behalf of Liberia to you, my dear Sir, as 
representing the United States, shall be gladly given, and may I 
not hope that I may be permitted to bear to the Liberian Government, 
assurances that in the near future steps may be taken looking to 
the establishment of a treaty such as has been suggested.</p>

<p>I have the honor to be, my dear Sir,<lb/>
Sincerely yours,<lb/>
JC Hartzell,<lb/>
Bishop of Africa and<lb/>
Special Envoy on behalf of<lb/>
Liberian Government.</p>

<p>P.S.- I herewith <unclear extent="one word"/> to you a copy of the 
official Journal of the Liberia Annual Conference of 
the Methodist Episcopal Church, which be of interest
in giving information concerning <unclear>one</unclear> part 
church and educational work in Liberia.</p>
   
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
