<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.book.0015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Frederick Starr - "The Truth About the Congo" (1907)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Mbilain, Unyoh N." xml:id="unm">Unyoh N. Mbilain</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.book.0015</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>
Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.
</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Truth About the Congo: The Chicago Tribune Articles</title>
<editor n="Starr, Frederick 1858-1933" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/45085839">Frederick Starr</editor>
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
<publisher>Forbes &amp; Company</publisher>
<date when="1907">1907</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Encounters with Africans</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Non-Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/72334287">Bentley, W. Holman (William Holman), 1855-1905</term>
<term>Calamba</term>
<term>Casati</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64062958">Casement, Roger, 1864-1916</term>
<term>Chief Chicoma</term>
<term>Chief Maiila of the Bachoko</term>
<term>Chief Mbumba</term>
<term>Chief Ndombe of the Bakuba</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/289194770">De Winton, Francis, Sir, 1835-1901</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12606197">Du Chaillu, Paul B. (Paul Belloni), 1835-1903</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/58007512">Funston, Frederick, 1865-1917</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39742616">Glave, E. J. (Edward James)</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/55385545">Ide, Henry C. (Henry Clay), 1844-1921</term>
<term>Ikoko</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70604029">Jaja, King of Opobo, 1821-1891</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42142167">Junker, Wilhelm, 1840-1892</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/264072032">Leopold II, King of the Belgians, 1835-1909</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/82967082">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/1913409">Lothaire, Hubert Joseph, 1865-1929</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41884042">Morel, E.D. (Edmund Dene), 1873-1924</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71396743">Reclus, Élisée, 1830-1905</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32065073">Root, Elihu, 1845-1937</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27187771">Schweinfurth, Georg August, 1836-1925</term>
<term>Smith, Jacob H.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/27071894">Stanley, Henry Morton, 1841-1904</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/45085839">Starr, Frederick 1858-1933</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54448046">Supan, Alexander, 1847-1920</term>
<term>Tumba</term>
<term>Vankerckhoven</term>
<term>Verner, Samuel P.</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68999368">Vierkandt, Alfred, 1867-1953</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/47066218">Wagner, Hermann, 1840-1929</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/284497166">Wahis, Théophile, 1844-1921</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/11483793">Waller, Littleton Waller Tazewell, 1856-1926</term>
<term>Woodruff</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Antwerp (Belgium)</term>
<term>Aruwimi River</term>
<term>Bakongo (Congo)</term>
<term>Bolobo (Congo)</term>
<term>Bomanih (Congo)</term>
<term>Basoko (Congo)</term>
<term>Benin</term>
<term>Boston (Massachusetts)</term>
<term>Brussels (Belgium)</term>
<term>Burauen (Philippines)</term>
<term>Chumbiri (Congo)</term>
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Cuba</term>
<term>Dahomey</term>
<term>Eala (Congo)</term>
<term>French Congo</term>
<term>German Africa</term>
<term>Ikoko (Congo)</term>
<term>Isangila (Congo)</term>
<term>Ituri (Congo)</term>
<term>Kasai (Congo)</term>
<term>Kasai River</term>
<term>Lake Leopold II</term>
<term>Lake Mantumba</term>
<term>Leopoldville (Congo)</term>
<term>Leyte (Philippines)</term>
<term>Liberia</term>
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Lualaba River</term>
<term>Lukolela (Congo)</term>
<term>Malolos (Philippines)</term>
<term>Manila (Philippines)</term>
<term>Manzi (Congo)</term>
<term>Matadi (Congo)</term>
<term>Matamba (Congo)</term>
<term>Mobandja (Congo)</term>
<term>Mputu (Congo)</term>
<term>Natal</term>
<term>Ndombe (Congo)</term>
<term>Nigeria</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Nouvelle Anvers (Congo)</term>
<term>Ogowe River</term>
<term>Philippines</term>
<term>Polynesia</term>
<term>Ponthierville (Congo)</term>
<term>Rubi River</term>
<term>Samar (Philippines)</term>
<term>Sankuru River</term>
<term>San Salvador (Congo)</term>
<term>Soudan</term>
<term>Stanley Falls</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
<term>Uganda</term>
<term>Yambuya (Congo)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Austria</term>
<term>Belgium</term>
<term>Denmark</term>
<term>France</term>
<term>Germany</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Holland</term>
<term>Italy</term>
<term>Norway</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>Sweden</term>
<term>Turkey</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Indian</term>
<term>Arab</term>
<term>Bakete</term>
<term>Bakuba</term>
<term>Baluba</term>
<term>Bangala</term>
<term>Bantu</term>
<term>Batetela</term>
<term>Batua</term>
<term>Bobangi</term>
<term>Egyptians</term>
<term>Filipinos</term>
<term>Pulajanes</term>
<term>Pygmy</term>
<term>Zappo Zap</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-12-04" who="kln">encoding and review</change>
<change when="2019-11" who="unm">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p000a"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Truth About the Congo</p>

<p>The Chicago Tribune Articles</p>

<p>By Frederick Starr</p>

<p>Chicago<lb/>
Forbes &amp; Company<lb/>
1907</p>

</div2>

<pb n="p000b"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>This book is dedicated 
to 
Manuel Gonzales, 
my companion and photographer 
upon my Congo Expedition 
and to 
our black boys, Manoeli and Tumba</p>

</div2>

<pb n="vii"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Preface</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>When I returned to America, I had decided 
to express no opinion upon the public and 
political questions of the Congo Free
State. Having found conditions there quite different 
form what I had expected, it was impossible for me 
to state my actual impressions without danger of 
antagonizing or offending some whom I valued as 
friends. Hence, on landing at New York, I refused 
to say anything upon those matters to several reporters 
who interviewed me. A little later, the <hi rend="italics">Chicago 
Tribune</hi> asked me to write upon these subjects,
urging the importance of the whole matter to our 
nation, and leaving me entire freedom in viewpoint 
and mode of treatment. In response to its request, 
I prepared a series of articles, which appeared in successive 
issues from January 20 to February 3, 1907.</p>

<p>The articles were received with general interest
only, and as I have much other Congo matter for 
books and pamphlets&#8212;more directly in the line of 
my professional work&#8212;I was inclined not to reprint 
them. But I soon found myself the subject of bitter 
attack. Malicious and untrue statements were 
made regarding me and my motives. I have concluded,

<pb n="viii"/>

therefore, that it is best that my articles 
should be accessible to all who are interested. What 
I wrote, I am ready to defend. I am not ready to be 
judged from misquotations, or condemned for what 
I never wrote. Hence this book.</p>

<p>I am not personally responsible for the title&#8212;
<hi rend="italics">The Truth about the Congo</hi>. Although I believe all 
my statements are true, I should not have selected 
that title for my articles. No man can say all that 
is true on any subject, and I do not arrogate to myself 
a monopoly in truth-telling, either about the 
Congo or any other topic. But after my announcement 
under that heading, I decided to let it stand.
I preferred some less assertive title, but I am content.
So I use the same title for this book. The headlines 
of the articles, however, I have suppressed. They 
were not of my preparation and did not adequately
suggest the matter or the treatment. The articles 
are reprinted with no changes except corrections in 
spelling, punctuation, or mistaken words.</p>

<p>No man more desires the happiness and progress 
of the Congo natives than do I. I know them 
pretty well. I am their friend; they are my friends. 
I shall be glad if what I here present makes them and 
their cause better known to thoughtful and sympathetic 
men and women. Mere emotion, however violent, 
will not help them. Stubborn refusal to recognize 
and encourage reforms, which have been seriously 
undertaken for their betterment, will only harm them.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="1"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>The Truth About the Congo</p>

<p>I.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>January 20, 1907.</p>

<p>My own interest in the Congo Free State began at 
the St. Louis exposition. As is well known,
that exposition made a special feature of groups
of representatives of tribes from various parts of the world.
These natives dressed in native dress, lived in native 
houses, and so far as possible reproduced an accurate 
picture of the daily life to which they were accustomed in 
their homes</p>

<p>Among the groups there brought together was one of 
Congo natives. This group was commonly known as the 
pygmy group, though but four out of the nine members 
composing it made claims to be such. The group was
brought by Mr. S. P. Verner, at one time missionary to the
Congo, who was engaged by the exposition to make a 
special journey into central Africa to procure it. Four 
members of the group were Batua, the others were large 
blacks representing the Bakuba and Baluba.</p>

<p>The idea of visiting Africa was one which I had never 
seriously entertained, but in the study of these Congolese 
it seemed to me that there were interesting questions the 
solution of which would well repay a visit. The consequence 
was, that I determined to visit the Congo Free 
State&#8212;and specifically that part of the state from which
these natives had been brought</p>

<pb n="2"/>

<p>About this time I received considerable literature from
the Congo Reform Association at Boston, the reading of
which had its influence in deciding me to undertake the 
expedition.</p>

<p>After reading this literature I started for the Congo,
fully prepared to see all kinds of horrors. I supposed that
mutilations, cruelties, and atrocities of the most frightful 
kinds would everywhere present themselves. I expected
to find a people everywhere suffering, mourning, and in 
unhappiness.</p>

<p>My errand, however, was not that of a searcher after
all these dreadful things, but purely that of a student of 
human races, with definite questions for investigation.</p>

<p>I may say that my opportunities for forming an opinion
of conditions in the Congo have been exceptional. Mine 
was no hasty journey, but a tarry in the country extending 
over more than one year.</p>

<p>While my original plan was to spend the greater portion
of my time in the district ruled by the Bakuba chief,
Ndombe, with but a short period in other parts of the 
state, I had decided before reaching the mouth of the 
Congo to more evenly distribute my time, and to see far
more of the Congo proper than I at first intended. As a 
consequence, I went first into the Kasai district, where I
spent four months, after which, returning to Leopoldville,
I went up the main river to the head of navigation, and 
even beyond, to Ponthierville, the terminus of the newly
built line of railroad. We also went up the Aruwimi, to
the famous Yambuya camp, where the navigation of that 
river is interrupted by cataracts.</p>

<p>I have, therefore, seen not only the lower Congo, which

<pb n="3"/>

has been so frequently visited in recent years, but traveled
thousands of miles upon the great river and two of its most
important tributaries.</p>

<p>In this extended journey I came into constant contact
with representatives of the three groups of white men who 
live in the Congo Free State&#8212;state officials, missionaries,
and traders. I had repeated conversations with them all,
and have heard opinions upon the Congo State from these
diverse points of view.</p>

<p>My position with reference to Congo matters is peculiar,
doubly so. I may even say it is unique. My journey was 
made at my own expense; I was not the representative of 
any institution, society, or body. I was without instructions, 
and my observations were untrammeled by any 
demands or conditions from outside.</p>

<p>While I am under many and weighty obligations to 
scores of state officials, missionaries, and traders, I am not 
prevented from speaking my mind in regard to any and 
every matter. Both to the missionaries, state officials,
and traders I paid board and lodging at every stopping
point&#8212;with the single exception of one American mission 
station&#8212;a fact which leaves me freedom. While the 
state facilitated my visit and my work in many ways, I was 
not, at any time, in relations with it of such a kind as to 
interfere with free observations or free expression. I
made this entirely clear on my first visit to the state authorities 
at Brussels, and it was understood by them that I 
should speak freely and frankly of everything which I 
should see. On their part, the state authorities expressed 
the liveliest satisfaction that an independent American
traveler should visit the Congo Free State, and said that

<pb n="4"/>

they did not wish anything concealed or attenuated, as 
they felt sure that such a visit as mine could only do them 
good.</p>

<p>I have said that my position was doubly peculiar. I 
was not only independent and untrammeled in observation
and expression, but my personal attitude to the whole question 
of colonization and administration by a foreign power,
of natives, is radical. Personally I dislike the effort to
elevate, civilize, remake a people. I should prefer to leave
the African was he was before white contact. It is my belief
that there is no people so weak or so degraded as to be 
incapable of self-government. I believe that every people 
is happier and better with self-government, no matter how 
unlike our own form that government may be. I feel that 
no nation is good enough, or wise enough, or sufficiently
advanced to undertake the elevation and civilization of a 
"lower" people. Still less do I approve the exploitation 
of a native population by outsiders for their own benefit.
Nor do I feel that even the development of British trade
warrants interference with native life, customs, laws, and 
lands. I know, however, that these views are unpopular
and heretical.</p>

<p>In the series of articles, then, I have been asked 
to prepare, I shall try to take the standpoint of the practical
man, the business man, the man of affairs, the philanthropist, 
the missionary. All these agree that civilized folk 
have a perfect right to interfere with any native tribe too
weak to resist their encroachment. They agree that it is 
perfectly right to trample under foot native customs, institutions, 
ideas&#8212;to change and modify, to introduce innovations, 
either to develop trade, to exploit a country, to

<pb n="5"/>

elevate a race, or to save souls. I am forced, then, to 
look at Congo matters from the point of view of these
eminently practical men.</p>
    
<p>Of course, I saw much to criticise. It is true that there 
are floggings, and chain-gangs, and prisons. I have seen
them all repeatedly. But there are floggings, chain-gangs,
and prisons in the United States. Mutilations are so rare
that one must seek for them; and I had too much else to 
do. There is taxation&#8212;yes, heavy taxation&#8212;a matter
which I shall discuss quite fully further on. And in connection 
with taxation there is forced labor, a matter which,
of course, I disapprove, but it appears as just to all the 
groups of eminently practical men to whom I have referred. 
There are, no doubt, hostages in numbers, but I saw
less than a dozen. And the whole matter of hostages is one
which merits careful and candid discussion. And I know
that in many a large district the population is much smaller
than in former times. The causes of this diminution in 
numbers are many and various, and to them I shall return.</p>
    
<p>Flogging, chain-gang, prison, mutilation, heavy taxation, 
hostages, depopulation&#8212;all these I saw, but at no
time and at no place were they so flagrant as to force themselves 
upon attention. And of frightful outrages, such as
I had expected to meet everywhere, I may almost say there
was nothing. It is, of course, but fair to state that I was 
not in the district of the A. B. I. R. I cannot believe, however, 
that conditions in that district are so appalling as the 
newspaper reports would indicate.</p>
    
<p>On the contrary, I found at many places a condition
of the negro population far happier than I had dreamed
it possible. The negro of the Congo&#8212;or Bantu, if you
    
<pb n="6"/>

please&#8212;is a born trader. He is imitative to a degree.
He is acquisitive, and charmed with novelties. He is 
bright and quick, remarkably intelligent. He readily
acquires new languages, and it is no uncommon thing to 
find a Congo Bantu who can speak six or seven languages
besides his own. In disposition variable and emotional,
he quickly forgets his sorrow. I saw hundreds of natives
who were working happily, living in good houses, dressing 
in good clothes of European stuff and pattern, and saving 
property. That this number will rapidly increase I have 
no doubt.</p>
    
<p>And now, on my return, after having many of my preconceived 
ideas completely shattered, and feeling on the 
whole that things in Congoland are not so bad, and that 
improvement is the order of the day, I am startled to find 
the greatest excitement. Pages of newspapers are filled 
with stories of atrocities, many of which never happened,
some of which are ancient, and a part of which, recent in
date, are true.</p>
    
<p>I find a fierce excitement about the Belgium lobby,
vigorous resolutions presented in the senate, and the President 
of the United States outrunning his most urgent
supporters and advisers, ready to take some drastic action 
to ameliorate the conditions of the suffering millions in the 
Congo Free State. The surprise is so much the greater,
as my latest information regarding the American official
attitude had been gained from the letter written by Secretary 
Root some months ago.</p>

<p>What can be the reason of such prodigious and sudden 
change?</p>

<p>What has happened in the Congo since April to produce
    
<pb n="7"/>

the present state of mind? What is the motive underlying 
the bitter attacks upon Leopold and the Free State
which he established? Is it truly humanitarian? Or
are the laudable impulses and praiseworthy sympathies
of two great people being used for hidden and sinister ends
of politics?</p>
    
<p>I do not claim infallibility. I do claim that my having
spent a year in the Congo Free State, independently, should
qualify me to express opinions on the conditions. I have
heard both sides. I have traveled thousands of miles in 
Congo territory. I have visited natives of twenty-eight
different tribes. No interference has been placed in my 
way. I have gone where I pleased, and when and how 
I pleased. No preparations have been made with reference 
to my visits. I believe no changes in practice have 
been produced by my presence.</p>
    
<p>In the series of articles before us it is my intention to 
present in detail what I have seen, and much of what I 
have heard, in the Congo Independent State. I may make 
errors, but I shall tell no intentional falsehoods. I shall
criticise what deserves criticism. I shall praise what is 
praiseworthy. I trust that those who are interested in 
forming a true idea of Congo conditions may find something 
useful in my observations.</p>
    
<p>At this point it is necessary for us to know something 
of the Congo native himself. In Dark Africa&#8212;for northern 
Africa is and always has been a white man's country&#8212;
there are three negro or negroid masses. There is little 
doubt that the original inhabitants of the continent were
dwarf people, ancestors of the pygmies of the high Ituri
forest, and the Batua of the upper Kasai.</p>
    
<pb n="8"/>

<p>To-day the pygmies are mere fragments, scattered and 
separated, but retaining with tenacity their ancient life.
They are the same to-day as they were 5,000 years ago,
when they were objects of interest to the old Egyptians.
Little in stature, scrawny in form, with a face shrewd, cunning, 
and sly, the pygmy is a hunter. With his bows and
poisoned arrows he kills the game of the forests and makes 
no pretense of doing aught in agriculture. He is universally 
feared by the large blacks in the neighborhood of
whose towns he settles. He trades his game for agricultural 
products with his large neighbors.</p>
    
<p>In the Soudan and neighboring parts of western Africa
live the true negroes, notable for their thick lips, projecting 
lower faces, and dark skin.</p>
    
<p>Throughout southern Africa we find a group of populations 
much lighter in color, and on the whole more attractive 
in appearance, than the true negro. These tribes,
plainly related in language, are no doubt of one blood, and 
are called Bantu. The name is unfortunate, as the word
bantu simply means "men" in that group of languages.
Practically the while of Congo population are Bantu
&#8212;there being almost no true negroes and but few pygmies 
in the area.</p>
    
<p>It would seem as if the Congo native should be so well
known by this time that the current description of him in 
the text-books would be accurate; yet at least in two
respects, these stereotyped accounts are wrong. The 
Congo Bantu are not long-headed, and it is not true that 
they differ from the real negro in the absence of a characteristic 
and disagreeable odor. There are scores of Bantu
tribes, each with its own language and minor peculiarities
    
<pb n="9"/>

in appearance and life. It would be untrue to say that all 
smell badly, but I have often wished the writers of the 
books could be shut up a while in the same room with, for 
example, a group of Bobangi. It is certain that no type of 
African smells worse.</p>
    
<p>It would be, however, a mistake to think that the Bantu
are dirty. Far from it. I have repeatedly observed my 
carriers, when we came to some brook in the forest, set their 
loads aside, strip themselves when necessary, and bathe 
in the fresh cool water. They are scrupulous in attention
to their teeth, and use, often several times a day, a little
stick of wood, somewhat larger than a lead-pencil, shredded 
at one end, to clean their teeth. The instrument, by 
the way, serves its purpose far better than our own toothbrushes.</p>
    
<p>According to hisKing Ndombe tribe, the Bantu may be short, medium, 
or tall. King Ndombe of the Bakuba measures six feet
three in stature, and is well built, though not heavy.
Among the Bakuba, Baluba, Batetela, and Bakete, tall
statures are common. It is rare, however, that the Bantu 
present what we would call finely developed forms; their
chest is often flat and sunken; their shoulders not well
thrown backward; and the musculature of their back,
their chest, arms, and legs, is poor. Of course, there are
exceptions, and one sometimes sees magnificently developed 
specimens. In the lower Congo, where on the whole 
the men are shorter, they make excellent carriers. In the 
old caravan days the standard burden was sixty or seventy
pounds, and a man would carry it without difficulty all the 
working day. The Kasai tribes are poor carriers and 
indifferent workers. The chopbox of sixty pounds weight,

<pb n="10"/>

which the lower Congo man shoulders easily and carries
without complaint, will be slung to a pole to be borne by 
two carries among the Baluba.</p>
   
<p>In life the Bantu populations, so far as the Congo is concerned, 
present notable general uniformity. The general 
pattern is the same everywhere, though there are local
and tribal differences of minor sort. Thus, almost every
tribe has its own tribal marks cut into the flesh of face or 
body.</p>
    
<p>Similarly, the members of one tribe may be distinguished 
by their mode of dressing the hair. To a less
degree, the form to which the teeth are chipped and broken
mark tribal differences. It may almost be said that no 
two tribes in all the Congo build houses that are just alike,
and almost every tribe has its characteristic mode of arranging 
the houses in a group. Thus, in one tribe the 
houses will be arranged in continuous lines, one on each 
side of a straight road; in another the houses may be 
grouped around the three sides of a square, the group
belonging to a single chieftain and being succeeded in the 
village by other similar groups of buildings; in another 
the houses will be arranged in two curved lines, leaving the 
open space in the center of the village oval or elliptical.
The chairs or stools of one tribe will differ in form and 
decoration from those of another; so will the wooden 
spoons, the stirring-sticks, the combs, the dress and ornaments.</p>
    
<p>The Congo natives for the most part still lead a tribal
life. A chief is the head of a little community clustered
about him. He may not be the chief of a whole village;
for example, at Bomanih, on the Aruwimi, there are three
    
<pb n="11"/>

chiefs. Each one has his own cluster of houses, and though
the three clusters are arranged continuously in two, parallel, 
straight lines, every native of the village knows precisely
where the domain of the individual chiefs ends or begins.</p>
    
<p>The power and authority of the chief has been greatly
weakened by contact with the whites, but he still retains
great influence. At least over the members of his own
household, including, of course, his slaves, he had the 
power of life and death. In large affairs, interesting a 
considerable number of people, he usually acted on the 
advice and opinion of his fellows as expressed in a village
or tribal palaver. The chief was, and still is, distinguished 
from the common people by his dress and ornaments.
He is usually a man of wealth, and has a considerable 
number of people actually dependent upon him, subject 
to his orders, and a force upon which he can depend in
case of war or trouble.</p>
   
<p>When I first entered the Congo my heart sank, for it 
seemed as if the native life was gone. In fact, in letters 
written from Matadi I doubted whether I had not come 
too late for aught of interest.  My spirits began to 
revive, however, with the railroad journey from Matadi
to Leopoldville. Groups of natives, with scanty dress and 
barbaric ornaments, replaced those who at Matadi and its 
neighborhood gathered at the station to see the train pass.</p>
    
<p>In my first walk from the mission house where I lodged
at Leo, within three minutes' walk of the mission I found 
a little cluster of Bateke houses which, with its inhabitants, 
much delighted me.</p>
    
<p>Almost naked women, the abundance of beads and 
teeth hung at their necks as ornaments, with hair elaborately
    
<pb n="12"/>

dressed and bodies smeared with red camwood
powder, squatted on the ground, were making native 
pottery in graceful forms</p>
 
<p>In the shade in front of the door of one of the houses
was a true barbarian, lord of the place. By rare good 
luck he spoke a little English, so that we were able to carry 
on a conversation. When I asked him who the women
were, he replied that they were his wives. I think there 
were three of them, and it was my first introduction to 
African polygamy. Each of these  women occupied a 
separate house. Each of them had a garden patch in 
which she worked. All of them contributed to the importance 
and support of their husband.</p>
    
<p>Polygamy, of course, prevails throughout Dark
Africa. But do not misunderstand me. I do not use 
the word "dark" to characterize polygamy. It is a 
settled institution which seems to work quite well. Later
on I saw the wives of Ndombe, thirty-four in number.
Ndombe is a really important chief, but compared with 
some whom we met or of whom heard in the Upper 
Congo, he was but scantily equipped. Sixty, seventy, a 
hundred, or hundred of wives and female slaves, which
count for much the same, are in possession of great chieftains. 
There is, of course, always one favorite or principal
wife. When Ndombe used to come, as he frequently did,
to my house to see the stereoscopic pictures, he frequently
brought his favorite wife with him. She was a pretty
creature&#8212;young and plump, graceful and modest.
She wore good cloth and any quantity of beads and brass
arm and leg rings.</p>

<p>In every case the women of a chief or rich man live in
    
<pb n="13"/>

separate houses, each having her own. Until a man is 
married he is but little thought of. The greater the number 
of wives, the more important he becomes. As 
each one cultivates a field and does other productive 
labor, it will be seen that the man with the most wives
is the richest man.</p>
    
<p>The man has his own house, but visits and lives in the 
houses of his wives in turn. The child in Africa is rarely 
weaned before it is two or three years old, and during the 
period of time when a child is unweaned the father has no 
marital relations with the woman. On the whole, there is 
less quarreling among the wives of a polygamic husband
than one would expect. Bantu women, however, are often
termagants, as women elsewhere, and at times the chief's
house group is lively.</p>
    
<p>Domestic slavery still flourishes. The state, of course,
has done much to end the actual slave trade for supplying
white men and Arabs. It is, however, difficult to deal 
with the matter of domestic slavery, and in fact is scarcely
worth the candle.</p>

<p>Every chief or man of any consequences has slaves.
Calamba, my interpreter, at Ndombe, though a young
fellow, probably not more than 25, had two. It is rare
that the lot of the domestic slave is unhappy. It is usually
women or children who are brought, and they are treated
in all respects as if members of the family. Little is required 
of them in the way of work and service, and they 
must absolutely be provided for by the master, who is 
also frequently responsible before the public for their
misdeeds. Formerly, of course, there was the possibility
of being killed upon a festal occasion, the accession of the

<pb n="14"/>

chief to increased power, or to grace his funeral. Within
those districts where the state has a firm hold and strong
influence this possibility is done away with, and the most 
serious disadvantage in being a slave is thus removed.
Slaves may become rich men, and not infrequently themselves 
hold slaves.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most striking characteristic of the Bantu,
as of the true negro, is his emotionality&#8212;one instant
joyous, the next in tears. Vowing vengeance for an injury 
to-day, he is on the happiest terms with his injurer
to-morrow. He laughs, sings, dances. Of all the introductions 
of the white man, perhaps the accordion is the 
favorite. Men use it, but women play it constantly.
Most of them play one song piece only, and one may 
hear it from one end of the state to the other at every 
hour of the day and night. Of course, there are native 
instruments in plenty, drums of every size and form, from 
the small hand drum, made by stretching a skin across an 
earthen pot three or four inches in diameter, up to the 
great cylindrical, horizontal drum made by hollowing
logs a yard in diameter and ten feet long. There are horns,
fifes, pipes, and whistles, and a great series of stringed
instruments, ranging from the musical bow with but one
cord to lutes with ten or twelve. Of course, the instrumental 
music goes with the dancing.</p>

<p>The native is born to dance. Babies, two or three
years old, dance with their elders. Men dance together;
women have their special forms; but in the majority of 
cases the two sexes dance together. There is, however,
nothing like our waltzes or round dancing, individuals 
keeping themselves separate. The dances are most frequent

<pb n="15"/>

and lively when the moon is growing. On moonlight 
nights hundreds of people&#8212;men, women, and children
&#8212;gather at dusk, and to the noise of drums dance 
wildly, often till morning. It is no uncommon thing for
people working on plantations to work all day and dance
almost all night, and this day after day. While some of 
the dances are extremely graceful, most of them are ob-
scene and are followed often by frightful orgies.</p>

<p>One thing greatly interested me. Had I been asked 
before my trip to Africa about the cake-walk&#8212;a form of 
amusement which I love to see&#8212;I should have said that 
it originated in America among the black folk of our 
southern states. But no, the cake-walk is no American 
invention. In every part of the Congo one may see it&#8212;
even in regions where white influence has seldom penetrated. 
The American cake-walk is an immigrant.</p>

<p>The Bantu child is wonderfully precocious. This 
precocity displays itself in everything. The children run 
about with perfect freedom, instead of tottering along, one 
unsteady step after another, as our children of the same
age. They speak astonishingly soon. A babe in arms
eats solid food&#8212;notwithstanding the fact that it is not 
weaned until two or three years of age&#8212;shockingly early.
The little child imitates the every action of its older
friends. Children of four or five, in shrewdness, comprehension 
and intelligence, are like our ten-year-olds.
This precocity suggests the fact of early ripening. As a
fact, boys of sixteen and girls of thirteen are frequently 
ready for marriage. A man of twenty-five is in the prime 
of life, a man of thirty aged, and on the whole the term
of life closes at thirty-five.</p>

</div2>

<pb n="16"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>II.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>January 21, 1907.</p>

<p>Life is easy in the tropics. Wants are few. A 
house to live in can be built in a few hours. Food
can be gathered or produced with little labor.
Dress is needless. Where life is easy there is little impulse 
to labor.</p>

<p>The chief incentive to the Bantu to work is secure
the wherewithal to buy a wife. The boy, who, through a 
careless, happy childhood, has done naught but play,
begins to think of settling down. But to have a wife he 
must have money or its equivalent. So he goes to work.
It may require a year or more before he has the pieces of 
cloth which are necessary for the purchase of his desired
loved one. The same stimulus which impelled him to 
labor for one wife may prod him to efforts for others. But
with the establishment of a home, and the purchase of two 
or three wives to care for him and produce him wealth, his 
work is done. From fourteen years to twenty-five is his 
working period. Before that time a child, after that time 
he is a man of means. What wealth comes later comes
through the women and their labor, and through trade.</p>

<p>We have already stated that the Bantu is notably
acquisitive. Wealth, apart from women and slaves, is 
counted mostly in cloth. One of the chief aims in life is 
to accumulate cloth, not for use as clothing, but as evidence
of wealth and for the final display when the man dies and 
is buried. Among the Lower Congo tribes the dead body 
is wrapped in piece after piece of cloth, until the body 
disappears in a mass of wrappings made of scores of pieces,
each piece consisting of eight or sixteen yards, as the case

<pb n="17"/>

may be. Young men have cloth, and it is most interesting 
to look through the boxes of the "boys." At Basoko we 
were robbed, and the authorities instituted a search. I
was asked to inspect the boxes of all the workmen on the 
place. Without warning, every man and boy had to open 
his trunk, chest, tin box, or other store. I saw young fellows 
of no more than sixteen or seventeen years who had a
dozen pieces of good cloth carefully folded away, watches, 
jewelry, ornaments, knives, dishes&#8212;every kind of white 
man's tradestuff that could be imagined. When they are
thirty those "boys" will be rich men, with women, slaves, 
and piles of stuff.</p>

<p>The government of the Free State has issued coins for 
native use. There are large coppers of the value of one,
two, five, and ten centimes. There are silver coins of half-franc, 
franc, two franc, and five franc value. But these
coins have no circulation beyond Leopoldville. In the 
Kasai district and the Upper Congo every commercial
transaction is done by barter.</p>

<p>Certain things are so constantly in use as to have fixed 
values. For articles of trifling value nothing is so good as
salt. A standard which varies from place to place is the 
brass rod, or mitaku. This is simply a piece of brass wire
of certain length. The mitaku in the Lower Congo are
short, those in the Upper Congo much longer. Beads
have ever been used in trade, but the wise traveler avoids 
them, as their value has dwindled, and the taste not only
varies from place to place, but from time to time. The 
bead which one traveler found useful in a given district
may have lost its attractiveness before the next traveler,
loaded with a large supply, comes that way.</p>

<pb n="18"/>

<p>At Ndombe the brass rod has no vogue. There the 
cowries (sea shells) are the standard in small transaction.
Cowries were once used in many parts of Africa, but in 
most places have ceased to have value. Ndombe, how-
ever, arrogates to himself and family the sole right of wearing 
brass arm and leg rings. Hence mitaku are not used,
and the old-fashioned cowry remains. But the chief
tradestuff, of course, is cloth. With it you may buy
chickens or goats, pigs or wives. In the Upper Kasai a 
piece of cloth means eight yards&#8212;"four fathoms." In
the Upper Congo a piece of cloth is sixteen yards, or eight
fathoms. Formerly at Ndombe eight or ten chickens
were given for a piece of cloth, value five francs, or one 
dollar in our currency. To-day one must pay a fathom
for each fowl.</p>

<p>The attempt to introduce the use of coin among the 
natives was unsatisfactory alike to the people and the 
trader. It has, however, taken hold strongly in the Lower
Congo, and in time the use of true money must push its 
way up the river. Curious is the contempt of all for coppers. 
Ten centimes in Belgium would give delight to many
a boy of twelve or fifteen years. The Congo native frequently 
throws it away or returns it to the person who 
gave it to him. Nothing less than a half-franc piece&#8212;
ten cents&#8212;is valued.</p>

<p>I have seen this illustrated many, many times, the first
time in my own case. We were visiting a miserable fishing 
village of poor Bakongo. As I entered the village a 
naked child, no more than two or three years old, met me.
I smiled at him and he at me. I extended my hand, which 
he clasped and accompanied me for half an hour as I

<pb n="19"/>

wandered from house to house, never once relaxing his 
hold upon my fingers. It caused great amusement to the 
adult portion of the village, as apparently the little one
rarely made such friendships. When I was about to leave 
I took a ten centime piece from my pocket and gave it to
him. Such a look of disgust came over his face would 
not be expected in any one short of adult years. It was
the last time that I gave a copper to a native.</p>

<p>Unquestionably one of the most striking characteristics
of the Congo people is loquacity. Their tongues hang 
loosely, and wag incessantly. Anything will do to talk
about. Start one and he will talk until you stop him.
Quarrels, troubles, friendships, joys, plans, and achievements, 
all are retailed at any hour of the day or night.
When excited, several will talk together with great vivacity,
though it is plain that no one knows what any other is 
saying.</p>

<p>One of the chief occupations of the man is the palaver.
The Portuguese term applies to any serious consultation
on any subject, pleasant or otherwise. A palaver may be 
confined to chiefs or it may include practically all the men
of one or more villages. In many towns there is a place
for gathering for palavers under a tree known as the palaver 
tree. Those who participate in a palaver bring their
chairs or stools or a roll of skin, which they place upon the 
ground to sit upon. At the beginning there is more or less
formality, and each one presents his view decently and in 
order; sometimes, however, hubbub ensues, disturbance
arises, and the palaver breaks up in disorder. In these 
palavers frequently speeches of great length and finished
oratory are delivered. not only are the emotions played

<pb n="20"/>

upon by the speaker, but keen argument is employed, and 
the appeal is made to the intelligence.</p>

<p>All matters of consequence&#8212;tribal, intertribal, and
dealings with the white man&#8212;are settled in palavers. The 
white man who knows the natives is wise to conform to
native customs. If he has some difficulty to settle, some 
favor to ask, some business to arrange, he will do well to 
have a formal palaver called in which he himself participates.</p>

<p>On the occasion of my second visit to Ndombe I found 
the town in great excitement. Going to the chief's headquarters, 
we found a great palaver in progress. Our coming 
was looked upon as a favorable omen, and with much 
formality chairs were brought and placed for us in the
midst of the gathering. The remarks were translated to 
me as they were made.</p>

<p>Ndombe's town is really an aggregation of villages.
Not one but four different tribes are represented in the
population. The central town, walled and of Bakuba
style, was Ndombe's own. Three or four Bakete towns
were clustered near it. In another direction were several
Baluba towns, and close by them small villages of Batua.
These four populations, though living by themselves, were
all subject to Ndombe, and the group of villages taken
together made a town of some pretension.</p>

<p>The day before our visit, there had been a battle with 
the Bakete in which several men had been wounded,
though none were killed. The trouble was taxes. The
state demanded increased payments. The proud Bakuba
decided that the Bakete should pay the new tax, and so 
informed them. Against this there had been a feeling of

<pb n="21"/>

rebellion, and the Bakete refused to pay the tax. Hence
the battle. All were greatly excited. The speeches were 
full of fire. The men&#8212;Bakuba&#8212;challenged each 
other to show mighty deeds of valor; they belittled and 
derided the unfortunate Bakete; they drew unpleasant
contrasts between themselves and their vassals.</p>

<p>Many of the speeches were fine efforts, and the words
were emphasized by the most graceful and vigorous gesticulation. 
Finally an old woman crowded in from one side 
where she had been listening to the speeches. In impassioned 
language she described the heavy labors which the 
women of the tribe already endured. They could stand 
no more. If the Bakuba were men let them prove it now 
or forever after remain silent. Force the Bakete to work.
Put no more heavy tasks upon your mothers, wives, and 
Sisters. The old woman's speech stirred the audience, and 
the meeting broke up, the men hurrying to prepare themselves 
for a new battle.</p>

<p>The market was among the most important institutions
of the Congo native. It retains importance to the present
day. In the Lower Congo a week consisted of four days,
and market was held at each market-place once a week.
The markets were named from the day of the week on 
which they were held. Thus, a Nsona market was a 
market held on the day of that name.</p>

<p>To these markets people came in numbers from all the 
country round and it was no uncommon thing to see
thousands thus gathered. There were special places for 
certain products. Thus, women who brought pottery for 
sale occupied a set place; those who brought bananas
would be grouped together in their section; sellers of camwood

<pb n="22"/>

sweet potatoes, kwanga (native cassava bread),
palm wine, oil, salt, fowls, pigs, goats&#8212;all occupied
places well known to the frequenters of the market. In
the olden times, of course, there was a section devoted to 
the sale of slaves.</p>

<p>Such a market presented a scene of active life and 
movement. Yet order was preserved. No crime was 
considered more serious than the disturbance of a market. 
Such an act deserved severest punishment, and 
those in whose hands the maintenance of order lay never
hesitated to kill the offender at once, and to make a public
display of his punishment as a warning to all.</p>

<p>There is no question that the Congo native is cruel, and
this cruelty shows itself in many ways. The killing of 
slaves was extremely common. It is true that it was never 
carried to the extreme in Congoland that it reached in
some true negro kingdoms, as Dahomey and Benin. It 
was, however, customary to kill slaves on the occasion of 
the death of a man of any consequence. The body of one 
of the slaves thus killed was placed first in the grave to 
serve as a pillow for the dead man. It was a common 
practice to preserve the skulls of victims sacrificed on 
such occasions as memorials.</p>

<p>Not only were slaves sacrificed to grace the funeral 
ceremony of chiefs, but often one or more were killed upon
occasions of festivity and joy. King Ndombe once presented 
me a skull. It was that of a Batua slave who had 
been killed upon the occasion of the chief's coming into
power. In this case, apparently, judging by the condition 
of the skull, the victim had been killed by simply
knocking in his head.</p>

<pb n="23"/>

<p>Until lately all through the Congo public executions 
were of a more formal character than this. At Lake 
Mantumba we were shown the exact mode of procedure.
A sort of stool or seat was set upon the ground and sticks
were tightly driven in around it, in such a way as to limit
the motions of the victim after he was seated; in fact, to 
almost prevent all movement. A sapling was then thrust
in the ground. A sort of cage or framework made of pliant
branches was fixed about the head of the victim. The
sapling was then bent over in an arch and firmly fastened
to the cage, thus holding the head firmly and stretching
the neck tense and hard. The hands were tied together,
as were the feet. When all was ready the executioner
with his great knife at a single blow struck off the head.</p>

<p>Enemies killed in battle were often mutilated, and 
fingers, nails, bones, or the skulls were treasured as trophies. 
When the white men first visited the villages of 
the Upper Congo there was scarce a house without its
ghastly trophy, and the houses of greats chiefs displayed
baskets filled with skulls.</p>
   
<p>It is doubtful whether the Congo native has as keen
a sense of physical suffering as ourselves. In almost every
tribe men and sometimes women, are marked with tribal
marks upon the face or body; thus, among the Bangala
each member of the tribe bears a projection like a cock's
comb running vertically across the forehead from the nose 
root to the hair line. This excrescence is frequently
three-quarters of an inch in breadth and of the same elevation. 
Its development begins in childhood, when a series
of short but deep horizontal lines are cut in the child's
forehead; these are irritated to produce swelling; later
    
<pb n="24"/>

on they are cut again, and again, and again, until the 
full development is produced. We should certainly find 
such an operation painful in the extreme. I have seen 
women whose entire bodies were masses of raised patterns, 
produced by cutting and irritating.</p>
    
<p>When being operated upon the subject usually squats 
or lies in front of the operator, who sits cross-legged on
the ground. The head or other portion of the body which 
is being cut rests upon the lap or knees of the cutter. No
particular pain is shown by the subject, though the cuts
are often deep and blood flows copiously. A few minutes
after the operation, smeared with fresh oil on the wounds,
the scarred person walks about as if nothing had happened.</p>
    
<p>The first subject that I saw treated for rheumatism was
a young woman. She was standing before her house 
door, while the old woman who was treating her was
squatted on the ground before her. In her hand the old
woman had a sharp, native razor, and with it she cut lines
several inches long and to good depth in the fleshy part of
the leg of her standing patient. Not once nor twice, but 
a dozen times the old woman cut, and rubbed in medicine
in the open wounds. The patient gave but little signs of
pain. Once or twice she winced as the knife went a little 
deeper than usual; she held a long staff in her hand, and 
in the most serious moments of the cutting she clutched
it a little the tighter. But there were no groans, no cries,
nor tears. I have never seen a white person who could
have stood the operation with so little evidence of suffering.</p>
    
<p>Part of the time that we were in Ndombe's district we
had charge of an establishment employing 140 natives,
    
<pb n="25"/>

more or less. Among these natives was one Casati. I 
think he was a Zappo Zap. Originally a man of quickness 
and intelligence, he had become a complete physical
wreck through drink and other forms of dissipation. He
boarded with a girl named Tumba. One afternoon
they presented themselves before me with a palaver. It
was some question in regard to payment and service.
Like most Bantu difficulties, its beginning seemed to 
extend backwards to the world's creation.</p>
    
<p>I knew Tumba to be a worthy and industrious girl;
Casati was a miserable and worthless wretch. I therefore
refused to decide the difficulty, stating that the parties
interested must wait until the return of the true owner of 
the establishment, who would decide their question.
This was not at all to the satisfaction of Casati, who,
merely to show his dissatisfaction, took a sharp knife and 
cut three big gashes in his own shoulder. It seems plain
to me, from this apparent lack of pain under scarring,
medical treatment, and self-infliction, that there is a notable 
difference between the Bantu and ourselves.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling"/>
    
<pb n="81"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>X.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>January 29, 1907.</p>

<p>What has the Congo Free State done during
its twenty-two years&#8212;almost&#8212;of existence?</p>

<p>It has taken possession of a vast area of 
land, 800,00 square miles in extent, and dominated it.
It has most skillfully developed a mighty waterway. We
    
<pb n="82"/>

are already familiar with the simple and original method
of development which has been and is being pursued. We
have already called attention to the fact that, notwithstanding
interruption to navigation here and there in
the Congo and its larger tributaries, there are long stretches
of navigable water above the obstacles. The plan of utilization 
and development has been to occupy directly the 
natural stretches of navigable water and to get around 
the cataracts by the shortest railroad lines possible. This
has been done already at two points, and will be done at
others in the near future. It is the most economical manner 
of developing a way of penetration into the great area
to be developed and exploited.</p>
    
<p>It has continuously carried on geographical explorations 
by which the world's knowledge of African geography 
has been profoundly increased. We have already 
called attention to the fact that during the eight years when
the A.I.A. was in existence, Belgium equipped and maintained 
six expeditions; during the same period France
maintained but two, Germany one, and England none.
In other words, Belgium did more for geographic science
during that time than the other three great nations combined.</p>
    
<p>It has put an end to inter-tribal wars, to execution of 
slaves at funerals and festal occasions, and to cannibalism 
in all those districts to which its actual authority
into remote parts of its territory. There are still inter-tribal 
wars in remote parts of the Congo Free State; executions 
and the eating of human flesh are no doubt still
    
<pb n="83"/>

common in districts which have but little felt the influence 
of the white ruler. With the extension of the definite 
power of the state into these remoter sections, these
evils will disappear as they have disappeared in the more 
accessible portions of the country.</p>
    
<p>It has developed a native army which is available in
case of attack upon the integrity of the state, and which 
serves as a policing party within its territory. In the first
days of the state's history its soldiery was drawn from the 
Zanzibar district, and to a less degree from the English
possessions along the western coast of Africa. It soon
was realized that from every point of view this condition
was undesirable. Between the foreign soldiery and the
native people there were no bonds of common interest.
No national feeling or spirit could develop among them.
From the point of view of expense the foreign soldier was
extremely costly. For these different reasons the state
early developed the idea of an army made of Congo
natives. To-day there are but few foreign soldiers in the 
public force.</p>
    
<p>If there is ever to be a real nation in the Congo district
there must develop in some way a feeling of unity of 
blood and interests among the people. In tribal life each 
tribe is absorbed in its own interests&#8212;petty, of course&#8212;
and looks upon all other tribes as enemies. Many of the 
tribes were insignificant in number and in the area which
they occupied. Nothing but an outside influence can 
unite into one useful whole such a multitude of petty, dis-
trustful, hostile groups of men. In the public force there
are soldiers from almost every tribe within the Congo.
At the great training camps men are brought together who
    
<pb n="84"/>

speak different languages, have different customs, and 
come from widely separated areas. Under the military
discipline, these men are brought into close and long continued 
relations. They must accommodate themselves
to one another. They must respect each other's ways 
of thought and doing. At the end of his term of service
the soldier goes out necessarily broadened in his ideas,
necessarily less prejudiced more tolerant. The army
is the most important influence toward arousing national
existence.</p>
    
<p>It has conducted many interesting experiments and 
researches along scientific lines. While these had frequently 
practical ends, they were in themselves worth 
doing, and their beneficent results are not confined to the 
Congo. Thus, at Leopoldville there is a well-equipped 
bacteriological institute for the study of tropical diseases.
Naturally, the most of its attention up to the present has 
been given to the subject of sleeping-sickness.</p>
    
<p>The experiments upon the utilization of the African
elephant and the zebra have general interest; if they fail,
the warning may be useful; if they succeed, their results
will be by no means confined to the Congo Free State.
At Eala is a botanical garden creditably devised and well
conducted. Six hundred species of plants are there in
cultivation, something more than half of them being 
foreign species. There experiments are being made upon 
a broad scale to discover the uses of native plants and the 
possibility of cultivating them to advantage. Forty species
of African plants yield rubber; those the product of which 
is of a quality to warrant experimenting, are here being 
cultivated with reference to ascertaining their value in
    
<pb n="85"/>

plantations. Foreign rubber producers, coffees from 
different portions of the globe, medicinal plants, dye and 
other useful plants are being tested to find out how they 
flourish in Congo.</p>
    
<p>Nor is the interest of the Congo Free State in scientific 
investigations limited to its own enterprises. Some
time ago a British commission, consisting of three specialists 
in tropical medicines, visited the Congo with the purpose 
of investigating the sleeping-sickness. Not only
were they given every facility for their investigation, but
after they returned to England the total expenses of their
expedition were returned with the compliments of the 
State government in recognition of the general value and
utility of their investigations. Individual investigators
and expeditions of a scientific character within the Congo
State always have found the government interested in 
furthering and aiding their studies.</p>
    
<p>It has developed a significant and growing section of 
the world's commerce. When Stanley came down the 
Congo, the value of the exports from that region was so 
small that it might be neglected. To-day the Congo
furnishes the world with ivory and supplies a most significant 
portion of the rubber which is used. To-day
Antwerp is the greatest market for these two products.
That Liverpool should lose in relative importance in the 
matter of West African trade is no doubt hard for Englishmen. 
But the world gains by having several great
trading centers in place of one.</p>
    
<p>It has checked the extension of the Arab influence
with all its horrors. To one who reads Stanley's description 
this means much. With this checking, the foreign
    
<pb n="86"/>

slave trade ceased. Do not misunderstand me. There 
was much admirable in the Arab culture. There is no
question that the practical men, whose views we always 
keep in mind, and to whom we make our argument,
would approve the substitution of it or the barbarism
that existed before. But it is certain that it stood in 
the way of European influence; that it came into conflict
with European ideas, and if it were desirable that these
should ultimately prevail, the Arab life and culture must
disappear.</p>
    
<p>We might, of course, continue and extend our list of
the achievements of the Congo Free State. We have
said enough, however, to show that it has done much 
toward carrying out its promise to civilize and modify the 
native population in the direction of our own ideals. Even
the bitter enemies of the Free State government will admit
all this, and more. But they claim that all the credit of
it disappears in view of the atrocities, the cruelties, and 
horrors connected with its own administration.</p>
    
<p>Atrocities no doubt exist; they have existed; they will
exist. They are ever present in cases where a population 
of natives is exploited by an active and aggressive 
"higher race." The process of elevating natives, of making 
them over in new pattern, is never a happy one for 
the native. The wrenching of old ties, the destruction
of old ideals, the replacing of an ancient life by one different 
in every detail, is a painful thing.</p>
    
<p>I deplore atrocities, but I have often thought that, if 
I were a member of a race that was being improved by
outside influences, I would rather they should kill me outright 
with bullet or with knife than subject me to the
    
<pb n="87"/>

suffering of years in molding me to new ideas. In other
words, I sometimes feel that flagrant outrage is less painful 
to the victim than well-meant direction, teaching, and 
elevation to their object.</p>

<p>Let us turn, however, to the whole subject of atrocities.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>XI.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>January 30, 1907.</p>
    
<p>Much has been said of flogging and the chicotte.
There is no question that flogging is general 
throughout the Congo Free State. The English 
word "flogging" is one which is generally known and 
understood by officials of every nationality throughout the 
country; it is known, too, by a surprising number of 
natives. The chicotte is known to everybody within the 
state limits&#8212;its name is Portuguese. In all my journey 
in the Congo, while I frequently heard the word "flogging"
and constantly heard the word "chicotte," I never heard 
the French term for either. Nor do I think the native has.
It is plain that neither flogging nor the chicotte was
introduced by Belgians. These found them in the country 
on their arrival, introduced by English and Portuguese.</p>
    
<p>It is not the fact of flogging in itself that raises objections; 
not only the state and traders but the missionaries
find it necessary to whip their black employes. In fact,
at a missionary conference&#8212;I think it was&#8212;one missionary
referred laughingly to the boys whom another
(by the way, one of the chief witnesses against the state)
"had flogged into the kingdom of heaven." He did not 
mean the boys had died as a result of the flogging, but
    
<pb n="88"/>

simply that they had found salvation through its means.
It is, then, the amount, severity, and undeservedness of
the whipping which are reprobated.</p>
    
<p>I saw, of course, plenty of flogging. Not, indeed, with
such an instrument as has been recently shown throughout
the United States by a complaining missionary. I was 
conversing recently with a friend who had been profoundly
stirred in connection with Congo atrocities. He happened
to mention the chicotte, then said: "Have you ever seen
a chicotte? You know it is made of six thongs of hippopotamus 
skin, twisted tightly together." I told him
that I had seen hundreds of chicottes, but that I had never
seen one such as he described. As a matter of fact, I 
have seen chicottes of a single thong and of two or three
twisted together, but I have never seen one composed of 
six. I do not know whether such an instrument would 
cause greater suffering in punishment, but it certainly is
better suited for display to sympathetic audiences who 
want to be harrowed by dreadful reports. The first
flogging that I happened to see was at a distance. I was 
busy measuring soldiers; hearing cries, I looked in the 
direction whence they came, and saw a black man being
publicly whipped before the office of the commissaire.
An officer of proper authority was present inspecting the 
punishment, which I presume was entirely legal.</p>
    
<p>In the second flogging which I witnessed, this time at
close quarters, I was myself implicated to a degree. We 
were at a mission station. The mission force and practically 
all the people from the place were attending Sunday
morning service. It was fruiting time for the mango
trees, which were loaded with golden fruit. Suddenly
    
<pb n="89"/>

we heard an outcry, and in a moment the mission sentry,
delighted and excited, came up to our veranda with an
unfortunate prisoner, whom he had taken in the act of 
stealing fruit. He insisted on leaving him with us for 
guarding. I turned him over to my companion, who set
him on his veranda, telling him to stay there until the 
missionary should come from the service.</p>
    
<p>The prisoner squatted down upon the veranda without 
a word of discussion, laying the fruit, evidence of his
guilt, upon the floor at his side. We were so angry at
him that he made no attempt at escaping, and did not even 
eat the fruit which he had stolen, that we washed our
hands of the whole affair, and believed he deserved all
that might be coming. The service over, the missionary 
appeared, accompanied by the triumphant sentry. When
the prisoner had admitted his guilt, the missionary asked
whether he preferred to be sent to the state for punishment 
or to be whipped by him, to which the prisoner replied
that he should prefer the mission flogging.</p>
    
<p>With great formality the instrument of punishment was
produced; it consisted of two long and narrow boards,
perhaps six feet in length and two or three inches wide;
between them was fixed a board of the same width,
but of half the length. At one end these were firmly
screwed together, while the other end was left open. It
will be seen that when a heavy blow was given with the 
instrument the free ends of the two long sticks would strike
together, producing a resounding whack which, no doubt,
produced a psychic suffering in the victim in addition to the 
true physical pain. However that may be, fifteen blows,
I think, were administered, and the prisoner discharged.</p>
    
<pb n="90"/>

<p>One day, upon the Kasai steamer, we witnessed a 
wholesale whipping, which was typical of this mode of 
punishment as regularly administered. The night before
we had been forced to tie up beside the forest. The 
night was dark and the cutters refused to make wood for 
the next day's journey. This was a serious act of insurrection, 
involving delay and trouble. When, finally, the 
next morning the wood had been loaded and the steamer
was under way, ten of the rebels were marched up to the 
captain. In turn each lay down upon the floor, a friend
held his hands and wrists, while the capita administered
twenty blows. It is comparatively rare that the white
man himself does the flogging; usually it is the regular
capita who is in charge of the workmen, or a special one
of the working force detailed to play the part.</p>
    
<p>It makes a notable difference in the way in which the 
punishment is received whether the hands are firmly
held to prevent struggling. An English-speaking white
man not in the government or company employ, who had
had more or less opportunity for observation in our 
Southern states, and whose experience in the Congo
extends over several years, told me that flogging with the 
chicotte was a rather mild and simple punishment; that 
it hurt but little, and that, for his part, he preferred to hit 
the workmen on the head and kick them in the shins,
those being places more tender to the application than the 
part subjected to the chicotte. On the whole, I am inclined 
to think that there was something in what he said.
It is certain that in most cases the suffering from a flogging
is momentary. I have even seen persons undergoing 
serious flogging exchange significant glances and signals
    
<pb n="91"/>

with their friends, in which the suggestion of pain was
quite absent. Many a time, also, I have seen a man
immediately after being flogged, laughing and playing with 
his companions as if naught had happened. Personally,
though I have seen many cases of this form of punishment,
I have never seen blood drawn, nor the fainting of the 
victim.</p>
    
<p>It is common to speak of the chain-gang with great 
sympathy. One sees chain-gangs at every state post;
it is the common punishment for minor offenses to put
the prisoner on the chain. Sometimes as many as twelve
or fifteen are thus joined together by chains attached to
iron rings placed about their necks. They are employed
in all sorts of work&#8212;bringing water for use about the 
station, sweeping roads, clearing fields, carrying burdens.
On our arrival at a state post, immediately after we had
presented our introductions to the commandant, the chain-gang 
would be sent to bring our freight and baggage to
the rooms to which we were assigned. The ring around
the necks of these prisoners is a light iron ring, weighing
certainly not to exceed two pounds. The weight of chain
falling upon each prisoner can hardly be more than six 
or eight pounds additional. In other words, the weight
which they are forced to carry in the shape of ring and 
chain does not exceed, probably does not equal, ten pounds.</p>
    
<p>From the viewpoint of service rendered, the chain-gang 
has little value. It dawdles, lags, idles, and plays;
only when it is carrying burdens does it really work. I 
have never seen a chain-gang composed of women, nor
have I seen women on the same gang with men. It is 
stated by the missionaries that such things occur. 
 
<pb n="92"/>

Certainly, every one would object to the chaining together of 
male and female prisoners. Apart from this, the chain-gang 
does not particularly arouse my sympathy. It is 
a very mild form of punishment, and one which, of course, 
is common in as bad a form or worse throughout many of
our Southern states. To grieve over the weight carried
in the form of chain and ring is simply ridiculous; there
are  to-day thousands of women among these Congo tribes
who for the sake of decoration carry about their neck a 
heavy ring of brass weighing twenty, twenty-five, or thirty
pounds. It is no uncommon thing for both men and women
to have a weight of thirty, forty, or fifty pounds of brass
and iron rings and ornaments upon them.</p>
    
<p>I cannot believe that the ordinary flogging, such as I 
have seen, causes notable suffering to people who, for 
purposes of decoration or treatment of rheumatism, submit 
without evidence of pain to such operations as I have
described in detail in an earlier article. Nor can I feel 
that the mere fact of carrying chain and ring of less than
ten pounds' weight involves terrible suffering for people
who regularly carry much heavier burdens of ornaments.</p>
    
<p>Much has been said of late in regard to hostages. The 
taking of hostages and holding them until some obligation 
or agreement had been performed was a common 
native custom. Stanley frequently captured women
and children, or even men, of tribes in the districts through
which he was passing and held them as hostages until they 
should show him the trail he should follow, or until their 
people supplied him with the food or other things which
he desired. At the ill-fated Yambuya camp the rear
guard frequently seized the women of the natives who
    
<pb n="93"/>

had failed to bring in food supplies in return for the trade
stuffs offered. This seizure of hostages is mentioned
repeatedly in the writings of the early travelers, and seems 
to have caused no outcry on the part of the sensitive
civilized world at that time. Why should it now?</p>
    
<p>It is a common practice, though a disagreeable one to 
us, for one who sells a thing to keep back a part of it in
making delivery of the goods. On one occasion we brought
a musical instrument, a marimba, which consisted, in
part, of a dozen gourds as resounding bodies. Every one
of these gourds was necessary to the instrument, yet the
seller, after we had examined it with care to see that it 
was perfect, removed three of the gourds, in accordance
with this custom. The instrument was sent to us by the 
son of the seller's chief, old Chicoma's son had a companion
with him. We at once decided to hold the chief's son as 
a hostage, sending word by his companion that he would 
be set free only on the appearance of the missing gourds.
when we told the youth that we had "tied him up," that
being the expression for holding a person hostage, he 
looked sheepish, but made no complaint, recognizing the 
justice of out action.</p>
    
<p>This was at 4 o'clock in the afternoon. He made no
attempt to escape, although we had not in any way actually
interfered with his freedom of movement. We gave him
supper when the time came and breakfast in the morning.
He found his stay tedious, however, and finally, when none
was looking, slipped away. He must have met the messenger 
bringing the missing gourds before he was any
    
<pb n="94"/>

distance from the house, as he appeared with our property 
about half an hour after the flight.</p>
    
<p>The only other personal experience in the matter of 
hostages that we had was in the High Kasai. A white
man, agent of the Kasai company, was our guest for the 
night. In the early morning our friend, Chief Ndombe,
appeared, in great excitement, begging us to loan him
cloth, as the white man had seized one of his slaves and 
would not release him until he had finally paid a debt which
the white man claimed he owed him. The question
appeared complicated, and we let him have the cloth,
after which we went over to hear the palaver accompanying 
the payment. Both sides told their story with much 
gesticulation. The white man's boy had owned a woman,
for whom he claimed to have paid six pieces of cloth; she 
had run away, and he had sought in vain for her. The 
chief, old Chicoma, told him that the woman was at 
Ndombe and in the house of the great chief. So they 
seized Ndombe's slave&#8212;a little lad about 11 years of age,
whose bright face and curious head shaving always had 
greatly attracted me. This boy our visitors were holding 
as a hostage until Ndombe should produce the woman or 
pay her value.</p>
    
<p>Of course, the whole procedure was illegal, and I was 
inclined to take up the matter vigorously. There were,
however, so many elements of doubt in the matter that
I finally concluded to let it pass. Of hostages held by 
company agents or by state people we saw but few, and 
never learned the circumstances under which they had 
been taken. They were rarely in actual confinement, and 
we saw no evidences of bad treatment toward them. In

<pb n="95"/>

native custom, the hostages are regularly well treated and 
fed regularly, while held in captivity. While we have
never seen maltreatment of hostages, we can readily 
understand how such could arise. Taken, as they usually
are, in order to force the bringing in of food or forest
products, if their holding does not produce the desired
effect the feeling of vexation resulting may easily lead 
to cruelty.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>XII.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>January 31, 1907.</p>
  
<p>People in this country seem to expect that every
traveler in the Congo must meet with crowds of 
people who have had one or both hands cut off.
We have all seen pictures of these unfortunates, and have
heard most harrowing tales in regard to them. Casement,
the English consul, whose report to the British government
has caused so much agitation, and who described many 
cases of mutilation, himself saw* but a single case; and that
case, though put forward by the missionaries as an example
of state atrocities, was finally withdrawn by them, as the 
subject had not been mutilated by human assailants, but
by a wild boar. Casement traveled many miles and spent
much time in securing the material for his indictment, and 
yet saw* but this one case. We saw a single case of mutilation. 
It was a boy Ikoko, probably some twelve years
old. He had been found, a child of three or four years, by 
the side of his dead mother, after a punitive expedition had 
visited the town. His mother's body had been mutilated

<note>* I am here in error. Casement <hi rend="italics">saw</hi> more than one case of mutilation; he carefully <hi rend="italics">investigated</hi> but one.</note>
    
<pb n="96"/>

and the child's hand cut off. We might have seen a second
case of this sort at this place if we had searched for her.
There is a second there.</p>
   
<p>No one, I think, would desire to excuse the barbarity 
of cutting off the hands of either dead or living, but we
must remember that the soldiers in these expeditions are
natives, and in the excitement and bloodthirst roused by a 
military attack they relapse to ancient customs. There 
has, indeed; been considerable question recently whether
the cutting-off of hands is really a native custom. Sir
Francis de Winton, himself an Englishman, and Stanley's
successor in the administration of the Congo State, says 
that it was. And Glave says: "In every village in this 
section (Lukolela) will be found slaves of both sexes with
one ear cut off. This is a popular form of punishment in 
an African village. It is not at all unusual to hear such 
threats as 'I will cut your ear off,' 'I will sell you,' or 'I
will kill you,' and often they are said in earnest." Where
such customs were constant in native life it is not strange
that they have lasted on into the present.</p>
    
<p>Of course, in this connection we must not forget that 
mutilation of dead bodies is not by any means confined to 
the Congo Free State, nor to its natives. Only a few
months ago in Southern Africa the British force cut off
the head of a hostile chief. When the matter was investigated, 
the excuse given was that it was done for purposes 
of identification, and that the body was afterwards brought 
in and buried with it.</p>
    
<p>The most of the difficulty with the natives of the Congo
Free State, of course, comes in connection with the demand
to gather rubber. The native hates the forest; he dislikes
    
<pb n="97"/>

to gather rubber; it takes him from his home, and com-
fort, and wife. We have never accompanied a party of
natives gathering rubber, but we have seen them started 
and have also seen them bringing in their product. The 
best rubber of the Congo is produced by vines which frequently 
grow to several inches in diameter. The same 
vine may be tapped many times. The milky juice, which 
exudes abundantly, promptly coagulates into rubber; as
it hardens it is rolled into balls between the palm and some 
portion of the body, such as the chest or leg.</p>
    
<p>The place where we have seen most of rubber production 
is in the High Kasai, where the famous red rubber is
produced, which sells for the highest price of any African 
caoutchouc. My missionary friends have told me that 
conditions in the Kasai are not bad and that they have no 
special fault to find with the Kasai company. While there 
were things that might be criticised, there was apparent
fairness in the business. The natives waited several days 
after they had gathered their balls of rubber before bringing 
them in. This was for the reason that the company's
agent had but an unattractive stock of goods in his magazine 
at the moment; they preferred to wait until a new 
stock should come up on the expected steamer. As soon
as it appeared they sent word that they might be expected
the following day.</p>
    
<p>The old Bachoko chief, Maiila, was brought in state, in
his blue hammock; his people came singing and dancing
with the baskets full of balls of rubber on their heads. All
proceeded to the magazine, where the great steelyards were 
suspended and the rubber weighed; each man looked carefully 
to see that his stock balanced evenly, and one of their
    
<pb n="98"/>

number, who understood the instrument and could figure,
stood by to see that all went fair. While the rubber was
a demanded tax, a regular price of 1 franc and 25 centimes
the kilo was paid. This was given in stuffs, of course, and
the native selected what he pleased from the now abundant
stock of cloths, blankets, graniteware, and so forth. It 
may truly be said that they came in singing gayly and 
went home glad.</p>
    
<p>At Mobandja we saw a large party setting out to the 
forest to gather rubber, different from any that we had seen
before in that a considerable number of women formed a 
part of it. This feature I did not like, although I presume 
it is an effort to meet the criticisms of the report of the royal
commission of investigation.  The commission particularly 
criticised the fact that the men, in going into the for-
est, were deprived of the company of their women&#8212;a
hardship strongly emphasized. It is surely a mistake,
however well it may be meant, to send the women into the 
forest with the men to gather rubber. Such a procedure 
involves the neglect of her fields and interrupts the woman's
work.</p>
    
<p>And here we touch upon the thing which in my opinion
is the worst feature of the whole Congo business. Anything 
that affects the woman's work necessarily brings
hardship. I have seen many heart-rending statements in
regard to the loss of work time which the man suffers by
going to the forest to gather rubber. We are told that by
the time he has gone several days' journey into the dense
forest, gathered his balls of rubber, and returned again
to his village, he has no time left for work, and his
family and the whole community suffers as a consequence.
    
<pb n="99"/>

But from what work does this gathering of rubber take
the man?</p>
    
<p>We have already called attention to the fact that the 
support of the family and the actual work in any village
fall upon the woman. The man, before he went into the
forest to gather rubber, had no pressing  duties. His wife
supported him; he spent his time in visiting, dancing, 
lolling under shelters, drinking with his friends, or in palavers,
sometimes of great importance but frequently of no
consequence; in other words, he was an idler, or a man
of leisure. I feel no sorrow on account of the labors  from
which he is restrained. Personally, I should have no
objection to his idling. If he does not want to work and
need not work, I see no reason why he should not idle.
But my readers are practical men, who talk much of the 
dignity of labor and the elevation of the lazy negro. Very
good; if work is dignified and the elevation of the negro
necessary, let him collect rubber, but do not mourn over
the fact that he is deprived of opportunity to earn a living
for himself and family.</p>
    
<p>There is, indeed, one set of circumstances under which
the man may really be deprived of opportunity to aid in
the work of gaining of a living. Where the men in a community 
are really fishermen&#8212;they are not always so&#8212;
to take them from their fishing entrails a hardship.</p>
    
<p>The thing which seems to me the worst is the kwanga
tax on women and the fish tax on men. The former is at
its worst, perhaps, in Leopoldville; the latter is bad enough
at Nouvelle Anvers. Leopoldville is situated in a district 
which yields much less for food than necessary.
It has always been so. Even in the days before the white
    
<pb n="100"/>

man came, the people in the native villages on Stanley
Pool were obliged to buy food supplies from outside, as they
themselves, being devoted to trading, did no cultivation.
With the coming of the white man, and the establishing 
of a great post at Leopoldville, with thousands of native
workmen and soldiers to be fed, the food question became
serious. The state has solved problem by levying a 
food tax on the native villages for many miles around.</p>
    
<p>The women are required to bring a certain amount of 
kwanga&#8212;native cassava bread&#8212;to Leopoldville within
a stated period of time. To do this involves almost continuous 
labor, and really leaves the women little time for 
attending to the needs of their own people. Some of
them are forced to come many miles with the supply of
bread. When they have cared for the growing plants in
their fields, prepared the required stint of kwanga, brought
it the weary distance over the trails, and again come back
to their village, they must begin to prepare for the next
installment. For this heavy burden there must certainly
be found some remedy. Personally, it seems to me that
the women belonging to the workmen and the soldiers
might be utilized in cultivating extensive fields to supply
the need. The condition of the men who pay the fish
tax is analogous to that of these kwanga-taxed women.</p>
    
<p>The question of the population of the Congo is an
unsettled one. Stanley estimated it at 29,000,000 people;
Reclus, in 1888, estimated it at something over 20,000,000;
Wagner and Supan claimed 17,000,000, and Vierkandt sets
the figure at 11,000,000. The governor-general, Baron 
Wahis, who has several times made the inspection of the 
whole river, is inclined to think that even Stanley's figure

<pb n="101"/>

is below the true one. Between these limits of 11,000,000
and 29,000,000 any one may choose which he prefers.
No one knows, or is likely for many years to know. Those 
who believe that Stanley's figure was true in its time, and
that Vierkandt's is true at present, may well insist, as they 
do, that depopulation is taking place.</p>
   
<p>Personally, I have no doubt that depopulation is going
on. Of course, the enemies of the Free State government
attribute the diminution in population chiefly to the cruelties 
practiced by the state, but it is certain that many
causes combine in the result.</p>
    
<p>This distribution of the Congo population is exceedingly
irregular. From Stanley Pool to Chumbiri there has 
been almost no population during the period of our knowledge. 
On the other hand, from Basoko to Stanley Falls
the population is abundant and there is almost a continuous 
line of native villages along the banks for miles.
Practically, the state of population is really known only
along the river banks. Back from the riverines are inland
tribes, the areas of which in some cases are but sparsely
settled, while in others they swarm. They are, however,
little known, and just how the population is distributed 
is uncertain. The district which we personally best know 
&#8212;the Kasai&#8212;is one of the most populous of all the 
Congo State, and around the Sankuru, one of the main 
tributaries of the Kasai, we perhaps have the densest
population of the country. If we take Stanley's estimate
as accurate, the population would average twelve to the 
square kilometer.</p>
    
<p>Among known causes for the diminution of Congo
population we may mention first the raiding expeditions
   
<pb n="102"/>

of the Arabs. These were numerous and destructive in
the extreme, throughout the region of the Upper Congo 
and the Lualaba. Organized for taking slaves and 
getting booty, they destroyed ruthlessly the adult male 
population and deported the women and children. Towns
were burned and whole districts left unoccupied. There
is no question that many of the punitive expeditions of the 
state have been far more severe than necessity demanded;
"the people must be shown the power of Bula Matadi."
It is said that Vankerckhoven's expedition destroyed
whole towns needlessly in the district of Chumbiri and 
Bolobo. Certainly, the population in this section was formerly 
abundant. Everywhere along the shores one sees
the groups of palm trees marking the sites of former
villages; probably the present population is no more than
one fourth that which existed formerly.</p>
    
<p>Throughout the whole district, where the French
Congo touches on the river, it is a common thing for timid
or disgruntled villagers to move <hi rend="italics">en masse</hi> across the river
into French territory. These wholesale removals are an
advantage to the natives, as that portion of the French
Congo is less well occupied by white posts and government 
officials than the corresponding part of the Congo
Free State. The natives who have thus removed unquestionably 
have an easier time in the French colony.
This, however, can hardly be called depopulation, as it 
involves no loss in persons, but merely a transfer from the 
Free State side to the other. It does not at all affect the 
actual number of the race.</p>
    
<p>Sleeping-sickness is carrying off its tens of thousands.</p>

<p>But after we suggest these causes we are still far from
    
<pb n="103"/>

a full solution of the problem of depopulation, which is a 
mysterious thing. In Polynesia we have another example
of it on a prodigious scale. In Polynesia we have neither
slave raids, nor punitive expeditions, nor sleeping-sickness.
Yet, adults die and children are not born. If things continue 
in the future as in the past, the time is not far distant 
when the Polynesian&#8212;one of the most interesting 
and attractive of human races&#8212;will be a thing completely
of the past.</p>
    
<p>The case of our own American Indians is similar.
Whole tribes have disappeared; others are dying out so
rapidly that a few years will see their complete extinction.
I am familiar with the arguments which, from time to
time, are printed to demonstrate that the number of 
American Indians is as great as ever. It seems, however, 
that it is only rich tribes that hold their own; the
reason is not far to seek, but we may not here pursue
the argument further.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="title">

<p>XIII.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>February 1, 1907.</p>
    
<p>Nor is apparent depopulation of the Congo a matter 
of recent date. Quotations might be given
from many travelers. We quote three from
Bentley, because he was well acquainted with the country
and because he was an English missionary. In speaking
of the town of Mputu, an hour and a half distant from San
Salvador, he describes the chief, Mbumba, a man of 
energy, feared in all his district. He was strict in his 
demands regarding conduct. In his presence others were 
required to sit tailor-fashion. "To ease the cramped
    
<pb n="104"/>

limbs, by stretching them out before one, is a gross breach
of decorum; any one who did so in Mbumba's presence
was taken out, and was <sic>fortuate</sic> if he lost only an ear. We
have known several great chiefs who would order a man
who sat carelessly to be thus mutilated. His own people
were much afraid of him on account of his cruel, murderous 
ways; for a small offense he would kill them
relentlessly. He was superstitious and very ready to kill
witches. Through his evil temper, pride, and superstition,
his town of several hundred people was reduced to eighty 
or ninety souls."</p>
    
<p>Again he says: "Our next camp was at Manzi; but as we
had so many people, the natives preferred that we should
camp in a wood at Matamba, twenty minutes' walk beyond
the town. The wood marked the site of a town deserted
some years before. There were no other towns on the road
from there to Isangila, a distance of thirty miles, for the 
wicked people had killed each other out over  their witch
palavers. This was what the natives told us themselves.
Yet they went on killing their witches, believing that if 
they did not do so all the people would be exterminated.
Two wretched villages of a few huts each were to be found
a few miles off the path, but the country was practically 
depopulated."</p>
    
<p>In another place he says, in speaking of the caravan
days: "All the carriers suffered acutely from fever, and 
this was the case with all the caravans on the road. This 
mortality was largely increased by the improvidence of the 
carriers themselves. Thousands of men were engaged 
in transport work at the time, but very troubled to 
carry enough food with them, or money wherewith to buy
    
<pb n="105"/>

it. As a rule, the young men staid in their towns as long 
as they had anything to buy food with; when they failed,
they borrowed until their debts became too great. Then
they arranged to go with some caravan to carry, and 
received ration money for the road. This would be partly
used up in the town, and the rest go to those from whom
they borrowed. On the road they lived largely on palm
nuts and raw cassava, and returned to their homes in a 
terribly exhausted condition. With the influx of cloth
gained by transportation came hunger, for wealth made
the women lazy; they preferred to buy food rather than
produce&#8212;the gardens came to an end, then hunger followed, 
and sickness and death. Women staid at home
to mourn, and the mischief became worse. Sleep-sickness 
and smallpox spread. The population of the cataracts 
district is not more than half what it was fifteen
years ago. The railway is now complete, and the country 
will adapt itself to its new conditions."</p>
    
<p>Those who are hostile to the state, of course, will find
great comfort in this quotation; for the transport system
was an introduction by the Belgians. It will be observed,
however, that the author mentions no cruelty on the part
of the new masters in this connection; it must also be
remembered that the missionaries were as much interested
in the caravan system as any, and assisted in its development. 
My chief object in introducing the quotation is 
to show how impossible it is to affect native conditions in
one way without bringing about a connected series of 
changes, not always easy to foresee.</p>
    
<p>To me, the real wonder is that there are any of the Congo 
peoples left. Think of the constant drain due to the foreign
    
<pb n="106"/>

slave trade, continued from an early date until after
the middle of the last century. Think of the continuous
losses due to the barbarism of native chiefs and demands
of native customs&#8212;to wars, cannibalism, execution, and 
ordeal. Think of the destruction caused by punitive
expeditions&#8212;towns burned, people killed. Think of 
the drafts made by the caravan system and the public
works which the state has been forced to carry out. Think
of the multitudes who have died with the diseases of the 
country and from pestilence introduced by the newcomers.
Yet the population really shows signs of great vitality
to-day, and the most discouraged missionary hesitates
a real prediction for the future.</p>  
    
<p>There is a most interesting and suggestive map in 
Morel's new book, "Red Rubber." It bears the legend,
"Map showing revenue division of the Congo Free State."
Upon this map we find marked with little crosses the localities 
where specific reports of atrocities have been received.
The distribution of these crosses is interesting. We find a 
concentration of them along the main river from the Rubi
River almost to the mouth of the Kasai, a notable bunch
of them in the region of the A. B. I. R., and in an area
worked by the Antwerp trust; also in the district of Lake
Leopold II. There are few crosses indicative of bad treatment 
in the Congo above this district, and practically none
in the lower Congo and the Kasai. It is precisely in the 
areas where these crosses are so frequent that the early 
travelers had difficulty with the natives in first traversing
the country. In other words, the districts where native
hostility has in recent years produced the acts of alleged 
cruelty have always been centers of disturbance and
    
<pb n="107"/>

attack against the white man. Districts which were
found occupied by peaceful and friendly tribes have been
the scenes of few outrages. This seems to me a point 
worthy serious consideration.</p>
    
<p>For my own part, I believe that any well-behaved white
man can to-day traverse Africa in every direction without 
dangers as long as his journey confines itself to areas of
Bantu and true negroes. Livingstone practically had no
trouble with native tribes; Schweinfurth, entering from
the Nile, penetrated to the heart of Africa with little
trouble; Du Chaillu traveled throughout the Ogowe
valley without difficulty with natives; Junker, following 
Schweinfurth's trail, penetrated farther into
what is now the Congo Free State, passing through
the territory of many warlike and cannibal tribes, but 
never armed his men and never had a difficulty with any 
native chief. It is true, however, that the tribes of the 
Congo differ vastly from each other in disposition. Some 
are warlike, some are peaceful to cowardice; some are 
genial, friendly, open; others are surly, hostile, reserved,
treacherous. While I have always felt that Stanley looked
for trouble and that he left a trail of blood unnecessarily 
behind him, I recognize that the Bangala and many of 
their neighbors are less agreeable, less kindly, more disposed 
for trouble than many of the other tribes in the Free
State. It is precisely with these tribes that the chief difficulties 
of the state have been.</p>
    
<p>Another curious point is shown on Morel's map.
From what has been said by critics of the state we would 
be justified in expecting to find those districts where the 
white man's influence had penetrated most fully, and
    
<pb n="108"/>

where he himself existed in greatest number, the worst in
the matter of atrocity. But it is precisely in these districts
that Morel's map shows no marks of reported atrocities.
It is plain, then, that the officials of the Congo Free
State are not, as a body, men delighting in cruelty and 
outrage. Where there are numbers of them, instead of 
conditions being at their worst they are at their happiest. 
It is only where there are lonely men surrounded
by depressing influences and in the midst of hostile
and surly tribes that these dreadful things are found.
It is natural to expect that with fuller penetration of the 
white men into these districts conditions will change
hopefully.</p>
    
<p>But why should we pick out Congo Free State for 
our assault? Atrocities occur wherever the white man,
with his thirst for gold, comes into contact with "a lower
people." He is ever there to exploit; he believes that
they were created for exploitation. If we want to find
cruelty, atrocities, all kinds of frightful maltreatment, we 
may find them in almost every part of negro Africa. They 
exist in the French Congo, in German Africa, in Nigeria,
even in Uganda. If we insist on finding them, we may
find cruelty, dispossession, destruction of life and property,
in all these areas. The only ruthless act involving the
death of a black native that we really saw was in French 
territory. If there were any object in doing so, we could 
write a harrowing story of British iniquity in Africa, but 
it is unnecessary; every one who stops to think and who 
reads at all knows the fact.</p>
    
<p>Wherever British trade finds native custom standing
in its way, we shall find cruelty. Why was King Ja Ja
    
<pb n="109"/>

deported? I have heard an interesting incident connected
with his case. One who for many years has voyaged up
and down the western coast of Africa tells me that while
Ja Ja was still at his height of power the natives of his 
district, paddling near the shores in their canoes, were
always happy and joyous. Ja Ja stood in the way of the 
British traders gaining so much money as they wanted,
and so he was exiled and taken a prisoner to distant lands.
From the day of his departure the happiness of life was
gone from all the country. Few natives put out in their 
canoes, and those who did were silent; the song and 
laughter of former days were hushed. Until the day when
he was brought home, a corpse, for burial, somberness
and sadness settled down upon his people, before so gay 
and light hearted. What was it caused the trouble at 
Benin but British greed insisting on opening up a territory 
which its natives desired to keep closed? The 
Benin massacre that followed was dreadful, but it did not 
begin to compare in frightful bloodshed with the punitive
expedition which followed&#8212;a feat scarce worthy of
British arms. What was the cause of hut-tax wars? What
is the matter now in Natal? Do we know all that 
goes on in Nigeria? Wherein is excellence in the expropriation 
of lands and products in Uganda for the 
benefit of concession companies of the same kind exactly 
as those in Congo? Why is it worse to cut off the 
hands of dead men for purposes of tally than to cut
off the heads of dead chiefs for purposes of identification? 
But let it pass&#8212;we are not undertaking an assault
on Britain.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling"/>
    
<pb n="119"/>

<div2 type="titles">

<p>XV.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>February 3, 1907.</p>

<p>Ought we to interfere? In this whole discussion
I have looked at the question solely from the 
humanitarian standpoint. I assume that Secretary
Root's first presentation of the matter was carefully prepared. 
He insisted that we had no grounds for interference, 
insofar as the Berlin conference was concerned. It is 
only, then, from the point of view of interest in the natives,
the desire to save them from suffering and from atrocity, 
that we can join with England in calling a new conference 
of the world's powers to consider Congo matters.
Ought we to pursue such a course? We ought not, and 
that for several reasons.</p>
    
<p>First&#8212;We should not interfere in Congo matters from 
philanthropic reasons, unless we are ready to undertake
the policing of the whole of Africa. If the atrocities in
the Congo are sufficient to involve us in difficulty with 
Belgium or with Belgium's king, the atrocities and cruelty
practiced in the French Congo, throughout German
Africa, in the Portuguese possessions, and even in the 
English colonies, must also attract our notice. If we really
intervene to save the African black man from white 
oppression, we must do this job thoroughly and on a large 
scale.</p>
    
<p>Second&#8212;We should not interfere with the conditions
in Congo unless we desire strained relations with France
and Germany. No possible agitation will bring about a 
second meeting of all the powers that participated in the 
Berlin conference. Turkey alone, so far, has signified her
willingness to act with England. The only other nation
    
<pb n="120"/>

in which there seems to be the slightest trend toward participation 
is Italy. No Scandinavian country&#8212;Sweden,
Norway, Denmark&#8212;will join in the movement. The 
many Scandinavians who, in one capacity or another,
have labored in the Congo Free State are, on the whole,
well satisfied with the conditions. Though there is a 
vigorous and aggressive Swedish mission in the country,
it is significant that its members have never joined in the 
agitation. Nor is Holland, which has sent a large number
of individuals into the Congo State as employés of government 
and concession companies, likely to favor an
agitation. Austria, for various reasons, stands aloof.
France has a definite understanding whereby in case of
the dissolution of the Congo Free State she becomes heir 
to all the district. Germany, responsible for the foundation 
of the Congo Free State, has, on the whole, always
favored its existence, and would certainly oppose interference 
in its affairs. In case of the partition of the 
Congo, Germany would be willing enough to take her
share, but it is really more to her interest both at home
and abroad to maintain its independence. All these
European countries speak quite freely in regard to England's 
design. France and Germany would seriously oppose 
any demonstration by England and the United States.</p>
    
<p>Third&#8212;We ought not to interfere unless we are really
willing to play the undignified part of pulling England's
chestnuts from the fire. What would we, nationally,
gain by the partition of the Congo? Our repeated
declarations about not wishing new territory in distant
regions are, of course, looked upon as twaddle by other
nations. If we really mean them, we must avoid the very
    
<pb n="121"/>

appearance of evil. What will the natives gain by partition? 
They will have their oppressors, only they 
will be divided around among three instead of being 
exploited by one. Suppose the redistribution did take
place. Suppose France, Germany, and England divided
the Congo between them; suppose&#8212;as would be certain
&#8212;that oppression and atrocity continued in the divided
territory. Would we still continue our noble effort in
behalf of the suffering black millions?</p>
    
<p>Fourth&#8212;We should not interfere, unless we wish to
present a glaring example of national inconsistency. Distance 
lends enchantment to the view. We are solicitous
about the Bantu in their home under the rule of Leopold
II.; we have 12,000,000 or more of them within our own
United States. The Bantu in the Congo we love. We
suffer when he is whipped, shudder when he is put upon
a chain-gang, shriek when he is murdered. Yet, here he 
may be whipped, put on the chain-gang, murdered, and 
if any raise an outcry he is a sentimentalist. Our negro
problem is a serious and difficult one. We do not know 
how to treat it. But it is at our door. and we can study it
and strike out some mode of treatment. But the years 
pass, and we do nothing. So complicated is it and so 
united together and interdependent its issues and its elements, 
that any course of action is dangerous, because we 
frequently cannot foresee the outcome of well-meant
effort. With this example constantly before us, one 
would suppose that we would hesitate in meddling with
the equally complicated problem, regarding conditions
of which we know little or nothing, on the other side of 
the globe.</p>
    
<pb n="122"/>

<p>Fifth&#8212;We ought not to interfere, unless we come with
clean hands. We have an even closer parallel to Congo
conditions than our negro problem in the South. In the
Philippines we found a people to be elevated; an inscrutable
Providence&#8212;so we say&#8212;thrust the Philippine
Islands, with their millions, upon us. A few years ago
we heard much of benevolent assimilation. Benevolent 
assimilation is the most dreadful of all forms of cannibalism. 
Our Congo reformers emphasize the fact that
the Congo State was founded with many philanthropic
assertions and with high-sounding promises of improving 
and elevating the native population. The parallel
is close. We took the Philippines and Filipinos for their 
good. So we said. Of course, we took them just as
the European nations have taken Africa&#8212;for exploitation. 
Had there been no hope of mines, of timber, of
cheap land for speculation, of railroads to be built, and
other enterprises to be undertaken and financed, we
should never have had such a tender interest in the
advancement of the Filipinos. And how has our benevolent 
assimilation proceeded? Just exactly as it always
proceeds everywhere in tropic lands with "lover peoples."
Torture, punitive expeditions, betrayal of confidence
and friendship, depopulation&#8212;these have been the agencies 
through which we have attempted to elevate a race.</p>
    
<p>You will tell me that what I am about to quote is 
ancient history and has lost its force. It is no more 
ancient than the bulk of the atrocities and cruelties
within the Congo. We quote a newspaper of April 12,
1902:</p>

<p>"From the Philippines authentic news is now at hand
    
<pb n="123"/>

tending to confirm the charges of barbarity on the part of 
American army officers, which have hitherto been strenuously 
and sweepingly denied. This news comes in Associated 
Press dispatches reporting the court-marital trial of
Major Waller, now in progress at Manila. This officer led 
an expedition last winter into the interior of the island of 
Samar. After being given up for dead, he and his party
returned to camp January 28th, delirious from privation.
Major Waller was next heard of in this connection in a dispatch 
of March 6th from Manila. He had been subjected
to court-marital proceedings, on charges of having, while
on this ill-fated expedition, executed natives of the island
of Samar without trial. One of the specifications alleged
that in one instance the accused had caused a native to
be tied to a tree, and on one day to be shot in the thigh, on 
the next in the arm, on the third in the body, and on the 
fourth to be killed. Friends of Major Waller attributed
his horrible action to delirium caused by privation; but
Major Waller himself refused to make this defense, insisting 
that he had acted under superior authority."</p>
    
<p>This sounds like an indictment of the Belgians in
the Congo put forth by the Congo Reform Association.
It is revolting; it is horrible; it probably is true.
Personally, I believe that Major Waller must have suffered
from the physical, the mental, the moral disintegration
which the tropics so constantly produce in white men.
It is unlikely that he was by nature a man of exceptional
cruelty. He became what he was&#8212;either permanently or 
for a time&#8212;through the environment in which he lived.
He had excuse; so have the Belgians. There is another
respect in which this quotation sounds Congo-like. Major
    
<pb n="124"/>

Waller insisted that he had "acted under superior
authority."</p>
    
<p>This phrase, he "acted under superior authority,"
is constantly harped upon by Morel and others of the
Congo agitators. Much is made of it, and we are constantly 
asked to trace home the order which issues from 
superior authority From whom came Major Waller's
orders? In his trial, February 8th, 1902, he disclosed
the startling nature of General Smith's orders, as he had
understood them. He swore that General Smith had
said: "I wish you to kill and burn. The more you 
kill, the more you will please me. The interior of Samar
must be made a howling wilderness. Kill every native
over ten years old."</p>
    
<p>When serious complaints of maladministration are
brought before the Belgian authorities of the Congo, investigation 
and trial are usually ordered. The Congo agitators 
lay great stress upon the fact that in the Congo these
trials are farces; that the accused is rarely sentenced to punishment; 
that sometimes after his acquittal he is lionized,
made a hero of, advanced in office. This is an unpardonable 
crime when committed by the Belgians. Lothaire&#8212;
and really Lothaire was as bad as any&#8212;was thus treated.
One would imagine from the chorus of complaint along this 
line that every English or American officer accused of 
cruelty, misgovernment or maladministration was promptly
and severely punished.</p>
    
<p>Major Waller received the verdict that he had acted "in
accordance with the rules of war, the orders of his superior,
and the military exigencies of the situation." This, again,
can hardly be improved upon in all the cases put forward
    
<pb n="125"/>

joyously by the reformers. When complaint is made it is 
never treated honestly. There is always whitewashing.
Why howl over Belgian failure to punish? Waller's verdict 
shows that we do precisely the same thing in the same
circumstances. But look at what was done with General
Smith, the man who ordered that down to ten years of age 
the natives should be killed. He, too, was ordered to 
undergo court-martial. From a newspaper of May 3d,
1902, we quote: "At the opening, Colonel Woodruff
announced his willingness to simplify the proceedings by
admitting that most of the accusations were true. He said 
he was willing, in behalf of General Smith, to admit that
inasmuch as the country was hostile, General Smith
did not want any prisoners, and that he had issued 
orders to Major Waller to kill all persons capable of bearing 
arms, fixing the age limit at ten years, because many
boys of that age had borne arms against the American
troops, and that he had ordered Major Waller also to burn
the homes of the people and to make Samar a howling
wilderness."</p>
    
<p>What was done with General Smith? His court-marital
began on April 25. Its result was, of course, a whitewash;
it always is, whether the person tried is American, French,
German, or Belgian. It is curious, however, to observe
how others were affected by this case. There was one
man who knew better than any other all the facts relating
to the Philippines. His utterance, which we shall quote, 
was expressed, indeed, before this trial, but it was expressed
with full knowledge of similar facts. That man, on
March 5th, made the assertion: "It is not the fact that 
the warfare in the Philippines has been conducted with
    
<pb n="126"/>

marked severity; on the contrary, the warfare has been
conducted with marked humanity and magnanimity on
the part of the United States army." What a pity that we 
are less ready to talk of marked humanity and magnanimity 
of others! Can Waller's crime be surpassed by
anything from Congo; can any order be more cruel than 
General Smith's?</p>
    
<p>I have said that this would be called ancient history. At
Leopoldville I asked about atrocities; the response was that 
at present there was nothing serious to complain of in that 
region beyond the kwanga tax; when I reached Ikoko,
where undoubtedly many cruel things have taken place,
they told me that at present such things did not occur there,
that to find them I must go to the A. B. I. R.; that the fish 
tax was too heavy, but that of cruelties, atrocities and mutilations 
there had been none for years. At Bolobo I heard
precisely the same story&#8212;the most frightful things had
taken place at Lake Leopold II.&#8212;that recently nothing
serious had happened at Bolobo itself. I presume that
there are outrages and cruelties of recent date in the A. B. 
I. R. and the Antwerp Concession. But here, again, the 
parallel between the Congo and the Philippines is close.
While the Waller and Smith incident is ancient, there is
plenty doing at the present time. We quote a paper
August 18, 1906: "The Pulajanes&#8212;wild tribesmen of the
Philippine island of Leyte&#8212;continue their fighting. Five
Americans, including a lieutenant and a surgeon, were killed 
in a hand-to-hand encounter in the town of Burauen on the
9th. It was reported on the 14th that Governor-General
Ide has determined to exterminate the Pulajanes, even if it
should take every American soldier on the islands to do it."</p>
    
<pb n="127"/>

<p>This sounds like depopulation. And why is depopulation 
worse in Africa than in the Philippines? Why should
a President who views the latter with complacency&#8212;and
I may say with commendation&#8212;feel so keenly with reference 
to the former? A special message of commendation
was promptly sent to an American leader for his killing of
hundreds of men, women, and children; depopulation on a 
large scale and of the same kind as he reprobates when done
by Leopold's soldiers. Our friends of the Congo Reform
Association are strangely silent in regard to such letters of 
commendation; they are much grieved because Lothaire
was lionized, but they hurrah over the accumulating honors 
of a Funston.</p>
    
<p>When our hands are clean and when we have given the
Filipinos their well-deserved independence and free government, 
and left them to work out their own salvation, then
and not till then, should we intervene in the Congo Free
State for reasons of humanity. I say when we have left
the Filipinos to work out their own salvation; we have 
strange ideas regarding the kindnesses we do to other
peoples. Thus Cuba is supposed to be under an eternal
debt of obligation to us for the government which we set up
in that unhappy land. We devised a model government,
according to our own ideas; to be sure, it is a government so 
expensive to keep up that few, if any, portions of the 
United States with the population of Cuba could possibly 
support it. We put in sanitary improvements, nominally 
for the benefit of Cubans, but actually with a shrewd
afterthought for ourselves, which we demanded should be 
maintained at any price. Of course, it is impossible for a 
country with the population and resources of Cuba to maintain
    
<pb n="128"/>

them. This will give us repeated opportunities for 
interference in the affairs of the island, interference which
ultimately may weary the people into assent to uniting with
us. They will lose both independence and happiness, and 
we will gain an added problem; and the only persons
profited will be those who are, and will be, exploiting the
island for their selfish ends.</p>
 
<p>So, in the Philippines, we will develop a government
which, theoretically, may seem perfect. The difficulty is 
that it must be much less suitable for Filipinos than a less
perfect government, planned and carried out along lines of 
their own ideas. Lately a Filipino in this country has said
something which has the ring of truth. "We have money
enough to maintain a better and less expensive government
than that costly one which is trying to make the people
what the government wants them to be, and not to make
itself what the people want and expect, dictating laws one
day which next day are canceled and changed in a thousand
places and in a thousand ways, so that justice is converted 
into a mere babel. Believe me, dear sir, that even
our ephemeral government at Malolos showed no such incapacity. 
This is due to the fact that he who governs the
house goes not belong to the house, and everybody knows 
the old Spanish proverb, 'The fool is wiser in his own
house than the wise man in his neighbor's.'"</p>
    
<p>If it is necessary for us as a nation to look for African
adventure; if to give a strenuous President the feeling that
he is "doing something" we must meddle in the affairs of 
the Dark Continent, there is a district where we might intervene 
with more of reason, and consistency, and grace than
we are doing by going to the Congo. We once established
   
<pb n="129"/>

on African soil, whether wisely or not I do not intend to 
discuss, a free republic for the blacks. In Liberia we have 
an American enterprise, pure and simple. It has not been
a great success. It is just possible&#8212;though I doubt it&#8212;
that Liberia would at several times have profited and been 
advantaged by our instruction and interest. But it seems 
to possess little interest for us. Just now, like the Congo,
it is attracting British attention. Whether it has large or 
little value, whether it possesses great opportunities or not,
it is now a center of interest to Great Britain. She does not
need our help in pulling chestnuts from the fire there, and
there has been strange silence and ignorance in this country 
regarding it as a new sphere for English influence. If
we assist England in expanding her African possessions at 
the expense of the Congo Free State, Liberia will be the
next fraction of Africa to succumb to English rule. England's 
methods of procedure are various. It might be a 
useful lesson for our statesmen and politicians to study
Liberia's prospects with care. We are still young in the 
business of grabbing other people's lands. England could
teach us many lessons. The latest one may well be worthy
our attention since in a certain sense it deals with a district 
where we naturally possess an interest.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>