<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0108">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>American Missionary, Althea Brown Edmiston, "Missions in Congo Free State, Africa" (1908)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0108</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Missions in Congo Free State, Africa</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/34126331">Edmiston, Althea Brown, 1874-1937</author>
<title level="j">American Missionary</title>
<date when="1908-12">December 1908</date>
<biblScope unit="page">306–10</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>"Othering" Africans</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/73234071">Cravath, Erastus Milo, 1833-1900</term>
<term>Fearing, Maria</term>
<term>Sheppard, Lucy G.</term>
<term>Thomas De Yampert, Lillian</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Ibanj (Congo)</term>
<term>Kassai River</term>
<term>Luebo (Congo)</term>
<term>Luebo River</term>
<term>Lulua River</term>
<term>Matadi (Congo)</term>
<term>Stanley Pool</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Ba-Congo</term>
<term>Baluba</term>
<term>Bakete</term>
<term>Bakuba</term>
<term>Bangala</term>
<term>Bashelele</term>
<term>Bena Lulua</term>
<term>Bimtadi</term>
<term>Zappo Zap</term>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Southern Presbyterian</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-09" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p306"/>

<head type="main">Missions in Congo Free State, Africa</head>

<head type="sub">By Mrs. Althea Brown Edmiston</head>

<p>I count it one of the greatest honors
and opportunities of my life to be
present at the Annual Meeting of the
American Missionary Association. I am
glad to be able to thank you in person for
what you, through Fisk University, have
done for me, also to tell you what God,
through the instrumentality of some of
your own disciples, is doing in Central
Africa, and that I may carry from here a
deep spiritual inspiration that shall be
most helpful to those among whom we
labor in darkest Africa.</p>

<p>Since I am one of the rough stones
which you have polished, you will be interested 
to know what induced me to go
to Fisk University and to be a foreign
missionary.</p>

<p>My parents, having no learning themselves, 
desired that their children should
be educated. Having heard of Fisk University 
through one of its graduates, and
having secured the promise of a scholarship 
of fifty dollars, the lot fell on me,
the fifth of their ten children. In 1892,
with a little tin trunk containing my

<pb n="p307"/>

meager wardrobe, I left a very humble
home on a cotton plantation in Mississippi 
for Fisk University. When I
reached Fisk University in Nashville,
Tennessee, it was to me a new world! a
wonderland! a Paradise! And could <hi rend="italics">I</hi>, a
poor, half frightened country girl, with
common calico dress and hair done up
in little knotty braids, enter! Yes, they
really let me in!</p>

<p>I was able to make the seventh grade
in the English School. After three
months, through the influence of some of
the teachers, I became a Christian, and
with this new birth came the distinct call
to Africa as a missionary. I made this
fact known to my friends and decided to
take the collegiate course. This seemed
a mighty undertaking; the goal nine
years off and no money! I was, no
doubt, regarded by teachers and students
as was Columbus when he started out to
discover America. But the Lord had
laid His hands on me and kindled in my
heart a burning desire to help those sitting 
in the dense darkness of heathendom.
At the first opportunity I signed the
declaration card of the Student Volunteer
Movement and with a strong determination 
I started out to win the fight in spite
of poverty.</p>

<p>My parents were able to help me but
little. After four years they could do no
more. I worked as a servant in families,
until I was able to teach. After that
with the fifty-dollar scholarship given
me I had no trouble in helping myself. 
My clothing came from the missionary 
barrels you so kindly send
South.</p>

<p>During those nine years of hard work
and struggle I was not unmindful of the
kind helpful words and deeds, not alone
of my beloved teachers, but also of dear
Dr. Beard. The American Missionary
Association offered to help me through
school, but wise Dr. Cravath thought it
would make a much better woman of me
—a stronger woman in every way—if I
were left to bear my own burden.</p>

<p>Nineteen hundred and one brought me
to the end of my nine years and I graduated, 
receiving the degree B.A. But the
goal had not yet been reached. My
destination was Africa. Through all
those years I could not put aside the call
of the Lord! I could see my less fortunate 
sisters, whose souls I had learned
to love and longed to win for Christ,
groping. in darkness, waiting for the
light.</p>

<p>I wanted to go out under the Board
of my own church, the Congregational,
but found it necessary to turn to another
Board, whose requirement was that I
join their denomination. It was indeed
hard to leave the church in which I became 
a new creature, "but a little talk
with Jesus made it right, all right."</p>

<p>Having a year to wait, I went to Chicago 
and, taking two years in one, graduated 
May, 1902, from the Bible Course
of the Chicago Training School for City,
Home and Foreign Missions.</p>

<p>You will see the broadness of my religion 
when I tell you that I was born a
Baptist, united with a Congregational
church, was educated in a Congregational
institution, took a Bible course in a Methodist 
training school and went to Africa
under the Southern Presbyterian Board.</p>

<p>Just here I wish to commend the
Southern Presbyterian Board for its kind
consideration for and courtesy toward us
as colored missionaries. We are most
cordially received at the mission rooms
and invited to speak before the churches
and missionary societies when on furlough. 
On the field our missionaries are
made up of half southern white men and
women and half colored. We work together 
in perfect harmony.</p>

<p>In August, 1902, I left the homeland
for the fatherland. When we loosed from

<pb n="p308"/>

the shore and the band began to play
"America," I realized for the first time
that I was leaving all that was nearest
and dearest to me, but there was joy in
the thought that I was going in obedience
to the Saviour's last command, bearing
to a benighted multitude His message of
love, salvation and redemption.</p>

<p>Our mission being in the very heart of
Africa, far away from all civilization and
all means of supplies, we must take with
us every needful thing, such as household
articles, food, clothing, barter goods, etc.
These we buy in, London, England, repeating 
the order annually.</p>

<p>Leaving England, three weeks' sailing
brings us to Matadi on the Congo River,
sixty miles from its mouth. Here the
river is rendered unnavigable by sixty-two 
cataracts, around which we travel
two hundred and sixty miles on a little
narrow gauge railroad train, which running 
only by day brings us in two days to
Stanley Pool, where the Congo River is
again navigable. Here our own mission
steamer meets us, and, traveling by day
only, on the Congo, Kassai, Lulua and
Luebo rivers, brings us in twenty-six
days to our great mission station, Luebo.</p>

<p>Our second station, Ibanj, is forty
miles farther in the interior, to which we
go in strong canvas hammocks suspended
on a bamboo pole borne by native men.
This station proved to be my goal. Having 
picked up a few sentences of the language 
on the way, I began work the next
day after my arrival, and have had five
and a half years in the blessed work of
my heart's greatest desire. For nearly
three years I was the only foreign woman
at Ibanj Station. My special work has
been that of making a dictionary and
grammar in the unwritten language of
the Bakuba tribe, teaching in the day-schools 
and Sunday-schools, helping to
organize the native women into Christian
bands, being matron of a girls' home,
making charts and text books for the
school and working among the women
and children in general.</p>

<p>Our mission, 1,200 miles from the
coast, and five degrees south of the
Equator, is situated in the Western Central 
part of the Congo Free State, in
which we find many distinct tribes speaking 
totally different languages, and varying 
in superiority of intelligence, dress,
industry and habits of living. Their villages 
are usually very large and neatly
laid off in rectangles and are from one to
ten miles apart, with from five hundred
to ten thousand inhabitants. Their tribal
distinction is tattooing, which often adds
to or subtracts from their personal appearance. 
They vary in color from a jet
black to a very light brown. Some tribes
go perfectly nude, others wear a small
piece of cloth, still others wear a neat
tunic extending from the waist to just
below the knees. Children from birth to
about eight years of age do not wear anything.</p>

<p>They have many very interesting industries. 
They raise an abundance of
Indian corn, peas, pumpkins, sweet potatoes, 
sugar cane, peanuts, bananas,
plantains, pineapples, and cassava. There
are among them excellent blacksmiths,
who make from native ore spears, arrows, 
axes, razors, hoes, knives, adzes,
needles and pins. They also make many
kinds of beautiful baskets, mats, water
jars, and pots. They weave in little hand
looms their cloth, which consists of
threads made from the pineapple and
palm leaves. Much time is spent by the
men in hunting, fishing and gathering
rubber. They have weekly markets and
a regular commodity of exchange. They
cook only one meal a day, which is supper. 
Their principal food is "greens"
and boiled bread. However, they often
have chickens, goats, fish, antelopes, elephants, 
pork, buffalo, monkey, boa-constrictors,

<pb n="p309"/>

rats, and such dainties as
shrimps, grasshoppers, caterpillars, locusts, 
grubworms and big white ants.</p>

<p>They have organized governments,
with kingdoms, chiefdoms, towns and
villages, having judicial courts, with
lawyers and judges. They punish crime
by imprisonment, fines and death.</p>

<p>Their marriages are considered sacred
and binding. Families of three and four
generations may be seen dwelling together. 
Among many of them is found
great family affection. Their standard
of morality is remarkably high.</p>

<p>Their language is beautiful, highly inflected, 
rhythmical, musical and full of
stories, fairy tales and songs. They have
many games, and musical instruments
and some of their dances would compete
in grace with our Delsarte.</p>

<p>The people are not altogether homely.
We find among them handsome men with
fine, tall, stalwart physiques. Some of
the women are really pretty with even
features, delicate forms, and quiet, lady-like 
appearance. Some of them are very
bright, intelligent, diplomatic, witty and
deep thinkers.</p>

<p>They believe in a great Spirit known
as Midi Mukula or Nzambi, whom they
regard with terrible dread. They know
Him not as the true God who "so loved
the world that He gave His only begotten
Son that whosoever believeth in Him
shall not perish but have everlasting life."</p>

<p>How great has been our joy to declare 
unto them the unknown God and
the loving Saviour whom so many of
them now worship as Father, Son and
Holy Ghost, and sing with us the songs
of Zion: "Come thou fount of every
blessing," "Jesus loves me this I know,"
"Pass me not, O gentle Saviour," and
scores of others. The light of Jesus
Christ does truly dispel the darkness.
The fetters with which they have been
bound by Satan so many centuries are
now being broken, and we see many evidences 
of the Spirit's working in the
hearts of the people and souls are being
born daily in the Kingdom of God.</p>

<p>Though our mission is very young, we
have an enrollment of nearly seven thousand 
Christians. There are more than
four thousand pupils in our Sunday-schools, 
more than two thousand in our
day-schools. We have nearly two hundred 
native ministers, teachers and helpers, 
all trained in our mission schools.
There are two main and forty-eight out-stations, 
where preaching services are held
daily and where more than eight thousand 
souls hear the Gospel message on
the Sabbath. Every day is Sunday with
us in Africa! We go to church three
hundred and sixty-five days in the year.
There were added to the church last year
seven hundred and ninety-eight souls on
confession of their faith in Christ, an
average of two a day.</p>

<p>Our greatest hope is in the young people. 
We have two flourishing "Homes"
for girls, out of which come each year
well-trained young women who are making 
excellent wives for our native ministers. 
We have an Industrial School for our
boys, out of which are coming some of
our best Christian workers.</p>

<p>Among our converts are representatives 
from many tribes. I bring you
greetings to-day from our Christian
Baluba, Bakuba, Bakite, Bashelele, Bimtadi, 
Bena Lulua, Bangella, Ba-Congo
and Zappo Zaps.</p>

<p>I need not tell you that no condition in
Africa is more <hi rend="italics">pitiable</hi>, more <hi rend="italics">pathetic</hi> than
that of the women, who are the beasts of
burden, slaves for service and victims for
vice! But, praise the Lord, I am glad to
tell. you that Christianity is doing for
these what it has done for women wherever 
it has gone. They are among the
majority of our converts. We have four
Christian organizations for them in which

<pb n="p310"/>

they are being lifted up. They are beginning 
to see that there is something
sweeter, higher and more beautiful in life
than a mere existence. They are being
more tenderly regarded and loved by
their husbands, and they show more
thought, love and care for husband, children 
and home. Instead of an offensive
body, greased, matted hair and a small
loin cloth, many are now seen with
combed hair and clean bodies, neatly
draped from shoulders to ankles. Among
them are some of our best teachers and
helpers.</p>

<p>How I wish I could tell you more of
the wonderful way in which God is blessing 
that work, how the hearts of the people 
are open to the Gospel, how eager
they are and anxious for education.</p>

<p>I wish that I could tell you of the
capsizing of our mission steamer five
years ago, when one of our missionaries
and twenty-three of our native Christians 
were drowned and all of our annual
supplies went down. I wish also that I
could tell you of the terrible revolt four
years ago by the great Bakuba tribe,
against all foreigners, both friend and
foe, because of oppression. At that time
our mission station at Ibanj was burned
and entirely destroyed. We were made
destitute of every earthly possession and
barely escaped with our lives! How I
wish I could tell you of our return to and
the rebuilding of Ibanj Station, of the
great spiritual results, of how we are
now getting hold of that very tribe.
Many of their boys and girls, as never
before, are now under our daily care and
instruction. Surely we have seen many
demonstrations of God's causing "the
wrath of man to praise Him." That
station is now larger and more beautiful
than ever before, God has also given us
another lovely steamboat, much larger
and far more comfortable than the first.
Thus we are thoroughly persuaded that</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Ill that He blesses is our good,</l>
<l rend="indent">And unblessed good is ill,</l>
<l>And all is right that seems most wrong</l>
<l rend="indent">If it be His sweet will."</l></lg>

<p>However, in spite of these bright features 
I bring before you it is only a mere
beginning of a great work yet to be done.
There are thousands in our own vicinity
that have not yet been touched. We can
not reach them because of our limited
strength and numbers. They are still in
the midnight darkness of ignorance,
superstition, vice, degradation and sin,
waiting, hungering, thirsting, pleading
and begging for the bread of life. Their
greatest curse is domestic slavery, which
is the root of ninety per cent. of all the
evil among them.</p>

<p>In conclusion, I wish again to thank
you, most honored friends of the North,
for what You have done for me. I owe
all I am and all I hope to be to you,
through Fisk University. You have prepared 
me for serving God and my fellowman. 
Not for me only have you done
this, but for thousands of others of my
race. We have nine other colored missionaries 
on our field, among whom are
Mrs. Lucy G. Sheppard, Miss Maria Fearing 
and Mrs. Lillian Thomas De Yampert,
educated by you at Talladega College,
and who are doing a most efficient work.</p>

<p>I wish also to thank you for the consecrated,
self-sacrificing men and women
whom you have sent to teach us. Their
lives and example are even of greater
help and inspiration to us than their instruction 
from text books. When I think
of those grand, noble men, our beloved
Professors Rennett, Spence, Chase and
President Cravath, <hi rend="italics">immortal men</hi> who
lived and died in our service and whose
last expiring breath went up before the
throne of God pleading for Fisk University 
and the Negro race, I am filled
with a greater desire to do my very best
in life's service.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
