<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0003">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A. M. E. Church Review, J. G. Robinson, "Africa, and the Educated and Wealthy Negroes of America" (1893)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Perry, Jade" xml:id="jp">Jade Perry</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0003</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">Africa, and the Educated and Wealthy Negroes of America</title>
<author>Robinson, J. G.</author>
<title level="j">African Methodist Episcopal Church Review</title>
<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<date when="1893-07">July 1893</date>
<biblScope unit="page">158-163</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Missionaries</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Periodicals</term>
</keywords> 

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Africa</term>
<term>Chicago (Illinois)</term>
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Hudson River</term>
<term>Mississippi River</term>
<term>New Orleans (Louisiana)</term>
<term>New York (New York)</term>
<term>Niger River</term>
<term>Nile River</term>
<term>Philadelphia (Pennsylvania)</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#kln">metadata edits</change>
<change when="2019-03-01" who="#kln">encoded</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">corrections, marked up</change>
<change when="2016" who="jp">transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<pb n="p158"/>

<div2 type="title">

<p>Africa, and the Educated and Wealthy Negroes of America.</p>
    
</div2>
   
<div2 type="article">

<p>Africa, doubtless, is the greatest land upon the face
of the globe. You cannot pick up a newspaper of any
note, political or religious, without seeing plans put
forth by some one concerning the development of
Africa. Just now, more eyes are being turned to the
continent of Africa than any other part of the known
world. Millions of acres of uncultivated soil, the richest 
upon the face of the globe, are claiming the attention
of the agricultural classes of England, France, America
and many other civilized portions of the world.</p>

<p>The great Nile, Niger, and other navigable streams
flowing through the continent of Africa, mightier than
the Hudson or the Mississippi, are looked at with great
care by the masters of commerce, with the anticipation
of making them add to the glory of the commercial
world, and at the same time hoping to make them subject 
to the commercial centres of their governments.
The gold, silver, iron, copper, and other treasures that
are deposited among the mountains of Africa, awaiting
the "pick and shovel" of the miners, are being talked
about by the money kings of Europe and America—
not only talked about, but they are laying claims to
vast regions of Africa, with no other purpose than to
get the rare wealth which it affords, then leave the
natives in heathenism and darkness.</p>

<p>Through the Providence of an All-wise Creator, this
continent has for centuries been protected from the
wholesale slaughter of other races.</p>

<pb n="p159"/>

<p>Millions of uncivilized beings, without the knowledge 
of race development, inhabit this greatest of great
countries. Africa must be civilized. Who will do the
work, and who can best do the work? are the questions
that are before the thinking peoples of to-day.</p>

<p>The Negroes of the Southern States have been surrounded 
by conditions darker than any other race of
mankind upon the face of the earth. The institution
of slavery is ancient, but when I think of the causes
that led to the building of this government—how the
colonists had to fight to break the yoke of Great Britain
from their necks—it looks as though it would have
been impossible to ever get them to oppress or allow a
class weaker than themselves to be oppressed within
the bounds of this great "Home of the brave and land
of the free(?)" It was not the intention of the makers
of the Constitution of the United States that slavery
should be carried to such a great extent, and thereby
blast the name of America forever.</p>

<p>The hellish institution of African slavery in the
Southern States of America was unparalleled in its
mode of evil treatment by the master to the slave. In
many parts of the world a slave has been allowed an
education—at a certain age was given his freedom. But
not so in the time when your and my father and
mother were subject to the Southern human beast of
our America. Laws were placed upon the statute
books, making it a penalty for a master to teach or allow 
his Negroes to be taught to read and write. They
were held as slaves from birth to death, regardless of
what their age might be. Mothers and fathers were
sold from their children, infants were taken from the
cradle (?) and sold from the embrace of their mothers,
to be brought up in a cold world and have their hopes
blasted forever.</p>

<p>Something more than a quarter of a century ago,

<pb n="p160"/>

after many debates upon the floors of the Senate and
Hall of Representatives of the United States, by great
statesmen, a mighty conflict for the preservation of the
Union took place. This being the supreme moment of
action by the lovers of liberty, they took advantage
and the Negro was given his freedom. Amendments
to the Constitution of the United States and conventions 
by the Southern States made the once Negro slave,
an American citizen. Many have been the changes which
have taken place in this period. Ex-slaves have been
members of the Senate and Congress of the Nation, judges,
legislators, district attorneys, clerks of courts, sheriffs,
mayors, and in short many offices of a political and
diplomatic nature have been filled by them with credit
to themselves and honor to the country which made
them citizens.</p>

<p>The Negroes of this country have proved themselves
equal to every science handled by his once white
master. Hebrew, Greek, Latin, German, French and
many other languages are spoken by them. Mathematics, 
astronomy, geology and all the other sciences
are mastered by the brain of the "brother in black."</p>

<p>The American Negro worships the same God of his
former master, preaching the gospel of the blessed
Christ in a purer way than any other class of people
(as a whole) upon the American soil, advocating "God
our father, Christ our redeemer and man our brother."
Turned loose without anything to protect them, they
saw the wealth of the white man, and "caught on,"
and to-day the Negro pays taxes upon millions of dollars 
worth of valuable property in the same sections
where they were held as slaves. With all of the before-mentioned, 
and many other developments, it is strange,
yet true, that the Negro will never rise to the greatness
to which he aspires, the height of manhood which
belongs to him, so long as he remains in this "white

<pb n="p161"/>

man's country." Class legislation, mob violence, race
discrimination, disfranchisement of citizenship, social
caste, and other white American aristocratic absurdities
will always keep the Negro in the background of
American greatness. Therefore, if the educated and
wealthy Negroes of this country would turn their attention 
to the development of the resources of Africa
go there, cut down the forest, build up commercial
and manufacturing interests with the great civilized
centres of the world, organize territories, build states,
shape a government, civilize the tribes, set up an army
and navy—then the world will know that the Negro
is a man, and can attain the same greatness as other
nationalities. If the American Negroes of education
and wealth would go at this work with energy and
push, what will be the result? The sun-burnt sons of
Africa will be seen sitting presidents over the greatest
and richest country in the world; governors of states
greater than New York or Pennsylvania; poets, historians, 
orators, dramatists, and authors of various
kinds, reading the once greatness of Egypt inscribed
upon the "everlasting stone," will spring up more illustrious 
than Whittier, Milton, Bryant, Josephus,
Demosthenes, Shakespeare, Homer, or any others who
have made their names illustrious in the field of letters. 
The "black hand" that is being trained in the
machine shops of the industrial departments of the
colleges of America, and then turned loose to find
"iron-clad" organization of the "white brother"
against him, thereby forcing him to abandon his trade
as a machinist and seek other occupations for a livelihood, 
will take hold of the throttle, and pull the
"giant horse" across the continent of our fathers, to
the astonishment of the world. The medical student,
who graduates in this country, and goes out to find
himself hemmed off by the Southern medical examiner,

<pb n="p162"/>

and in many instances pronounced "root doctor" by
his own race; an oath in the Southern drug stores not
to fill a prescription for a "nigger" doctor; these and
other obstructions cause him to lay aside his profession, 
and go to "preaching." (?) Hence the great number
of Negro preachers in this country. Why should not the
medical student be included in building up this new
civilization? There are plants and minerals in Africa,
abounding with medical properties. The Negro doctor
can have laboratories in Africa greater than any in
this country. Instead of being flunkies, porters, carriage 
drivers, barbers, and other classes of servants, the
educated will have a vast field in which to develop
their skill.</p>

<p>After some years of toil, the Negro will see the
necessity of inventions, and inventors will rise up, and
the Edison and others of to-day will find their equals,
or superiors.</p>

<p>If the American Negro would go to work—earnest
work—at the development of the continent of Africa,
in the twentieth century, a civilization will "loom up"
on the banks of the Nile and Niger, greater than the
civilization on the Hudson and Mississippi. Cities
greater than New York, Chicago, Philadelphia or New
Orleans. Telegraph companies mightier that the
"Western Union." Railroads longer than any to be
found in America. Colleges greater than Oxford,
Howard or Lincoln. Lumber companies larger than
any Michigan company. Clothiers greater than Wanamaker. 
Statesmen greater than Sumner, Garrison,
Sherman, Blaine or Gladstone. Ministers surpassing 
Whitfield, Wesley, Spurgeon, Lindon, Beecher
or Brooks. Orators will rise up to picture the
greatness of the country, with tongues of fire, who
will be listened to by large concourses of intelligent
citizens, who will clap their hands and bless the Amer-

<pb n="p163"/>

ican Negro pioneer. Many will say it will call for too
many hardships. I answer, you cannot go through
more hardships than you have gone through. Also, it
can be said, of a truth, that nothing great can be 
obtained without hardship and toil. Therefore, if we
want to live in a land where we can protect our
mothers, wives, sisters and daughters from the fiendish
snares that await them in this land, we must begin to
develop our "fatherland." If we want to wear the
full badge of citizenship, we must "go over and possess 
the land " that God has reserved for us for ages.
Then, and not until then, will the Negro be known as
a man "walking without crutches."</p>

<p>J. G. Robinson.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
