<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.letter.0012">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Despatch from John G. Willis to Lewis Cass, January 26, 1859</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Schirf, Kayla" xml:id="ks">Kayla Schirf</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2018</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.letter.0012</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Despatch from John G. Willis to Lewis Cass</title>
<date when="1859-01-26">January 26, 1859</date>
<title level="m" type="microformat">Despatches from United States consuls in St. Paul de Loanda, 1854-1893</title>
<publisher>United States Department of State</publisher>
<biblScope unit="roll">1</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Commerce and Trade</term>
<term>Slave Trade and Slavery</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>       
    
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Gabriel, Edmund</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/11863869">Huntley, H. V. (Henry Vere), Sir, 1795-1864</term>
<term ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/74921314">O'Sullivan, John L. (John Louis), 1813-1895</term>
<term>Totten, Benjamin J.</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Ambriz (Angola)</term>
<term>Congo River</term>
<term>Kinsembo (Congo)</term>
<term>Lisbon (Portugal)</term>
<term>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="empires">
<term>Great Britain</term>
<term>Netherlands</term>
<term>Portugal</term>
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName>Willis, John G.</persName>
<placeName>St. Paul de Loanda (Angola)</placeName>
<roleName>U.S. Commercial Agent for Loanda</roleName>
<date when="1859-01-26"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/74646968">Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866</persName>
<roleName>U.S. Secretary of State</roleName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-04-16" who="kln">Reviewed and edited encoding.</change>
<change when="2018" who="lkw">Creation of individual xml files, review, and addition encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="ks">Transcription and initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0012.001"/>

<div1 type="document" xml:lang="en">

<note>No 2.</note>

<p>United States Commercial Agency<lb/>
St Paul 'd Loanda January 26, 1859</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I last had this honor, under date of
October 11th '58, informing you that I had arrived
at this Port &amp; had entered upon the duties of this 
office. I also informed you that the American Yacht
Wanderer was then in the Congo River, during the
latter part of the month She left the River &amp; it is
said, with a Cargo of Slaves.</p>

<p>Since the capture &amp; burning of the Brig "Rufus 
Soulé" off the Congo by H.R.M. Steamer "Viper",
in October last, a statement of which was given
to Capt. Totten of the U.S.S. "Vincennes" I have
heard of four or five Shipments being made, the last
one a few days since in which one thousand Slaves
were placed on board one vessel. The Trade has now
gone in part, from the Congo River to the North of
that river. Owing to the French Apprentice System,
Slaves are rather scarce &amp; the price has advanced.
It is said there are a number of vessels off the
Coast waiting for their Consignees to arrange a
Congo.</p>

<p>On the 8th December Sir Henry 
Huntley, HBM Consul for this Port arrived
now. He came out as a Consul &amp; Clerk to the

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0012.002"/>

English Slave Commission presuming that Mr 
Gabriel, HBM Arbitrator would return to England,
&amp; then he would be acting Arbitrator &amp; Consul; but as
Mr Gabriel does not intend leaving this at present, Sir
Henry is officiating as Consul without accepting the
post as Clerk to the Commission, &amp; waiting for further
instructions from his Government.</p>

<p><sic>Accompaning</sic> this I enclose the Returns 
from this Commercial Agency for the Quarter ending 
December 31, 1858 &amp; have drawn on Your Honor for 
Two Hundred forty-four &amp; 07/100 dollars, being balance
of my Salary for that Quarter. I am not able to 
fill up the blanks with the exact value of the Inward
&amp; Outward Cargoes, for the reason that a vessel entering
or clearing at this Custom House is not obliged to place
on her Manifest the value thereof. For a year estimate
of the American Business done at this Port. I should
say that at the present time it will not exceed
One hundred thousand dollars. Two or three years
ago it would amount to one hundred &amp; fifty thousand
dollars, but since that time the Crop of Palm
Oil has failed &amp; the Natives were obliged to eat the
Palm Nut to keep from starvation. Palm Oil it 
is now thought will this year prove very fair. &amp; if so
it will enable the Portuguese Merchants here to pay
their Debts, which in may instances have been standing

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0012.003"/>

very long. their debts once settled will cause the two 
American Houses here to order larger Invoices &amp; then of 
course the Business will again increase.</p> 

<p>It is the wish of the Governor General of this Province
to take possession of the River Congo, but I understand the
English Government will not allow them to go North of
Ambriz. If Portugal should take that River, there will
be no more Slave Trade there, &amp; perhaps England may in
time change her views in this respect as it will save her
considerable expense in taking of the African Squadron.</p>

<p>The occupation of Ambriz by the Portuguese has not
yet resulted favorably. They have been at considerable expense
&amp; there is now only one foreign House there &amp; that
an American. The two English Houses that formerly done 
business at Ambriz, have now left on account of the
high duties (which are more than Mr O'Sullivan the
late U.S. Minister at Lisbon was given to understand
by the Portuguese Minister) &amp; have gone to a place
called "Kisembo", 7 miles north of Ambriz, together
with a Branch of the American House &amp; a Dutch
House, where they get a clear of all Custom House charges
&amp; at the same time do considerable Trade with the Natives.</p>

<p>The Copper Mines at Ambriz have not proved
so favorable as they were at first expected &amp; it is said
will result in a great loss to those concerned.</p>

<p>Some time since, I wrote the Department in

<pb n="teaa.en.letter.0012.004"/>

respect to a Burial Place in Loanda for deceased
Americans, &amp; under date of February 15th 1858 I am
informed by the Department that the United States
Minister at the Court of Lisbon will be informed of
my request. As yet nothing relating thereto has been
received at this Agency, &amp; I now take the liberty of 
again calling the attention of the Department to this
subject.</p>

<p>Very Respectfully<lb/>
Your Obt. Servt<lb/>
John G. Willis</p>

<p>Hon Lewis Cass<lb/>
Secretary of State USA.<lb/>
Washington D.C.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
