<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.analysis.0001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>General Act of the Conference of Berlin Concerning the Congo. Analysis</title>
<author n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</author>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.analysis.0001</idno>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Original.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>

<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Analysis</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="document" target="teaa.en.government.0001">Document</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2019-03-21" who="#kln">updated encoding</change>
<change when="2014-07-02" who="#kln">modified encoding and document structure</change>
<change when="2014-05-05" who="#kln">Edited for new TEI and file naming structures.</change>
<change when="2014-02-12" who="#kln">Revised earlier version of transcription and encoding.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="analysis">

<div2 type="bibliography">
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">General Act of the Conference of Berlin Concerning the Congo</title>
<title level="j">The American Journal of International Law</title>
<biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
<biblScope unit="page">7-25</biblScope>
<publisher>Baker, Voorhis &amp; Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date when="1909-01">January 1909</date>
</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="analysis">

<head type="main">Summary</head>

<p>The General Act of the Berlin Conference was signed on February 26, 1885 at the close of the Berlin Conference of 1884-5. The signatories of the act represented the United States, Germany, Belgium, Spain, Denmark, France, Italy, the United Kingdom, Austria-Hungary, the Netherlands, Russia, Portugal, the Ottoman Empire, and United Kingdoms of Norway and Sweden. The General Act, once ratified, bound the signatory nations to combating the continental slave trade in Africa, recognizing the sovereignty of the Congo Free State, respecting the protectorates and territorial possessions already present in Africa, and insuring the free navigation of the Congo and Niger Rivers and their tributaries. On the latter point, the Act dictated that railroads, roads, and "lateral canals" connected to the rivers be zones of free commerce and navigation. It made provisions to establish the International Commission of Navigation of the Congo to oversee this. <ref type="internal" target="teaa.en.government.0001">(See Article 20)</ref></p>

<p>Additionally, by declaring the free navigation of the Niger, the Act ended the British and French dispute over which nation held sovereignty over the river. The Act also outlined the boundaries of the Congo Basin and committed all signatories to insuring "commercial liberty" in the basin, its embouchures, and its "neighbouring country, and dispositions connected therewith." Accordingly, the Act forbade commercial monopolies in the Congo and prevented "powers" in the region from enacting import and export duties on goods brought into the region for twenty years. Mindful that foreign travel to Africa had increased during the nineteenth century, the Act required the signees to protect "natives," travelers, and missionaries, as well as guarantee "liberty of conscience" and "religious toleration" for these persons. The conference attendees charged each signee to urge their respective governments to ratify the document within one year of its signing. The United States was the only power represented at the conference that did not deposit its ratification with the Berlin Foreign Office by April 1886.<ref type="footnote" target="n01">1</ref></p>

<p>The General Act, in many ways, recognized what was occurring on in the continent since the early nineteenth century&#8212;the incremental penetration of the continent by Europeans, predominantly. This penetration intensified in the 1860s and 1870s with such events as Britain's punitive expedition against Abyssinia (1867-1868), King Leopold's claim to the Congo Free State in 1876, and Henry Morton Stanley's Anglo-American Expedition of 1878, to name a few. The dispute between France and Great Britain over Egypt in the 1880s brought the question of control over Africa to a head. In the immediate years following the signing of the Act and its ratification, European powers solidified their control over West Africa, establishing protectorates with access to the Atlantic coast. While the Act pledged to protect the natives and gave special protection to "[C]hristian missionaries, the savants [scientists], the explorers, their escorts, properties and collections," it became increasingly clear that the European powers aimed to dispossess Africans of their most fertile lands, to mobilize African labor (oftentimes violently) in service of the empire, to force Christianity on Africans, and to decrease the influence of Islam on the continent. In the last decade of the nineteenth century, European imperialist met resistance from African kingdoms, caliphates, states, and acephalous societies. However, by the turn of the twentieth century, most of Africa was under European control with the exception of Liberia and Abyssinia.<ref type="footnote" target="n02">2</ref></p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<note xml:id="n01">1. See Stig Förster, Wolfgang J. Mommsen, and Ronald Robinson, eds., <hi rend="italics">Bismarck, Europe, and Africa: the Berlin Africa Conference 1884-1885 and the Onset of Partition</hi> (London: German Historical Institute; New York: Oxford University Press, 1988); Sir Edward Hertslet, R. W. Brant, H. L. Sherwood, eds., <hi rend="italics">The Map of Africa By Treaty, Volume 2</hi> (London: Cass, 1967) [originally published London, H.M.S.O., 1909], 486.</note>
<note xml:id="n02">2. John Iliffe, <hi rend="italics">Africans: The History of a Continent</hi> (London: Cambridge University Press, 1995), 187-190.</note>
</div1>
</back>

</text>
</TEI>