<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="teaa.en.periodical.0107">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John Edward Bruce - The Black Sleuth (1907-1909)</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2019</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>"To Enter Africa from America"</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">teaa.en.periodical.0107</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a" type="main">The Black Sleuth</title>
<author ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41943529">Bruce, John Edward, 1856-1924</author>
<title level="j">McGirt's Magazine</title>
<date from="1907" to="1909">1907-1909</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>

<textClass>

<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Imagined Africa</term>
<term>Missionaries</term>
<term>Pan-Africanism</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Fiction</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>Yorubaland</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="powers">
<term>United States</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term>Ekiti</term>
<term>Yoruba</term>
<term>Zulu</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term>Catholic</term>
<term>Christianity</term>
<term>Islam</term>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="teaa.analysis.0021">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>

</textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2022-01" who="kln">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="book" xml:lang="en">

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter 1</head>

<p>"Do you mean to tell me that that nigger is a detective, and that
you are going to put him on this case, Mr. Hunter?"</p>

<p>The speaker was Capt. George De Forrest, a somewhat choleric and
impulsive person, who would easily be mistaken for a gentleman—
only gentlemen do not use the word "nigger" when speaking of Negroes, 
nor spell it with two gs when writing about them.</p>

<p>The question was addressed to Mr. Samuel Hunter (very appropriately 
named), who was the manager of the International Detective
Agency, a private concern which had achieved considerable success
in the apprehension and conviction of at least a dozen famous burglars, 
notably the daring safe-cracker O'Brien, who got away with
$400,000 in cash and bonds a few years ago, in Chicago, and Keene,
the great counterfeiter, who for five years had successfully defied detection 
and baffled and thwarted the best men in the U.S. Secret Service.</p>

<p>The running down of these notoriously clever criminals gave the International 
Detective Agency high standing, and resulted in increasing its yearly revenues a hundred fold.</p>

<p>It had branch offices in all the great capitals of Europe, and it employed 
hundreds of trained thief catchers—men of every civilized
race, who thoroughly understood their business, and generally got
whatever they went after.</p>



<p>The conversation above recorded took place in the London office
of the agency, and related to the loss of an uncut diamond, which had
been stolen from Captain De Forrest, an American seafaring man engaged
in the East India trade. Mr. Hunter, having gotten the details of
the Captain's story and a retainer, announced his purpose to assign an
intelligent young African in the employ of the agency—a Yoruba
man—to the case, knowing that if the facts stated by the Captain were
what he said they were, the Negro would run down the thief, or thieves.</p>

<p>But the Captain's American prejudice got the better of his judgment
and good taste, and impelled him to make the coarse and insulting remarks 
quoted.</p>

<p>The "Nigger," whose black face had been the cause of the remark,
was from the Ekiti County in Yorubaland on the West Coast, and was
one of the most valuable men in the service of the agency. He was well
educated, having graduated from Eton College, in England, with high
honors, a fine linguist, an expert at chess, and as perfectly developed
physically as an Apollo Belvidere. Yet, with all of his natural and acquired
attainments, he was the personification of modesty and good
breeding.</p>

<p>The gruff old sea dog had not meant that his words should be heard
by the "nigger"; yet, nevertheless, they were heard, and the "nigger"
then and there registered a vow that he would make that particular
captain own the force of his genius and feel very much ashamed of
himself by showing him how cleverly a "nigger" can do his work.</p>

<p>Captain De Forrest was of Southern birth. His father, Gamaliel De
Forrest, a Louisianian, had been captain of a slaver, and when Congress, 
in 1808, forbade the further importation of African slaves into
the United States by law, he went to the East Indies with his young
wife and son, and took service on one of the vessels of the East India 
Company as captain.</p>

<p>The boy followed the sea from his tenth year, and from his father,
who was an experienced navigator, he acquired a practical knowledge
of navigation.</p>

<p>On his twenty-eighth birthday, through the influence of his father,



he was made captain of the "Norman K. Peters," a merchant vessel
trading in the East Indies and other ports, and for forty years he
ploughed the raging main from the Occident to the Orient, visiting
nearly every country on the globe.</p>

<p>In each port that he visited he procured some valuable memento of
his visit to adorn his personal residence in the suburbs of London. Although 
he was an American by birth, he was English by adoption, but
with the foolish American antipathy and prejudice to people of darker hue.</p>

<p>As already stated, nearly every country on the globe had been laid
under tribute to him or his agents, so that he possessed a collection of
rare curios and bric-a-brac of almost priceless value.</p>

<p>There were jade vases from China, handsomely wrought rugs from
Persia, coats of armor from Japan, swords of curious design from Damascus,
pipes of intrinsic value from the Ottoman Empire, articles fashioned 
from ebony, mahogany and gold from the Dark Continent, precious 
stones, pins, rings, watches and an endless variety of things from
almost every country where such things are used.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter II</head>

<p>In South Africa, whither he had journeyed to take on a cargo of
hides and other native products, Captain De Forrest had had the good
fortune to meet at Kimberley, where the famous diamond mines are
located (which made Cecil Rhodes, as they are making hundreds of
others, rich beyond the dreams of avarice, yet are still avaricious), a
young African of possibly nineteen or twenty, who was wandering aimlessly, 
as it seemed to him, in the direction of his vessel, along the water front.</p>

<p>He was a magnificent type of African young manhood, tall–fully
six feet—and physically well developed. He was attired in the full
dress usually affected by the African on his native heath—a loin cloth
of white material—and wore on his head a delicately wrought cap
without a visor made of the native grass of the country. As he strolled
leisurely along the water front he seemed to enjoy the cool and refreshing
breezes wafted shoreward by the trade winds from the broad
expanse of old ocean, and to be at peace with all the world.</p>

<p>There was something in his bearing that attracted the captain's attention.
He held his head high and walked with the precision of one
who had seen service as a soldier. As he came nearer to where Captain 
De Forrest and a group of British officers were standing, chatting
of one thing and another, the captain, espying him, exclaimed, "Gad,
gentlemen, there is the finest looking black fellow I ever saw," pointing 
 


towards the approaching figure, who was all unconscious of the
fact that he was an object of admiration, and that, too, by an American 
with no particular fancy for Negroes. "Look!" said the captain to
his friends. "He is as straight as an arrow; what muscles, what a chest
development, what a splendid bearing. Gad! He is a picture."</p>

<p>The Englishmen, who had many times seen the African at his best,
and even more perfect types than the young man in question, did not
enthuse over him as much as did Captain De Forrest, though they very
frankly admitted that he was not bad to look upon. One of the officers,
who had seen thousands of Zulus in Cape Colony, remarked rather
carelessly, "There are Zulus who are better developed physically than
this chap, captain. You should see some of the Zulu warriors if you
want to see perfectly developed men. This chap is a Yoruba Negro,
and if you know anything about Negroes in Africa, you must know that
the Yoruba Negroes are among the best scholars in Africa." The young
man was now almost within speaking distance of the group and the
captain, excusing himself from his companions, advanced toward and
greeted him with a "How do you do, my friend?" The young man returned 
the greeting with "Quite well, I thank you. How are you, sir?"</p>

<p>The captain had not expected this kind of English from a half-naked 
"African savage," as Negroes in Africa are called by complacent 
egotists in the white race, who imagine that civilization, which,
as Da Rocha says, is a relative term, began and will end with them.</p>

<p>The captain looked the surprise he felt. The young African, noticing 
his embarrassment, added: "You seem surprised, sir, because I answered 
you in English. I speak very good English. Is it not so?"</p>

<p>"Oh, yes, yes," responded the captain, recovering from his shock.
"I was wondering where you learned our tongue. Your people have a
language of their own, have they not?"</p>

<p>"Certainly, sir," replied the young man with a polite bow. "There
are as many languages among Africans as there are tribes, and we
sometimes add to them. I speak and write the Yoruba language, that
is my tribal language. I also speak and write French, German, Arabic,
Italian and English."</p>



<p>"W-w-why, where did you manage to learn to speak and write all
those languages, young man?" asked the now thoroughly surprised captain. 
"Come aboard my ship. I want to talk to you. You really interest
me." Addressing his late companions he begged them to excuse him
while he interviewed the young black man, which they willingly did.</p>

<p>The captain repeated his invitation to the young man to visit him
in his cabin, but he seeming to hesitate, and the captain, divining what
he was revolving over in his mind, quickly assured him that he would
not carry him off in his ship. The young man smiled faintly and followed 
the captain into the little naphtha launch to his handsomely appointed 
cabin in the ship, in midstream, where he entertained that
worthy until the stars began to shed their lustre on the earth with the
story of his life.</p>

<p>Captain De Forrest, as soon as the young man had seated himself
in the comfortable arm-chair which he had placed for him, sat himself 
down in a big leather rocker directly opposite his visitor, and taking
from his coat pocket a well-filled cigar case, opened it and offered
the young black man one of the big black Havana cigars which it contained.</p>

<p>"I thank you for your kindness, sir," said Mojola—Mojola Okukenu
was the name of the young African—but I do not smoke or use
tobacco in any form."</p>

<p>"Drink?" queried the captain.</p>

<p>"I am glad to be able to say, sir, that that is another habit to which
I am not addicted."</p>

<p>"Well, my young man, I wish I could truthfully say as much as that,
but unfortunately I cannot," and removing the stopper from a well-filled
decanter which sat on the little round table, he filled his glass
with rare old Madeira, which he quaffed only as a connoisseur quaffs
an old vintage with a bouquet and a history. Setting his glass down the
captain lighted one of the big black cigars which lay on the table and
then settled back in his rocker in an easy attitude, a picture of contentment,
and requested Mojola to tell him something about himself.</p>

<p>"I do not know that my story will specially interest you, sir," said



Mojola, "but since you have asked it I will tell you as much of it as
modesty and time will permit." He began:</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">Mojola Okukenu's Story.</hi></p>

<p>"When I was quite a small boy I attended, with my brother who
is now in America, a mission school which had been established by
some white men who came from England in the village in which I was
born, in Yorubaland.</p>

<p>"I went to this school regularly for two years and learned while a
pupil there to speak English fluently and write it with considerable
facility. My teacher, seeing my aptitude for letters, encouraged me in
every way, and as time grew he persuaded my father, then a very old
man, to consent to my going to England with him, whither he was going 
to recuperate his health. The climate of Africa is death to white
men, and except in South Africa, where the temperatures are very similar 
to those of some portions of Europe, they cannot remain more than
six months or a year without showing the bad effects of the tropical
climate upon their health. So that for self-protection they are forced
to make bi-annual voyages to England, or Scotland, or Germany, and
if not too far gone physically, return and resume their work, but more
of them go home to die than to return.</p>

<p>"My father thought long over this request of my teacher to take me
to the white man's country, and in three weeks from the time it was
made he gave his consent, only on the promise that I was to be brought
back or sent back within a year from the day of sailing and at the expense 
of my teacher. This promise was made in writing, sealed, signed
and delivered to my father in the presence of the head men of our tribe,
which being done, I was placed in charge of my future guardian and
protector, who was to sail to England on the steamship "Crown Princess,' 
due to arrive within the next ten days.</p>

<p>"When my brother Sadipe learned that we were to be separated for
a whole year it made him quite sad at heart, and on the morning that



we took ship for England he showed the strength of the great love he
bore me by restraining his tears until just as the great vessel lifted anchor
and was getting up steam to make the long journey to England.
With his hand in mine we stood on deck gazing into each other's eyes
for a moment. Finally he broke the silence, saying: 'Brother Mojola,
you are going to a strange land and I feel that we are never to meet
again on this earth. I am going to America. Good-bye, my dear brother. 
May the God of races keep His strong arm of protection around us
and make us both instruments for good in His hands.' As he said these
words he burst into tears, and we embraced each other, both now
weeping as though our hearts would break.</p>

<p>"The deckhands and sailors were busy getting on board the cargo,
which was being brought to the ship in canoes by 'boys' and hoisted
on deck by ropes. There was a huge pile of all sorts of things on the
beach to be placed on board, and the captain was busy giving orders
to the workers on board, and everybody, both those ashore and those
aboard, were as busy as they could well be. I told Sadipe when he had
recovered from his fit of depression that I really did not want to go to
England, but that our father wanted me to go with my teacher and
learn more about the white man in his native land. He told me that I
would never be happy there, separated from kindred and friends, 'but
go, Mojola, and make the most of your opportunities. It may be that
you will be the better for it,' and so, brother Sadipe, I bowed to the will
of our good father, confident that he knew what was best for me. We
both agreed that it was perhaps a wise thing for me to go to England
and, much as I disliked the long journey, I felt that there was some
special providence in it. My brother and I stood at the rail on the upper 
deck and talked of many things until the ship was loosed from her
moorings, and when the whistle blew the last signal a native canoe
came alongside the ship and he was lowered into it and was taken
ashore.</p>

<p>"I stood on the after-deck of the great vessel and saw him safely
land, and I remained there and watched him and exchanged signals
with him until he faded from view.</p>
 


<p>"The good ship on which we journeyed reached Liverpool within
the time she was scheduled to arrive, and on the evening of the day of
our arrival we set out for London, our objective. My teacher had letters 
of credit on the great firm of Wellborne &amp; Coverdale, which he
presented, but owing to a clerical error he was obliged to wait until a
cable could be sent to Lagos, West Africa, to correct it. It was one of
those clerical blunders which even the best of clerks sometimes make.
This clerk had forgotten in his haste to write in the name of the bearer 
of the letter, and it had been necessary for Messrs. Wellborne &amp;
Coverdale to ascertain to whom they were really to pay over the £300
for which the letter called. The British Consul at Lagos satisfied them
that the letter was in the right hands, and that the money should be
paid bearer. The money, all in crisp Bank of England notes, was paid
to my teacher and we took a compartment in an afternoon steam car
for the great metropolis. I had never before ridden in a steam car and
you may well imagine my feelings and sensations on this my initial
overland trip on wheels propelled by steam."</p>

<p>"Got scared, eh?" queried the captain, blowing a big mouthful of
smoke in the direction of Mojola, which he skillfully dodged.</p>

<p>"I do not think, sir, that I ever was afraid or 'scared,' as you call it,
of anybody or anything except once in my life, and that was when I
first saw a man of your race, who came to our country wearing European 
clothes, the like of which we had never before seen. My people
declared it to be their belief that he was the devil, an evil spirit sent
to persecute and torment us. We Africans, I must here add, associate
the white man with the prince of evil and all that is wicked and bad.
No, I was not scared nor afraid, but I was filled with amazement, wonder,
surprise at the speed of the iron horse and the inventive skill and
genius of the white man, who had constructed this wonderful machine
which was bearing us through space almost with the swiftness of the
wind. Wonderful, wonderful, I kept saying to myself as I gazed out of
the window of the car and saw, as I then supposed, the houses and
trees and other inanimate objects moving speedily through space."</p>

<p>"I want to know about yourself, young man, and where you learned



to speak English so well and the other languages which you tell me
you can speak and write," said the captain eagerly.</p>

<p>"If you will permit me to summarize my story, sit, I think I can satisfy 
you on those points. I never had any one to teach me the languages
I speak other than my own and what you call English except nature,
and I was and tried always to be a conscientious and tireless student.
I hold that there is nothing within the scope of human endeavor which
a resolute man may not accomplish if he so wills. But I must tell my
story in my own way, sir. If you wish to hear me further I will proceed."</p>

<p>"Go on! go on! I beg pardon for interrupting you," said the captain.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter III</head>

<p>Continuing, Mojola said: "When we alighted from our compartment
in London that afternoon, 
we were met at the station by quite a number of the personal
friends of my teacher and a small delegation of the members of the
church which had sent him out to Africa to take up the 'white man's
burden' of civilizing, Christianizing and educating the heathen of that
'benighted land.'</p>

<p>"Due notice, of course, had been given of my coming, and when I
arrived in London I became the cynosure of all eyes and was paraded 
and exhibited in the churches of this particular denomination as a
specimen of the work turned out by the missionaries sent out to Africa
by its Foreign Mission Board. I was called on at missionary meetings
to read portions of Scriptures in my native tongue, and as I had a fair
voice and understood music to some extent, I was always asked to sing
some one or other of the white man's (meaningless to us) gospel hymns
in the Yoruba tongue.</p>

<p>"At the close of these meetings the people would crowd around me
and ply me with all sorts of foolish questions about Africa and say
many foolish things about the Africans which disclosed their crass ignorance 
of my country and its people, as well as their overweening
conceit. All of these things disgusted me more than I can tell you, sir,
for in my young mind I had conceived the idea that your race was representative
of the highest intelligence, and that modesty and good



breeding were its chief characteristics in matters religious, but this
experience disillusioned me; its pharisaism really disgusted me."</p>

<p>The captain gazed steadily at the bold young African, who was all
unconscious of the force of his words, winced and turned uneasily in
his chair. Continuing, Mojola said:</p>

<p>"My observation of things spiritual and temporal in England convinced 
me that I could never adapt myself to English ideas or customs, 
or accept with a sincere heart the white man's conception of the
religion taught and practiced by Jesus of Nazareth, of whom we in
Yorubaland have at least heard something.</p>

<p>"All that I had observed during the first few weeks of my sojourn
in England impressed me deeply with the idea that there was more
sham and hypocrisy than reality in the thing he is trying to inject into
the African and other so-called heathen—the hollowness of their
professions of brotherhood was to me so transparent I determined that
I would, on the first opportunity that presented itself, return to my own
country.</p>

<p>"In the course of a few months I was able to do this, and I do not
now regret that I left the 'centre of civilization' and returned to the
land of 'darkness and barbarism,' as Africa is ignorantly styled by
those who do not know better, and who are accustomed from long practice 
to reason with their prejudices."</p>

<p>"You are a pretty plain speaker, young man," said the captain, who
was quite red in the face.</p>

<p>"Truth should always be spoken plainly, sir," said Mojola. "Before
your race had a civilization or a religion, mine was, and from it your
race has borrowed and stolen all that was best and most useful in art,
science, religion, letters, politics and government, from which you
have evolved what you proudly term Anglo-Saxon civilization. Intelligent 
Africans laugh at your complacent egotism."</p>

<p>"Umph!" muttered the captain. "What do you do here?" said he,
trying to change the subject. "I mean what opportunities have you
here for using the knowledge you acquired in England?"</p>

<p>"I am teaching my people the true Gospel—that God is no respecter

 

of persons. The knowledge I acquired in England is only
useful for purposes of comparison: for, believe me, sir, we sift it as occasion
requires, and it sometimes suffers by comparison. We in Africa
are not nearly so dumb, ignorant, nor benighted as the white man
seems to believe us to be."</p>

<p>"Umph!" grunted the captain, looking askance at the bold young
African, who, without apparently noticing this interruption, went on
to say:</p>

<p>"The Yorubas are one of the most advanced African tribes. We have
the Bible translated from the original Greek and Hebrew texts by our
own native scholars, a grammar, hymn books, a history of Yorubaland
by native historians and many other evidences showing that we are
not as benighted nor as barbarous as white people with the missionary 
fever and itching palms represent us to be." This was too much for
the captain; he had heard enough. Rising from his comfortable armchair, 
he advanced toward the young man. Espying a small gunnysack 
on the floor of the cabin nearly under the chair in which Mojola
sat, he asked him what it contained, assuming that he was selling <hi rend="italics">curios</hi>.</p>

<p>"Oh, they are merely specimens of rock; I am very fond of geology,
sir, and I sometimes gather these specimens along the seashore and
other places in my wanderings to illustrate my lectures to our Yoruba
boys." The captain looked his astonishment. Here, in the heart of
Africa, Africa which he had been taught to believe was the home of a
wild and barbarous and heathenish people who ate good, white missionaries 
three times a day and each other, occasionally, according to
the missionary reports and friendly newspapers. He was standing
face to face with one of these heathen and barbarians who was better
educated than himself, who spoke purer English, and who had a better 
general idea of books than he, and a more analytical mind. His
Caucasian pride and conceit, however, would not allow him to discover 
his mental deficiencies to this half-naked black man, and despite 
his short comings he felt his superiority over a man whom his
own heart told him was his master in the force that wins—brains.</p>



<p>While he was thus musing, Mojola had opened the gunny-sack and
spread the specimens on the table at which they sat. The captain's experienced
eye detected among them one that struck him as being more
than a specimen. It was a flinty substance about the size of an English
walnut. The captain picked it up, ran his eye over it critically and laid
it down carelessly, but kept his eye on it. He examined other specimens; 
one resembling a moonstone and almost perfectly round excited 
his admiration. He asked its name, and received the answer; and,
as if forgetting that he had once examined the larger specimen, he
picked it up again and fondled it. The young African, who had been
watching him closely, and observing that he was particularly <hi rend="italics">interested</hi> 
in that specimen, vouchsafed the information that that was a diamond 
in the rough.</p>

<p>"A diamond!" exclaimed the captain in a tone that betrayed the
workings of his mind.</p>

<p>The young African, with aggravating nonchalance, calmly assured
him that it was, and that they were frequently to be met with in the
section of the country from which he came, some of them even larger
than this. The captain's eyes bulged out. The wily young African had
awakened in the avaricious white man before him the spirit which had
led thousands of his race to seek fame and fortune–mostly fortune–
in the "dark continent," which, with bitter irony, is not inappropriately
called the graveyard of the grasping nations of the earth.</p>

<p>Mojola smiled as he watched the face of the man who had been so
much interested in the story of his life, and he read his innermost
thoughts.</p>

<p>"Will you sell me this specimen, young man? I want it and
will pay you a good price for it."</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter IV</head>

<p>The eager tone of the captain's voice caused the young African
to smile as he looked up from the table over which he was engaged in
placing in the little gunny-sack the remaining specimens which he
had strewn upon it for the inspection of his host, and he answered in
the soft tones peculiar to the people of Yorubaland: "If it is of any value 
to you, sir, you may have it. I can easily find another and perhaps
a better one."</p>

<p>The captain's eyes almost popped out of their sockets at the words
"a better one." Could it be possible, thought he, that there was still a
better diamond on earth than his experienced eye told him this one
was? "Oh, no, no, no; I–I–I–I–want to, I must pay you something 
for it. It would not be right to take it as a gift," said he, more excitedly
than the occasion seemed to warrant.</p>

<p>"Very well," said the young African, "have your way about it, sir.
We Africans do not set our hearts on the possession of money. It is the
cheapest thing we have amongst us, except the air we breathe and the
water we drink. Our currency is made in nature's mint and is stamped
by a 'divinity that shapes our ends.' We use cowry shells, and about
a thousand of them would equal in value six of your English pennies."</p>

<p>"Your millionaires began saving about the year one, didn't they?"
queried the captain.</p>

<p>"We have no millionaires among our people, sir. The accumulation



and hoarding of wealth is an invention of the white man, and Africa
is just now the centre of his activity. He is plundering Africa like a
buccaneer in quest of gold and diamonds and ivory, and he returns to
Europe or America broken in health to die, or perchance he dies in
the wilds of my country in the mad struggle to possess himself of ill-gotten gains.</p>

<p>"Take the late Cecil Rhodes. Where was there a more grasping,
soulless creature than he? He accumulated millions on millions and
lived like a king amongst us, but he died without realizing his dream
of empire. He, like all who have preceded him or who are now following, 
or may hereafter follow his example of plundering the Africans
in the name of civilization and religion, will fail ingloriously in any attempt
to establish in the black man's country a white civilization or to
reverse the decree of the Almighty."</p>

<p>"Africa is for the African, and the white man can never permanently 
abide within its boundaries. The African will ultimately enjoy
the fruits of the white man's persistent labors in developing the country, 
and has obligingly died, leaving some other
misguided white man to take up his world. It is an old story, sir. For
a thousand years the nations of the earth have been casting lots for the
possession of Africa, but Africa possesses them, as their bleaching
bones in vale and forest mutely testify. God does not intend that the
white man shall possess our land. It is a 'Rubicon' he cannot cross.
No matter how many nations partition Africa, Africa will still be
Africa.</p>

<p>"Africans will absorb and assimilate your learning, will study your
system of government, and will analyze and dissect whatever is best
and most useful to them in your civilization, whatever is rational and
reasonable in your religion, whatever is practical and just in your legal
jurisprudence, and then construct her own code of morals and
ethics for use against the time when 'Ethiopia shall suddenly stretch
forth her hands unto God.' She will be equipped with all the learning
and wisdom and knowledge of all the races of the earth with whom she
has come in contact, and will be ready to take her proper place among


 
the nations. She has no fears as to her future. Her star is in the ascendant.
She stands upon the threshold of a future pregnant with hope
and big with magnificent possibilities."</p>

<p>As Mojola Okukenu uttered these words, Captain De Forrest, who
had lost interest in the fat cigar which he had been smoking and which
now lay beside his big, fat right arm, which was lazily resting on the
round table in his cabin, gazed in astonishment and amazement at the
speaker and finally uttered a deep sigh expressive of his feelings. In
a moment or two his tongue found speech and he said, "Young man, I
have listened with interest to your story and I have been profitably entertained 
and highly instructed by your display of learning and wisdom. 
You have talents and abilities of no mean order, and you have
the gift of putting your thoughts in clear, cogent and forceful English.
Not every man is as well qualified as you to give voice to his thoughts
in such clear, pungent, and terse language. Your story has most thoroughly
convinced me that there is no difference between men in the
republic of intellect; that the black man's brain is just as capable of
higher development as a white man's under proper conditions." The
Captain looked as wise and solemn as an owl after admitting this Solomonic
gem.</p>

<p>The young African replied, "That is hardly a compliment, sir. God
did not create black men or white men, but <hi rend="smallcaps">man</hi>, out of the loins of
whom came all the varieties of men who now inhabit the earth—equal
in the beginning, and equal always before Him.</p>

<p>"Opportunity and environment are the standards by which all men
should be judged, not color. It is no compliment to the Negro to tell
him that he is as good as a white man, for that presupposes that the
white man is a superior being, which is not true. His opportunities and
environment have done for him exactly what they would have done for
the black man similarly placed.</p>

<p>"Whenever the Negro has had fair opportunities, he has always
shown himself equal to them, and in my country there are many men
of learning and ability, equal and in many respects superior to those
who have been more fortunately placed.</p>



<p>"Color is no criterion of superiority or the lack of it, sir. All brains
have the same color; all blood is red.</p>

<p>"Your Scottish bard, Robert Burns, has expressed my thoughts in
these words:</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"'The rank is but the guinea's stamp;</l>
<l>A man's a man for a' that and a' that.'</l></lg>

<p>"And now, sir. I must beg you to permit me to say good evening to
you, for I have remained aboard your ship much longer than I had expected."</p>

<p>"Oh! You needn't be in a hurry, young man; you are excellent company 
and I enjoy your conversation immensely."</p>

<p>"I thank you for that, sir," answered the young African. "I trust I
have talked to some purpose."</p>

<p>"You have converted me and while you were talking so earnestly
and eloquently a few moments ago, I registered a vow that the black
man will ever find in me an unflinching friend, and now I give you my
hand, my young friend, in pledge of friendship to your race. My purse,
my house, my heart will always be open to any worthy Negro in trouble 
or need."</p>

<p>"Then our meeting has really been prolific of good?" asked Mojola.</p>

<p>"It has," replied the Captain. "I have learned more about the Negro 
today than I ever knew before or ever dreamed was true. You belong 
to a great race, and you have shown me why it is a great race.
When I was a boy at Sunday school I often read, without understanding 
it, a passage in the Bible which ran something like this: 'He that
is least among you will be greatest.' I know now what that passage
means."</p>

<p>"I am happy and gratified," said Mojola, "to know that I have been
the means of leading you to see the African in a new light, and I am
glad to number you among the true friends of my countrymen. And
now, Captain, again I must say good evening. I have enjoyed the meeting 
with you, and I assure you the benefits have been mutual."</p>

 

<p>The young man shook the Captain warmly by the hand and, stepping 
to the door of the cabin, was soon on his way down the rope ladder 
on the side of the great ship, where he was met by one of the numerous 
"boys" who had previously been ordered by Captain De
Forrest to come out and take his visitor ashore in a native boat, and
he was soon lost in the shadows of the evening.</p>

<p>"Most remarkable young Negro I ever met," mused the Captain,
picking up his cigar and lighting it. "We whites can never keep down
a race that produces men of that stamp." He strolled leisurely aft, and
sat down in a big steamer chair, smoked and thought of many things.</p>

<p>The skies in Africa in autumn are beautiful to behold. The stars
seem to be nearer to earth than they do in other parts of the world.
Their coruscations are like those of a newly cut diamond in a setting
of opal and gold. The captain shifted his chair to a point where he
could sweep the horizon with his big glass, and he gazed at the stars
and thought of Mojola for two or three hours, and then retired to his
comfortable bed, where he courted the god Morpheus, with a particularly 
strong cigar.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER V</head>

<p>Six days after the departure of Mojola for England, Sadipe Okukenu, 
his brother, who was three years his junior, took passage on an
American sailing vessel for the United States. He had pleaded earnestly 
with his old father for permission to go, and he had yielded, though
somewhat reluctantly, to his importunities. The name of the vessel on
which he sailed was the "Water Witch." Her captain was a down-easter, 
and, like most of the men from that part of America, he had a great
deal of genuine sympathy for the Negro. He, too, had urged the boy's
father to let him make the voyage, saying that it would be a liberal education
to him and that the knowledge thus gained would be useful to
him in the future. He promised to put the boy in a good school and to
have him properly and carefully educated, so that when he reached
his majority he could return to his native land and use his talents for
the uplift of his "benighted race." This philosophical observation caused
the shrewd old African to smile. His knowledge of white men, gained
from dealing with them on the coast, taught him that conceit was not
among the least of their accomplishments. "Nature has been kind to
them," he mused, "in the bestowal of her gifts, and this white man
actually believes that his race can teach my race something. He either 
forgets, or does not know, that the very Bible he professes to believe 
came from the East, not from the West, and that we Africans had
a great deal more to do with its promulgation than he is aware of."</p>

 

<p>These were some of the thoughts that ran through his mind while
he sat on his stool facing the white man who awaited his answer about
his boy Sadipe. Rising abruptly and pacing up and down for several
moments, he stopped directly in front of the captain and said:</p>

<p>"You say you will send my boy to a good school in America?"</p>

<p>"Oh, yes," answered the Captain; "I will take him with me to Maine
and place him in charge of my sister, who is very fond of black people. 
She will prepare him for school, and when he is ready to enter will
send him to a Negro college, where they will make a doctor or preacher 
or lawyer out of him."</p>

<p>"Are there any Christians in your country?"</p>

<p>"Why, certainly, my good man, America is the most Christian country 
on the globe. We contribute more money, verily, to civilize and
Christianize the heathen in foreign lands than almost any other nation
on earth. You could not send Sadipe to a better place than America;
it is a progressive country, and black men there enjoy the same rights
as white men."</p>

<p>"But why do you say you will send my boy to a Negro college when
he is prepared to go to one? Why do you have Negro colleges if all
men have the same rights in your country and are all equal? Why do
you thus separate the races?"</p>

<p>"Oh! That is the custom in my country; the black people have their
own schools and churches, and they would not come to ours."</p>

<p>"Then the black man is superior to the white man; is that it?"</p>

<p>"Well–er–er–hardly that. You see, we have a peculiar condition 
of affairs in America. The blacks were once in slavery to the
white race and are considered to be not quite equal to them in morals
and intelligence, due to their former condition. We have a very kind
feeling in our hearts for the black people and we are helping them
through our churches and schools of learning to become self-respecting 
and useful citizens. Politically they have all the rights that
white citizens enjoy and many of them hold offices of great trust and
responsibility."</p>

<p>"And yet you are divided in your schools and churches, where perfect



equality should exist?" asked the wily old African, who was not
quite as green as he looked.</p>

<p>"Tell me," he said, straightening himself up to his full height, "is a
man-stealer in your country regarded as an honorable man, and are
men-killers respected in your country? I have heard that you Americans 
have stolen thousands of my people from their homes here in
Africa to make them slaves, and that since freedom came to them you
kill them by burning them at the stake and lynching them, as you call
it. Are these white men superior to black men?"</p>

<p>Captain Barnard looked at the old African quizzically and intently
as he was speaking, as if trying to read his very soul. Here in the very
heart of Africa he was standing face to face with one of her sable sons,
who was discussing with him a question of ethics that made him blush
for shame for the "most Christian nation on earth."</p>

<p>A man whose appearance concealed more than it revealed; a deep,
cool-headed old Negro with a logical mind, who was putting questions
to him that stung his pride and made him ashamed to own the name
"American."</p>

<p>His answers to these questions were such only as an honest, God-
fearing white American could give them. He said:</p>

<p>"We do not, in America, regard men-stealers and men-killers as
honorable men, but as thieves and murderers; their crimes have disgraced 
the American name and made it a byword and hissing among
the nations, and our children and our children's children will bear the
stigma and suffer the consequences of these crimes against God and
man for generations yet unborn."</p>

<p>The Captain uttered the words with considerable feeling and emphasis, 
and there was no mistaking his sincerity.</p>

<p>The elder Okukenu listened respectfully to the white man, and when
he had finished he extended his hand and said:</p>

<p>"I am willing, sir, that my boy Sadipe shall accompany you in your
voyage to America. I wish him to go that he may see for himself how
the white man in America lives. I have no fear about his not returning 
to his home here in Africa. The Okukenus will not submit to oppression

 

or injustice in any form, no matter where they are, and if
Sadipe is not treated well in your country he will find a way to get back
to the land of his fathers. I give to both of you my blessings and my
prayers for a safe voyage. I am willing to trust him to your care, for
your speech shows you to be a good man, a God-fearing man, and men
who fear and reverence God can do no wrong."</p>

<p>The day after this remarkable interview between the Captain and
the elder Okukenu, exactly at high noon, the "Water Witch" lifted anchor 
and was soon speeding away on her long journey to the Western
Hemisphere.</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Unless above himself he doth erect himself,</l>
<l>How poor a thing is man."</l>
</lg>

<p>The finest thing in the human life is its constant struggle toward
something better–something noble.</p>

<p>The little black boy who stood on the forward deck of the "Water
Witch," as she rode majestically upon the bosom of the placid waters,
was destined for a better fate than he had ever dreamed of. The stars
in their courses were conspiring to make his future as brilliant, as successful. 
Sadipe was a boy of uncommon native and acquired abilities
for one of his age. He was of a lively temperament, high-spirited and
manly in bearing, quick-witted and apt. He was passionately fond of
books, and, young as he was—he was just turning nineteen—he
spoke two native dialects and was quite familiar with Arabic. He
could read the Koran understandingly, and had memorized many passages 
from it, which was not an uncommon performance for boys of
his age, and even younger, who were constantly thrown in contact with
the followers of Mohammed.</p>

<p>His father was of that faith, and five times each day in the year he
and his household reverently prostrated themselves before Him whom
Jean Paul Richter declares "is the holiest among the mighty and the
mightiest among the holy."</p>

<p>Sadipe stood unconsciously upon the threshold of a future pregnant



with mighty possibilities, and as they subsequently unfolded themselves 
to him he proved himself equal to every emergency that arose,
as the sequel will show.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter VI</head> 

<p>Of the details of Sadipe's experience after his arrival in America 
we will say nothing further than that Captain Barnard treated him
with the utmost consideration en voyage, and on his arrival at his home
in Maine (or rather the home of his good sister, for the Captain was a
typical sea rover) he and that good lady conspired to make the young
African feel as much at home as they knew how.</p>

<p>The Captain's sister, Mrs. Tabitha Pelham, was a motherly sort of a
woman, kind-hearted, indulgent and gentle of manner. She took the
greatest interest in Sadipe. From their first meeting she liked his face,
and told her brother that the boy was above the average of his race in
intelligence and that his manner and speech indicated that there was
really something in him. She was able to reach these conclusions from
the fact that she had for more than twenty years taught a school for
boys in an adjoining town and knew somewhat of boys.</p>

<p>She accordingly began to prepare her young African charge for the
business of real life. His natural aptitude was in his favor, and he
learned rapidly. He was particularly adept in mathematics and Latin,
and he had a taste for history which was encouraged by his patron.</p>

<p>The English classics were also a favorite study with him, and in
these he displayed a breadth of mind and a range of vision which not
only astonished but greatly pleased his instructor. He was eager to acquire
a knowledge of French and German, and to gratify his wishes



Mrs. Pelham, after a few weeks, employed a teacher of these languages
to come to the house two evenings in the week and instruct her young
charge in the mysteries of these languages. His knowledge of Latin
greatly facilitated the work of his instructor, and helped both the
teacher and the taught to make progress. Like most Negroes, he was
passionately fond of music, good music, and in the fullness of time
Mrs. Pelham employed a music teacher, Prof. Rogers of the conservatory, 
who taught him how to perform on the pianoforte, the young
man going to the conservatory two evenings a week when his daily
tasks were done. He was regarded as a sort of prodigy by some of the
villagers, who had views as to the intellectual capacity of the black
man. They could not comprehend how a black boy could advance so
rapidly in studies which required two, sometimes four years for white
boys to master.</p>

<p>Here was a black boy who within less than a year had become proficient 
in the fundamentals of learning and had learned to speak and
write Latin, French and German, mastered the rudiments of natural
philosophy, knew the English poets and was not a bad performer on
the piano. They shook their heads and asked each other, Will wonders
never cease?</p>

<p>But these good and well-meaning villagers did not know that the
race to which this "boy" belonged was born to scholarship; that the
tribe in Africa with which he was identified is, with the exception of
the Fantis, the most intellectual tribe in all Africa. Had they known
these facts they would not have marveled.</p>

<p>Sadipe had come to America to learn things, and he was determined
to learn all he could.</p>

<p>After eighteen months' hard and conscientious study, and having
exhausted good Mrs. Pelham's stock of information (for she confessed
that she could go no further with him), he was ready for college. At the
beginning of the fall term of the Eckington College for Colored Youth
he found himself the possessor of a scholarship—the joint gift of Mrs.
Pelham and Col. Amos Otis, President of the Sago National Bank, who



was greatly interested in the boy and as proud of him as Mrs. Pelham,
who showed her admiration for his fine abilities in many ways.</p>

<p>After much preparation he was sent off to Eckington College well
supplied with strong letters to prominent men of his own race living
in the vicinity of the school, who were advised of his phenomenal talents
and urged to show him the hospitality worthy of a young man so
well favored by nature. Finally on Saturday morning of that week he
took leave of his kind patron, Mrs. Pelham, and set his face toward
Eckington College, in that far Southern State, traveling as a first-class
passenger until he reached the capital city of the nation, which is
sandwiched between two of the old slave states, Maryland and Virginia, 
and where race prejudice is almost thick enough to cut with a
knife.</p>

<p>Here, in the home of the President of the United States, the seat of
power, where the laws which govern the country are made, where
equality of citizenship is proclaimed in the national Congress, and
where there were more Negroes of varying shades and conditions than
Sadipe had ever before seen in America, he received the first great
shock of the many which he was to experience on the two days' journey 
before him. His train arriving late in Washington, his journey was
delayed several hours, and he strolled out of the Pennsylvania Station,
up Sixth street, into Pennsylvania avenue and meandered leisurely toward 
the great white-domed Capitol, upon whose highest point the
Goddess of Liberty stood in mock seriousness keeping guard over
the liberties and rights of the people. Meeting a black man, he asked
the name of the building and the meaning of the big statue on the top.
Being told, he jotted down in the notebook given him by Mrs. Pelham
the name of the building and the Goddess misnamed "Liberty." Continuing 
his journey, he brought up at the Peace Monument at First
Street and Pennsylvania avenue. He read the legend at its base and
noted it in his book, and then, retracing his steps, soon found himself
again in the station just as the guard was crying "All aboard! This way
for the train South."</p>


 
<p>He started for the gate and attempted to enter. The ticket-taker, a
coarse, gruff, red-haired Irishman, stopped him. "Where's your ticket, 
old man? Yez can't go troo widout showing yure ticket." Sadipe
gave him a withering look of scorn and stepped out of the line. Going
over to a window, he searched his pockets for the coveted pasteboard,
which he had securely placed in an envelope with the cash given him
by Mrs. Pelham. Carefully replacing the envelope in an inner pocket
and fastening the pocket with the large safety pin which Mrs. Pelham
had also given him, to make sure of it staying there, he returned to the
gate and presented his ticket. The Irishman scanned it critically before 
punching it, punched it and slapped Sadipe on the back, saying,
"There's yure train, old man; step lively now."</p>

<p>"You are an insolent, impudent brute; how dare you strike me?"
said Sadipe, who was boiling with indignation at the coarse and vulgar 
and insolent action of the uniformed underling. "I have a great notion 
to slap your face!" said the spunky boy. A gentleman who had
witnessed the conduct of the ticket-taker and heard the objectionable
remarks which offended Sadipe here came forward and said: "Young
man, this fellow has wantonly and grossly insulted you, and you
should report him at once to the company. If you will give me your
name I myself will do so, and state what I saw and heard. I am a stockholder
in this company and am sure that the rules of the management
require that all employees shall at least be civil to its patrons."</p>

<p>While Sadipe and his newmade and unknown friend were thus talking 
the Southern train drew out from the station and left him. The gentleman
consulted a timetable and told him that there would be another 
train at 12:03. Stepping into the telegraph office in the station, he
wired the President of Eckington College that he had missed his train
and would take the 12:03. His newfound friend and he then sought
the office of the superintendent, which was upstairs, where they jointly 
complained of the action of the insolent employee at the gate, and
that person was sent for by the superintendent and confronted with
the charges made. He made an abject apology for his bad manner, and

  

was warned that if another complaint was made against him his name
would be changed from Michael to Dennis.</p>

<p>Having come off victor in shock number one, Sadipe was given
shock number two at exactly 12:15. He was now on the train going
South. It was rapidly nearing the Virginia line, where the metamorphosis 
of the colored people begins, when the conductor, with a scowl
on his face, approached him and took his ticket. "Here," he said,
gruffly, "you belong in the darkies' kyar; this heah kyar is for white
folks only; you must git, old man; your kyar is the last but one in the
rear; step lively, thar!" Sadipe could not believe his senses. He was
nonplussed, and he was also very angry, and he decided to fight. How,
we shall see in the next chapter.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter VII</head>   

<p>Remembering that he had purchased, as he believed, a first-class
ticket to his destination in the South, he made haste to apprise this
ungentlemanly minion of a soulless corporation that he would stand on
his rights as he understood them, as a first-class passenger.</p>

<p>"Yo' will, eh!" sneered the conductor, and with that remark he
stepped into the next car, whence he returned in a few minutes with
two able-bodied Negro porters. When the trio had gotten well into the
car the white passengers, anticipating a lot of fun, and possibly some
trouble, gathered in groups in the aisles and stood up in their seats to
see "the Nigger," as some of them expressed it, bounced into "Nigger
heaven," as the Jim Crow cars are sometimes called. Opening wide
the door of the car leading to the filthy and foul-smelling sweat-box
reserved for Negro passengers, and with the bravado and swagger of
the bully that his looks proclaimed him, the blustering underling commanded
the colored porters, one of whom was decidedly black, while
the other was quite fair, to "yank that fresh coon into the Nigro kyar,"
pointing toward Sadipe, who was now boiling over with indignation.
His African blood was at white heat, and he was the more incensed
because of the significance of this fresh insult—the bringing into the
car of two men of his own color and race to further degrade and humiliate
him at the bidding of a vulgar, ignorant and foul-mouthed
white man. He sat perfectly still in his seat and refused to budge.</p>

   

<p>"Be lively thar, now!" roared the big brute. "Yo' all take that Nigra
out'n this kyar. Yo' know ez well ez I do that he ain't got no business
in this heah kyar. This kyar's for white folk!" With this remark he
glanced toward the groups of white passengers gathered around as if
looking for a nod or a smile of approval of his superserviceable efforts
to relieve them from the disgrace and humiliation of riding in a steam
"kyar with a Nigra."</p>

<p>Sadipe now arose, and with a look of anger he said quietly but firmly:
"Conductor, I defy either you or these black men whom you have
brought here to drag me into a filthy car, which you call the 'Nigra
kyar,' to lay the weight of a finger on me. I shall not leave this car unless 
you or they kill me." And he said this so finely, so determinedly
and with such cool, calm deliberateness that the passengers (most of
whom were Northerners en route to Florida) applauded the plucky
black boy.</p>

<p>One of the porters, a strapping, handsome-faced black fellow, evidently 
ashamed of his part in the little comedy, said: "I did not come
in here with the intention of forcing you out of this car, mister. I am a
servant of this company, and I am expected to obey orders; but this is
one order <hi rend="italics">I will not obey,</hi> and I realize what a refusal to do so means."</p>

<p>The conductor glared at the manly porter and remarked: "Mr. Nigra, 
this is yo last run over this heah road."</p>

<p>"There are other roads," joined the porter, "and they do not lead to
hell." With this, he turned on his heel and went back to his car.</p>

<p>The other porter, a freckle-faced, sandy-haired specimen of the
genus African, was then ordered to take "thet Nigra out." He also refused. 
He did not seem to like the determined look in Sadipe's eye,
and then, too, neither he nor the conductor were quite sure that he was
not "loaded."</p>

<p>The blustering white bully being thus thwarted, made, or pretended 
to, some notes in a blank book and left the car. The passengers
snickered and resumed their seats. Sadipe changed his position and
thought of many things.</p>

<p>There was one interested witness to all that we have here recorded–



a white man, evidently a man of influence and culture. Just before 
the train pulled into Gordonsville, Va., he took his bag and other
belongings and came into the seat where Sadipe sat musing and
brooding over his experiences. "Excuse me," he said; "may I sit here
with you? I am afraid you are going to have some trouble, and I have
resolved to befriend you, if you will permit me."</p>

<p>Sadipe thanked him heartily for his kind interest in him and assured 
him that he was quite welcome to remain. The gentleman stooped
down, and, opening a small handbag, took out a six-shooter and deftly 
passed it to Sadipe, who understood and quickly placed the weapon
in the outer pocket of his great-coat.</p>

<p>The two then engaged in conversation and introduced themselves
to each other. The white gentleman passed his card to Sadipe. It read:
"General R. M. De Mortie, U.S.A." Sadipe wrote his name on a blank
card, "Sadipe Okukenu, West Africa." The white gentleman told Sadipe 
that he was from the West, where he commanded one of the crack
Negro regiments, and that he regarded Negro soldiers as the bravest
and best in the service. He said he had experienced enough with them
in the Civil War and in the Indian wars to satisfy him that there were
no braver men in the service.</p>

<p>While the two men were thus engaged in conversation some of the
other passengers became interested and moved up and down the aisle
of the car at intervals, as if to catch some word of the earnest 
conversation in which they were engaged, and they exchanged meaning
looks with each other. This General De Mortie observing, he lowered
his tone somewhat, and, changing the subject when the next eavesdropper 
strolled leisurely down to the ice-water tank, he asked Sadipe
for his name and place of birth.</p>

<p>"Oh!" he said; "then you are a British subject. How long have you
been in this country?"</p>

<p>Sadipe told him that he had lived here almost two years.</p>

<p>The spy heard these words; they were meant for his ears. Returning 
to his seat at the upper end of the car, he evidently communicated

  

what he heard to his companions, with whom he engaged in whispered 
conversation for several minutes.</p>

<p>"My young friend," said General De Mortie, "we are now nearing
Gordonsville. That cowardly rascal of a conductor may go out when
the train stops and bring in a lot of thugs and plug-uglies to force you
into the Negro car. If he does, and they attempt to interfere with you,
shoot the first scoundrel that lays hands on you. I will take care of the
others."</p>

<p>Sadipe felt in his pocket to make sure that the weapon was still
there, and, looking the General in the eye, he said: "I had already 
resolved, sir, to defend myself, and I assure you that I am not afraid to
die, if need be, in defense of my honor and manhood."</p>

<p>"Well said," replied the General. "Here we are; this is Gordonsville. 
Keep your eyes open and your hand on the trigger."</p>

<p>The train came to a standstill. From the window at which Sadipe
sat he saw a motley crowd of station loafers, lean, lank, hungry-looking 
poor whites; Negro men and women mingling with the crowd of
passengers, who were making their way to the train, trying to
dispose of fried chicken and green-apple pies. The poor whites were
seated on boxes of freight, barrels, trunks, anything that would support 
their lazy bodies. Across the way from the station were a half
dozen or more poor whites astride a fence, chewing tobacco and whittling 
with their jackknives pieces of pine wood. Presently the baggage
smashers came along with their four-wheeled trucks and dislodged
some of the sitters on the station platform and gathered up the boxes
and trunks and barrels and transferred them to the baggage car.</p>

<p>These stood up and yawned, and then moved their lazy, ill-clad carcases 
to another part of the platform, where they stood and gaped into
the car windows and made remarks to each other about the passengers, 
who regarded them with curiosity, some of them never having
seen before such an aggregation of shiftless, aimless white loafers and
were manifestly ashamed of the "superior race."</p>

<p>On the other side of the train, which was a long one, a number of



colored women, with trays of fried chicken, home-made biscuits and
pies of various kinds, were doing a brisk business with the hungry 
passengers within, and laughed gleefully at the witty sallies of their 
good-natured customers, who paid them liberally for their wares.</p>

<p>Just before the whistle blew the conductor came into Sadipe's car,
with a brakeman and another white man with a forbidding countenance, 
and again ordered Sadipe to go to the Negro car. He did not
appear to have sufficient courage to execute his own order. He was
manifestly a blustering coward, and demanded that the men he had
brought into the car with him should put the "Nigger" out. They started 
toward the seat occupied by Sadipe, and as they did so General De
Mortie, who was now thoroughly angry and who sat facing Sadipe,
arose and quietly informed the conductor and his accomplices that if
they attempted to carry out their purposes there would certainly be
trouble of a very serious kind. He handed the conductor his card and,
stepping up closely to him, said something that seemed to take all of
the bravado out of him, and he and his companions slunk out of the
car like whipped curs.</p>

<p>The passengers snickered as the train pulled out of Gordonsville,
and Sadipe once more found himself master of the situation. But he
sustained another shock, of which mention will be made in another
chapter.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">   

<head>Chapter VIII</head>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"And the night shall be filled with music,</l>
<l rend="indent">And the cares that infest the day</l>
<l>Shall fold their tents like the Arabs,</l>
<l rend="indent">And silently steal away."</l>
</lg>

<p>Sadipe, vexed, tired and hungry (he could not procure any food
on the train, though abundantly able to pay for it), arrived in the town
where the college was located at 6:25 that evening, and the principal
of the little school, which had been dignified by the name "college,"
came to the station to meet his distinguished pupil and to conduct him
to his own residence on campus.</p>

<p>When the train stopped, the porter passed through the car and announced 
the train would stop fifteen minutes for lunch. Some of the
hypercritical passengers wondered what kind of a lunch the train
would eat, and tittered at the colored man's remark. General De Mortie 
and Sadipe went out on the station platform together, the former
assisting the latter with his baggage.</p>

<p>The sight of a white man carrying a Negro's handbag was something
of a novelty to the particular class of white people in this locality, and
occasioned some comment. The two men stopped near the gate and
chatted for a few moments. The general remarked to Sadipe that he
had greatly enjoyed the ride from Washington, barring the annoyances



from the conductor and his crowd, and told Sadipe that he was very
glad to have made his acquaintance, and to have been of some help
to him. Just then a tall, well-built colored man, wearing gold 
eyeglasses, a black suit and a silk hat, approached, and with a courteous
bow asked if he was addressing Mr. Sadipe Okukenu. Sadipe assured
him that he was that person and the colored man said he was the principal 
of the college, and had come to the station to take Mr. Okukenu
to his house. They shook hands and Sadipe introduced him to General 
De Mortie. The three stood chatting for some moments, and while
thus engaged the trainmen called out "All aboard!" and then began a
scurrying of passengers to get aboard. Farewells were said hurriedly,
and the train moved slowly out of the station. General De Mortie shook
hands warmly with Sadipe and the college principal, and charged the
former to write him in detail as soon as he had gotten his bearings,
which he promised to do. The principal, taking up Sadipe's largest
handbag, invited him to follow. He led the way to the main entrance
to the station, where an old-fashioned family carriage stood, in charge
of one of the students. Placing the handbags in the front seat, he
opened the door of the ramshackle old vehicle and requested Sadipe
to enter, and then entering himself, closed the door and bade the
young man who acted as coachman to drive on quickly "as doubtless
our friend here is hungry." There was certainly no mistake as to that,
for Sadipe was genuinely hungry, not having tasted food since morning. 
He said he was "ravenously hungry." "Did you not bring a lunch
with you," asked the principal. "No," said Sadipe. "I supposed that I
would have no difficulty in purchasing all I wanted to eat on the train;
I was told there was a dining-car attached." The principal looked at
Sadipe and smiling pityingly said, "You are in the wrong part of the
country for that sort of hospitality. Negroes who travel in this section
are not permitted to enter the dining-cars on this road. They must either 
bring their lunches or go hungry till they reach their destination.
It is too bad, Mr. Okukenu, but we have no remedy. Prejudice to color 
is a wicked thing, but we in this section have to suffer a great many
inconveniences on account of our black faces."</p>



<p>"And does this awful prejudice against black people exist in this
town? Are black people proscribed against in the eating houses and
hotels here?" asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"Why, my dear young man, if you should enter one of the public
houses here and ask for accommodation you would almost be lynched."</p>

<p>"What is that?" asked Sadipe in all innocence.</p>

<p>The principal could not suppress a smile as he answered: "Why,
they would want to hang you."</p>

<p>"And is there no law to compel these places to serve the public?"</p>

<p>"They are licensed as public places, yes, but there is an unwritten
law which operates against Negroes who attempt to make themselves
part of the public," answered the principal.</p>

<p>"This is all very strange, indeed. I had no idea that human beings
could be so intolerant of the rights of others, and all this in free 
America! I cannot understand it, sir."</p>

<p>"Neither can we," said the principal, "but we are obliged to submit
to these things because we are helpless, and can do no better."</p>

<p>"Awful! Awful!" said Sadipe, "I do not think I shall like this part of
the country."</p>

<p>They had now reached the college grounds and were entering the
road that led to the principal's house, a modest little Queen Anne 
cottage, which sat on a knoll about seven hundred yards distant from
the college buildings, and overlooking the campus. It was an ideal site
for the home of a principal, as from his eyrie in the top story he could
command a splendid view of the grounds and the gate through which
students were compelled to pass in coming in or going out from the
grounds. The boys were well aware of the fact that the professor had
the advantage of them both day and night, and therefore played few
pranks peculiar to students except when the professor was away in the
North telling northern audiences what a wonderful work he was doing
down South toward the moral redemption and regeneration of the 
colored race, and how badly he needed an endowment of $30,000 to put
it on its feet, so that it could begin the work of solving on practical
lines the race problem which is still with us. On these trips the professor



usually remained away for six or eight weeks, depending somewhat 
on the state of the money market. And then the rising generation
had six or eight weeks of solid fun. With the assistant in charge, a
rather antiquated specimen of humanity, with no particular talent for
the work entrusted to him, he was what some of the boys who still
talked slang called a "good thing; dead easy."</p>

<p>Into this cosy home Sadipe entered with his host, the principal, and
was ushered into the neat little parlor, where he sat while the principal 
went to fetch his wife and daughter, to whom he introduced the
now thoroughly hungry young man. After the usual exchange of courtesies, 
he was shown to the room he was to occupy for the night and
left to arrange his toilet for the savory supper, the odor of which filled
the halls and crept in through the keyholes of his room door. He did
quick work here, divesting himself of his soiled shirt and collar, 
removing the surplus coal dust and cinders from his ears and face. Fifteen 
minutes was all the time consumed in preparing to face that supper. 
Descending the stairs as he had been bidden to do, he re-entered
the little parlor, where he found Miss Swift and her father waiting to
escort him to the dining-room, and he gladly yielded to their courteous 
invitation to "walk downstairs." He was quite willing to run down
if they had asked it, but they didn't; so he walked.</p>

<p>The supper was a typical Southern supper, well cooked, and there
was plenty of it. Sadipe addressed himself to the pleasant task of
putting himself on the outside of as much of it as a real hungry man
who understood his business could, with decency and consistency. After 
supper he went up to the parlor with Miss Swift and asked her to
play something on the piano for him. Like a sensible girl, she sat down
to the instrument and played the "Bohemian Girl" with the skill and
technique of a veteran performer. Sadipe was charmed, and told her
he was immensely pleased, that he was passionately fond of music,
and that her playing had almost made him forget his experiences and
troubles in coming to this place.</p>

<p>"Do you play, Mr. Okukenu?" she asked, naively.</p>



<p>"Yes," he replied, "though not as well as you, Miss Swift."</p>

<p>"Please let me be the judge of that," answered Miss Swift, leaving
her place at the piano. "You will do me a great favor, Mr. Okukenu, if
you will be so good as to oblige me with a selection of your own choosing. 
Here are three or four big books of music, vocal and instrumental."</p>

<p>Sadipe sat at the piano, and picking up one of the books, running
through it hastily, his eye fell upon "The Ascription of the Evening
Star," from "Tannhauser." Opening the book, he studied it for a moment, 
and then placing it before him he played the beautiful melody
with much expression, bringing out of it a wealth of sweetness and harmony. 
While he yet played, Principal Swift and Mrs. Swift entered the
parlor and sat down near their daughter, and drank in the sweet notes
which Sadipe's deft fingers were bringing out of the piano. When he
had finished, all unconscious of the presence of Principal and Mrs.
Swift, he turned on the piano-stool to ask Miss Swift how she had liked
his performance, and then for the first time realized that he had an 
audience of three instead of one, as he had supposed. All of them were
loud in praise of his skill as a pianist. Miss Swift averred that he was
a more expert performer than she, and that she was ashamed, since
hearing him, that she had played for him first, and thought that he was
real mean not to have told her at the beginning that he could play.</p>

<p>The evening passed off pleasantly. Miss Swift recited from one or
two of her favorite authors, Dunbar and McGirt; Professor Swift sang
very sweetly "Rocked in the Cradle of the Deep" in his fine bass
voice, to the accompaniment of his daughter, and Mrs. Swift sang with
magnificent effect "Good-by" by Tosti. Sadipe, who possessed a
sweet tenor voice, sang an African love song to his own accompaniment, 
and Miss Swift looked (as she no doubt felt) quite sentimental,
and her eyes followed Sadipe during the evening until he said goodnight, 
and retired to his room for needed rest. But he did not rest, for
his mind was uneasy. Before he retired he wrote a letter to General De
Mortie, and this is what it contained:</p>



<p><hi rend="italics">Sadipe's Letter.</hi></p>

<p>–––––, S.C., 18–.</p>

<p>Dear Sir: I have scarcely been in this place twenty-four hours,
but long enough to satisfy me that I shall not be contented or happy
here. I do not like the place nor my present environment. I cannot
here breathe freely the air of freedom. Where freedom is throttled
and manacled it cannot survive, and this seems to be its condition
here.</p>

<p>The principal of this little school and his wife and daughter are
very agreeable people. The school, as I have gathered from a brief
talk with the principal, is just an ordinary school, the promoters of
which have a most extraordinary ambition to make it a college. Its
curriculum does not begin to compare with that of our little village
school in Maine, and I should have no difficulty, were I going to
remain, in passing the examination for admission to all its departments 
in about two days or less. I am disappointed and disgusted,
and I have decided to return to Maine so soon as I can communicate
with my friends there, and have advised them of the conditions
which I find here. I have received a fairly good education in Maine
and I thought to be able to get the polish on it here—vain thought.
During our conversation on the train you intimated that you had a
friend who is establishing an International Detective Bureau, and
that you thought you could influence him to employ me. I think now
that I should like to engage in this work, and I am vain enough to
believe that I have some talent for this kind of work, so if you are of
the same mind I would feel very grateful if you will use your good
offices with your friend in my behalf, and I trust that before you take
any steps in the matter you will communicate with my friends in
Maine whose names and addresses I gave you. I am now in captivity, 
humbled and humiliated, and am therefore the more anxious to
break the chains that bind me.</p>

<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
Sadipe Okukenu.</p>



<p>Two days after this letter was posted it was received by General De
Mortie with a batch of mail which awaited his return from a pleasure
trip up the beautiful St. John's River, in Florida, whither he had gone
with a party of congenial friends for an outing. He was at breakfast in
the magnificent dining-room of the famous Ponce de Leon Hotel
when the polite waiter handed him the package of letters and papers
which he had forgotten to take after an interesting chat with the clerk
at the desk in the main office, on his way to breakfast. He was just on
the point of returning for them when the waiter entered the great 
dining-hall and handed them to him. He glanced over them quickly, and
picked out two or three of them, the superscriptions on which were 
familiar to his eye; these he laid aside to enjoy their contents while he
ate. He ran through them again, as if looking for an important letter,
and laid aside two others; one of them was Sadipe's; the handwriting
was new to him and he scrutinized it critically. The letters of his name
were regular and uniform, and the writing showed character and
strength of mind. What particularly impressed him was the neatness
with which the letter had been addressed. He could not place the 
correspondent, nor could he wait even to read his good wife's letter before 
finding out the name of the writer of the letter before him. So, taking 
up his penknife, he carefully opened the envelope and satisfied
his curiosity. The letter was from Sadipe, written in faultless fashion,
and very much resembled copperplate; every "t" was crossed and
every "i" was dotted, and its whole general appearance was satisfactory 
and pleasing to the eye of the kind-hearted old general. Laying it
aside with a satisfied smile, he opened another, his wife's, read it,
made a memorandum on the margin, and placed it in his pocket. The
next one he opened was not to be so easily disposed of; it was an autograph 
letter from a great statesman in Washington, D.C., and like
Melchisidek, had neither beginning nor ending. So, at least, thought
the general. As he could make neither head nor tail of the wonderful
production, he folded it, replaced it in the envelope, and laid it aside.
His breakfast was now ready, and pushing his mail to one side he addressed 
himself to its dispatch with the vigor and energy of a man



thoroughly hungry. After breakfasting he gathered up his mail, and
taking a toothpick, sauntered leisurely to the waiting-room, where he
procured writing material and answered all save one of the batch of
letters which he had received that morning. To Sadipe he wrote:</p>

<p>St. A––––––, Fla.,– 18—.</p>

<p>My dear young friend: I am happy to receive your nicely written
letter, and to hear from you so soon after my arrival here. I was quite
sure after my talk with you on the train that a change of environment 
would not heighten your opinion of America, at least of this
part of it. I did not care to advise you at that time, but now, since
you are resolved to leave these parts, [ advise you to lose no time in
getting away. The South is a veritable hell for a man of your culture
and taste, and if you remain here you will either be compelled to
swallow your pride by submitting to further indignities, or fight.
I am very busy this morning, but [ will take the time to write to my
friend in your behalf, and will urge him to give you a position.
A man of your spirit and talents has no business in the South.</p>

<p>Your friend,<lb/>
H. B. De Mortie</p>

<p>P.S.—I will see to it that you get the position. H.B.D.</p>

<p>Saturday morning's mail brought Sadipe the general's letter, which
he read eagerly and placed in his pocket. Professor Swift came for him
about 11 o'clock for a walk through the town, which he had expressed
a desire to see. A half hour's walk sufficed. He had seen enough to
strengthen his purpose to shake the dust of that town off his feet. White
men and even children whom the two had met in their walk stared at
him and alluded to him as "a new coon," "buck nigger," "a shade,"
and other choice terms peculiar to a class of whites in the South. The
professor cautioned him to pay no attention to these insults, as if he
did there would be trouble. Then it was that Sadipe proposed that they
return to the school grounds. He was boiling within, and it seemed
that he must speak or burst. But he forebore, survived the ordeal until

 

safely within the school grounds, when he told the professor very
frankly what he thought of the town and the people in it, with whom
he had come in contact, and expressed surprise that a man of his education 
and training could so long submit to such brutal and cowardly 
insults as had been heaped upon them in the few moments they had
been thrown in contact with the white people.</p>

<p>"We were better dressed than any white man or boy that we met in
our walk," said the professor, "and our prosperous appearance angered 
them. The poor whites here are lazy and shiftless, and all of
them have the idea that they are superior to a Negro, no matter how
ignorant they may be. They know that you are a stranger hereabouts,
that you are different in manners from the everyday, ordinary Negro
they meet, and that accounts for their display of bad manners. I never 
pay attention to them. I go on and attend to my business and do not
notice them any more than if they were not on earth."</p>

<p>"For my own part," said Sadipe, "I would never submit to such 
indignities as were offered us this morning without making a vigorous
protest."</p>

<p>"Which would mean a riot," said the professor. "A black man has not
only to swallow his pride, but all the insults the white people choose
to heap on him."</p>

<p>"Indeed," said Sadipe, shaking his head, "there are some queer
things going on in your country, professor."</p>

<p>The following Saturday Sadipe took part in the exercises in the
chapel, and very greatly surprised and astonished the faculty, the students 
and visitors, and this is how he did it:</p>
 
</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter IX</head>

<p>There was the usual hurry and bustle among the students to attend 
the special missionary meeting in the college chapel, which had
been hastily arranged by Professor Swift for Saturday morning, 11
A.M. A returned missionary who had spent many years in Western
Africa, Rev. Silas Skinner, of the M.E. Church South, was in the city,
and the local pastor had expressed a desire to have him address the
students to tell them something of his experiences among their heathen 
brethren in Africa. The principal was greatly interested in the
missionary, the more so since he had among his students a real live
African, whom he thought would be glad to hear from home, and so he
readily assented to the plans of Dr. Givin to hold this special meeting
for their benefit.</p>

<p>Promptly at 10:30 the students began to assemble, and soon filled
the benches, which were arranged semicircle that they might all get
a focus on the distinguished visitor. The girls occupied the seats on
the left, the young men those on the right. After they had all been 
comfortably seated, the principal, followed by Dr. Skinner, the local pastor 
of the white Methodist Church, Rev. Mr. Givin, and the assistant
principal, stepped from a side door opening upon the platform and
took seats. Some of the girls had placed two large vases containing
magnolias, wild roses and honeysuckle on the speaker's desk, and the
air was fragrant with the odor of these flowers.</p>

 

<p>At a signal from the principal the College Glee Club took up its 
position on the platform and sang very sweetly the coronation; at its 
conclusion the principal offered prayer, after which the assistant principal 
read the Scripture lesson. The Glee Club sang another selection,
and then Dr. Skinner was introduced in fulsome phrase by the principal. 
Dr. Skinner was well named; he was a tall, lank, gawky specimen 
of the Southern white man, who in slavery days might have been
taken for an overseer or a Negro trader. He had the high cheek bones
which distinguish the mountaineers of Kentucky; a heavy-set under-jaw, 
which indicated bulldog tenacity; steel gray eyes, and a voice like
a foghorn. No Southern Negro talked a broader dialect than Rev. Dr.
Skinner. He spoke with a drawl, as Southerners who address Negro
audiences usually do, and with much looseness of statement and self-confidence.</p>

<p>His talk was of the stereotyped kind. Much was said of the wonderful 
achievements of the white Christians of America in foreign
lands, of the wisdom of God in directing men everywhere to turn their
thoughts toward Africa, China, and Japan, and the islands of the sea,
by inference intimating that if He had not put it into the hearts of the
"all-powerful white race" to stretch hands across the sea and lift up
these people they would all be eternally lost. He alluded to the Cimmerian 
darkness which overshadowed Africa, particularly of the ignorance 
and superstitions of its peoples, and the great responsibility
which their condition placed upon the "favored race," to whom Almighty 
God had delivered the message and upon whom he imposed
the duty of lifting these black heathen, who were degraded and benighted, 
up to the light of truth. What the white man has done for the
Negro in America he can and must do for the Negro in Africa—give
him civilization, teach him morality, educate his head, heart, and
hand, and thus make him useful to his kind.</p>

<p>He concluded his address by requesting the Glee Club to sing Bishop 
Heber's hymn, "From Greenland's Icy Mountains," which it did.
Principal Swift opened the discussion which followed, and commended 
the speaker's zeal and interest as well as the self-sacrificing



spirit he had shown in going thousands of miles away from home to
teach black men how to find Jesus, to carry the message of good-will
and brotherhood to those who sit in darkness. Several of the students
spoke expressing a desire to go into the missionary field and do what
they could to enlighten and lift up their brothers in Africa when they
had finished their education. The principal called upon Sadipe to say
a word, and in an aside to Dr. Skinner proudly told him that the young
man was a native of Africa. Dr. Skinner looked uneasy, and shifted
rather nervously in his seat.</p>

<p>As Sadipe arose to speak their eyes met, and there was fire and several 
other things in the young African's eyes when he stepped out from
the front row of benches and advanced to within two feet of the platform. 
Looking Dr. Skinner squarely in the eye, he said: "Mr. Chairman," 
and said it in a clear, ringing voice, which indicated that there
was going to be an eruption. Dr. Skinner leaned back in his chair and
averted his eyes. Sadipe advanced a few paces further to the front,
where he could get a good focus on the missionary, who was now getting 
uncomfortably red in the face, and continuing his remarks said:
"I do not think, Mr. Chairman, that I care to discuss the address delivered 
by this excellent gentleman; it would take too long, even if I
were inclined to do so. Many of his statements about Africa and its
people are erroneous and misleading; some of them unworthy of serious 
thought, but I will say this much: that the so-called 'heathens' of
Africa are not nearly so barbarous and inhospitable to the stranger
within their gates, nor are they as inhuman and bloodthirsty as the 
so-called civilized white Christians of the South, who burn Negroes at the
stake and hang them from trees and telegraph poles, as I have learned
that they do, since my sojourn in this country. The African, heathen
or civilized, is hospitable and generous to strangers. Your white Christians 
whom I have met in this section are most inhospitable and insulting to
strangers if their faces, like mine, happen to be black. I am
at a loss to understand why the white Christians of America, with all
their prejudices to race and color, persist in sending missionaries to
Africa and the islands of the sea to civilize and Christianize the 



'heathen,' as we are called, when there are so many heathen at their own
doors who need the light of the Gospel, and to be taught good manners. 
But, as I remarked a moment ago, I do not intend to go into the
details of this remarkable address. As a loyal and patriotic African it
is my duty to say, in all courtesy and kindness, that your speaker's
characterization of my people as barbarous and ignorant is not absolutely 
correct.</p> 

<p>"I wish now to speak briefly of the hymn which we were asked to
sing at the close of his remarks, and which I did not join in singing 
because it is an insult not only to Africans but to Greenlanders and others 
whom it describes as 'heathens,' whose faces are red, black, brown
or yellow—all the so-called weaker races, whose weakness consists
in being unlike the Anglo in that they do not covet their neighbors'
goods and are not engaged in cruel warfare to extend their power,
reaping where they have not sown, and spreading desolation and woe
with the battleship, the maxim and other death-dealing instruments.
The weakness of these races will prove the sources of their greatest
strength when the awakening of nations, which is fast approaching,
takes place. No black man who understands the meaning of words
can sing this hymn and retain his self-respect. It is written, as you who
listen to me may know, by Bishop Heber. It is a hymn written from the
Anglo-Saxon standpoint, and it does not conceal the ego which inspired 
it and keeps it alive. It is a hymn imbued with the spirit of
boasting. It is written for a race at a time when human slavery dulled
the consciences of men. It was not written for all humanity, but for a
part of it.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter X</head>

<p>"It must be quite as absurd for a Greenlander 
as for an African to sing it and make melody in their hearts to the Lord.
The lips of the Greenlander and the African may sing it, but their hearts
and their intelligence would not accept it. It is written for lips that are
neither Greenlandine nor African. It was written to stir up the missionary 
zeal of the Anglo-Saxon. It was not written to infuse inspiration
or supply aspiration or zeal to the Negro or Greenlander. While we observe 
that the license of poetry did not brush away the ice from Greenland's 
mountains, the natural condition placed there by the Creator of
races and humanity, while the spirit of poetry did not fail to discover
that dark Africa is a libel, and that only sunshine Africa can produce
sunny fountains, and while the natural riches of the country, the 'golden 
sand,' the 'ancient rivers,' the 'palmy plains' come with a panorama
of grace hard to be denied, the offset on the side of man was equally
repelling. Africa and India, two great historic peoples, were the objects
of song, and the 'spicy breezes' of Ceylon were also carefully conjured
up, but can the African or Indian or Greenlander say:</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"'They call us to deliver</l>
<l>Their land from error's chain.'</l></lg>

<p>"Who calls? Whose land? Thank God that every prospect pleases;
but is man really and only vile? Is the Indian, African or Greenlander

 

only vile? Common courtesy would forbid such an aspersion, but race
pride is the most irreligious, uncivil and unreasoning thing in the
world. We are grateful that the gifts of God are strewn with lavish kindness 
everywhere in Africa; but is heathenism confined to Africa? If
the heathen in his blindness bows down to wood and stone, what do
the Anglo-Saxon Roman Catholics do with images and idols in their
churches? Would it be wrong to say the Anglo-Saxon Romish Christian, 
whose 'souls are lighted with wisdom from on high,' in their wisdom 
'bow down to wood and stone'?</p>

<p>"The other verses speak for themselves. I have merely called your
attention to the libelous and insulting character of this white man's
missionary hymn, and hope that it will never again be sung by Negroes 
in this chapel."</p>

<p>With this parting shot Sadipe sat down, and Dr. Skinner rose up.
All eyes were fixed on him, even Professor Swift saw a new light. The
shot fired by the young African had gone home, and it hit the mark.
The missionary from Africa, his face flushed and his eyes snapping,
showed that he felt the keen thrusts of the young student, but he was
too diplomatic and too much of a white man to publicly acknowledge
that a Negro had worsted him in argument. He coughed up a smile, a
sickly, hectic smile, and taking an attitude said:</p>

<p>"It has given me very great pleasure to be with you this morning,
and I feel very grateful to your principal for the honor of an invitation
to speak to you young Negroes. I was particularly interested in the
remarks of the last speaker, who, I am told by your principal, is an
African, a native African. He is a very able and logical speaker, and
he gives promise of becoming an orator of no mean ability. His remarks 
were very interesting and very instructive, and I am sure that
all of you enjoyed them as much as I did. I hope to have the pleasure
of addressing you again at some future time and of hearing this young
man speak. I regret that I cannot remain to hear other addresses, because 
I have another appointment to speak, and I am going to ask your
principal to permit me to withdraw, though not before thanking you
most heartily for your generous attention." The principal smiled his



assent, and, rising, escorted Drs. Skinner and Givin to the street door
and gracefully bowed them out. There were only two other brief addresses, 
but they were pointed and peppery, disclosing the fact that
Sadipe had not wrought in vain. The meeting soon adjourned and the
students went to their several rooms, or lingered about the campus until 
dinner time.</p>

<p>The local newspaper, <hi rend="italics">The Evening Scimitar</hi>, issued an extra about
1:30 or 2 o'clock about the size of a theatre programme, which purported 
to contain a full report of the meeting and of the several addresses 
there delivered. Although there had been no representative of
the paper present, there was a very fair account of the proceedings,
with a left-handed compliment to the Glee Club and some remarks
about the natural gifts of the Negro in the direction of music. Then in
a double-column, double-leaded article of a quarter of a column,
with a big scare head, was given extracts from Sadipe's address,
which was followed by an editorial, also double-leaded, the tenor of
which was that "higher education is not good for Negroes, as it makes
them uppish and impudent to their superiors and raises false hopes
in their minds about equality, and also gives them false notions and
ideas of their importance. The extracts from an address by a young
darkey at the darkey college this morning, which we are publishing in
another column of the <hi rend="italics">Scimitar</hi>, will, we think, open the eyes of the
thinking white men of this section to the importance of the fact that
the best possible education for the darkey is that comprehended in
the three Rs, and not too much of that."</p>

<p>When the <hi rend="italics">Scimitar</hi> reached the campus numbers of students were
there gathered in groups of two and three discussing Sadipe's speech.
They were unanimous in the opinion that it was a good speech, and
said so among themselves. When they read the <hi rend="italics">Scimitar</hi> they were
more convinced that the speech was all right, because that paper insinuated 
that it was all wrong. The white people of the town talked
about it for days. The principal saw danger ahead for his school, and
became convinced after many talks with leading white citizens who
had approached him on the subject that the young man ought not to

  

have been allowed to make such an address. One white man was frank
enough to aver that no Negro had a right to call into question any statement 
made by a white man. But the horse was now out of the stable.</p>

<p>In trying to explain it away to these white people the principal made
a mess of it. He could not tell them why he had not asked the young
man what he was going to say, and they were not satisfied with his
statement that he had not thought it necessary to ask him, since the
meeting was not political but religious in character, for an outline of
his speech.</p>

<p>He was told that he should have warned this young darkey of the
strained relations between the races in the town, and advised him to
say nothing that would be likely to give offense to the white people.
The idea of a darkey questioning the veracity of a white man! This was
a serious offense, and the white people of that community would not
tolerate anything of the kind.</p>

<p>The principal was <hi rend="italics">sore</hi> distressed. Here was trouble all around him
and in the distance, and he was not happy by any means. But we will
leave him to fight it out his own way.</p>

<p>When Sadipe left the chapel he went direct to the principal's house,
where he found a letter and a telegram awaiting him from his friend,
General De Mortie. The latter advised him that the position he sought
with the International Detective Bureau would be given to him, and
that letter followed. The letter told him that he had been appointed
special representative of this bureau, that he must leave at once for
New York City and meet General De Mortie at the Grand Union Hotel 
in two days from its receipt, when he would introduce him to the
chief of the bureau, who was then on his way from England, and who
was scheduled to reach New York on the same day Sadipe was expected to arrive.</p>

<p>A good-sized bank note was enclosed in General De Mortie's letter
to Sadipe, with his compliments, with the message that, "Philosophers
seldom have any money."</p>

<p>Sadipe said nothing to any one about his good fortune, but he quietly 
got together his effects and prepared for the journey northward.



As he had only two days to reach New York, he decided to leave the
town at midnight on the midnight train. He had heard of the row which
his remarks had caused, had read quotations from them in the 
<hi rend="italics">Scimitar</hi>, and he realized that if he remained among these people there
would be trouble. He chose, therefore, to go.</p>

<p>When the principal came to supper that evening he passed up to
Sadipe's room, an unusual thing for him, and found the young man
busy packing his grip.</p>

<p>"Why, what's up, young man?" he asked.</p>

<p>"O, nothing special. I am just preparing to return to the North. That
is all," answered Sadipe.</p>

<p>Under different circumstances this explanation would have called
for a vigorous protest from the principal, but he was too shrewd and
crafty a man to offer an objection in this case, and it would not have
mattered if he had. The very thing Sadipe was preparing to do voluntarily 
was the thing which a committee of white citizens had that
forenoon urged the principal to compel him to do under penalty of
losing the annual State appropriation for his school, some eight hundred 
or nine hundred dollars, which they assured him would not be
forthcoming if this darkey was allowed to remain, and so this cowardly 
principal had gone to Sadipe's room to break this news gently to him
and urge him to leave town.</p>

<p>"So you are really going to leave us, Mr. Okukenu?" he asked, in a
tone of mock regret.</p>

<p>"Yes, sir; I am. I could not think of remaining in a place where there
is so much of the spirit of the devil and so much unreasoning race prejudice."</p>

<p>"Well," said the principal, "I do not blame you for going, for, as you
say, there is a great deal of prejudice, and it is a bad place for a man
of spirit like yourself. For you to remain here longer would mean that
sooner or later you would be assassinated or lynched by some white
tough or by a mob. The white people are aroused over your remarks
today in answer to Dr. Skinner. You have stirred them up, and the
<hi rend="italics">Scimitar</hi> is fanning the flames. I don't want you to go, Mr. Okukenu,

   

and yet I do not want you to stay. You are too manly and courageous
to be murdered for opinion's sake, and this I am sure will be the sequel 
of today's meeting if you remain."</p>

<p>"Indeed, is it really as serious as that?" asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"Yes," answered the principal. "You do not understand these Southern 
whites as we who were born among them do. We who are indigenous 
to the soil know them as they know themselves."</p>

<p>Sadipe opened his hand-bag, and taking therefrom the revolver which
General De Mortie had given him on the train, examined it carefully
and placed it in an outer pocket of his coat. "Professor," said he, "I
am leaving this place at midnight. Can you arrange to get my traps to
the station in time for the 12:47 train?"</p>

<p>This announcement took the load completely off the principal's mind,
and he told Sadipe that he would have one of the students drive him
to the station at any hour he wished, and that there was an earlier train
that left at 10:32, an express that went right through to Washington,
making only one stop.</p>

<p>"Then I will take that train," said Sadipe. "Kindly see that my bags
are removed to the lower floor, and that your carriage is ready for my
departure at 9:30."</p>

<p>"Young man, I am very sorry you are going from here," said the
principal. "Indeed I am, but I cannot conscientiously advise you to
remain. You will need some money. Will you accept this bill?"</p>

<p>"Thank you; no," said Sadipe. "I am well supplied with funds, and
I could not accept charity."</p>

<p>"Oh, I didn't mean that," said the professor, who saw his mistake.
"You misunderstand me. I meant it as loan, assuming, of course, that
your finances are at a low ebb."</p>

<p>"I greatly appreciate your kindness," said Sadipe; "but I must even
refuse to accept a loan. You know Shakespeare says, 'Neither a borrower 
nor a lender be.' I have quite enough to carry me to my destination 
and a little over."</p>

<p>"I am glad to hear that," said the principal. "Well, I will have the
carriage ready for you at 9:30. Let us now go to supper." Sadipe put




on his collar and followed to the dining-room, where he ate a hearty
supper. After supper he went to the parlor and amused himself playing
 on the piano until the carriage was announced. His bags and boxes
were hastily bundled into it, and a big box of lunch was given him by
the principal's wife, containing sufficient food for at least four days'
journey. He said his good-byes to the household and beamed meaningly 
full upon the principal's pretty daughter, who proffered her hand
just as he was about to step into the old ramshackle family carriage.
Grasping the extended hand, he shook it warmly, and said good-bye,
and took his place beside the principal, and was driven rapidly to the
station, arriving there within fifteen minutes. After attending to the
purchase of his ticket and the checking of his baggage, he was ready
when the lumbering express train rolled into the station to shake the
dust of that town off of his feet and turn his face northward. He bade
the young man who drove him to the station a hasty good-bye, at the
same time pressing a crisp new $2 bill into his hand as he left the carriage 
with the principal, who saw him get on the train and who also
shook his hand with more than usual warmth, and said good-bye with
an unction which concealed more than it revealed.</p>

<p>At 12 o'clock that night the principal stood in his nightrobe at an
open parlor window facing an infuriated mob of white men and half-grown 
boys, and was saying to it: "Gentlemen, upon my word of honor, 
the man is not here. I expelled him from this school today, and he
left town tonight."</p>

<p>"Well, you open thet do', Mr. Nigger," said a coarse white brute in
the crowd, "and let us see if thet coon is raley gone as you say."</p>

<p>"Open the do', Nigger," yelled the mob, and the door was opened
instanter. But the bird had flown, and the mob retired in disgust. The
next and succeeding chapters will tell of the great diamond robbery
and the part that Sadipe played in running down the thieves.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter XI</head>

<p>Three years have elapsed since the events herein recorded took
place, and Sadipe, our hero, has made his mark in a calling for which
nature seems to have specially fitted him.</p>

<p>From the day he entered the service of the International Secret 
Service Bureau to the hour he rounded up on foreign shore four of the
most skillful swindlers on the continent of Europe his career as a sleuth
had been an Iliad of successes. He seemed to have been spurred on,
inspired by the sneering allusion to himself by Captain De Forrest as
"that Nigger" when the superintendent had told the captain he was
going to detail him to the case about which they had talked. On that
day Sadipe had registered a vow that he would make a record that
would compel the narrow-gauged American sea captain to own the
force of the Negro's genius and to acknowledge that he is a man.</p>

<p>After Captain De Forrest had purchased the diamond, of which we
have already spoken, from Mojola he placed it in his strong box in his
cabin, and on his return from South Africa to London he consulted
friends who knew much about such things, and on their advice took
the stone to the well-known firm of Cheltenham, Sykes &amp; Co., 
lapidaries and wholesale jewelers to the trade, to be cut and polished. This
was one of the most reliable firms in London, and in order that Captain 
De Forrest might have no difficulty in transacting his business
with this firm his friend, Lord Cromartie, gave him a letter of 



introduction to Mr. Cheltenham, who introduced him to the manager, Mr.
Sykes, after they chatted for some moments together in the office. This
had the desired effect. Mr. Sykes was all attention and patience.</p>

<p>"I know," said the captain, "absolutely nothing about diamonds,
except that they have a way of sparkling in the dark and glittering in
the sunlight. Beyond this my experience of their commercial value is
as dense as my ignorance of Sanskrit."</p>

<p>After the usual exchanges of commonplaces incident upon the presentation 
of a letter of introduction from a man of Lord Cromartie's
standing and wealth, Mr. Sykes, who was an expert and recognized authority 
on diamonds, gave the captain the benefit of his large information 
and knowledge of the commercial value of the product of auriferous 
earth by subjecting the specimen shown him to every known
test to determine its quality, its geological classification and its value. 
When he had completed his examination he turned to his visitor
and said:</p>

<p>"I find this to be a perfectly flawless stone. It looks like a pure white
African diamond. As it now stands it is worth a thousand pounds sterling. 
It is a very rare species of diamond, and when it is cut and polished 
it will double its value. Sir, I do not believe that there is another 
like it in all England. May I ask where you obtained it, Captain De
Forrest?"</p>

<p>"I bought it from a black fellow in South Africa on my last voyage
out there."</p>

<p>"Ah, I see," said Sykes. "I knew it was an African stone. These
South African diamonds are the purest in the world and fetch the highest 
prices. This is certainly the largest one I ever saw."</p>

<p>The captain's eyes sparkled.</p>

<p>They soon got down to business, and the firm was given the order
to cut and polish the stone. The captain said that he was going on a
voyage to the Indies on the 15th of the month and would probably be
absent four months. He would leave the stone and get it on his return
to England. Mr. Sykes called in a notary, who drew an agreement
which stipulated that in the event of his death, proof of which was to

   

be established to the firm's satisfaction, or failure to call for the 
diamond at the time agreed upon, or within sixty days thereafter, it was
to be delivered to the person named in this agreement upon the payment 
of all charges specified herein for labor performed and for its
safekeeping.</p>

<p>As the captain was a bachelor, he made this agreement—a sort of
last will and testament—in favor of a personal friend to whom he was
very much attached, and whose name, rumor said, would some day be
changed to De Forrest. The agreement was duly executed in duplicate, 
the captain retaining a copy and paying the notarial fees, to
which Mr. Sykes objected unavailingly. He paid also four pounds ten
on account, and took a receipt, which, together with the agreement,
he placed in his big leather wallet. These details over, Mr. Sykes
wrapped the stone in raw cotton, placed it back in the box which contained 
it, and placed the box in the safe, closed the ponderous doors
and turned the combination. Then he gave the captain a receipt for
the stone which contained its weight, color, size and general appearance 
and its approximate value. The captain pulled from his pocket
three big cigars and laid them on Mr. Sykes' desk, telling him that he
would find them particularly good. Mr. Sykes loved nothing better
than a fragrant Havana, and he felt more than compensated for the
time and attention he had given the captain by this gift.</p>

<p>After the captain left the office Mr. Sykes took his knife and cut off
the end of one of the cigars and lighted it carefully. He smoked it a
few seconds and said to himself, "I should say that this is a good cigar, 
Captain; come again." He unlocked the safe, took out the captain's
diamond and stepped across the hall with it to Mr. Cheltenham's office 
to show it to him. Mr. Cheltenham was the senior member of the
firm, very rich, and was dignity personified. When Mr. Sykes opened
the office door he saw a visitor, and was in the act of withdrawing, 
fearing to obtrude.</p>

<p>"Come right in, Mr. Sykes," said Mr. Cheltenham. "I was just about
to send for you."</p>

<p>Mr. Sykes entered, and was introduced to the visitor, Colonel Ewart



George Evelyn Bradshawe, K.C.B., R.A., a gentleman of imposing
presence and many medals. The colonel was quite affable, and received 
the introduction with the quiet dignity and graciousness of
manner of the well-bred gentleman, and sat down.</p>

<p>"Colonel Bradshawe has just come to consult us about a stone
which he has purchased on 'spec,'" said Mr. Cheltenham.</p>

<p>"Oh, I see," said Mr. Sykes. "Let's take a look at the sparkler, Harry. 
Have you examined it?"</p>

<p>"No," said Mr. Cheltenham. "I was just on the eve of sending for
you when you came in. Here it is. I wish you'd test it. It looks all right,
but I am afraid it isn't, as I have said to the Colonel."</p>

<p>"Suppose you gentlemen step into my room," said Mr. Sykes, rising 
and leading the way. This room was a combination of office and
workshop. It contained shelves, bottles of chemicals, queerly constructed 
scales, and in one corner a quantity of quartz. Near the window 
a big desk, and two chairs, and a wooden bench. The gentlemen 
entered and were given seats, and Mr. Sykes proceeded at once
to subject the stone to a test. First he weighed it, the result was not
satisfactory—a stone of its size should be heavier. Next he took a polished 
diamond from the safe, which was of the same physical conformation 
and the same size, and weighed them separately. Colonel
Bradshawe's diamond weighed three karats less than the other. Mr.
Sykes shook his head.</p> 

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">
   
<head>Chapter XII</head>
 
<p>Then he submitted it to another test
known to diamond experts, and still found it wanting. Whereupon he
frankly but delicately informed its owner that the thing was glass.</p>

<p>"What you say, it is glass?" asked the Colonel, eagerly.</p>

<p>"It is nothing else, except that it is a good imitation."</p>

<p>The Colonel affected to be very much put out by the discovery, and
said he had been deliberately robbed by the man from whom he purchased 
the stone. "It is a very fine imitation of a genuine diamond,"
said Mr. Sykes, "and that is as near as it is to being a diamond. There
are great quantities of these on the market now. They come from
France, where they are sold by the bushel."</p>

<p>"I purchased it from a French sailor for 10 pounds sterling," said
the Colonel, "and I thought I had a bargain."</p>

<p>"No," said Mr. Sykes; "it was the sailor who got the bargain. He was
a very lucky man to get so much money for such a cheap piece of
glass." And, going to the safe, where he had placed the Captain's uncut 
diamond when he came from Mr. Cheltenham's room, he took it
out and, exposing it to the Colonel's view, said: "here is a diamond
worth owning. It is the most perfect uncut stone I have ever handled."</p>

<p>"Oh, by the way, gentlemen, what are your charges for making this
test? I beg your pardon for interrupting you, Mr. Sykes," said the
Colonel.</p>

<p>"We only charge <hi rend="italics">for testing diamonds</hi>, Colonel, and since this is



glass, there will be no charge," said Mr. Sykes, in his politest tones.
Reverting again to the Captain's diamond, he produced a stone about
the size of an English walnut, which he said had just been left by a
gentleman to be cut and polished, and which in its present state was
worth at least a thousand pounds if it was worth a penny.</p>

<p>"Whew!" exclaimed Mr. Cheltenham.</p>

<p>"Good gracious!" chimed in the Colonel. "It must be a fine one!"</p>

<p>"It is," said Mr. Sykes, holding it up between his thumb and forefinger. 
"It is a pure white South African stone. I have examined it carefully, 
and there isn't a flaw in it. This greatly enhances its value. It is
one of the largest clear white stones I have ever seen. When polished
it will be one of the most valuable stones in the United Kingdom. I do
not believe its equal will be found for years to come in all the world."</p>

<p>"Pray who is the Croesus to whom this valuable and priceless
gem belongs?" asked Colonel Bradshawe innocently. And before he
could think Mr. Sykes had given the name of the owner of the stone.</p>

<p>"Indeed!" said the Colonel. "I know the Captain well. I met him at
one of the receptions of the Governor General in India some three
years ago. Fine old fellow he; deucedly clever and rich beyond the
dreams of avarice. Well he can afford diamonds of that size."</p>

<p>Mr. Sykes felt some relief when he learned that the Colonel and the
Captain knew each other, and for the moment thought no more of his
bad break in revealing the name of a patron to a comparative stranger.
Mr. Cheltenham and the Colonel then had a look at the stone, examined 
it closely, noted its weight and decided that it was just what Mr.
Sykes said it was—a rare and valuable stone. Then Mr. Sykes took it,
placed it in its bed of raw cotton in the box from which he had taken
it, and, putting it carefully into the safe, closed the door and turned
the combination.</p>

<p>The Colonel's visit was cut short by the entrance of other callers on
business and after returning his thanks to Messrs. Cheltenham and
Sykes for courtesies shown him, he bade them good-morning with an
unctuousness which Mr. Sykes, who knew a few things about human
nature, noted and remembered.</p>

  
  
<p>When Colonel Bradshawe got outside the great establishment he
collected his wits and did some thinking. One of the important things
he did was to inscribe in his notebook the name of the owner of the
diamond he had been permitted to see. His next move was to locate
Captain De Forrest, to ascertain the name and whereabouts of his
ship, whither she was going, if she had not already sailed, and when
she would return to this port. He walked rapidly, and was soon at the
door of his humble lodgings, entering which he found his confederates 
awaiting him, to whom he gave a detailed account of his morning's 
work and his failure to dispose of his "spurious diamond." One
of the party was a beautiful English girl with sparkling black eyes and
lips that were the color of a ripe Delaware peach that has been kissed
by the sun. To her he said: "You must find this Captain De Forrest."
She understood and in less than an hour she was on his trail.</p>

<p>It was Machiavelli who said: "Men are so simple and yield so much
to necessity that he who will deceive will always find him that will
lend himself to be deceived."</p>

<p>With consummate judgment, Colonel Bradshawe laid his plans,
and thus far they had been worked out with a cleverness and skill
which had been as brilliant and successful in execution as they were
bright in conception.</p>

<p>His male chum and confederate, Algernon Hodder, was directed to
locate the captain's ship. This was an easy task, since all vessels that
entered port are required to register, giving name of master and owner, 
where from, character of cargo, etc. So Hodder went out next morning, 
and was absent just two hours by the clock. When he returned he
brought this memorandum: "'The Norris K. Peters,' Captain Geo.
De Forrest, master, American merchant vessel, trading in East Indies,
sails September 15 on six months' voyage; captain boards at Royal
Arms, is rich, fond of good wine, pretty women and curios." Hodder
passed the "memo" to Colonel Bradshawe, who read it aloud, remarking 
that he commended the captain's good taste in preferring the
company of pretty women and for liking good wine. This was a great
combination, "by Jove." Whereat all the party joined in a hearty



laugh, and before the echoes of it had died away Miss Crenshawe, who
had been sent on a similar mission to that of Hodder, entered the room
and reported progress. She had located The Royal Arms, and had
found out several other useful things. Colonel Bradshawe then called
them all around him and laid before them his plans to entrap De Forrest, 
which was as follows: Miss Crenshawe was to be sent to The Royal 
Arms daily for luncheon, and in the most aristocratic turnout to be
found in London. She was quietly to learn all she could about the captain, 
his habits, etc., and, if possible, to get up a flirtation with him.
This plan was at once decided on as the first step, and was to go into
operation the next day.</p>

<p>Now, The Royal Arms was one of the new fashionable hotels of London 
that employed a black waiter, in compliment to its American patrons, 
who made it their habitat during the London season, and
Sadipe, our hero, who was not ignorant of the plot which had been
hatched to rob Captain De Forrest, had communicated to his chief his
desire to be placed in this menial position. Accordingly a representative 
of the bureau called on the proprietor of The Royal Arms, and,
after explaining the object of his call, asked that Sadipe be thus employed. 
The request was immediately granted, and on the following
day Sadipe was installed as a waiter. He knew as much of waiting
as a boy, but he was quick to learn, and he did learn several of the little 
tricks of the profession, and in about a week was as obsequious a
dining-room genuflector as could be found in all London.</p>

<p>On the day that Sadipe took service at the Royal Arms Miss Crenshawe 
made her appearance at the noonday luncheon of this fashionable 
hotel. She arrived at the hostelry on the hour, in a handsome equipage, 
with liveried coachman and footman. When the vehicle stopped
in front of the ladies' entrance to The Royal Arms there stepped from
it a gorgeously attired lady in silks and laces and glittering jewels,
whose presence attracted the attention of the habitues. She also wore
a hat, which set off her beautiful face to advantage, and there was
something of the patrician in her queenly bearing. She walked with
dignity and grace to the door, at which stood a liveried servant, who



threw it wide open as she entered, bowing with the grace of a courtier
as she passed by on her way to the dining-hall.</p>

<p>Her cheeks were the color of June roses, and under the soft yellow
light of the huge electroliers, in the hall leading to the dining-room,
she was a picture of loveliness. Her eyes sparkled as she strode to the
table assigned to her. Guests who were returning to or going to lunch
could not resist the temptation to cast furtive glances at the beautiful
creature. One male guest who had already lunched and was leaving
the hall returned and, taking a seat at a table near that which she occupied, 
ordered another lunch and ate it slowly.</p>

<p>The Negro waiter, being something of a novelty in England, and particularly 
in The Royal Arms, was much in demand by the guests. We
will call him Randolph, because that was not his name. When Miss
Crenshawe had been comfortably seated she beamed on Randolph
sweetly, and the man who had followed her into the dining-hall looked
daggers at the black man. Randolph, who was standing in front of her
table with folded arms, awaiting her pleasure, advanced at a nod from
her and, bending sufficiently low to catch her softly spoken words,
learned that she wished for her luncheon two French chops, rolls, a
cup of coffee and—"Yes, that will be all at present." Randolph attended 
to this order promptly, and while he was away Captain De Forrest 
entered the room and went to the table which he usually occupied, 
and which was diagonally opposite that of Miss Crenshawe. He
did not at first observe the fair creature. He was busy with the shipping 
column of the <hi rend="italics">Thunderer</hi>. He laid the paper down for a moment
to make a memorandum, and his eyes wandered and fell upon the bewitching 
beauty opposite him. Picking up his paper again, he held it
so that he could see over the top of it without, as he thought, being 
observed. Presently his eye fell upon another man at a side table, who
was intently gazing in the same direction as himself, and who found
time to bestow a scowl on him. The lady was, or acted as though she
was, unmindful of what was going on in a quiet way.</p>

<p>She did not once look in the direction of either of her unknown 
admirers, and when Randolph returned with her luncheon she laid a



shining silver coin beside her plate for him, and asked him in her soft,
sweet voice to fetch her a pitcher of ice water. Randolph procured a
pitcher, filled it with cracked ice, and filled the lady's glass as deftly
as a veteran waiter could have done. "Take this; it is yours," she said,
pushing the coin toward him. Randolph took it and, thanking her with
a pretty little bow, he withdrew to a respectable distance. Presently
she raised her arched eyebrows and smiled sweetly. Randolph advanced 
toward her: "Waiter, can you tell me the name of that fat gentleman 
sitting opposite my table? He has been staring at me ever since
he entered the room. Is he the proprietor?"</p>

<p>"O, no, miss, that gentleman is a wealthy old sea captain. His name
is De Forrest, and he owns a ship called the 'Norris K. Peters.' He is
a bachelor, and stays in this hotel the year around when he is not on
a voyage." This was all said in a low tone of voice.</p>

<p>"Thank you," she said, bestowing another of her bewitching smiles
on the black man, and then she ordered another chop and a glass of
milk.</p>

<p>While Randolph was gone Miss Crenshawe, who was something of
an artist, took from her handbag a visiting card and pencil, and made
a clever outline sketch of Captain De Forrest, who had tired of gazing
upon her lovely features, and was now strenuously introducing a beefsteak 
with the concomitants into his interior.</p>

<p>When Randolph returned Miss Crenshawe finished her luncheon,
paid her bill, and swept out of the dining-hall as majestically as she
entered it. Her carriage awaited her, and she stepped into it and was
driven to her apartments.</p>

<p>As soon as she had left the room both Captain De Forrest and the
strange man plied Randolph with questions about her. Who is she?
What is her name? Where does she live? He did not know—that is,
he told them so. But he had photographed her face in his memory, and
no matter what her disguise in future, he would know her. He had seen
her before, and he was sure that he would see her again.</p> 
 
</div2>



<div2 type="chapter"> 
      
<head>Chapter XIII</head>    
  
<p>Hodder's coup in locating the "Norris K. Peters," finding out
when she was to leave port, her destination and the habits of her master, 
was no less a brilliant piece a work for a tyro than was Miss Crenshawe's 
triumph in bearding the lion in his den and taking his picture.
She had succeeded admirably in attracting to herself the attention
which she craved of the giddy old man who was later to become as
tractable as a kitten under her hypnotic influence. And we must not
forget Randolph, the black, whose role in this little drama, about to be
enacted, was, to say the least, as difficult as it was delicate and 
dangerous, yet for which he was admirably fitted in view of the fact that
his black face disarmed all suspicion as to his true character. To this
precious quartette full of complacent conceit of their specie, he was
simply a blackie. So far as they knew he was simply a few removes
from a benighted heathen, and, unlike the Anglo-Saxon, incapable of
understanding the meaning of things said in his presence. He was quiet, 
unobtrusive, obsequious, a model servant. Hodder, who had lived
in South Africa, where Englishmen whose education is defective spell
Negro with two "gs," was wont to remark when speaking of Randolph
to his companions: "he's a well-set-up nigger, and he's deucedly polite, 
don't you know. I really like him." Before Randolph was detailed
to the Royal Arms, the manager of the bureau had called him into 
consultation, and discussed with him the details of this case, and he 
 


reminded him that since he was so versatile and resourceful, it remained
for him to make a record as a sleuth, and run down the thieves who
had stolen the diamond which Captain De Forrest doubted the ability 
of a nigger to recover.</p>

<p>"There are several persons under suspicion, Mr. Okukenu," said
the manager, "but this bureau has been unable to find a clue. It has
run down at least ten of the cleverest crooks in England, and it is 
satisfied that they knew practically nothing about the robbery of Captain
De Forrest. So that we are now convinced by certain developments of
recent occurrence that it was the work of an organized band of thieves
who knew what they were about and have skillfully covered up their
tracks."</p>

<p>"I see," said Randolph. "I called at the Royal Arms yesterday to 
see a friend of my father—an Englishman who has lived many years
in Africa, and while we sat in his room talking, a card was brought to |
him by a messenger. He read the name aloud, and told the boy to send
the person up. When the visitor entered the room, I perceived that he
was some officer of high rank, for he wore many medals and was particularly 
well groomed.</p>

<p>"'Colonel Bradshawe, I believe,' said my friend, rising and offering
his hand, which the colonel took, shaking it warmly.</p>

<p>"'Yes, that is my name, sir,' he replied.</p>

<p>"Be seated, sir,' said my friend. The colonel took an armchair. 'I
am very glad to meet you, Colonel Bradshawe,' continued my friend.
'May I ask the purpose of your visit, sir? I do not recall that we have
ever met before.'</p>

<p>"'Why, don't you remember me, Mr. Stoughton?' asked the colonel,
with a trifle too much anxiety in the question.</p>

<p>"'You certainly have the advantage of me, sir. Will you be good
enough to tell me when and where we have met before?'</p>

<p>"Why, certainly. I was introduced to you above five years ago at
reception at the Governor-General's in Calcutta, where my regiment
was at that time stationed.'</p>

<p>'"By whom, please.'</p>



<p>"'By the Governor-General himself,' said the colonel, coolly.</p>

<p>"'Ah yes, yes, I quite well remember you now. There was a lady
with you. As I recall the circumstance, a very attractive, a very beautiful 
lady, colonel. By Jove! I shall never forget her face. Was she your
wife or a relative, colonel?'</p>

<p>"'She was my w-i-f-e.'</p>

<p>"'Ah, yes. I remember now she was introduced as Mrs. Bradshawe.
Pardon my stupidity.'</p>

<p>"'Why, certainly, Mr. Stoughton. One can not be expected to keep
all the details of these social functions in one's head.'</p>

<p>"'Quite right, my dear colonel.'</p>

<p>"And changing the subject, Mr. Stoughton asked the colonel what
brought him to London at this season, and when he would return to
Calcutta.</p>

<p>"'Oh, I had some leave coming to me, and I concluded that it would
not be a bad idea to spend as much of it as I could among my kindred
and friends in dear old England.'</p>

<p>"'Is your lady with you, colonel?" asked Mr. Stoughton, innocently.</p>

<p>"And Colonel Bradshawe evidently forgetting that he had given his
'lady' the place of honor in a former answer about her, unwittingly 
answered that his friend, Miss Crenshawe, would remain in Calcutta for
some time yet.</p>

<p>"Mr. Stoughton looked at Sadipe, who was an interested listener,
and at Colonel Bradshawe, who never realized he made a decidedly
bad break, and he looked the confusion which he evidently felt. Mr.
Stoughton repeated the name Crenshawe several times, and Colonel
Bradshawe's color came and went. That he had made a tactical blunder 
was clear enough by referring to his 'lady-wife,' if she was really
his wife, as Miss Crenshawe. It put that person in the attitude of a 
mistress, and it did not speak well for the morals of either the colonel or
his lady. Mr. Stoughton recalled that some years ago there had been
printed in the <hi rend="italics">Calcutta Times</hi> a salacious story about a young woman
of the name of Crenshawe who had only recently come out from England 
and in some mysterious manner had ingratiated herself in the



confidence of a rich old man who had made an immense fortune in
Kimberley, South Africa. Such was her influence over him that he allowed 
her to pass as his daughter. Finally there was a scandal, followed 
by the discovery that the old man had been robbed of thousands
of pounds and a lot of valuable jewelry, many pieces being heirlooms
which had been in his family since the reign of Henry VIII.</p>

<p>"'I wonder,' asked Mr. Stoughton, 'if this young woman is related to
the Miss Crenshawe of whom I have spoken?'</p>

<p>"Colonel Bradshawe's face took on a deep crimson hue. He coughed
and fidgeted about in the big armchair for a second or two before he
answered. He said:</p>

<p>"'Really, Mr. Stoughton, I could not say as to that; but I do not believe 
that this young woman is related to the one to whom you allude.
I think I remember that circumstance. The woman was captured by
Scotland Yard men, and before she could be locked up she took poison 
and died a violent death within two blocks of Scotland Yard. Well,
I must be leaving now, Mr. Stoughton. I heard you were here, and I
merely called to pay my respects and to renew old acquaintance,' said
Colonel Bradshawe, rising, hat in hand, and moving toward the door.</p>

<p>"'Must you really go so soon, colonel?' asked Mr. Stoughton. 'I fear
I have bored you. Here we have been talking for almost an hour, and
I haven't given you an opportunity to say a word. Bless my soul, they
do say that we old men are garrulous; that when we get wound up we
cannot stop. Ha! ha! ha!'</p>

<p>"And Mr. Stoughton arose and extended his hand to the colonel,
who bowed himself out as graciously as he knew how. Sadipe, who had
been sitting by a window reading a copy of the <hi rend="italics">London Mail</hi>, found
time between periods to observe certain things which struck him as
being worthy of more than passing notice.</p>

<p>"'Did you ever meet this colonel before, Mr. Stoughton?' asked Sadipe, 
with a twinkle in his eye.</p>

<p>"'Well, I was just thinking about him as you spoke, Mr. Okukenu
I have an indistinct recollection of having met a colonel out in India
   


with a name sounding very like this, but he was a much stouter and
larger man than this Colonel Bradshawe. I am not sure that I have ever
met him socially, but I did not wish to embarrass him by telling him
that I did not know him. I presume he is some adventurer with a
scheme.</p>

<p>"'I did not like his answer about his wife or lady,' said Sadipe. 'A
married man never alludes to his wife by her maiden name when
speaking of her to others.'</p>

<p>"'True," said Mr. Stoughton. 'I noticed that myself, and I am the
more convinced that the man is a fraud.'</p>

<p>"'Have you a copy of the <hi rend="italics">Army Gazette</hi>?' asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"'Yes, there is one there on the shelf to the right, Mr. Okukenu,'
replied Mr. Stoughton.</p>

<p>"Sadipe reached for the ponderous tome and requested to be shown
the card of the colonel. Then he turned down two pages of the big book
carefully, but he found no such name as Bradshawe and no such regiment 
as that given on his card in India or anywhere else.</p>

<p>"'This is remarkable, Mr. Stoughton,' said Sadipe. 'I do not find the
gentleman's name in the <hi rend="italics">Gazette</hi>.'</p>

<p>"'No?' answered Mr. Stoughton.</p>

<p>"'No,' said Sadipe, 'it is not here.'</p>

<p>"'Well, I should say it is remarkable,' was the brief answer of Mr.
Stoughton.</p>

<p>"And then the conversation drifted to the West Coast. Sadipe asked
about his old father and friends of his boyhood days, and his old
teacher, who had gone out to England and returned to the West Coast.
Mr. Stoughton gave him full particulars of the most important events
which had transpired since he came away from his fatherland to tempt
fortune in the Western Hemisphere. They chatted over these things
for more than an hour, and then Sadipe took leave of his father's old
friend, promising to call again at the first convenient opportunity."</p>

<p>On his way to his lodgings he thought of Colonel Bradshawe, and
the more he thought of him the more he was convinced that he was a





counterfeit. Instead of going directly to his room, as he had intended,
he called a cab and directed the cabby to drive him to the International 
Bureau, where he found the manager up to his neck in work.</p>

<p>"Mr. Hunter," said Sadipe, "I have a clue to the De Forrest robbery."</p>

<p>Mr. Hunter looked up from the batch of papers he held in his hand
and, gazing at Sadipe, asked: "What makes you think so?"</p>

<p>"I have met today a Colonel Bradshawe, a very voluble gentleman,
who claims to have served in India."</p>

<p>"Bradshawe! Bradshawe!" repeated Mr. Hunter. "Describe him, Mr. Okukenu."</p>

<p>"I will," said Sadipe. "A man of medium height, florid complexion,
about forty years of age, auburn hair, and eyes almost blue; talks 
rapidly, and does not look you in the eye when speaking, and is rather 
reserved in manner."</p>
   
</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">    

<head>Chapter XIV</head>
 
<p>Mr. Hunter pulled out a drawer in his desk, and taking therefrom
a package, opened it, and selected a photograph from the package,
which he handed to Sadipe, and asked him if the man he had seen in
Mr. Stoughton's rooms looked anything like the man whose picture he
saw before him.</p>

<p>"Why, Mr. Hunter," said Sadipe, "this is the man I met in Mr.
Stoughton's rooms today; the very man, sir! How do you happen to have
his picture here? Is he a crook, a burglar?"</p>

<p>"Yes, he is both a crook and a burglar, and one of the most expert
cracksmen in the three kingdoms, Mr. Okukenu. There isn't a
more polished or gentlemanly swindler and confidence man in all England."</p>

<p>"Gracious," said Sadipe. "He must be the dean of the profession;
and where has this distinguished and accomplished specialist been
keeping himself that you have not been able to mingle with him in social 
alliance, Mr. Hunter? You know you somehow manage to meet all
the social lions that come to London, and I am a little surprised that
this gentleman has escaped your argus eyes."</p>

<p>Mr. Hunter made no reply to this criticism beyond laughing heartily 
at Sadipe's keen thrusts.</p>

<p>"You are sure, Mr. Okukenu, that this is the man you saw today (taking the photo from him)?"</p>



<p>"Mr. Hunter," said Sadipe, "an African, and I am told that a North
American Indian, never forget a face they have once seen. Have you
ever met this man Bradshawe, Mr. Hunter?"</p>

<p>"Oh yes; I have seen him several times."</p>

<p>"Very good," said Sadipe; "then let me make the identification more
complete, for I fear you are disposed to doubt its accuracy. This man
whom I met today has dark-gray eyes, walks with a shuffling gait, talks
with great deliberation and never looks you in the eye when conversing 
with you. There is on his right cheek a small mole, and behind
his left ear a small patch of gray hair, probably a birthmark, for he is
much too young to be turning gray; he can not be much over five and
thirty."</p>

<p>"Your supplementary description tallies exactly. You have certainly 
seen the man we have been looking for for so long a time. I am thoroughly 
convinced that the man you have seen and describe is the man
we want, and that he is not, as we have been led to believe, in France,
but is, as the journalists say, 'in our midst.'</p>

<p>"Now, since you have discovered him, Mr. Okukenu, I am going to
detail you to effect his capture, and this office will give you all the 
assistance in its power to enable you to bring about his capture. You 
ought, of course, to know something about this fellow, so that you may
go about your work intelligently. In the first place, his name is not
Bradshawe; that is one of his many aliases; his real name is Algernon 
Mandeville, and he is best known at Scotland Yard and by all our profession 
as 93,008. His photograph representing him in many disguises 
may be seen in the police headquarters of nearly all the capitals
of Europe. He is one of the smoothest, slipperiest rascals that ever
cracked a safe or picked a pocket, and he has done both and escaped
punishment, for no one has yet been able to fasten either of these
crimes upon him. He is said to be the dishonored son of a nobleman,
who himself figured in a court scandal many years ago and retired to
his country estates to live it down if possible. The boy was splendidly 
educated, and graduated with honors for the bar, but after his father's 
downfall he went to the bad and began a life of riotous living in



which wine and women played their usual parts, with the result that
young Mandeville was tabooed by his former friends, and so turned
'gentleman burglar.' He is a fine linguist, speaking French, Spanish,
Italian and German with fluency and correctness. He has been a bogus 
French count, Spanish don, Italian prince and a German Baron,
and has mingled in splendid alliance with the best blood of Europe
without discovering his real identity for months after he has played
his part, leaving behind him a trail of bad debts and unsavory stories. 
I was present at a social gathering in Vienna in the summer of
1899 at which he was a guest, though I did not then know who he
was, and I have only come to know him since by his photographs, nearly 
all of which I have seen. When the main topic of conversation was
about a disgraceful scandal in Genoa in which a certain French Count
Gevé De Alvord figured with the wife of a foreign minister who was
spending the summer there, and who lost her jewel bag and a large
sum of money after a carriage ride in the suburbs with the count, who
mysteriously left town the following day, the lady, for prudential reasons, 
could not afford to make much noise about her loss, heavy as it
was, but the facts leaked out some months after she had gone. She was
an American lady, and you know American ladies are fond of titles,
real or bogus. 'Count De Alvord' appears to be a man of discrimination 
and tact, and to have been very successful among these lion
hunters. I saw him on the occasion of which I speak listening intently 
to the recital of this incident in his career, and at its conclusion he
smiled one of those cynical smiles which are indulged in only by those
who are sure of themselves. I can never forget the expression on his
face when Baron Felderstrum, a Swedish nobleman, asked, 'Who is
this Count De Alvord? I never heard of him before.' Mandeville has
excellent control of himself. Beyond coloring slightly he betrayed no
other symptoms of alarm or fear. Taking from his pocket a large silk
handkerchief, daintily perfumed, he remarked to the lady who sat next
him, 'It is oppressively warm here, madame. Let us get nearer a window.' 
And suiting the action to the word he arose and taking the lady's
arm, escorted her to the farther end of the spacious salon, to a window



which overlooked a garden filled with choicest exotics. He was in another 
atmosphere. So, you see, my dear Mr. Okukenu, with whom you
will have to deal."</p>

<p>"Yes," replied Sadipe, "and yet I believe I shall be able to run down
this man, clever as he is."</p>

<p>"Very good, very good," said Mr. Hunter. "Tomorrow you shall have
a trial of your skill as a sleuth. If you round up Mandeville, your 
reputation as a thief catcher will be made, and you will be able to command 
the largest fees paid to the profession in the United Kingdom."</p>

<p>"Tomorrow didst thou say, Horatio?" said Sadipe, with a merry
twinkle in his eye. "I will make the preliminary trial tonight. I will 
locate this versatile and thrifty gentleman, and will thereafter camp on
his trail until he is safely landed behind the bars."</p>

<p>"Good! Good!" said Mr. Hunter. "I have every confidence in your
ability and in your judgment. You Africans have many advantages
over us Europeans, and there are some things which you can do better 
than we when you try. Your black face will be an important aid in
the capture of Mandeville (if you capture him), and your knowledge
of French will come in handy, for in the presence of strangers he always 
converses in that language, and he will never suspect that you
understand that tongue."</p>

<p>Sadipe smiled, and rising, bade Mr. Hunter good night.</p>

<p>Our hero went forth from the presence of his chief with a fixed 
determination to locate "Colonel Bradshawe," and ultimately capture
him. The insulting words of Captain De Forrest, "You don't mean to
say that you are going to turn this case over to that nigger," still rung
in his ears, and he renewed his vow to make the Yankee captain acknowledge 
the force of his genius as a sleuth, not only by capturing
the thief who had stolen the diamond which he had lost, but by recovering the diamond itself.</p>

<p>In four hours after leaving Mr. Hunter's office Sadipe, disguised as
an African student, of which at that time there were many in London,
pursuing their studies in the law and medicine, strolled into one of the
many music halls of the great metropolis to enjoy the singing, and 

   

<sic>incidently</sic> to get a little refreshment. Sitting down at a table in the rear
of the great hall, a pretty English barmaid hastened to him to learn his
wishes. He ordered some crackers and a mug of ale, which he sipped
slowly, occasionally munching a cracker to kill the bitter taste of the
ale, of which he was not overfond, but which he drank on the advice
of his physician, more as a strength-giving tonic than as a beverage.
He had gotten into the hall just before the orchestra began its part of
the elaborate program arranged for the evening. The only song he
heard (and he was particularly fond of vocal music) was De Lara's
beautiful song, "The Garden of Sleep," which was admirably rendered
by a buxom English lassie with wonderfully red cheeks (suspiciously
red) and a voice of remarkable volume and purity, which penetrated
every corner of the great hall. When the last note died out, the audience 
rose to its feet and applauded the singer so vociferously that she
responded with an <hi rend="italics">encore</hi>, Lassen's "All Souls' Day," which evoked as
much applause as the former song. Sadipe ordered another mug of ale,
and started the applause afresh, and kept at it so industriously and
energetically that the now overworked soloist gave "Within a Mile of
Edinboro Town." The audience was enraptured, thrilled, charmed,
delighted, and clamored for yet another song from the fair singer. But
the manager, as soon as she had finished this song, quickly advanced
to the front of the platform and announced that the orchestral concert
would now begin, and read from a slip, which he held in his hand, the
numbers which it would play. Among them were included: "Hoch Hapsburg," 
J. N. Kral; "Dans Tes Yeux," E. Waldtenfelt; Waltz, "Bleue," Margis; 
March, "Crusader," Sousa; "Queen of the North," Bucallassi; "Irish
Patrol," Puerner; March, "Punjaub," G. Payne; Waltz, "Greek Slave," S.
Jones; Finale, "God, Save the King."</p>

<p>Each number was well executed. The orchestra was composed of Englishmen, 
East Indians, Africans, and one Russian. The audience, a
large one, representing many races and classes of society, enjoyed this
part of the program immensely, judging from the manner each number 
was received and applauded by it. Even Sadipe joined in the general 
acclaim. When "God, Save the King" was played the audience

  

rose to its feet, and part of it sang the words of this particular air.
Standing in a front seat in the first gallery, near the stage, was "Colonel
Bradshawe" in military uniform, and a few of his many medals, a vizorless 
cap in his hand, and the inevitable monocle. Sadipe got a
glimpse of him, then a full view, then a quarter view.</p>

<p>"I have him," he said to himself; "no matter how he dresses or
disguises himself, I can never forget that face. Where I see it I will
know it."</p>

<p>When the orchestra ceased playing, the audience passed out. Sadipe, 
whose seat was near the door, sat down until the crowd thinned
out, and passed out just as those from the upper floors were going out.
As "Colonel Bradshawe" came down the stairs Sadipe stood a little to
the side of the main entrance, where he could get a full view of him.
As the "Colonel" stepped in the street Sadipe fell in with the passing 
throng, and shadowed the "Colonel" for six or seven squares. He
turned into a side street, just off the main street, and walked rapidly
to the red brick house midway of the block, and giving a sharp whistle, 
waited a moment or two, when the street door was opened by a
woman who greeted him with a merry laugh, and he entered quickly,
after tossing into the street the butt of a Havana. Sadipe crossed the
street and took the number of the house, and walking rapidly to the
corner, hailed a passing cab, which he heard approaching, entered it
and directed the cabby to drive him to his lodgings. The following
morning bright and early he was on the trail of the "Colonel." At exactly 
8:25 he saw the "Colonel," accompanied by a woman, descend
the steps of this house and pass up the street to the corner, where there
was a cabstand. After a few words with the driver they both got in and.
were driven away. Sadipe took a cabriolet and directed the driver to
follow the hansom cab, which had just left the stand. The first cab was.
driven at a smart pace to the Royal Arms Hotel, about twenty squares
away. The second, in which sat Sadipe, which was only three or four
minutes behind it, stopped there also. Sadipe gave the driver half a
crown, told him to wait, and went in. Approaching the clerk's desk,
which commanded a view of the spacious dining-room, he inquired



what the rates were for breakfast, and ordered that breakfast be served
him at 10:30.</p>

<p>As he walked slowly to the street door he saw through the huge plate
glass window which separated the rotunda from the dining-hall, "Colonel 
Bradshawe" and the lady who accompanied him from the house
we have mentioned at breakfast. Jumping into the cab, he directed the
driver to take him quickly to the office of Mr. Hunter, and in less than
a quarter of an hour he was seated in the private office of his chief, to
whom he gave a detailed statement of all that he had accomplished
the night previous; and on that morning Mr. Hunter was pleased with
the progress he had made and told him that he was doing finely.</p>

<p>"You had better send a messenger back to the hotel, Mr. Okukenu,
with a note cancelling your order for breakfast," said Mr. Hunter; "and
as it may be in the course of preparation I will just give you a small
check to cover its cost. It would not be fair to order it and not pay for
it, even though you do not eat it. Now that we are certain about the
identity of our man, we must devise some plan to get him without creating 
a scene. What do you suggest, Mr. Okukenu?" asked Mr. Hunter.</p>

<p>"Well," said Sadipe, "if I can get into that hotel as a waiter, I may
be able to get evidence enough to convict the Colonel and his 
confederates, for he has confederates."</p>

<p>"Capital idea," said Mr. Hunter. "I think I can arrange that; but you
will have to take off that moustache you wear and those good clothes,
and your rings; they can be put in the safe here until this matter is
pulled off. I will go right down to the Royal Arms and see the proprietor,
whom I know very well, and induce him to take you on as a waiter."</p>

<p>Mr. Hunter then called a messenger boy, a man of about thirty, and
dispatched him with the note cancelling the order for breakfast for
Sadipe and a check for five shillings. Putting on his hat, he took
Sadipe with him to a less pretentious hostelry around the corner from
the office, where they had a sumptuous breakfast of fried soles, broiled
ham, coffee, boiled eggs, toast and cocoa.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter XV</head>

<p>After breakfast they parted, to meet again at 12 o'clock, sharp.
Sadipe went to a barber's and had his moustache removed, and from
there to his lodgings, where he donned a cheap black suit with a short
coat, such as are affected by hotel waiters, and promptly on the hour
was back in headquarters, ready for orders.</p>

<p>Our readers have already been told of the dinner at the Royal Arms,
at which Miss Crenshawe contrived to secure an introduction to Captain
De Forrest, master of the "Norris K. Peters." Colonel Bradshawe,
who was an habitue of this famous hostelry, had also cunningly managed
to scrape up an acquaintance with the doughty old sea captain. It came
about this way: One morning after breakfast he strolled leisurely into the
smoking-room, where the captain, with other guests of the hotel, was 
enjoying his morning paper and cigar. The captain, who was fond of comfort, 
was seated in the largest and most comfortable armchair in the room.
On a small table within reach were several letters which he had opened
to read. On the floor beside his chair were the London morning papers.
The captain was reading the ship news in the Times and noting with a
blue pencil such items as interested him. Colonel Bradshawe walked
over to where he sat and addressed him as follows:</p>

<p>"My lord, I am delighted to meet you here this charming morning.
I have not seen you since we met in India. I hope you are very well."</p>

<p>Captain De Forrest flushed a deep crimson, and, looking up from



his paper into the face of his visitor, beheld a fine specimen of manhood 
in the person of Bradshawe, who wore a military coat, on the left
breast of which depended three gorgeous medals. In his right eye he
wore a monocle. The captain was flattered. To be taken for a lord of
the realm tickled him immensely, and he blushed a deeper crimson
as the wily Bradshawe fawned on him. Laying the Times down on the
rug beside his chair, he arose and said:</p>

<p>"My dear sir, you have evidently made a mistake. I am Captain De
Forrest, of the 'Norris K. Peters,' trading in the East Indies."</p>

<p>"Wonderful resemblance," remarked Colonel Bradshawe, the
while chuckling to himself at the ease with which the Yankee captain
had swallowed the bait. "I sincerely beg your pardon, sir. I was sure
you were my old and valued friend Lord Cromartie, of Aberdeen. You
look enough like him to be his twin brother. I never saw two men who
more closely resembled each other," said the colonel, coyly.</p>

<p>The captain blushed again, and looked confused.</p>

<p>"I know Lord Cromartie very well, sir," said he. "We have been
friends for more than thirty years, and I am proud of the friendship of
such a man."</p>

<p>"You speak very well, sir," replied the colonel. "Lord Cromartie
is a most excellent man, and one whose friendship is really worth having. 
I myself have known him for twenty years."</p>

<p>"Won't you be seated, sir," said the captain, drawing a chair for the
colonel.</p>

<p>"Thank you, yes," answered the colonel, sweetly, as he seated himself 
in the armchair opposite the captain.</p>

<p>"And now, my dear sir," said the captain, "we have had a most delightful 
chat about a mutual friend. Be good enough, if you please, to
inform me whom I have the honor of addressing. Your face is familiar,
though I do not recall that we have ever met socially."</p>

<p>The colonel apologized for not having disclosed his identity earlier, 
and producing a beautiful Russia leather card case he extracted
therefrom one of his visiting cards, containing his name, all his titles,
and a coat of arms.</p>



<p>Adjusting his glasses and reading the name, Captain De Forrest extended 
his hand to the colonel, who grasped it and smiled a self-satisfied smile.</p>

<p>The captain asked the colonel if he smoked, and being answered
in the affirmative handed him his cigar case, from which he took one
of the big black Havanas, such as the captain always smoked, and
which the colonel lighted. Soon the two men were energetically puffing 
away at the fragrant weeds and filling their section of the smoking-room with smoke.</p>

<p>For nearly an hour the two talked, smoked and swapped stories. The
colonel was greatly pleased with himself in that, without any apparent 
effort, he had been able to obtain from the captain information
which would be useful to his clever female accomplice, who had already 
begun her campaign, with a fair chance of winning.</p>

<p>One of the results of this chance meeting between the colonel
and the captain was a dinner given in the honor of the captain and a
few friends by Colonel Bradshawe in one of the handsome private
dining-rooms of the Royal a week after their first meeting.</p>

<p>At the dinner at the Royal Arms Colonel George Evelyn Bradshawe 
renewed the acquaintance with Captain De Forrest, and introduced 
the "old salt" in effusive phrase to the "beauty" whom to know
he had been willing to pay Sadipe a handsome fee. Of course, the captain 
was inexpressibly happy. His joy was unbounded, and his vocabulary 
contained no word which could adequately express the great
pleasure it gave him to meet such a charming and attractive personality 
as Miss Crenshawe confessedly was. It is amusing to watch an
old man when [he] is in love with a pretty face, to note his grimaces,
to listen to his silly and vapid inanities, and it is equally amusing to
see with what ease and skill a young and experienced adventuress,
who understands her business, can twist one of these silly old fools
around her finger and bend him to her will.</p>

<p>Captain De Forrest had yearned long and earnestly for the opportunity 
which was now his. He was basking in the smiles of one of the
cleverest adventuresses in all England. He was loath to leave London,



no, not that, he was loath to leave behind him the soulful eyes, the
cherry red lips and the bewitching smiles of the woman who had ravished 
his silly old heart without his exchanging a dozen words with
her. Of course he did not know that this was her specialty, and she did
not tell him.</p>

<p>There is a vulgar phrase to the effect that "there is a sucker born
every sixty seconds." Captain De Forrest was one of the early
species, and he had swallowed bait, hook and sinker. Miss Crenshawe
had him completely in her power, and if she told him to stand on his
head, old as he was, he would have attempted it.</p>

<p>The quartet, after dinner at the Royal Arms, and the good-byes had
been said, held a conference to determine upon the plan of attack
when the captain should return from his contemplated trip to the East
Indies. It was decided, since he was so completely "gone" on Miss
Crenshawe, to give him a return dinner this time. Miss Crenshawe was
to be the hostess, and the guest of honor was to sit at the same table
with her where he could feast his eyes on her beauty to his heart's content. 
The beauty, in the meantime, was to lead him gently on and find
out things about the wonderful diamond, its value, its location, and
what use was to be made of it. All this was agreed upon without demur, 
for it had been made clear to all who had observed the captain's
actions during the dinner that day that he was an easy mark for Miss
Crenshawe, and that she, better than any of the company, could handle 
him according to her own sweet will. The quartet, having agreed
to this much, decided to have a luncheon in the Royal Arms the following 
day, to formally ratify their action with wine and song and a few
general remarks.</p>

<p>Promptly at 2:30 the next day they met, as per agreement, but in
another section of the great hotel, in one of the private dining-rooms,
and Sadipe, our hero, was detailed by arrangement to serve them. The
conversation was in French. English was spoken only to the black.
While they were enjoying their luncheon they talked volubly in French
of their plans to inveigle the old sea captain into their meshes, and to
get possession of the diamond which he possessed. Miss Crenshawe



was to make love to him as ardently as she knew how (and she knew
how), was to arrange to go with him to the lapidary's where he had left
it to be cut, and to do her best to induce him to bring it away with him
to show it to Colonel Bradshawe, Hodder, and his lady friend, who
were consumed with desire to see such a valuable and priceless gem.
This accomplished, the captain was to be asked to drink to the health
of Miss Crenshawe in a bumper of Mumm's Extra Dry, properly drugged,
and at the psychological moment, when the drug had taken effect, to relieve him of the treasure. The colonel, his old friend,
with the assistance of Hodder and the black, were to take the captain
for a little air in the carriage, leave him in a room in a notorious resort 
which they knew, where he would sleep off the effects of the drug,
and wake up the next morning in a strange part of London some five
or six miles from his hotel. The conspirators were to assemble again
at midnight, in tourists' attire, and take a late train for Paris, and on
the following day depart for Belgium as quietly and mysteriously as
they had entered Paris, where they would take a steamer bound for
the United States. Sadipe understood every word they said, and as
soon as they had left the room, which they did shortly, after tipping
him liberally, took his notebook from his pocket and made several important entries.</p>

<p>As soon as he had cleared the table and put the room to rights he
wrote out in detail the salient points of the remarkable plot which he
had heard outlined, and communicated the same to his chief.</p>

<p>At noon the following day he received these instructions: "Keep a
sharp eye on all these people; report their movements daily—where
they go, and what they say; if possible, find the private house where
they congregate, and don't let them escape you. Hunter."</p>

<p>The next day, dressed as a native African, and carrying a grass bag
filled with curios from his native land, he made a visit to a house in
side street not more than twenty squares from the Royal Arms. He did
not know who lived there. He had passed it many times, and the
thing that struck him about it was that, though it was inhabited, the

 

windows and curtains were always down, except those in the English
basement, where the servants worked. He knocked on the iron gate,
and a sprightly red-cheeked English lassie, with large blue eyes,
laughing eyes, opened it, and instantly remembered him from having
seen him passing at other times. She knew or believed that he was a
peddler, and asked him what he had to sell. Sadipe dropped into pidgin 
English, and said:</p>

<p>"Me show you, lady, many beautiful tings made in my country. I sell
'em cheap. Yo want buy some ting today?"</p>

<p>"Oh, I don't know," said the girl. "Come in and let me have a look
at your trinkets." And she opened the gate wide and passed the black
into the servants' reception-room, where there were several chairs, a
big round table, on which were a few copies of old magazines and
newspapers and a pack of playing cards.</p>

<p>Sadipe advanced toward the table and, opening his bag, put a number 
of articles on view. Among them were some curiously wrought
work baskets made of the tough African grass, and highly colored, and
some really pretty floor mats made of the same material.</p>

<p>While the two maids were examining these Sadipe picked up the
playing cards and began to shuffle them. One of the girls, noticing
him, asked him if he could tell fortunes.</p>

<p>"Oh, li'l bit. W'y yo wan' fortune tole?" he asked.</p>

<p>"How much?" asked the girl.</p>

<p>"Me tell yo lots for shilling," answered Sadipe.</p>

<p>So a bargain was struck immediately, and the other maid, who had
been listening to the conversation, withdrew, closing the hall door, and
left the black man and her fellow-servant together.</p>

<p>Sadipe proved to be so clever with the cards that the girl looked at
him in amazement. He told her her name, age, and the details of a love
affair of her earlier life in which the only man she had ever really and
truly loved had been accidentally shot on the morning of the day they
were to be married. That she was now engaged to a man whom she had
only recently begun to doubt, that her doubts were well founded, as



he was already married. He described the man so accurately that the
girl gave a faint scream. Recovering from her excitement, she told him
to "Go on, go on."</p>

<p>"No more," said Sadipe. "It is not good fo' yo' know too much."</p>

<p>She paid him the shilling and called her friend into the room and
held a whispered conversation with her, the result being that Sadipe
had to tell her fortune also.</p>

<p>"Can you read palms?" she asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"Yes, me tell fortune wid card, wattah, and read face."</p>

<p>"I want you to read my palm."</p>

<p>Sadipe took her slender hand in his and scrutinized closely the
lines below the "mount of Venus." The first words uttered were:</p>

<p>"Yo' have a long life an' yo' marry rich man, but he not in dis country. 
Yo have trouble much. Dere is one woman who love dat man same
like yo', but he no love her." (The girl shuddered.) "He true to yo'. She
try pizen him when she no make him love her, an' she goin' write yo'
one bad letter, try scare yo', but yo' must not notice dat. Yo' lover he
by yo' side in sixty day. Yo' catch one letter from him inside tree day,
an yo' will be very happy woman."</p>

<p>The girl smiled, and Sadipe went on reading her palm.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter XVI</head>  
   
<p>"He bring you beautiful presents, much gold and fine goods. He
is make rich where he bin, and you will go back to de lan' where he
come from. He is tall man wid black hair and big heart and he love
you same as he love his life."</p>

<p>The description of the girl's affianced was perfect. She was delighted 
with the reading and cheerfully yielded up the shilling charged.</p>

<p>Both the girls then made a number of purchases, and just as Sadipe
was about to go the beauty of the quartet, of whom we have been talking, 
came into the room to give some orders and, espying the black, recognized 
him as a peddler from whom she had some time ago purchased
some curios, and asked what he had new and to show her his stock.</p>

<p>"He tells fortunes beautiful," said one of the maids in the tone of
voice of a person who had gotten a quid pro quo for value received.</p>

<p>"Oh, he does, eh?" replied her mistress. "Has he told yours?"</p>

<p>"Yes'm; an' he's told it true—told me things that nobody except the
Lord, my sweetheart and myself could know. That he did, ma'am."</p>

<p>"Well," said madame, "he must be a real genius. I will have to test
his wonderful powers as a seer. What are your charges, my good man,
for lifting the veil and giving us a peep into the future?"</p>

<p>Sadipe shook his head, as though not fully comprehending this flow
of language, and was silent. Milady, seeing that her words were lost,
said:</p>

            

<p>"I want my fortune told before I buy anything from you. How much
I pay you?"</p>

<p>Sadipe's eyes brightened at the prospect of another customer, and
he replied softly:</p>

<p>"Me charge one shilling, lady."</p>

<p>"Very well. How do you tell fortunes, by cards or the palms?"</p>

<p>"Any way you like me to do, lady," said Sadipe.</p>

<p>"Tell it by the cards," she said, drawing a chair up to the table on
which Sadipe had spread his wares. He began to shuffle the cards 
vigorously, and while he was doing so both the maids retired from the
room and closed the door between, leaving their mistress and the
black alone. When he had finished shuffling the cards, he asked her
to cut them in three parts. She did so. He picked up the first part she
had laid down, looked the cards over carefully, did the same to the two
other parts and then, taking up again the first part, he said:</p>

<p>"There is one very old man who is thinking much of you, but you
have not known him very long. He is very rich, has a great many jewels 
and diamonds and much money. He would marry you."</p>

<p>Picking up the next part: "He is now on the water. He is a seagoing
man, and he is now going to a far country. The cargo that he will bring
back with him will be worth a king's ransom, it will be so valuable."</p>

<p>Picking up the third part and running them slowly, he said: "He has
a valuable gem. It looks like a diamond. It is not with him. It is here
in London. You are to get this gem, but he will not give it to you."</p>

<p>Madam looked at the black. He went on:</p>

<p>"There are three other persons besides you who know of this stone,
but you only will handle it. You will have it in your hands within sixty 
days. You have talked with three other people about it within the:
past forty-eight hours. Its possession will create trouble and bloodshed. 
You will see this old man and eat with him in less than two
months. He will propose marriage to you. You do not love him, though
he loves you. You love a soldier. He is a tall man, a great rover and
adventurer. The cards say that he will be engaged in a transaction

   

which will involve him and three others in great trouble and probable
imprisonment."</p>

<p>Sadipe shuffled the cards again and requested the woman cut them.
She did not move nor utter a sound, but sat in her chair, her face as
white as a sheet, staring at him. Finally she found her voice and said:
"Tell me no more. J have heard enough. Here is your money," and she
handed him a half-crown. "Keep it," she said. Recovering from her
agitation, she purchased a few trinkets, paid for them and left the room.</p>

<p>Sadipe packed his bag and prepared to follow suit when one of the
maids came in, flushed and agitated, saying:</p>

<p>"You told my mistress bad news, didn't you?"</p>

<p>"I told her the truth," said Sadipe, "and I could have told her more,
but she would not stay to listen."</p>

<p>"She feels very bad over whatever it was you told her, and she is
sitting in the dining-room crying as if to break her heart."</p>

<p>"She will cry harder than that if she does not abandon the purpose
of which I told her."</p>

<p>The maid's curiosity was now aroused, and she, with all a woman's
artfulness, began to ply Sadipe with questions, promising secrecy if
he would tell her what it was he told her mistress which had wrought
such a change in her.</p>

<p>"No; that would not be honorable," said Sadipe. "You have no more
right to know what I told her than she has to know what I told you. She
gave me her confidence as you did, and I am bound in honor not to reveal 
her secrets or yours."</p>

<p>The maid looked sheepish and took another tack.</p>

<p>"You must have said something to her about the old sea captain who
has gone away. I've heard her and the colonel discussing him for
hours."</p>

<p>"Colonel who?" asked Sadipe, innocently.</p>

<p>"Colonel Bradshawe," answered the girl.</p>

<p>"Does Colonel Bradshawe live in this house?" he asked the girl.</p>

<p>"Why, certainly he does," she said.</p>



<p>"What does he do? What is his occupation?" asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"He doesn't do anything," said the girl.</p>

<p>"Who else lives here?"</p>

<p>"There is a new couple here since Monday—a Mr. Hodder and a
young woman who speaks French."</p>

<p>"Does this Mr. Hodder speak French, too?"</p>

<p>"Oh, yes, they all speak it."</p>

<p>"Do you speak it?"</p>

<p>"Yes, but very imperfectly. I understand it very well. I was a maid
in a French family at Bologne—Sur Mer—for five years, and learned
to speak and write the language, but I'm a little rusty now."</p>

<p>"Oh, I see," said Sadipe. "Does your mistress know that you speak
and understand French?"</p>

<p>"Oh, no," said the girl.</p>

<p>"Very good," said Sadipe. "How long have you lived with these people?"</p>

<p>"Oh, about three years; just three years lacking six weeks."</p>

<p>"Have they always lived in this house?"</p>

<p>"Yes, since I have been employed by them. They sometimes go
away to France or Belgium and remain for six or seven weeks."</p>

<p>"Does anybody come here to see them in their absence?"</p>

<p>"Yes, last year they left rather hurriedly at night without saying
where they were going, and two or three days after they had gone two
men came here looking for Colonel Bradshawe."</p>

<p>"What sort of looking men were they?"</p>

<p>"One was a thick-set man with a heavy beard and a very red face,
the other was a tall, slim man with a moustache. The big man was
dressed in tweed and the slim man wore a blue serge suit. They looker
like business men."</p>

<p>"Did they say what they wanted with the colonel?"</p>

<p>"No; they merely inquired if he was in town."</p>

<p>"Did you give them his out-of-town address?"</p>

<p>"I did not."</p>

<p>"Why?"</p>



<p>"Because my instructions were to give no one his out-of-town address. 
I simply told them that I did not know what it was."</p>

<p>"But you did know?"</p>

<p>"Yes."</p>

<p>"Well, I must be going," said Sadipe; "but I am coming here again
in a few days and will give you a good palm reading, and if you can
really keep a secret I will tell you something that will be of the greatest 
interest and profit to you. You need not say that I have asked you
these questions. I will be here in three days, and I shall want to talk
with you on a very particular matter."</p>

<p>"Very well, sir," said the maid. "You may trust me. Come when you
will."</p>

<p>"Thank you," said Sadipe.</p>

</div2>



<div2 type="chapter">

<head>Chapter XVII</head>

<p>On leaving this house, where he had gathered so much valuable
and useful information, Sadipe went at once to headquarters, where
he reported progress, and to ask for further instructions. He related
all the facts minutely to his chief and was complimented by him o
his skill as a seer.</p>

<p>Sadipe laughed heartily at the compliment, and said that he did not
know one card from another, and that he had merely guessed at the
things he told the girls which had pleased them so much and their mistress, 
to whom his message had given such evident pain.</p>

<p>"So these gentlemen are now out of the city, eh!" said the manager
of the bureau. "I thought as much," he added, "and I think I know
where they are to be found," he continued. "Your Instructions, Mr. Okukenu, 
are to take the midnight train tonight and go at once to Paris.
This time you must travel as a gentleman of leisure, a rich African
merchant. This letter will give you full instructions what to do when
you reach Paris. You are the only man who can successfully carry out
those instructions, and I have implicit confidence in your ability to do
so because you have already shown marked skill as a sleuth in that
you successfully located the rendezvous of these shrewd swindlers,
who have thus far eluded the vigilance of the best detectives of Scotland 
Yard. Now, if you can see that servant girl again before you go, it
would not be a bad idea to question her sharply and find out where



Colonel Bradshawe is, as this knowledge would save time and enable
you to go directly to the town in which he is now domiciled outside of
Paris."</p>

<p>"But you wish me to go away tonight, and there is no time to see
this girl," said Sadipe, "unless my trip can be deferred for, say, two
days at most. The girl does know a great deal that would be useful to
the bureau, and I believe that if I could see her again and read her
palm, as I have promised to do, and would like to do, I could induce
her to talk freely, and we could act then more quickly than we will be
able to do by my going to Paris and shadowing these people for, say,
a week or ten days. She understands French, as she told me, and it
follows that she heard this quartette discuss their plans. All we want
is the right <hi rend="italics">clue</hi>, is it not so, chief?"</p>

<p>"By jove!" answered the manager, "your plan is the correct one, Mr.
Okukenu. Wait here a few moments until I go into the main office and
talk it over."</p>

<p>Sadipe picked up a copy of The Times, which was lying on the 
manager's desk, and taking an armchair near the window, sat down and
was busy scanning its newsy columns. His quick eye fell on an item
dated from Rouen, reading as follows:</p>

<p>"Rouen, France, Sept. 19.—At a reception given at the residence
of Monsieur and Mlle. Jean Jacques Magloire on Thursday evening
last the guests of honor were two wealthy English gentlemen, General 
Sir Edward Bradford, K.C.B., the Hon. Mr. Hoddersford, and his
excellency Count Rudolph Blatzheim, a member of one of the oldest
families in Prussia."</p>

<p>The item went on to relate how these gentlemen were the lions of
the hour, and how the ladies raved over them, etc., etc.</p>

<p>Presently the manager returned, smiling, and said, "Mr. Okukenu,
we have delayed your trip until the day after tomorrow. You will leave
at midnight, going direct to Paris, and you will carry out the instructions 
contained in the letter given you. You are to understand, of course,
Mr. Okukenu, that instructions are given to you merely for your guidance 
and are not arbitrary; that they contain certain facts impossible

      

for you to get except through the bureau's agents in France. You are
to use your own best judgment as to methods, and work up this case
according to your own plans."</p>

<p>"Very good, very good," said Sadipe, "I understand perfectly."</p>

<p>Picking up <hi rend="italics">The Times</hi>, which he had laid on the manager's desk
he pointed out to him the news item which he had read, and asked him
to read it, first asking him if he had seen it. He had not, and began to
read it with considerable interest. When he finished reading it he remarked, 
"That is an important piece of news, Mr. Okukenu."</p>

<p>"I should say it is," was all that Sadipe would say.</p>

<p>"I shall be leaving now, chief," he said. "Tomorrow I read palms;
good day."</p>

<p>"Good day, Mr. Okukenu."</p>

<p>The following day about 11 o'clock Sadipe, who had donned his
African costume, took up his grain bag of curios and wended his way
to the house where he had made a reputation as a seer. He found the
maids in cheerful mood and glad to see him. They invited him into the
servants' sitting room, which had been tidied up, and he took an armchair
and began to explain to them why he had called again, so early
after his last visit. He said he was thinking of returning to his own
country in a very few days, as the climate of England was much too
severe to one who had always lived in a tropical country, and as the
winter was coming on and as it promised to be a severe one, he would
very probably go to Liverpool in the next few days and take ship for
his beloved West Coast. He had called to make good his promises to
the ladies to read their palms and to dispose of as many more of his
African curios as they might wish to purchase of him. The young
women said they were very sorry to learn that he was leaving England
and they hoped he might return soon.</p>

<p>"I shall be very likely to return," he said; "I like your country very
much, and I have met some very excellent people here. England is a
great country and English people, when you know them well, are very
kind and sympathetic."</p>

<p>Having thus prepared the way and disarmed them of suspicion as



to the real object of his call, he said he was ready, if they were, to tell
them their fortunes. The cook wanted hers told first, so the house
girl went to the kitchen, closing the sitting-room door after her.</p>
 
<p>"I will make no charge to you for this reading. You have been kind
enough to buy my trinkets and I appreciate it very much."</p>

<p>"Oh, thank you," said the cook, blushing; "that is very nice of you,
indeed."</p>

<p>"Do you wish me to read the cards or your palm?" asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"I think I will have you read the cards," she answered.</p>

<p>"Have you cards here?" asked Sadipe.</p>

<p>"Yes," she replied; "in that table drawer there is a new package."</p>

<p>"Good!" said Sadipe, opening the drawer at her direction. He took
out the cards and, removing them from the case, began to shuffle them
like a veteran soothsayer. The girl drew her chair up to the table and
Sadipe passed the cards to her and asked her to cut them in three
equal parts. With a great deal of seriousness the girl complied with
his request. Sadipe picked up the first part of the three sections, ran
them over once or twice before saying a word to her, shook his head,
smiled meaningly, and said:</p>

<p>"My young lady, it is better to be born lucky than rich." Laying down
a card on the table—the ace of diamonds—he continued: "there is
on its way to you a letter from a distant land which contains the best
news you have ever received. Following this letter will come to you a
sum of money, which you have been expecting for years but feared you
would never get, and you will be rich the remainder of your days."</p>

<p>The girl gasped and attempted to speak.</p>

<p>"Wait a moment," he said; "there is some sad news here for you,"
laying down the ten of spades, "but it is not serious. A relative whom
you have never met—an old man who was very rich—is dead. He was
some relation to your mother. I see a woman here," he said, showing
her the queen of hearts, "who"—</p>

<p>The girl could wait no longer and burst out with the information that
the dead man pictured in the cards was her uncle Algernon who had
gone out to Australia before she was born, to engage in sheep raising.



Then she wept a little, but soon recovered her composure. Sadipe took
up the next section.</p>

<p>"You have had a proposal of marriage within the past nine days from
a man who knows what I have just told you. He is a messenger in the
office of the lawyers from where you will get the letter telling you of
your good fortune. If you are wise you will have nothing to do with this
man, who is merely a fortune hunter and doesn't love you."</p>

<p>"Oh!" she said, "that is Martin Coverdale."</p>

<p>The king of spades happened to be the next card Sadipe picked up,
so he took a chance and guessed what sort of chap Martin looked like.
"He is a tall, dark featured man, with very black hair, and dresses
well."</p>

<p>"That's Martin," said the girl, and with that Sadipe threw down the
king of spades, where she could see it. The girl gazed at it intently for
a moment and said, "I'll never marry him."</p>

<p>Taking up the last section, Sadipe said: "Good hearts follow you,"
throwing down the ten of hearts, "the man who loves you most is the
one you think of least, but he is an honest, true-hearted man, and if
you marry him will make you a good husband. He is neither poor nor
rich, but he has enough to make you comfortable. You met him in a
gathering not long ago and shunned him. See," he said, "there's the
room" (throwing down the four of clubs) "and there are the people"
(throwing down the ten of clubs). The girl was dumfounded, and began 
to confirm Sadipe's guess.</p>

<p>"That man is Barney Huddleston," she said, "and as true as you
live we met at a party the other night, and I avoided him. And you say
he loves me?"</p>

<p>"As surely as you live, miss, and better than any man you know. He
worships you."</p>

<p>The girl's face beamed with smiles. Sadipe shuffled the cards twice
more and told her the same story each time and she was <hi rend="italics">happy</hi> ever
afterwards.</p>

<p>Then she bought a great quantity of his trinkets and gave him 25
shillings as a present for the good news he had brought her.</p>



<p>"This is all I can now tell you, Miss," said Sadipe. Placing the
cards in their case, he opened the table drawer and put them into it.</p>

<p>"You were saying when we last talked together, Miss, that you 
understood the French language but could not speak it very well."</p>

<p>"Yes, I perfectly understand that tongue, and can speak it; my only
difficulty (and it is only the result of carelessness) is that I do not 
pronounce my words exactly as a French person would, and am sometimes 
misunderstood because I put the accents in the wrong places."</p>

<p>"Oh I see," said Sadipe, "that isn't a very serious misfortune. You
were telling me that your employers often conversed in that language;
are they not English?"</p>

<p>"As English as I am," said the girl, "and I was born in Devonshire."</p>

<p>"Well I can not understand why they would speak in French, being
English, as you say they are, unless they have something to say which
they are afraid to have their servants hear if spoken in English. You
are sure that they do not know that you are familiar with that tongue?"</p>

<p>"Quite sure, sir, for I have never told any one that."</p>

<p>"Good, good," said Sadipe. "By the way where have Col. Bradshawe
and his friends, Mr. Hodder and the Count, gone? I learned yesterday 
that they are in France; do you know what town or city they have
gone to?"</p>

<p>"Yes, sir; he did not tell me himself, but I heard him in conversation



with the Count and Mr. Hodder, say in French, that 'we are going
to Rouen.'"</p>

<p>"Did you say Rouen, Miss?"</p>

<p>"Yes, Rouen," she answered.</p>

<p>"Did they say that they were going anywhere else beside Rouen?"</p>

<p>"The Colonel said they would spend four or five weeks in Rouen
and then go to Belgium."</p>

<p>"Ah, I see. How long have they been away?"</p>

<p>"Just twelve days."</p>

<p>"Do you know these people very well, Miss?"</p>

<p>"Why, how do you mean?"</p>

<p>"I mean do you know what kind of people they are, whether they
are respectable folks or not?"</p>

<p>"Really I see very little of them, especially the men, for they are
very seldom here when in England. They go out a great deal in the
nighttime and come in very early in the morning and are never seen
by the servants except at meals. Sometimes the young woman goes
away in a carriage with them and remains out very late."</p>

<p>"You have never seen the old Sea Captain De Forrest, have you?"</p>

<p>"Only once, sir; he was here once before he sailed; there was no
one here except Miss Crenshawe and the servants, and he did not remain 
over twenty minutes. When Col. Bradshawe came she told him
in French, while at dinner, that the diamond was safe, that the captain 
had called while he was absent, to assure her that the lapidaries
had about finished cutting and polishing it and that he would surely
let her see it as soon as he received it; they both laughed very heartily, 
though I confess I didn't quite see the point."</p>

<p>"You promised me, Miss, when I was first here that if I confided a
secret to you you would keep it; can I trust you with that secret now?"</p>

<p>"I pledge you on the honor of a woman and in the fear of God that
I will not divulge to any one the confidence you repose in me, sir."</p>

<p>"I accept the pledge, Miss, in all good faith and will trust to your
honor to keep it."</p>

<p>"You may well do that, sir," she answered.</p>



<p>"These people with whom you are living," said Sadipe, "are not
honest; they are crooks. Thieves, that is a better word. They are being
hunted for many robberies committed by them at various times, but of
which there is no direct proof. The men are gentlemen thieves, the
woman is an adventuress and is used by these men to inveigle rich old
men, and get them into compromising positions, where they fear exposure 
and disgrace, and force them to pay large sums for immunity.
Some day the whole household including the servants will be arrested 
by the police and exposed."</p>

<p>"Mercy!" cried the girl.</p>

<p>"This is the secret I impart to you, Miss; keep it inviolate. Take my
advice and get out of here as soon as possible or your whole life will
be ruined."</p>

<p>This ruse had its effect on the girl, who had been considerably
wrought up. She regarded Sadipe as a man of mystery since he had revealed 
to her certain hidden things in her life and she felt that he was
able to penetrate her innermost thoughts.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics">(To be continued.)</hi></p>

</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>